<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>psychology &#8211; Thoughts of Stone</title>
	<atom:link href="/category/psychology/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>/</link>
	<description>short essays, usually about humans</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Sat, 18 Feb 2023 04:06:15 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=6.1.3</generator>

<image>
	<url>/wp-content/uploads/2020/07/cropped-icon-32x32.jpg</url>
	<title>psychology &#8211; Thoughts of Stone</title>
	<link>/</link>
	<width>32</width>
	<height>32</height>
</image> 
	<item>
		<title>THE LAST HISTORY AND THE END OF MAN</title>
		<link>/the-last-history-and-the-end-of-man/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[j stone]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 13 Jan 2023 04:45:23 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[cosmology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[human ecology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[ideas]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[psychology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[science]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[technology]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=762</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Why most planetary civilizations collapse &#160; I didn’t get into video games until I was in my 40s. Oddly enough, it was a historian who triggered my interest. Niall Ferguson, the bestselling author, columnist, TV personality and Stanford professor, penned a 2006 New York Magazine piece, “How to Win a War,” that persuasively extolled the &#8230; <a href="/the-last-history-and-the-end-of-man/" class="more-link">Continue reading<span class="screen-reader-text"> "THE LAST HISTORY AND THE END OF MAN"</span></a>]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><em>Why most planetary civilizations collapse</em></p>
<p><span id="more-762"></span></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>I didn’t get into video games until I was in my 40s. Oddly enough, it was a historian who triggered my interest. Niall Ferguson, the bestselling author, columnist, TV personality and Stanford professor, penned a 2006 <em>New York Magazine</em> <a href="https://nymag.com/news/features/22787/">piece</a>, “How to Win a War,” that persuasively extolled the virtues of video games as tools for learning about history. He was particularly impressed by a certain turn-based PC strategy game that purported to model World War II—playing it, he said, had seriously challenged some of his own beliefs about the war.</p>
<p>I was not as impressed when I played that particular game, and later a more sophisticated competitor. The limitations of consumer-level computers and developer teams meant that these games simply couldn’t model the dynamics of the WW2-era world very well. However, even at that very modest level of simulation, the experience of replaying a historical period <em>again and again</em>, for dozens to hundreds of playthroughs, did prompt some thoughts about history in general.</p>
<p>One was simply that replaying a given stretch of history, which is to say, generating one variant history after another, has the effect of diminishing the significance of any of those variants. Naturally, in the highly abstracted milieu of a video game, one expects to be far less sensitive to details than one would be in real life. But I noticed that I became progressively desensitized to the details of the real-life WW2 as well: they seemed less interesting and meaningful.</p>
<p>To put it another way, my picture of this period of history was no longer formed from one clear image-capture, but from many—and in that multiple exposure, so to speak, most details were nonrecurring; they therefore tended to fade away as the number of exposures grew.</p>
<p>Would real-life history look different each time if we could re-run it from the same initial starting point? It absolutely would. Even one modern country is an enormously complex and nonlinear system—it will <em>always</em> vary significantly in how it runs from the same starting conditions, and the details of its course will be hard to predict very far in advance. (Think of how hard it is for us to foresee the course of a much simpler nonlinear system, the weather.)</p>
<p>Even so, we almost never think of history in this way. Experience encourages us instead to think of any historical episode as a singular phenomenon—one unique block of spacetime, never to be repeated—and that in turn leads us to frame any history as a sets of events linked by cause-effect relationships. Typically, we also try to draw big lessons from it all: the “lessons of history.” By contrast, when we have the ability to simulate replays of that block of spacetime again and again, seeing how things play out differently each time<em>, </em>it makes the inherently probabilistic nature of history stand out much more sharply. We are, in effect, forced to face a reality we normally wouldn’t acknowledge.</p>
<p>To illustrate again with an extreme example: Suppose one had a large bucket filled with a million marbles, each with its own identifying number, and suddenly dumped them onto some perfectly flat, expansive surface—and recorded precisely how they all bounced and rolled and reached some final arrangement. To the average person, that “history” of the marbles wouldn’t be particularly interesting, would it? The average person would understand intuitively that this marble-history was basically random, would look different in every re-run, and had nothing to teach, other than that marbles reliably obey known laws of mechanics. For that reason, writing a detailed History of the Marbles—or worse, having a dozen marble historians write their own competing tomes—would be absurd. Possibly such histories would be of interest <em>to marbles</em>, who might be curious about all the individual collisions that had brought them to their present positions. But to beings capable of a wider perspective, a history of the marbles would seem pointless—a measuring of statistical noise, as mathematicians would say.</p>
<p style="text-align: center;">*</p>
<p>Apropos of all that, at some point in my WW2-gaming sojourns I came up with a weird thought-experiment:</p>
<p style="padding-left: 40px;"><em>Suppose the virtual soldiers and citizens populating any given playthrough had human-like feelings, and regarded that playthrough—their playthrough—as the only one that had ever happened? What would these virtual people do if I, as the Player-God above them, suddenly revealed to them the true nature of their existence—in other words, revealed their “history” as but one chance-ridden playthrough among many?</em></p>
<p>They would <em>despair</em>, wouldn’t they? Not only at the revelation that their existence was a mere simulation, but also in the recognition that it was <em>merely one of many variant, stochastically determined existences—</em>one semi-random timeline among thousands, or really <em>billions</em> considering the wider universe of players with their separate copies of the game. They would see that, <em>even as a simulation, their existence was effectively meaningless</em> in the grand scheme of things.</p>
<p>Someday, computer games may be invented that not only simulate human events with a high degree of complexity, but also, via the right hardware, imbue their human-like characters with some degree of consciousness. Given the situation of these simulated humans, aware that they are trapped in worlds of no meaning or consequence, we as godlike players will feel sorry for them. However, the sufferings of our virtual creatures should be the least of our worries at that point—for by then we should have recognized that, as creatures of no consequence ourselves, we are in the same damned boat.</p>
<p style="text-align: center;">*</p>
<p>Can that be true? Is what you or I experience as “real life” merely one probabilistically determined playthrough among an infinitude of them?</p>
<p>The short answer is: very likely yes. And this is arguably the most important revelation—or, if you like, compelling theory—produced by science to date. Moreover, the idea I propose here is that any human civilization capable of grasping this true nature of our reality will eventually enter a state of deep and chronic despair, which perhaps can end only in human extinction.</p>
<p>This putative process of discovery and despair has an interesting, foreshadowing parallel in the most famous Western account of human origin, that of Adam and Eve in the Garden of Eden. For we are, with our science, compulsively eating a forbidden, toxic fruit (of the Tree of Knowledge) and are thereby, in effect, exiling ourselves from the lush, blissfully ignorant existence we briefly had.</p>
<p>And this may not be just a human affliction. It may be one that always strikes species once they reach a certain level of technical and scientific advancement. If so, then plausibly it has already extinguished most of the smart species across the universe, and has made the rest avoidant lest they transmit to us truths we cannot handle. This would explain the paradox—“Fermi’s Paradox”—that the universe probably has incubated trillions upon trillions of alien civilizations, yet the latter’s visits to us appear to have been relatively few and furtive.</p>
<p style="text-align: center;">*</p>
<p>Science, as we know it, is a very recent development. Broadly speaking, it is one of the fruits of the Neolithic Revolution, which began in the Eastern Mediterranean about 15,000 years ago, and by about 1000 A.D. had spread to almost every human society. This major shift in the human lifeway, from nomadism to farming and settlement-building, triggered a rapid, self-catalyzing increase in the scale and complexity of our societies, and the development of many new institutions. Science, however, was one of the slowest to emerge—and as an ongoing, global institution, dominant over magic and religion, has existed for only about a century and a half.</p>
<p>The progress of science has been bittersweet. On the one hand, it has led to better living standards through better knowledge and technology—e.g., better crop yields, better sanitation, better medicines, and a vastly better understanding and command of our environment. On the other hand, it has relentlessly belied man’s instinctive, high opinion of himself as a special creature of God, “made in His image.”</p>
<p>One of the earliest and most famous examples of this type of psychologically problematic scientific knowledge was the idea (introduced by Copernicus in 1543, and later refined and popularized by Kepler and Galileo), that our planet is not at the center of the universe. It took hundreds of years and considerable technical developments in astronomy for this painful truth that <em>the universe does not revolve around us</em> to be accepted. But in a sense, we are still struggling to cope with the implications. If we are not situated centrally in the universe, how could it have been made specifically for us, as our religions have led us to believe? A cosmology that placed us in one wispy spiral arm of one nondescript galaxy among <em>trillions</em> of galaxies might have been an important step forward for our science—but it was a giant leap downward for our self-image.</p>
<p>Then, of course, there was Darwin. Humans as mere animals, evolutionary cousins of apes? Impossible! The Church resisted that theory as it had resisted Galileo and Copernicus. But by Darwin’s time, science was much stronger, the Church much weaker, and within only a few decades, serious opposition to the theory of evolution by natural selection started to fade away.</p>
<p>It was also becoming clear, by then, that Earth couldn’t have been around for only a few thousand years, as accounts such as Genesis implied. Empowered by the discovery of radioactivity and radioactive decay, geologists by the mid-1920s understood that Earth was formed <em>billions</em> of years ago. This implied that we, <em>H. sapiens,</em> are merely an incidental and very recently developed addition to our planet’s fauna. In fact, many paleontologists now suspect that, had that asteroid not hit our planet about 65 million years ago, largely wiping out the then-dominant dinosaurs, tool-making primates like us might never have evolved.</p>
<p>Since the end of the 1900s, cosmologists generally have been in agreement that our observable universe has existed for roughly ten billion years before our solar system was even formed. That means that humans are almost certainly latecomers to the higher intelligence club—and may be as primitive and uncomprehending, in relation to truly advanced species, as ants or amoebas are to us.</p>
<p>All this points to the conclusion that a God of the Universe, if anything like Him exists, has no special interest in humans; and, moreover, that all human “meaning” and “significance” is strictly local—strictly confined to our tiny speck of reality.</p>
<p style="text-align: center;">*</p>
<p>Probably like most people who grew up in the latter half of the 20<sup>th</sup> century, I’ve tended to react to these scientific revelations by ignoring them. To the extent that I did think about them, in my younger years, I assumed with vague optimism that humans someday, through better technology, could spread from one star system to another, and so on until they establish their universality, perhaps ultimately melding with whatever force or entity made the universe. I think it’s fair to say that a lot of other people, including prominent advocates of space exploration, still think the same way.</p>
<p><img decoding="async" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-763" src="/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/spacefaring2.jpg" alt="" width="556" height="682" /></p>
<p>I now see such optimism as a form of denial—a denial that is going to be harder and harder to maintain, as time goes on and we humans are increasingly confronted with the nature of our reality.</p>
<p>How we understand that reality is something that I expect will undergo various elaborations in the coming decades. But it should already be apparent that the idea we could ever “conquer the universe,” or in any way escape the utter insignificance of our existence, is naïve.</p>
<p>The most obvious (though not even the worst) part of the problem is that the universe is just unmanageably vast: larger than we can ever observe, expanding faster than light, and very likely infinite—which would mean that the human realm or contribution, in relation to the whole, could never be more than infinitesimal. This idea that space is effectively infinite the physicist and cosmology popularizer Brian Greene has <a href="https://www.amazon.com/Hidden-Reality-Parallel-Universes-Cosmos/dp/0307278123">described</a> as “consistent with all observations and . . . part of the cosmological model favored by many physicists and astronomers.”</p>
<p>The human mind is not really adapted for contemplating infinities, but as Greene has pointed out, a truly infinite universe would contain, at any moment, infinite numbers of worlds identical to ours, some moving through time precisely as ours does, others with variations—in fact, all possible variations.</p>
<p>Again, compared to the whole of this Infinite Universe, and, we might also say, in the eyes of its Creator, the histories of individual worlds within it, along with their systems of morality and meaning, should be of infinitesimal significance. If we could take a God’s-eye view, zooming out from our planet to encompass our whole galaxy, and then galaxy clusters, and clusters of clusters, we would see the histories of individual worlds much as the video game player sees our world: less as sets of interlinked events, and more as manifestations of a broader, stochastic process, whose function is essentially only <em>to ink over the space of possibility</em>.</p>
<p>Contemporary physics, specifically quantum mechanics, delivers us to an even colder, darker destination. Quantum mechanics has at its core an equation, the Schrödinger wave equation, that implies a weird multiplicity of states for any given quantum-scale particle (an electron, for example) traveling through time. Physicists in the early years of quantum theory clung to the belief that these multiple states somehow probabilistically “collapse” to one state whenever one tries to observe the particle with a measuring device. However, in the past few decades the field basically has abandoned that rather hand-waving interpretation, mostly in favor of a simpler, more parsimonious one: that the multiple possible states a particle can be observed to have are all, in a sense, <em>real</em>.</p>
<p>In other words, these alternate states represent multiple actual particles existing in different “worlds” or “universes.” Thus, a physicist recording the impact of one particular state of an electron has, at that moment, otherwise identical counterparts in otherwise identical alternate universes who record the impacts of all the other states.</p>
<p>The reality implied by this interpretation—now called the Many Worlds Interpretation (MWI)—encompasses not just one very big universe but, rather, an infinite number of them, a “multiverse,” across which everything that can happen does happen. There is a perfection here that, at least in a technical sense, should impress those who always believed Creation would be flawless and complete.</p>
<p>Of course, from the usual sentimental human perspective, MWI looks bizarre and horrifying. Even so, its superior simplicity and parsimony, as a way of thinking about quantum phenomena, has enabled it to survive and spread despite its implications—which physicists don’t “like” any more than you or I do.</p>
<p>As Greene has <a href="https://www.amazon.com/Hidden-Reality-Parallel-Universes-Cosmos/dp/0307278123">noted</a>:</p>
<p style="padding-left: 40px;">I find it both curious and compelling that numerous developments in physics, if followed sufficiently far, bump into some variation on the parallel-universe theme.</p>
<p style="text-align: center;">*</p>
<p>“The multiverse will drive you crazy if you really think about how it affects your life, and I can’t live like that,” the philosopher of physics and MWI theorist Simon Saunders once told a <a href="https://www.newscientist.com/article/mg19526223-700-parallel-universes-make-quantum-sense/">reporter</a>. “I’ll just accept [it] and then think about something else, to save my sanity.”</p>
<p>Is <em>thinking about something else </em>a viable strategy to escape the psychological consequences of modern cosmology?</p>
<p>Conceivably it is, up to a point. Humans evolved with basic, powerful drives towards survival and procreation, and even religiosity; they thus probably have, on average, a significant innate resistance to nihilist worldviews. Even now, well into the third millennium A.D., most of the human population professes belief in one religion or another. Also, obviously, the average person has no deep understanding of, or interest in, MWI or other modern cosmological theories.</p>
<p>Yet the things we do learn and think about ultimately affect our behavior, if only subconsciously. One doesn’t have to be a philosopher or a psychologist to understand—to take another extreme example—that if we all knew our solar system would be obliterated within a year, making it obvious that our existence was and always had been inconsequential, enough of us would fall into despair that our societies would start to disintegrate immediately.</p>
<p>I think the reason we’ve largely been able, so far, to resist the toxic implications of modern cosmology is simply that we haven’t been forced to confront them. But that situation is changing.</p>
<p>When I was growing up in the 1970s and early 80s, cosmology was expansive but still quite tame compared to what was coming. Carl Sagan’s 1980 <em>Cosmos</em> TV series on PBS, for example, was hardly despair-inducing. One could contemplate the large universe depicted by Sagan and other pop cosmologists of the time, and, as I noted above, could still fantasize about humans’ someday traversing and conquering it. MWI and other infinite-universe theories had not yet caught on, certainly not at the popular level.</p>
<p><img decoding="async" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-764" src="/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/sagan-cosmos.jpg" alt="" width="714" height="440" /></p>
<p>These days, by contrast, MWI and similar “parallel universe” themes are essential elements of pop cosmology, and, perhaps more importantly, are also common in <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Everything_Everywhere_All_at_Once">pop culture</a> generally.</p>
<p><img decoding="async" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-765" src="/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/everything-ev.jpg" alt="" width="800" height="399" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/everything-ev.jpg 800w, /wp-content/uploads/2023/01/everything-ev-768x383.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 709px) 85vw, (max-width: 909px) 67vw, (max-width: 984px) 61vw, (max-width: 1362px) 45vw, 600px" /></p>
<p>Moreover, although technologies based on quantum mechanics (such as lasers) have been around for decades, newer quantum tech such as quantum computing and quantum encryption emphasizes, for the first time, the spookier, multiplicity-of-states aspect of quantum mechanics—the aspect that MWI essentially was devised to explain. Thus, from popular science to tech to popular media culture generally, people are being exposed to the infinite-universe/multiverse idea as never before, and in ever-stronger doses.</p>
<p>The impact of that rising exposure won’t be immediately obvious. There are, and in the coming decades will continue to be, many other drivers of despair, disruption, suicide, and social disintegration in the modern world—drivers such as <a href="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/cultural-feminization-an-introduction/">cultural feminization</a>, mass immigration, and <a href="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/the-ouroboros-economy/">human-displacing AI systems</a>. Trying to disentangle the effect of one of these from the others is going to be challenging, to put it mildly. But, if my hypothesis is correct, “cosmological despair” will weigh more and more heavily and evidently on developed societies—especially among younger people, who will encounter MWI and similarly harsh cosmologies in their formative years, never having had the comforts of older, friendlier worldviews. In other words, if the world is now entering an Age of Despair principally for other reasons, cosmology will keep it there terminally.</p>
<p style="text-align: center;">*</p>
<p>There probably aren’t very many clear examples, yet, of people taking their own lives as a result of belief in MWI or other toxic cosmologies. However, something like this seems to have happened in the case of Hugh Everett III—the physicist who developed the original version of MWI (“<a href="https://www.google.com/url?sa=t&amp;rct=j&amp;q=&amp;esrc=s&amp;source=web&amp;cd=&amp;cad=rja&amp;uact=8&amp;ved=2ahUKEwieh-2-sbb8AhXvNlkFHcDLBqwQFnoECAkQAQ&amp;url=http%3A%2F%2Fwww.weylmann.com%2Frelative_state.pdf">’Relative State’ Formulation of Quantum Mechanics</a>”) as his Princeton PhD thesis in 1956.</p>
<p>Everett eventually became a financially successful tech entrepreneur and, in most ways seemed normal, being married with children, having friends, and pursuing ordinary hobbies and pleasures that included wine-making and ocean liner cruises. However . . .</p>
<p style="padding-left: 40px;">Everett firmly believed that his many-worlds theory guaranteed him immortality: His consciousness, he argued, is bound at each branching to follow whatever path does not lead to death—and so on ad infinitum. [<a href="https://space.mit.edu/home/tegmark/everett/everett.html#e24">link</a>]</p>
<p>Probably at least partly due to this belief, he smoked, drank, and ate with abandon, which ultimately gave him a <a href="https://www.washingtonpost.com/archive/local/1982/07/23/dr-hugh-everett-iii-founder-of-data-firm/16fc45d5-0e5e-445e-9714-12550bb6354e/">fatal heart attack</a> in 1982, when he was only 51 years old. In accordance with his wishes, his body was cremated and his ashes were thrown out with other household garbage.</p>
<p>A decade and a half later, Everett’s troubled 39-year-old daughter Liz took her own life even more directly. She left a note to the effect that she wanted her own ashes thrown out with the garbage, so that she might “end up in the correct parallel universe to meet up w[ith] Daddy.”</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p style="text-align: center;">***</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>THE OUROBOROS ECONOMY</title>
		<link>/the-ouroboros-economy/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[j stone]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 02 Dec 2022 04:32:55 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[economics]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[fall of the West]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[human ecology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[immigration]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[psychology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[technology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[USA]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=730</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[You are about to become obsolete. &#160; When labor becomes scarce, expensive, and/or unreliable, business owners start looking for alternatives. For most of the past 30 years, a very attractive alternative was offshoring—to countries like China, where labor was cheap, plentiful, and reliable. In the past three years, the COVID pandemic and the maturing of &#8230; <a href="/the-ouroboros-economy/" class="more-link">Continue reading<span class="screen-reader-text"> "THE OUROBOROS ECONOMY"</span></a>]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><em>You are about to become obsolete.<br />
</em></p>
<p><span id="more-730"></span></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>When labor becomes scarce, expensive, and/or unreliable, business owners start looking for alternatives. For most of the past 30 years, a very attractive alternative was offshoring—to countries like China, where labor was cheap, plentiful, and reliable. In the past three years, the COVID pandemic and the maturing of once-cheap labor markets, plus the increasing obviousness of China’s IP theft and overall hegemonic ambitions, have begun to reverse that trend. Economists are now forecasting “the end of globalization,” with labor scarcity <a href="https://www.conference-board.org/topics/recession/how-high-will-US-unemployment-go">continuing</a> for decades as the workforce shrinks. Big companies, desperate for workers, are even indicating a willingness to hire people <a href="https://www.wsj.com/articles/employers-rethink-need-for-college-degrees-in-tight-labor-market-11669432133">without college degrees </a>for positions that traditionally required them.</p>
<p>To me, though, the idea that labor will continue to be scarce seems wrong. As I see it, mechanization and AI are now moving onto the steepest part of the innovation slope, and will soon start “disemploying” people all the way up the labor value chain, from manual trades to those overpaid millennial marketing girls sipping lattes on TikTok. Even I, with my fairly challenging profession and decades of experience, am likely to be left jobless at least a few years before I’d like to retire.</p>
<p>AI has taken longer than expected to arrive in useful forms, but is now definitely arriving and ready to start disrupting. It can, technically if not yet legally, drive cars, tractors, trains, and boats; fly planes and drones; and guard warehouses. The mechanization technology underlying humanoid robots has been making big advances too—such robots now can open doors, climb stairs, recover from falls, hold and manipulate heavy objects, etc. Once such robots are mass-produced and made available for leasing, their use as replacements for factory workers, waiters, construction workers, checkout clerks, etc. will become a viable proposition. Will we have to wait as long as five years before that starts?</p>
<p>AI language-processing software that can be taught, or can teach itself via the Internet, should start displacing office worker bees well before then—and by worker bees I mean basically anyone whose job consists largely of emailing, writing reports, filling out spreadsheets, and doing other routine kinds of paperwork. And we’ve all seen the AI text-to-image and text-to-movie <a href="https://huggingface.co/spaces/stabilityai/stable-diffusion">packages</a> that were unleashed recently and have been improving at a rapid pace. How long will it be before a single writer, working with one of those algos, generates a feature-length film on his own? A year from now? Two?</p>
<p>Essentially, we’re facing the prospect of the abrupt end of the labor market, an institution that has been at the center of human civilization for millennia.</p>
<p><img decoding="async" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-732" src="/wp-content/uploads/2022/12/silent-running.jpg" alt="" width="1200" height="638" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2022/12/silent-running.jpg 1200w, /wp-content/uploads/2022/12/silent-running-768x408.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 709px) 85vw, (max-width: 909px) 67vw, (max-width: 1362px) 62vw, 840px" /></p>
<p>I’m aware that critics of earlier forms of labor-saving technology, such as the Luddites and their ilk, were somewhat shortsighted in their predictions of mass labor displacement. These early industrial workers were themselves displaced in large numbers, and in that sense had every reason to complain. What they failed to see was that the labor-saving innovations that displaced them would, on the whole, lead to greater productivity and economic growth, and ultimately a net rise in demand for labor.</p>
<p>But that was then, and this is now. The tech that’s going to be released into the world in this decade will be capable of displacing humans from their jobs much faster than the latter will be able to keep up. In other words, if you are laid off because your employer or clients can just buy an AI package to do the same job more cheaply, and you then decide to retrain for some “AI-proof” job, it’s quite likely that that “AI-proof” job will be overtaken by AI long before you can get into it. Even if that job stays available, you’d be competing for it with an exponentially rising number of other displaced human workers.</p>
<p>It’s impossible to predict in detail how this will all play out. But I can easily imagine an early phase in which language-processing AI, vehicle AI, warehouse robots, and a few other related innovations are hailed as game-changers for businesses and other organizations, allowing them to do much more with fewer workers and at less cost—and alleviating inflationary labor shortages along the way. Close on the heels of that “denial” phase, though, will come the bargaining, depression, and acceptance phases, as the pace of disemployment accelerates. I see this as an ouroboros—snake-eating-its-tail—process, because it involves the economy effectively consuming itself, i.e., destroying, with every increment of growth and investment in innovation, the employment earnings that are the principal fuel for a modern economy.</p>
<p>There may be no stable equilibrium in this process for a long while. Governments probably will try to tax businesses, especially AI-using businesses, to fund welfare payments to the unemployed masses, but will that work? Even if governments could manage it fiscally, what would be the psychological effect on tens of millions of people who can no longer earn a living for themselves? (We already know that <a href="https://blogs.lse.ac.uk/politicsandpolicy/men-are-more-likely-to-suffer-adverse-health-consequences-as-a-result-of-unemployment-than-women/">men become easily depressed when unemployed</a>.)</p>
<p><img decoding="async" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-734" src="/wp-content/uploads/2022/12/wall-e.jpg" alt="" width="790" height="331" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2022/12/wall-e.jpg 790w, /wp-content/uploads/2022/12/wall-e-768x322.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 709px) 85vw, (max-width: 909px) 67vw, (max-width: 984px) 61vw, (max-width: 1362px) 45vw, 600px" /></p>
<p>It also seems unlikely that Western governments would ever simply disallow the use of AI and robotics. One of the great lessons of the mass immigration era is that Western governments, ostensibly “democratic,” <em>like</em> having electorates made up of financially stressed people whose votes can be bought with government largesse.</p>
<p>It stands to reason that the disemployment situation will be easier in countries that currently have relatively small workforces—or rely on guest workers who can be sent quickly back to their home countries if needed. By the same logic, countries with open borders and huge, low-skill, permanent immigrant populations, like the US, could be in serious trouble. Those countries will suddenly have many millions of excess mouths to feed, and to do so might easily require taxation levels that trigger capital flight.</p>
<p>I’m not totally averse to the idea that at the end of this transition lies a society in which robots do everything for near-zero cost and humans can stay busy however they like without worrying much about money. But it’s hard to believe this transition will occur without historic levels of pain. I’ve written often in this space about various drivers of Western decline, collapse, and general upheaval; the now-imminent “ouroboros economy” of AI and robotics is surely another one.</p>
<p style="text-align: center;">***</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>IT&#8217;S NOT &#8220;WOKENESS&#8221;&#8212;IT&#8217;S WOMEN</title>
		<link>/its-not-wokeness-its-women/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[j stone]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 10 Oct 2022 04:49:27 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[ethnicity]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[fall of the West]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[freedom of speech]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[ideas]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[immigration]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[psychology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[science]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[wokeism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[women]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=682</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[The rise of wokeness, ESG, the trans mania, etc. is all due to women&#8217;s new power in institutions The new Western culture, especially the American variety, offers the old-fashioned conservative male dissident many trends to bewail. Discrimination against white males! Promotion of LGBTQ lifestyles! The trans mania with its mutilation of children and destruction of &#8230; <a href="/its-not-wokeness-its-women/" class="more-link">Continue reading<span class="screen-reader-text"> "IT&#8217;S NOT &#8220;WOKENESS&#8221;&#8212;IT&#8217;S WOMEN"</span></a>]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><em>The rise of wokeness, ESG, the trans mania, etc. is all due to women&#8217;s new power in institutions</em></p>
<p><span id="more-682"></span></p>
<p>The new Western culture, especially the American variety, offers the old-fashioned conservative male dissident many trends to bewail. Discrimination against white males! Promotion of LGBTQ lifestyles! The trans mania with its mutilation of children and destruction of women’s sports! Suppression of meritocracy, free speech, free scientific inquiry, and due process of law! Runaway entitlement spending! Open borders! Critical race theory! The ESG investing fad! No-prosecute policies in violent cities! Proliferation of social contagions and hysterical illnesses, from ROGD and PTSD to Tik-Tok Tourette’s! Cascades of cancellations of perfectly competent white males, e.g., for “<a href="https://www.theguardian.com/us-news/2022/oct/06/nyu-professor-fired-maitland-jones-jr-student-petition">grading too hard in organic chemistry</a>,” or for <a href="https://www.nydailynews.com/news/national/ny-apple-exec-fired-tiktok-arthur-20220930-rdsgzpbzr5anxjyqar5avuiyv4-story.html">cracking an off-color joke</a>! Widespread exclusion (in effect) of males from important professions, including public relations, publishing, and clinical psychology/psychotherapy. “Math is White Supremacy!” “Showing up for work is White Supremacy!!” “Not being a pea-brained slob is White Supremacy!!!”</p>
<p>My argument here is that everybody should <em>stop</em> bewailing these trends as separate phenomena—should stop fighting “wokeness” or “ESG” or the trans mania. They should, instead, focus on the one factor that underlies and causes all of these social developments.</p>
<p>Of course, I mean <em>women</em>—or more precisely, women’s newfound power in organizations and institutions, and in the culture generally.</p>
<p>An assumption everyone seems to have made during the decades of female emancipation is that women see things more or less as men do, and are just as devoted as men to the principles underlying Western civilization. Not so! As some feminist writers, including Virginia Woolf, warned long ago, women when they enter public life in business and government tend to look around and see lots of things they want to change. They’re just not fans, to the extent that men are, of things like free speech, open debate, due process of law, meritocracy, free scientific inquiry, maximizing shareholder value, equality of opportunity, and so on.</p>
<p>It’s not that women have worked things out logically and carefully and comprehensively, and now want to formally enact a scheme they think is better. It’s more that things in Western civ, which was made by men, often go against the emotional grain with women, causing them real discomfort, and compelling them to react. Women’s instincts were shaped by evolution for a maternal and domestic context, and seem to bias them towards short-term, feelgood, nurturing, and protective outcomes—on average compared to men. These instincts seem to be especially aroused by things like persistent racial inequality, discussions of race-based IQ differences, ruthless meritocratic competition unleavened by sympathy for the losers, stern cross-examinations of women making rape claims, medical skepticism over women&#8217;s unverifiable symptoms, and the kind of frat-boy humor that has gotten so many men cancelled. Now that women are largely in charge, they question why we need such things—or peremptorily try to stamp them out.</p>
<p>There are some nuances to this general theory. First, a lot of women are not woke. But the argument here is really about women on average as compared to men on average, and I don’t think it could be reasonably disputed that women, on average and compared to men, are significantly biased in the direction of wokeness. It’s also obviously true that modest average psychological differences between the sexes could translate to big social changes when one sex takes power from the other. I would suggest too that the women who seek power in institutions are less likely to be “average” women and more likely to be childless activist types. There is, moreover, a hell of a lot of depression and anxiety among modern women, especially younger ones, and that as well may push many women to embrace the woke activism mindset as a therapeutic source of meaning and purpose.</p>
<p>Another nuance has to do with women’s apparently superior ability, compared to men, to align themselves emotionally within a group. This means, in effect, that women in an organization will tend to be less independent-minded, with the tradeoff that they can collectively punch above their weight. Among the examples that come to mind is the recent <a href="https://www.tmz.com/2020/03/06/woody-allen-memoir-canceled-hachette-publisher-staff-walkout/">cancellation of Woody Allen</a> from his publisher due to activism among the publishing company’s <em>junior staff</em>. (The publishing industry, like public relations and psychology/psychiatry/psychotherapy, is utterly dominated by women—“junior staff” in publishing generally means millennial women.)</p>
<p>Women, as I’ve suggested in a recent <a href="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/always-be-capturing/">essay</a>, may also have, collectively, a stronger drive to dominate organizations, to eliminate the greater discomfort they experience when exposed to male organizational culture. Certainly the female-to-male ratio in many organizations now is one that would be condemned as discriminatory (by women) were the proportions reversed.</p>
<p>A further nuance, which I think will become increasingly obvious and important as our societal &#8220;<a href="https://americanmind.org/salvo/pink-shift/">pink shift</a>&#8221; advances, is that women, as they align emotionally within groups, and ultimately purge dissenting voices, tend to cause the institutions they control to become unstable. In other words, like hysteria-prone convents of half a millenium ago, female-dominated institutions become relatively susceptible to groupthink contagions that swing them irrationally this way and that. Today these contagions introduce relatively mild new absurdities like pronoun declarations and land acknowledgments. But I expect it&#8217;s all going to get loopier, and more harshly enforced, as time goes on and female control solidifies.</p>
<p>Lastly, somewhat hair-splittingly, I don’t think that women when left to themselves running male-built institutions <em>necessarily</em> become woke in the way that we see now. I see wokeness as a contemporary, contagious mindset (not quite an ideology) that corresponds very well to, and thus easily infects, the average female mind, still moreso the younger, more neurotic, more activist female mind. But in principle, under different circumstances, one could gin up something substantially different that would also spread well among women, provided that it pressed their main buttons. Certainly in the centuries before women took such a large part in public life, thought contagions among them were common and varied, though usually localized and rarely very consequential (rarely but not never—see, for example, the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Salem_witch_trials">Salem Witchcraft Hysteria</a>).</p>
<p>But back to my main argument: If wokeness and its variants are all epiphenomena of the new, historically unprecedented power of women in public life, measures taken against wokeness etc. could be ineffective if there is no acknowledgment of the true source of the problem. Indeed all means short of <em>reducing women’s presence in public life</em> might be futile.</p>
<p>I’m not advocating a specific strategy, but I think it’s important at least to highlight this dilemma, which Western countries obviously have no easy way of resolving. It may be that over time, the current, Cultural Revolution-like surge of wokeness subsides and becomes less radical, as the women pushing wokeness are increasingly forced to acknowledge some of its adverse consequences, such as rising crime from weak law enforcement, social dissolution from uncontrolled immigration, the institutional incompetence that flows inevitably from the abandonment of meritocracy, and the aforementioned institutional instability.</p>
<p>Then again, by the time things get bad enough for women to acknowledge that they aren&#8217;t necessarily better than men at managing our civilization, the process of degeneration might be very, very advanced. Indeed, it&#8217;s plausible that, by then, other, even stronger, less reversible adverse processes—ethnic conflict, for example—will be underway, effectively sealing the West’s fate.</p>
<p style="text-align: center;">***</p>
<p><em>Author’s note:</em></p>
<p><em>I’d appreciate it, reader, if you would link to my essays on cultural feminization (or otherwise cite them) wherever you see this topic being discussed. I’ve been writing about “cult-fem” for more than a decade—which, as far as I know, is much longer than anyone else. Some of my essays have <a href="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/cultural-feminization-a-bibliography/">circulated widely</a></em><em> in recent years, and I’ve even placed <a href="https://americanmind.org/salvo/pink-shift/">one</a></em><em> in a moderately well-read webzine. I like to think that my contributions have helped seed what is becoming an important public discourse. Yet those contributions of mine are almost never acknowledged by the better-known opinionators who have ventured into this realm in the last year or so. Being pseudonymous and writing principally from a personal website seem to have left me in the unhappy state of being “much read but seldom cited.” (I discuss the general problem of citation in the Internet age in my short essay “<a href="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/the-tree-of-knowledge/">The Tree of Knowledge</a></em><em>.”)</em></p>
<p><em>Also, though I don’t charge a subscription to this website, or put ads on it, or even solicit donations, you could buy a copy of my e-book (see image below, linked to its Amazon page) if you’d like to support my writing.</em></p>
<p style="text-align: center;">*</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>WOMEN, INCLUSIVITY AND THE PALEOLITHIC</title>
		<link>/women-inclusivity-and-the-paleolithic/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[j stone]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 05 Sep 2022 00:10:24 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[fall of the West]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Paleolithic]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[psychology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[wokeism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[women]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=666</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[A hypothesis about the origin of some female psychological traits &#160; One of the traits that women seem generally willing to acknowledge as their own is a greater affinity for “inclusivity” and the related “equity.” In other words, compared to the average man, the average woman seems to have a stronger preference for a society &#8230; <a href="/women-inclusivity-and-the-paleolithic/" class="more-link">Continue reading<span class="screen-reader-text"> "WOMEN, INCLUSIVITY AND THE PALEOLITHIC"</span></a>]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><em>A hypothesis about the origin of some female psychological traits</em></p>
<p><span id="more-666"></span></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>One of the traits that women seem generally willing to acknowledge as their own is a greater affinity for “inclusivity” and the related “equity.” In other words, compared to the average man, the average woman seems to have a stronger preference for a society in which meritocratic competition and rewards, and the resulting inequalities, are minimized. To the extent that this is so, women (compared to men) would therefore tend to prefer flatter, more egalitarian and less hierarchical social groupings&#8212;as has often been observed.</p>
<p>Meritocratic competition and hierarchical ordering are among the pillars of Western civilization, so it should be concerning if these are now being weakened by the <a href="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/cultural-feminization-an-introduction/">cultural and political ascendancy of women</a>. However, this brief essay is not (mainly) a judgment of the fitness of this feminine trait-set—it’s a speculation about its origins.</p>
<p>Has anyone done a conclusive study of why women are relatively inclined towards inclusivity/equity and against competition, meritocracy and hierarchy? If so, I’m unaware of it. Since human traits typically are rooted in the prehistoric past, I’m not sure a conclusive study of such a thing is even possible.</p>
<p>In any case, let us assume that these female biases do have primordial roots. What could those roots be?</p>
<p>As I’ve suggested <a href="https://www.amazon.com/dp/B09Z7MWJ7R">elsewhere</a>, and I guess is the obvious, default explanation, wanting to promote inclusivity/equity could have originated and persisted as a maternal instinct. This instinct would have worked to inhibit the otherwise inevitable rivalries and battles among a mother’s children, thus perhaps increasing their summed chances of surviving to adulthood and reproducing.</p>
<p>Is this “maternal-origin hypothesis” the end of the story? Or can other aspects of prehistoric life also account for the egalitarianism of the modern female mindset?</p>
<p>The primitive social structure in which <em>H. sapiens</em> is thought to have lived the longest—by far—was the extended family-based band that dominated the Paleolithic (“hunter-gatherer”) period. This basic mode of existence was practiced by humans, and perhaps also by their hominin ancestors, for millions of years, whereas more advanced social forms have been shaping us for only the last 10,000 years or so, i.e., the period following the Neolithic revolution.</p>
<p>From a modern perspective, one of the more striking features of the typical Paleolithic social grouping—which still can be observed in various remote parts of the world—is its lack of what we would call private property, a strong share-and-share-alike ethic, and a simple, non-hierarchical, “flat” organization. The 1980 South African film, <em>The Gods Must be Crazy</em>, did a decent job of depicting one such group (of Kalahari Bushmen) and the possessiveness and envy that threatened their harmony when they discovered an unusual and valuable object (a Coca-Cola bottle, dropped from a passing airplane).</p>
<p><img decoding="async" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-667" src="/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/gods.jpg" alt="" width="800" height="448" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/gods.jpg 800w, /wp-content/uploads/2022/09/gods-300x168.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2022/09/gods-768x430.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 709px) 85vw, (max-width: 909px) 67vw, (max-width: 984px) 61vw, (max-width: 1362px) 45vw, 600px" /></p>
<p>The implication of the story, and indeed of standard anthropological descriptions of such bands, is that egalitarianism is and was necessary to keep these groups together—and keeping these groups together presumably conferred some evolutionary advantage by improving the survival chances and overall Darwinian fitness of their constituent individuals.</p>
<p>As Francis Fukuyama has put it in <em>The Origins of Political Order</em>:</p>
<p style="padding-left: 40px;">Within a band-level local group, there is nothing resembling modern economic exchange and, indeed, nothing resembling modern individualism . . . Both hunting and gathering are done on a group basis by families or groups of families. Hunting in particular leads to sharing, since there is no technology for storing meat, and hunted animals must be consumed immediately . . . Many of the moral rules in this type of society are not directed at individuals who steal other people’s property but <em>rather against those who refuse to share food and other necessities</em>. Under conditions of perpetual scarcity, the failure to share can often affect the group’s prospects for survival. Band-level societies are highly egalitarian . . . within the band, there is relatively little differentiation between families, no permanent leadership, and <em>no hierarchy</em>. [my italics]</p>
<p>That this “paleo mindset” corresponds to key aspects of the modern female mindset points to the possibility that the one helped seed the other—in other words, that the relative female preference for inclusivity and equity in modern times originated not only in maternity but also in the social organization that dominated during the Paleolithic.</p>
<p>As for men, it seems likely that with the Neolithic revolution and the rise of towns, cities, private property, hierarchical government, stratified societies, meritocratic competition for wealth and status, and so on, their mindset was reshaped for this more structured and competitive environment. (This, incidentally, would have given Neolithic men a huge edge over their more peaceful, less competition-minded hunter-gatherer counterparts—an edge that is still painfully evident wherever modern and paleo-type peoples are in contact.)</p>
<p><img decoding="async" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-668" src="/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/crudes.jpg" alt="" width="800" height="400" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/crudes.jpg 800w, /wp-content/uploads/2022/09/crudes-300x150.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2022/09/crudes-768x384.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 709px) 85vw, (max-width: 909px) 67vw, (max-width: 984px) 61vw, (max-width: 1362px) 45vw, 600px" /></p>
<p>The female mindset would not have been reshaped to the same extent by the Neolithic revolution if, as I suspect, this revolution brought much less change to women’s lives and roles. Women were still principally concerned with raising children, and in that context their relative preferences for inclusivity and equity, and aversions to competition and hierarchy, would have remained adaptive. Women’s roles in farming also might not have represented a big departure from their gathering lifestyle of paleo days. And although female sexual competition would have made more and more sense in a world where men’s status began to vary greatly, it’s unclear that women—often treated as patriarchal property before marriage in premodern times—had much freedom to engage in such competition until relatively recently. Certainly the competitions for wealth, status, and power that the Neolithic revolution and town/city life introduced would have been almost entirely male pursuits.</p>
<p>Of course, the trait differences resulting from these distinct roles and selection pressures would not have been absolute. Men and women differ genetically by only a single chromosome among 23 pairs of them, and the outcome of that tiny genetic difference is mediated by the environment as well as by factors such as sex hormones, whose doses during development can vary considerably. Just as some women are on the mannish side of the distribution of looks, some would have been on the mannish side of the distributions of psychological traits.</p>
<p>In the same way, or through other mechanisms of atavism, some men even in modern societies would continue to be very “paleo” and egalitarian in their thinking. It’s tempting to speculate further that this reversion, with its associated conviction that simpler times were better times, underlies some relatively old religions and political movements, including Christianity and socialism*—which, though they were invented by men, tend now to be favored more by women.</p>
<p>In any case, to sum up the main idea here: Key feminine psychological traits favoring inclusivity and equity and opposing hierarchy—traits that seem especially influential now as drivers of social change in the era of female empowerment—may have had their origins in the band-level social organization that dominated the Paleolithic period, not just in maternity per se.</p>
<p>I’ll grant that I’m not a professional anthropologist, and my idea here is not particularly complicated or sophisticated. I’m sure there’s a lot more to be said about the origins of sex-specific psychological traits. But my idea seems worth considering—indeed I think anthropologists would have suggested and explored it already, if their feminized, wokeified profession hadn’t effectively suppressed this and many other areas of inquiry.</p>
<p>Incidentally, my hypothesis itself suggests why this suppression is occurring. If women’s instincts on issues relating to inclusivity, equity, and hierarchy are instincts adapted for maternity and a primordial, long-outmoded social structure, then in modern societies these instincts are probably <em>mal</em>adaptive when expressed in the public policy realm, however suited they may still be for family life and the raising of children. Even as a hypothesis, this is not a view that feminists can ever tolerate.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>*Marx considered paleolithic bands the original communist societies.</p>
<p style="text-align: center;">* * *</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>CULTURAL FEMINIZATION: AN INTRODUCTION</title>
		<link>/cultural-feminization-an-introduction/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[j stone]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 24 Aug 2022 23:24:31 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[fall of the West]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[freedom of speech]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[psychology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[science]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[testosterone]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[wokeism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[women]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=641</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[&#160; A quick summary for those coming to this for the first time. &#160; I’ve been in the habit of citing one of my 2019 essays, “The Great Feminization” or “The Day the Logic Died,” as an introduction to the idea of cultural feminization. Since those pieces were written, though, I’ve posted other essays on &#8230; <a href="/cultural-feminization-an-introduction/" class="more-link">Continue reading<span class="screen-reader-text"> "CULTURAL FEMINIZATION: AN INTRODUCTION"</span></a>]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><em>A quick summary for those coming to this for the first time.</em></p>
<p><span id="more-641"></span></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>I’ve been in the habit of citing one of my 2019 essays, “<a href="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/the-great-feminization/">The Great Feminization</a>” or “<a href="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/the-day-the-logic-died/">The Day the Logic Died</a>,” as an introduction to the idea of cultural feminization. Since those pieces were written, though, I’ve posted other essays on this topic, expanding this “idea space” a bit more with each one. So it might be useful now, to those coming to this for the first time, to have an updated short summary of the whole picture as I see it.</p>
<p><strong>In a Nutshell</strong></p>
<p>Women, because of their different ways of thinking and behaving on average, and their new, strong influence over culture and politics, are the principal drivers of modern social change, including all aspects of wokeness.</p>
<p><strong>From Home to Office</strong></p>
<p>American women—whose sociocultural circumstances are very similar to those of other Western women—obtained full equality in voting rights by constitutional amendment more than a century ago. That had significant cultural and political consequences, but it was only a small part of the story of women’s modern empowerment. The big change occurred in the period 1950-2000, when women shifted, <em>en masse</em> and on a durable, peacetime basis, from being dedicated homemakers to participating more or less equally alongside men in the working world and public life. The labor force participation rate charts below (the first for American men, the second for women) clearly show this shift.</p>
<p><img decoding="async" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-652" src="/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/fredgraph-men.jpg" alt="" width="1168" height="470" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/fredgraph-men.jpg 1168w, /wp-content/uploads/2022/08/fredgraph-men-300x121.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2022/08/fredgraph-men-1024x412.jpg 1024w, /wp-content/uploads/2022/08/fredgraph-men-768x309.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 709px) 85vw, (max-width: 909px) 67vw, (max-width: 1362px) 62vw, 840px" /><img decoding="async" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-653" src="/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/fredgraph-women.jpg" alt="" width="1168" height="470" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/fredgraph-women.jpg 1168w, /wp-content/uploads/2022/08/fredgraph-women-300x121.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2022/08/fredgraph-women-1024x412.jpg 1024w, /wp-content/uploads/2022/08/fredgraph-women-768x309.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 709px) 85vw, (max-width: 909px) 67vw, (max-width: 1362px) 62vw, 840px" /></p>
<p>As I wrote in “<a href="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/the-great-feminization/">The Great Feminization</a>”:</p>
<p style="padding-left: 40px;">The historic significance of this migration on its own appears to have been underappreciated. Women never made such a move, to such a degree, in any large human society in the past. It significantly altered the structure of ordinary life.</p>
<p style="padding-left: 40px;">But women in the late 20th century didn’t just move into the workforce. They moved into its upper ranks, to professions that strongly influence societal culture and policy. They became journalists, public relations specialists, lawyers, academics, novelists, publishers, filmmakers, TV producers, and politicians, all to an unprecedented extent. In some of these culture-making professions, by the 1990s and early 2000s, they had achieved parity or even dominance (e.g., writers, authors, and public relations specialists) with respect to men. Even where they fell short of full parity, they appeared to acquire considerable “veto” power over content. A 2017 report by the Women’s Media Center noted evidence that at the vast majority of media companies, at least one woman is among the top three editors.</p>
<p><strong>Women Think Differently About Cultural and Political Matters</strong></p>
<p>Women’s ascension to power in culture- and policy-making professions has been followed by extensive cultural and political changes. Why? Because women, on average, think differently than men do about cultural and political issues. This should not be surprising: The bodies and minds of women and men were shaped long ago by biological and cultural evolution for their distinct traditional roles in life. Women’s distinct roles obviously have required certain psychological traits or tendencies that are different from male traits. I think most of us would agree that these innately feminine traits include:</p>
<ol>
<li style="list-style-type: none;">
<ul>
<li>A greater emotional sensitivity and capacity for empathy/compassion/nurturing.</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ol>
<ul>
<li style="list-style-type: none;">
<ul>
<li>A greater fearfulness and aversion to risks (concerning dangers to themselves and others), including an extra sensitivity to the risks of toxic and other environmental threats (reflected in hormone-driven pregnancy behaviors such as food/odor aversions and compulsive “nesting”).</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<ul>
<li style="list-style-type: none;">
<ul>
<li>A greater affinity for people and relationships, and lesser affinity for constructed, systemized, and abstract things.</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<ul>
<li style="list-style-type: none;">
<ul>
<li>A greater tendency to align emotionally when in a group, especially a group of other women—a tendency that implies a superior ability (individually and collectively) to transmit emotions and other social contagions.</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<ul>
<li style="list-style-type: none;">
<ul>
<li>A reduced affinity for competition and capacity for resistance to aggressors.</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<ul>
<li style="list-style-type: none;">
<ul>
<li>Greater affinity for themes of suffering and victimhood, with correspondingly less interest in triumphant “male” themes of exploration and conquest.</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<p>Probably most of these traits are interrelated. In any case, when one considers these broad aspects of “innate femininity,” it isn’t hard to see that the very sudden extension of their dominance—from women’s traditional domestic domain to all areas of public life—would help account for the dramatic social changes of the past half-century or so.</p>
<p>It also isn’t hard to see that women tend to support these social changes more than men do—although it&#8217;s important to understand that by altering the culture, women have influenced not only their own but also <em>men’s</em> thinking and behavior.</p>
<p><strong>Social changes likely to have been driven by the ascendancy of female traits</strong></p>
<ul>
<li style="list-style-type: none;">
<ul>
<li>Much more generous welfare programs.</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<ul>
<li style="list-style-type: none;">
<ul>
<li>Extensions of the concept of welfare to include more types of intervention (e.g., affirmative action) and more groups needing intervention (“traditionally marginalized groups”).</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<ul>
<li style="list-style-type: none;">
<ul>
<li>Excessively honoring (e.g., with pronoun declaration rituals) anyone with a claim to victimhood or some other “special identity” status.</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<ul>
<li style="list-style-type: none;">
<ul>
<li>Very strong social reactions to media portrayals of racial injustice/inequity, e.g., the near-hysterias following the police killings of Michael Brown in Ferguson, MO and George Floyd in Minneapolis, MN.</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<p><img decoding="async" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-225" src="/wp-content/uploads/2021/06/bethesdaawokening-1.jpg" alt="" width="800" height="450" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2021/06/bethesdaawokening-1.jpg 800w, /wp-content/uploads/2021/06/bethesdaawokening-1-300x169.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2021/06/bethesdaawokening-1-768x432.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 709px) 85vw, (max-width: 909px) 67vw, (max-width: 984px) 61vw, (max-width: 1362px) 45vw, 600px" /></p>
<ul>
<li style="list-style-type: none;">
<ul>
<li>Inflations of the traditional definitions of “harm,” “offense,” “trauma,” “violence,” “aggression,” etc., as reflected in new terms such as “microaggressions” and “triggers.”</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<ul>
<li style="list-style-type: none;">
<ul>
<li>An astounding belief (from men’s perspective) in slight or even imaginary emotional upsets as sources of real harm in the world. This belief is reflected in everyday female-produced media content but also in the new hyper-focus on psychological trauma in law and medicine, and of course in the vast inflation of trauma-related syndromes such as PTSD (and the recovered-trauma-memory syndromes of the 1980s/90s, before they were discredited).</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<ul>
<li style="list-style-type: none;">
<ul>
<li>A shift away from the traditional deterrence of criminal behavior with punishment and stigmatization, in preference for compassion-based, non-stigmatizing solutions (e.g., non-prosecute policies for most crimes, free needles for addicts).</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<ul>
<li style="list-style-type: none;">
<ul>
<li>Reduced tolerance of deaths in war, despite (ironically) a greater inclination to enter foreign conflicts in response to emotion-evoking atrocities portrayed on television.</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<p><img decoding="async" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-644" src="/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/boy1.jpg" alt="" width="194" height="259" /></p>
<ul>
<li style="list-style-type: none;">
<ul>
<li>Less tolerance for capital punishment and other harsh sentences, especially where the “traditionally disadvantaged” are concerned.</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<ul>
<li style="list-style-type: none;">
<ul>
<li>Less restrictive immigration policy, again driven by stories and imagery (pitiable refugee children, huddled masses, etc.) that evoke maternal protective/nurturing instincts.</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<p><img decoding="async" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-646" src="/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/refugee.jpg" alt="" width="800" height="524" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/refugee.jpg 800w, /wp-content/uploads/2022/08/refugee-300x197.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2022/08/refugee-768x503.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 709px) 85vw, (max-width: 909px) 67vw, (max-width: 984px) 61vw, (max-width: 1362px) 45vw, 600px" /></p>
<ul>
<li style="list-style-type: none;">
<ul>
<li>In general, much more emphasis in media and policy contexts on compassion-evoking stories of individuals, with correspondingly less emphasis on (even condemnation of!) coldly logical risk/benefit analyses focused on the long term.</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<ul>
<li style="list-style-type: none;">
<ul>
<li>Suppression of potentially upsetting ideas or expressions (“hate speech,” “mansplaining”), words, facts (e.g., on racial differences in criminality), free debate and free speech, due process of law (especially when women are plaintiffs), and even some fields of scientific inquiry.</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<ul>
<li style="list-style-type: none;">
<ul>
<li>Helicopter parenting.</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<ul>
<li style="list-style-type: none;">
<ul>
<li>Obsession with safety, e.g., as seen in new terms such as “safe space.”</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<ul>
<li style="list-style-type: none;">
<ul>
<li>Rise of “green” movement and related cultural themes involving opposition to nuclear power, GMO, “toxins,” “chemicals,” even vaccines (a movement that was increasing in popularity, with female leadership, pre-COVID-19). Related shift towards “natural” foods and medicines, including those produced by the relatively unregulated supplements industry. Rise of hysteria variants involving claims of chemical hypersensitivity, toxic metals, etc.</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<ul>
<li style="list-style-type: none;">
<ul>
<li>Decline in interest in engineering, as shown by greater reliance on foreign-born students at e-schools, loss of Western pre-eminence (to China) in advanced engineering projects.</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<ul>
<li style="list-style-type: none;">
<ul>
<li>Predominance of “social media” in Western life.</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<ul>
<li style="list-style-type: none;">
<ul>
<li>Shift away from technical themes and toward social (woke) themes in female-dominated STEM media and professions, e.g., “math is white supremacist.”</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<ul>
<li style="list-style-type: none;">
<ul>
<li>Shift away from traditional, hierarchical, rule-based religions toward more loosely structured and therapeutic forms of worship and spirituality.</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<ul>
<li style="list-style-type: none;">
<ul>
<li>Frequent and rapid social contagions of new cultural themes (e.g., wokeness and its various associated behaviors and terminology, from BLM worship to the trans mania), affecting virtually all organizations and institutions&#8212;because women, the chief transmitters of these contagions, are highly influential in organizations and institutions.</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<ul>
<li style="list-style-type: none;">
<ul>
<li>Increase in the frequency and prevalence of overtly pathological social contagions (hysterias) such as Tik-Tok-induced Tourette’s-like behavior.</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<ul>
<li style="list-style-type: none;">
<ul>
<li>Tendency of professions and institutions to become female-dominated by systematically excluding (especially white) males—who are “problematic” for grouped women, simply because of their innate male resistance to institutional feminization.</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<ul>
<li style="list-style-type: none;">
<ul>
<li>General increase in intolerant, “hive-mind” behavior in institutions and professions as a consequence of increasing female dominance.</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<ul>
<li style="list-style-type: none;">
<ul>
<li>Marked preference for inclusivity and equity over traditional meritocratic discrimination, everywhere from schools to companies to political appointees and candidates. “Participation trophies.”</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<ul>
<li style="list-style-type: none;">
<ul>
<li>Virtually uniform emphasis on victimhood themes in Western literary fiction, coincident with female takeover of publishing industry.</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<ul>
<li style="list-style-type: none;">
<ul>
<li>Reduced public interest in adventurous endeavors such as manned space exploration (“we should fix poverty and inequality here on Earth first”).</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<ul>
<li style="list-style-type: none;">
<ul>
<li>Demotion of traditional heroes such as Christopher Columbus and Thomas Jefferson and promotion of their alleged victims, e.g., Native Americans, Sally Hemings.</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<p>Obviously, not every woman out there likes or is driving these changes. The differences between men’s and women’s mindsets are differences <em>on average</em>.</p>
<p><img decoding="async" class="aligncenter wp-image-12" src="/wp-content/uploads/2020/07/coulter-twitr.jpg" alt="" width="472" height="134" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2020/07/coulter-twitr.jpg 578w, /wp-content/uploads/2020/07/coulter-twitr-300x85.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 472px) 85vw, 472px" /></p>
<p>Moreover, the mindset underlying these shifts—a mindset that, in some of these cases, seems sensitive to the point of neuroticism—might not even be that of the <em>average</em> woman. I suspect it more closely represents the attitudes of the single, childless activists who have been most energetic in pushing these social changes. For them, perhaps, society and its “disadvantaged,” from African-Americans to Rio Grande-crossing illegal immigrants, are substitutes for the children they don’t have.</p>
<p><strong>Cultural Feminization is Problematic</strong></p>
<p>One sufficient and conservative reason for doubting that cultural feminization is a good thing is simply that it entails the abrupt replacement of a large set of civilizational traits that were embedded in Western people, culturally and probably biologically, over thousands of years. Not every Western trait is essential to the West’s survival or is even still adaptive in the modern world. But discarding these traits at the whim of female activists seems a bit like deleting genes willy-nilly from the human genome. Could you do that without bad consequences? Yes, conceivably&#8212;but it&#8217;s far more likely to end in disaster.</p>
<p>Another good reason to oppose or limit cultural feminization is that, while men traditionally led societies and thus would have been expected to evolve attitudes and behaviors appropriate for that role, women traditionally were confined to other, more private roles, centering on maternity. In other words, why should we suppose that being a mother, or being shaped by evolution for motherhood, is a better preparation for public life than . . . serving in public life, as men have done for ages?</p>
<p>There are further reasons that have to do with specific effects of feminization. For example, feminization appears to have brought a new cultural and political emphasis on short-term, feelgood consequences, with less emphasis on—I would say a blindness to—long-term consequences. It should be obvious that this is unsustainable and must end badly.</p>
<p>Moreover, females&#8217; lesser affinity, even hostility, for due process of law, free debate, unfettered scientific inquiry, and related aspects of Western, small-l liberalism, seems likely to render the West relatively static, sclerotic, and poor if allowed to run to its logical conclusion.</p>
<p>Then, of course, there is the apparent female (relative to male) embrace of mass immigration to the West from the Third World, which I think has the potential to dissolve Western societies faster than any other factor.</p>
<p><img decoding="async" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-165" src="/wp-content/uploads/2021/03/merkel-1.jpg" alt="" width="600" height="422" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2021/03/merkel-1.jpg 600w, /wp-content/uploads/2021/03/merkel-1-300x211.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 709px) 85vw, (max-width: 909px) 67vw, (max-width: 984px) 61vw, (max-width: 1362px) 45vw, 600px" /></p>
<p>I think it’s worth mentioning too, though it&#8217;s more speculative, that the apparent decades-long slide in testosterone levels in men might be an effect of cultural feminization. Testosterone levels in men (and women) are known to be regulated by social cues, such as winning or losing competitions, and so <a href="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/testosterone-civilization-and-social-cues/">it would make sense</a> that cultural messaging condemning and suppressing traditional masculinity would have a T-lowering effect. Lower T means lower fertility, which below a certain threshold—one that Legacy Americans sank beneath long ago—leads ultimately to the extinction of the population.</p>
<p>Lastly, there is the sense of <em>taboo</em> that enshrouds the idea of cultural feminization, in general but especially when it is framed negatively. The high-profile MSM types (<a href="https://www.bloomberg.com/opinion/articles/2021-09-19/woke-movement-is-global-and-america-should-be-mostly-proud">Cowen</a>, <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2022/01/12/opinion/gender-gap-politics.html">Edsall</a>) who have touched the subject (only in the last year or so, as far as I know) have been approving or very mild in their concerns. Also, for more than a decade now, most of the short essays I’ve tried to get published on this subject, including in some pretty right wing publications, have been rejected. In every case, a female editor had veto power, and I think her male colleagues also feared the hostile ululations that would ensue if they published my unvarnished take. Anyhow, an old quote (often attributed to Voltaire) seems apt here: “If you want to know who rules over you, look at whom you’re not allowed to criticize.”</p>
<p><strong>Further reading</strong></p>
<p>&#8220;<a href="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/the-great-feminization/">The Great Feminization</a>&#8221; (2019)</p>
<p>&#8220;<a href="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/the-day-the-logic-died/">The Day the Logic Died</a>&#8221; (2019)</p>
<p>&#8220;<a href="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/cultural-feminization-a-bibliography/">Cultural Feminization: a Bibliography</a>&#8221; (2021)</p>
<p><a href="https://www.amazon.com/dp/B09Z7MWJ7R"><em>The Great Feminization: Women as Drivers of Modern Social Change</em></a> (2022)</p>
<p style="text-align: center;">* * *</p>
<p><em>Author’s note:</em></p>
<p><em>I’d appreciate it, reader, if you would link to my essays on cultural feminization (or otherwise cite them) wherever you see this topic being discussed. I’ve been writing about “cult-fem” for more than a decade—which, as far as I know, is much longer than anyone else. Some of my essays have <a href="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/cultural-feminization-a-bibliography/">circulated widely</a></em><em> in recent years, and I’ve even placed <a href="https://americanmind.org/salvo/pink-shift/">one</a></em><em> in a moderately well-read webzine. I like to think that my contributions have helped seed what is becoming an important public discourse. Yet those contributions of mine are almost never acknowledged by the better-known opinionators who have ventured into this realm in the last year or so. Being pseudonymous and writing principally from a personal website seem to have left me in the unhappy state of being “much read but seldom cited.” (I discuss the general problem of citation in the Internet age in my short essay “<a href="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/the-tree-of-knowledge/">The Tree of Knowledge</a></em><em>.”)</em></p>
<p><em>Also, though I don’t charge a subscription to this website, or put ads on it, or even solicit donations, you could buy a copy of my e-book (see image below, linked to its Amazon page) if you’d like to support my writing.</em></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>TESTOSTERONE, CIVILIZATION, AND SOCIAL CUES</title>
		<link>/testosterone-civilization-and-social-cues/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[j stone]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 14 Jul 2022 22:08:56 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[fall of the West]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[psychology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[science]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[testosterone]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[women]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=621</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Adapted from a chapter in my recent book, The Great Feminization&#8230; &#160; From conception through adolescence, male and female humans—mammals in general—are driven along distinct neural and anatomical developmental pathways by androgen and estrogen hormones, men having more of the former, women having more of the latter. The divergences in those developmental pathways lead to &#8230; <a href="/testosterone-civilization-and-social-cues/" class="more-link">Continue reading<span class="screen-reader-text"> "TESTOSTERONE, CIVILIZATION, AND SOCIAL CUES"</span></a>]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><em>Adapted from a chapter in my recent book,</em> <a href="https://www.amazon.com/dp/B09Z7MWJ7R">The Great Feminization</a>&#8230;</p>
<p><span id="more-621"></span></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>From conception through adolescence, male and female humans—mammals in general—are driven along distinct neural and anatomical developmental pathways by androgen and estrogen hormones, men having more of the former, women having more of the latter. The divergences in those developmental pathways lead to the innate differences in attitudes and behaviors between men and women.</p>
<p>One of the most striking of these behavioral/attitude differences has to do with risk: Women are, on average compared to men, markedly less willing to undertake risks—more “risk-averse”—and this gender difference has been shown (<a href="https://www.pnas.org/doi/10.1073/pnas.0907352106">here</a> and <a href="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/26135946/">here</a>, for example) to be broadly testosterone (T)-linked. In general, research in the past few decades suggests that either the bloodstream T level, or a marker (based on relative finger lengths) of prenatal T exposure, or both, predicts a person’s propensity for risky behaviors, as well as for competition and aggression.</p>
<p>Social psychology experiments on risk aversion typically examine risk behaviors, such as gambling choices, that can be studied relatively tidily in a laboratory setting. At the same time, in the modern West, low risk-aversion is often framed as a negative, maladaptive trait that tends to lead people astray. In fact, in the real world, the ability to cope with fear and take big risks is probably an essential step in the process of civilization. As Camille Paglia famously quipped, “If civilization had been left in female hands, we’d still be living in grass huts.”</p>
<p>Indeed, a greater willingness to take risks, even in comparison to other male-run civilizations, is plausibly one of the reasons the West got so far out in front of the rest: exploring and conquering most of the non-European world, developing the most technologically and culturally advanced societies ever known, exploring outer space, etc. But now that the West’s culture and policy have been heavily feminized, the lesser female enthusiasm for risky adventures like space exploration—a difference that seems even more pronounced <a href="https://twitter.com/alicefromqueens/status/1219459846401069056">anecdotally</a> than it is in <a href="https://theconversation.com/women-are-less-supportive-of-space-exploration-getting-a-woman-on-the-moon-might-change-that-118986">surveys</a>—helps explain why spending on such endeavors has become just a tiny fraction of spending on welfare and other matters dear to women’s hearts.</p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><img decoding="async" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-625" src="/wp-content/uploads/2022/07/spacexploration.jpg" alt="" width="723" height="420" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2022/07/spacexploration.jpg 723w, /wp-content/uploads/2022/07/spacexploration-300x174.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 709px) 85vw, (max-width: 909px) 67vw, (max-width: 984px) 61vw, (max-width: 1362px) 45vw, 600px" />[<a href="https://theconversation.com/women-are-less-supportive-of-space-exploration-getting-a-woman-on-the-moon-might-change-that-118986">link</a>]</p>
<p>That testosterone <a href="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/15939408/">reduces fear</a>, enhances the <a href="https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0306453021000883">willingness to compete</a>, and enhances the <a href="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/16483890/">desire to dominate</a> probably is a major reason men, on average compared to women, are more competitive, more willing to engage in violence, less subject to anxiety and fear, and less emotionally sensitive in general. Again, this is entirely what one would expect from men’s traditional roles not only as explorers but also as hunters and warriors. And, of course, we know that the vast majority of violent criminals are male. Thus, “willingness to fight” and related traits are obviously gender-determined to a great extent.</p>
<p>Should we care if the West’s feminization makes its people and their leaders less inclined towards fighting as well as exploration? Yes, we should care, especially if not all countries have been feminized. In the latter context, a country’s feminine aversion to fighting could result in its becoming enslaved, or even extinguished in genocide, by a less-feminized rival. But even a more subtle weakness could make a country highly susceptible to a bully’s manipulative threats.</p>
<p>For example, many already <a href="https://www.stuff.co.nz/national/politics/124914696/prime-minister-jacinda-ardern-labelled-the-wests-woke-weak-link-over-reluctance-to-join-five-eyes-china-stance">view</a> the current New Zealand prime minister, Jacinda Ardern, as a personification of that weakness.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><img decoding="async" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-638" src="/wp-content/uploads/2022/07/ardern.jpg" alt="" width="600" height="210" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2022/07/ardern.jpg 600w, /wp-content/uploads/2022/07/ardern-300x105.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 709px) 85vw, (max-width: 909px) 67vw, (max-width: 984px) 61vw, (max-width: 1362px) 45vw, 600px" /></p>
<p>In general, human civilization seems to requires a willingness—at least in a critical mass of the population—to undertake fearful hardships, stresses, even violence and death, for good ends. Without men and their fear-lowering testosterone, who would supply that crucial willingness?</p>
<p><strong>Testosterone and a feminized culture</strong></p>
<p>Speaking of testosterone, if you haven’t been living in a cave for the past two decades, you know that T levels in men have been declining&#8212;in other words, men at a given age today tend to have lower T levels than men of the same age a few decades ago. Studies [<a href="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/17895324/">link</a>, <a href="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/23161753/">link</a>, <a href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC7063751/">link</a>, <a href="https://www.renalandurologynews.com/home/conference-highlights/american-urological-association-annual-meeting/aua-2020-virtual-experience/testosterone-levels-declining-young-males/">link</a>] have found this alarming trend in multiple developed countries including the US. Some of these studies have specifically controlled for potentially confounding factors such as increases in obesity, which lowers T, and still have found evidence of a decline.</p>
<p>No one really knows what is causing this drop in T levels among men. Apart from rising obesity, which almost certainly accounts for some of the problem, suspected culprits include <a href="https://www.npr.org/2011/03/02/134196209/study-most-plastics-leach-hormone-like-chemicals">estrogen-mimicking compounds that leach out of common plastics</a>, and the big decline in cigarette smoking among men (smoking <a href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC3490106/">inhibits estrogen synthesis</a>, and a few studies have <a href="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/17163954/">linked</a> smoking to higher T).</p>
<p>One hypothesis that never gets mentioned—well, except by <a href="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/the-great-feminization/">me</a>—is that cultural feminization is itself a significant driver of declines in T. In other words, the recent feminine shift in cultural themes and norms, which effectively suppresses and stigmatizes many traditional aspects of traditional masculinity, and the related loss of male power in society, has had an essentially feminizing effect on the male brain, resulting among other things in lower T levels.</p>
<p>This hypothesis could be tested, to some degree, with simple experiments. For example, I would guess that exposure to images or videos of women shouting&#8212;a pretty common motif in modern media&#8212;could be enough, depending on the dose, to measurably lower T levels in ordinary males.</p>
<p><img decoding="async" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-598" src="/wp-content/uploads/2022/07/kavanaugh1.jpg" alt="" width="800" height="519" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2022/07/kavanaugh1.jpg 800w, /wp-content/uploads/2022/07/kavanaugh1-300x195.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2022/07/kavanaugh1-768x498.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 709px) 85vw, (max-width: 909px) 67vw, (max-width: 984px) 61vw, (max-width: 1362px) 45vw, 600px" /></p>
<p>To some of you, it may seem totally implausible that sociocultural factors, working via cognition and emotion, could influence something as deeply biological as the secretion of a sex hormone. However, it is a well-established phenomenon—in fact, it’s quite clear that the androgen system in mammals was specifically designed by Evolution to be regulated by social and other external cues.</p>
<p>It is known, for example, that sexual activity raises T levels in men (and women). Also, sports players and even their <a href="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/9811365/">fans</a> show increases in T levels after winning games, whereas <a href="https://www.warandgender.com/wgmaleag.htm">losers show decreases</a>. In general, it seems that T levels in men tend to rise before fights and other <a href="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/21458721/">challenges</a>, and either stay high or keep rising after wins, and drop after losses—one of Nature’s “winner take all” effects. (There is even evidence that <a href="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/21911391/">becoming a father—which requires a less aggressive, more nurturing character—downregulates T production</a>.) In other words, T levels definitely do rise or fall based on external sociocultural cues, with negative experiences being more likely to drive T levels lower. And thus, in a feminized society that hands men Ls every day, we really should <em>expect</em> them to show significant drops in T.</p>
<p><strong>T and Civilization</strong></p>
<p>In principle, the consequences of lower T levels aren’t all bad. For example, there appears to have been a striking <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Crime_drop">drop</a> in the rate of violent crime in the US since the 1980s and early 90s.</p>
<p><img decoding="async" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-627" src="/wp-content/uploads/2022/07/rwy6380658543185571658.027.jpeg" alt="" width="1080" height="617" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2022/07/rwy6380658543185571658.027.jpeg 1080w, /wp-content/uploads/2022/07/rwy6380658543185571658.027-300x171.jpeg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2022/07/rwy6380658543185571658.027-1024x585.jpeg 1024w, /wp-content/uploads/2022/07/rwy6380658543185571658.027-768x439.jpeg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 709px) 85vw, (max-width: 909px) 67vw, (max-width: 1362px) 62vw, 840px" /></p>
<p>Of course, there are many other factors, including declining lead exposures, the passing of the 80s/90s crack-cocaine epidemic, and changes in urban policing policies, that could help explain this trend. But the hypothesis that falling T levels, over the same period, have contributed, is at least plausible. Wouldn’t that be a good thing?</p>
<p>Maybe in that narrow sense, it would. But, again, there would be tradeoffs. Some would involve men’s health: Low-T, for example, is known to promote depression, osteoporosis, obesity, erectile dysfunction and heart disease, among other adverse health consequences. Other tradeoffs might affect society even more profoundly. In particular, low-T would be expected to reduce men’s sperm counts—which, by the way, is a trend that researchers have specifically <a href="https://www.theatlantic.com/family/archive/2018/10/sperm-counts-continue-to-fall/572794/">detected</a>. Lower T and lower sperm counts would be expected, in turn, to make men less likely to marry and/or have children. One well-known <a href="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/21911391/">study</a> did find that lower-T men in their mid-20s were less likely to be married several years later—and of course many studies have noted the wider trends of falling <a href="https://www.usnews.com/news/healthiest-communities/articles/2020-04-29/us-marriage-rate-drops-to-record-low">marriage</a> and cohabitation rates, and associated <a href="https://econofact.org/the-mystery-of-the-declining-u-s-birth-rate">birth rates</a>, in recent decades.</p>
<p><img decoding="async" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-629" src="/wp-content/uploads/2022/07/rwy6380658543185571658.028.jpeg" alt="" width="429" height="551" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2022/07/rwy6380658543185571658.028.jpeg 429w, /wp-content/uploads/2022/07/rwy6380658543185571658.028-234x300.jpeg 234w" sizes="(max-width: 429px) 85vw, 429px" /></p>
<p style="text-align: center;">[<a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/OkCupid/comments/5i6m5y/women_have_unrealistic_views_of_how_men_look/">link</a>]</p>
<p>Endemic low-T in a society, or a wider civilization as in the case of the West, might thus be considered a clear warning sign that the bottom is dropping out. One would expect this warning sign to emerge in a society that has been subject to a major defeat in war. In the West, in a historically unprecedented turn of events, it may be happening <em>despite</em> Western war victories and geopolitical supremacy. In other words, Western social liberalism, with its handover of most cultural power to women, may have delivered to its men, and to Western civilization, the equivalent of a crippling defeat.</p>
<p style="text-align: center;">* * *</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>A SPIRALING FRENZY</title>
		<link>/a-spiraling-frenzy/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[j stone]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 07 Jul 2022 23:44:52 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[ethnicity]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[fall of the West]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[human ecology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[immigration]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[psychology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[USA]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[wokeism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[women]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=590</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[The Great Awokening as a social mania In prior essays on this site and elsewhere, I’ve argued that the spread of wokeness and its recent marked intensification (the &#8220;Great Awokening&#8221;) is best seen as a social contagion—of feelings and sociocultural ideas that broadly reflect women’s maternal instincts, and are much more transmissible among women than &#8230; <a href="/a-spiraling-frenzy/" class="more-link">Continue reading<span class="screen-reader-text"> "A SPIRALING FRENZY"</span></a>]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><em>The Great Awokening as a social mania<br />
</em></p>
<p><span id="more-590"></span></p>
<p>In prior essays on this <a href="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/the-critical-mass-problem/">site</a> and <a href="https://americanmind.org/salvo/pink-shift/">elsewhere</a>, I’ve argued that the spread of wokeness and its recent marked intensification (the &#8220;Great Awokening&#8221;) is best seen as a social contagion—of feelings and sociocultural ideas that broadly reflect women’s maternal instincts, and are much more transmissible among women than among men.</p>
<p>I’ve also suggested that wokeness is apt to be ultra-transmissible among females whose feminine, maternal energies aren’t absorbed by husbands and children and may seek another outlet. The terms “cat lady” and “wine aunt” refer to a subset of these individuals, but many unmarried girls and young women, as well as successful career women, also fit this description.</p>
<p>I’ve proposed, moreover, that wokeness is driven into institutions not just by the conversion of (especially female) workers already in place but also by the <a href="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/always-be-capturing/"><em>takeover</em> </a>of those institutions by women and tamed males, via biased hiring.</p>
<p>I’m more certain now than ever that all these hypotheses are correct, as far as they go. But I think there is one more aspect of wokeness that requires an explanation. I’m referring to what could be called wokeness’s <em>spiraling frenzy</em>—its tendency to move away from norms of belief and behavior and towards extremes, wherever it takes hold.</p>
<p>To put it another way: The woke women and their enablers who in the past decade or two have effectively taken control of virtually all major American institutions and professions have not been content to implement a modest set of reforms and leave it at that. As their power has grown, they have increasingly attacked the core values of Western civilization: everything from due process of law to meritocracy to the shielding of children from sexual deviants and predators. As their policies have become extreme, so have their methods. They have made it clear that they don’t want sober deliberations—they want emotional shock and awe!</p>
<p><img decoding="async" class="size-full wp-image-597 aligncenter" src="/wp-content/uploads/2022/07/femen2-1.jpg" alt="" width="800" height="595" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2022/07/femen2-1.jpg 800w, /wp-content/uploads/2022/07/femen2-1-300x223.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2022/07/femen2-1-768x571.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 709px) 85vw, (max-width: 909px) 67vw, (max-width: 984px) 61vw, (max-width: 1362px) 45vw, 600px" /></p>
<p><img decoding="async" class="size-full wp-image-594 aligncenter" src="/wp-content/uploads/2022/07/femen1.jpg" alt="" width="800" height="451" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2022/07/femen1.jpg 800w, /wp-content/uploads/2022/07/femen1-300x169.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2022/07/femen1-768x433.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 709px) 85vw, (max-width: 909px) 67vw, (max-width: 984px) 61vw, (max-width: 1362px) 45vw, 600px" /></p>
<p><img decoding="async" class="size-full wp-image-601 aligncenter" src="/wp-content/uploads/2022/07/bloodprotest1.jpg" alt="" width="700" height="357" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2022/07/bloodprotest1.jpg 700w, /wp-content/uploads/2022/07/bloodprotest1-300x153.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 709px) 85vw, (max-width: 909px) 67vw, (max-width: 984px) 61vw, (max-width: 1362px) 45vw, 600px" /></p>
<p><img decoding="async" class="size-full wp-image-604 aligncenter" src="/wp-content/uploads/2022/07/6611fddd-8ba3-49ac-8eec-43537e9c4aa5-12__AP_Senate_Supreme_Court.3.jpg" alt="" width="800" height="529" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2022/07/6611fddd-8ba3-49ac-8eec-43537e9c4aa5-12__AP_Senate_Supreme_Court.3.jpg 800w, /wp-content/uploads/2022/07/6611fddd-8ba3-49ac-8eec-43537e9c4aa5-12__AP_Senate_Supreme_Court.3-300x198.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2022/07/6611fddd-8ba3-49ac-8eec-43537e9c4aa5-12__AP_Senate_Supreme_Court.3-768x508.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 709px) 85vw, (max-width: 909px) 67vw, (max-width: 984px) 61vw, (max-width: 1362px) 45vw, 600px" /></p>
<p><img decoding="async" class="size-full wp-image-599 aligncenter" src="/wp-content/uploads/2022/07/crazy-teacher.jpg" alt="" width="800" height="457" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2022/07/crazy-teacher.jpg 800w, /wp-content/uploads/2022/07/crazy-teacher-300x171.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2022/07/crazy-teacher-768x439.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 709px) 85vw, (max-width: 909px) 67vw, (max-width: 984px) 61vw, (max-width: 1362px) 45vw, 600px" /></p>
<p><img decoding="async" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-606" src="/wp-content/uploads/2022/07/crazy1.jpg" alt="" width="800" height="530" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2022/07/crazy1.jpg 800w, /wp-content/uploads/2022/07/crazy1-300x199.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2022/07/crazy1-768x509.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 709px) 85vw, (max-width: 909px) 67vw, (max-width: 984px) 61vw, (max-width: 1362px) 45vw, 600px" /></p>
<p><img decoding="async" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-607" src="/wp-content/uploads/2022/07/crazy2.jpg" alt="" width="600" height="607" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2022/07/crazy2.jpg 600w, /wp-content/uploads/2022/07/crazy2-297x300.jpg 297w" sizes="(max-width: 709px) 85vw, (max-width: 909px) 67vw, (max-width: 984px) 61vw, (max-width: 1362px) 45vw, 600px" /></p>
<p><img decoding="async" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-608" src="/wp-content/uploads/2022/07/crazy3.jpg" alt="" width="800" height="449" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2022/07/crazy3.jpg 800w, /wp-content/uploads/2022/07/crazy3-300x168.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2022/07/crazy3-768x431.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 709px) 85vw, (max-width: 909px) 67vw, (max-width: 984px) 61vw, (max-width: 1362px) 45vw, 600px" /></p>
<p>One could argue that there is a counter-cultural logic to this movement—that it wants to collapse the existing order as completely as those hijacked planes collapsed the Twin Towers on 9/11.</p>
<p>But is the Great Awokening replacing the old culture with a new one that can bind society sustainably&#8212;a &#8220;successor ideology&#8221;?</p>
<p>Wokeness and the Great Awokening are driven chiefly by women, who have their own ways of thinking and persuading&#8212;ways that typically seem more emotional and less rational than men&#8217;s. So one might suppose that there <em>is</em> a genuine ideology being built here, albeit a feminine one that seems alien to the average male, and that the Great Awokening is just the final, dramatic dash in this &#8220;<a href="https://americanmind.org/salvo/pink-shift/">pink shift</a>&#8221; takeover of Western culture.</p>
<p>However, to me, that&#8217;s not the full story. To me, the Great Awokening&#8217;s spiraling frenzy, and its attraction for people who are evidently mentally ill, suggest that it is for the most part only a temporary and reactive social phenomenon: a social &#8220;mania.&#8221;</p>
<p><strong>Logic and Madness</strong></p>
<p>As many have noted, the Great Awokening bears a strong resemblance to the Chinese Cultural Revolution of 1966-76.</p>
<p>The CCR’s spearpoints were cadres of “Red Guard” fanatics, young people (even teens) whose instability and restlessness, suggestibility, and high susceptibility to fanaticism were probably comparable to what one finds in today’s millennial Antifa brigades. These howling Maoist minions sought the erasure of whatever competed with Maoism, which in practice meant just about anything predating Maoist China—history books, art, architecture, temples, even genealogical records. Red Guards and their camp followers toppled statues of Confucius, pasted huge banners with their slogans everywhere, and went around attacking intellectuals or anyone even lightly connected to the teaching of pre-Maoist history or philosophy.</p>
<p><img decoding="async" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-366" src="/wp-content/uploads/2022/01/fourolds.jpg" alt="" width="1000" height="750" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2022/01/fourolds.jpg 1000w, /wp-content/uploads/2022/01/fourolds-300x225.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2022/01/fourolds-768x576.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 709px) 85vw, (max-width: 909px) 67vw, (max-width: 1362px) 62vw, 840px" /></p>
<p>That was the counter-cultural logic part of it. But there was also the crazypants part—shocking, obscene, savage stuff, ultimately including murder and even cannibalism.</p>
<p style="padding-left: 40px;">At some high schools, students killed their principals in the school courtyard and then cooked and ate the bodies to celebrate a triumph over &#8220;counterrevolutionaries&#8221; &#8230;  Government-run cafeterias are said to have displayed bodies dangling on meat hooks and to have served human flesh to employees. [<a href="https://www.nytimes.com/1993/01/06/world/a-tale-of-red-guards-and-cannibals.html">NYT</a>]</p>
<p>Not content with attacking living reminders of the old China, Red Guards also broke into cemeteries and dug up the skeletal remains of ancient Chinese emperors and nobles, desecrating them and denouncing the persons these remains had once been.</p>
<p>Other examples of these social frenzies come to mind. In some of the pre-Christian feasts of Rome and northern Europe, open drunkenness and debauchery, and various other intentionally shocking inversions of everyday social norms, were encouraged, at least in part as cathartic but controlled ventings of accumulated stress. (Modern parties, especially the ones teens and young adults have, seem like echoes of these displays.) As Samuel Johnson famously said, “He who makes a beast of himself gets rid of the pain of being a man.”</p>
<p>Or a woman. The infamous <a href="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/girl-power/">convent hysterias</a> of 1500s-1700s Europe supply many illustrations of spiraling frenzies among women, especially sexually frustrated younger ones. In the 1632-34 Loudoun case, for example, at a public exorcism of supposedly demon-possessed Ursuline nuns, a Sister Claire “fell on the ground, blaspheming, in convulsions, lifting up her petticoats and chemise, displaying her privy parts without any shame, and uttering filthy words. Her gestures became so indecent that the audience averted its eyes.” [<a href="https://www.thriftbooks.com/w/the-encyclopedia-of-witchcraft-and-demonology/8811250/">link</a>]</p>
<p>Sexual themes dominated the antics of “possessed” nuns, although there were maternal—or inverted maternal—themes too, for example claims of mystical pregnancy, and stories of secret witch conclaves (“witches’ sabbaths”) at which children were eaten.</p>
<p>Themes of sexual violation and impregnation, theft or killing of unborn babies, and witchcraft, along with the same spiraling of fantastic claims and odd behavior, were also typical in the medicalized versions of possession—&#8221;multiple personality disorder” and “UFO abduction”—that were popular among young women in the 1970-90s, and ended up discrediting many therapists and psychiatrists, as well as the whole idea of &#8220;hypnotically recovered memories.&#8221;</p>
<p>To me, these are examples of social manias&#8212;not just contagions (for even healthy, sustainable behaviors can be contagious) but contagions that spread intense and increasingly bizarre, often counter-cultural activities, and are essentially reactions to excessive stress.</p>
<p><strong>A holiday from stress and inhibition</strong></p>
<p>As the comment by Dr. Johnson implies, human beings in modern civilizations are inhibited and stressed by the social rules they are supposed to obey and the complex social environments they are supposed to navigate—the “pain of being a man.”</p>
<p>It makes sense that women nowadays would be relatively hard-hit by such stresses. Women’s basic lifestyle has shifted dramatically—much more than men’s has—over the past few generations. Women during this interval generally have had to face new stresses from:</p>
<ul>
<li style="list-style-type: none;">
<ul>
<li>higher education and the pressures at higher levels of the working world;</li>
<li>the postponement or abandonment of marriage and child-bearing;</li>
<li>a new (or newly de-civilized) courtship environment in which their natural desire for love and motherhood is taken advantage of again and again without being fulfilled.</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<p>All the while, women have been told (by the most authoritative sources, including Hollywood and feminist activists) that these changes represent &#8220;progress&#8221; and must not be resisted.</p>
<p><img decoding="async" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-609" src="/wp-content/uploads/2022/07/sexandthecity1.jpg" alt="" width="800" height="550" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2022/07/sexandthecity1.jpg 800w, /wp-content/uploads/2022/07/sexandthecity1-300x206.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2022/07/sexandthecity1-768x528.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 709px) 85vw, (max-width: 909px) 67vw, (max-width: 984px) 61vw, (max-width: 1362px) 45vw, 600px" /></p>
<p>Women also, compared to men, appear to have an innately greater desire for “equality” and social harmony. Yet these lofty, sentimental social goals, during the same critical period, have slipped—frustratingly—further and further out of reach, as the West has intensified its effort to remake itself as a highly multi-racial/ethnic civilization.</p>
<p>In addition to having to face these new stresses, women are (on average) more emotionally sensitive than men, and thus are apt to be more affected by the same stressors.</p>
<p>Small wonder, then, that a very large proportion of women and girls in Western societies can now expect to be diagnosed with a mood or anxiety disorder. It probably also should be unsurprising that the essentially feminine notion of “trauma”—a highly stressing psychological injury—has now taken on an <a href="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/the-great-feminization/">outsized role</a> not only in Western medicine but also in the wider culture.</p>
<p>On the whole, then, the recent changes in the standard female lifeway, and the demographic makeovers of Western societies, have created a large and chronic background level of stress for women. But the severe emotional contagion of the Great Awokening was triggered only after additional, more acute stressors appeared in the first half of 2020: the pandemic with its lockdowns, social isolation, and widespread fears of illness/death; and then the inflammatory treatment—by left-leaning media, activists, and politicians—of various police killings of miscreant African Americans.</p>
<p><img decoding="async" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-225" src="/wp-content/uploads/2021/06/bethesdaawokening-1.jpg" alt="" width="800" height="450" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2021/06/bethesdaawokening-1.jpg 800w, /wp-content/uploads/2021/06/bethesdaawokening-1-300x169.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2021/06/bethesdaawokening-1-768x432.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 709px) 85vw, (max-width: 909px) 67vw, (max-width: 984px) 61vw, (max-width: 1362px) 45vw, 600px" /></p>
<p>Thus I think one can fairly easily fit the Great Awokening into the broader category of stress-induced, stress-relieving social manias. Amid the furious revels of such manias, inhibitions are necessarily going to be relaxed (for some more than others, of course) and people who were relatively labile, even frankly nuts, to begin with will also be drawn in, given the camouflage these frenzies provide for their behavioral issues.</p>
<p><strong>The function of boundary-pushing</strong></p>
<p>A social mania—one that is true to the concept of mania—cannot run forever. It must end by depleting its energy source or by inducing resistance, just as an individual with psychiatric mania will become exhausted after many days without adequate sleep, and/or will cause herself to be hospitalized and treated by exhibiting increasingly abnormal behavior. If a social mania’s deep purpose is to relieve accumulated social pressures, then its tendency to be ever more immoderate might even be seen as <em>functional</em>—in the sense that the spiraling further and further away from social norms serves to reduce support and induce opposition, thus limiting the damage while allowing the requisite venting of steam. To put it crudely, a social mania with its spiraling frenzy is a societal “cry for help.”</p>
<p>This is all speculative. It’s also a group-level, forest-not-the-trees view that people with an ordinary individualistic bias might find hard to wrap their heads around. But it’s a novel take that I (obviously) think should be considered. On the whole, it suggests that the Great Awokening should interest us less as a new cultural movement, and more as a <em>signal</em> indicating deep problems with the existing culture and society. In other words, it’s a social version of a seismic tremor, or even earthquake, and its intensity and direction of slip are interesting mainly for what they tell us about the underlying stresses at work—stresses that are unbearable and thus have be relieved, in one way or another.</p>
<p style="text-align: center;">***</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>THE TREE OF KNOWLEDGE</title>
		<link>/the-tree-of-knowledge/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[j stone]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sat, 16 Apr 2022 21:52:30 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[ideas]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[psychology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[technology]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=566</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Encourage new ideas and more productive dialogue by giving idea-originators the credit they’re due &#160; Late in 2011, I first put pen to paper, or fingertips to keyboard, to describe an idea that had been bouncing around in my mind for several years—at least since Larry Summers’s public defenestration from Harvard in 2005. The idea &#8230; <a href="/the-tree-of-knowledge/" class="more-link">Continue reading<span class="screen-reader-text"> "THE TREE OF KNOWLEDGE"</span></a>]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><em>Encourage new ideas and more productive dialogue by giving idea-originators the credit they’re due</em></p>
<p><span id="more-566"></span></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>Late in 2011, I first put pen to paper, or fingertips to keyboard, to describe an idea that had been bouncing around in my mind for several years—at least since Larry Summers’s public <a href="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/the-day-the-logic-died/">defenestration</a> from Harvard in 2005. The idea was that women’s unprecedented mass entry into public life, in the US and other Western societies, had been “feminizing” public discourse and policy—leading among other things to the rise of political correctness culture, the increasing suppression of free speech, and the decline of capital punishment—due to women’s different way of thinking about the world.</p>
<p>I wasn’t a professional opinionator—just an amateur with a background in journalism. But I did have a website where I published occasional essays, which were read by a few hundreds to thousands of people every month, and there I first set down my thoughts in a <a href="https://james-the-obscure.github.io/the-demise-of-guythink/">short piece</a> about the demise of the male cognitive style. In the ensuing decade, I developed the basic idea in further essays, including in two web magazines with significant readership. I joined Twitter to promote these essays. Eventually I had some recognition as an introducer of this idea.</p>
<p><img decoding="async" class="size-full wp-image-573 aligncenter" src="/wp-content/uploads/2022/04/spotted-toad.jpg" alt="" width="591" height="224" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2022/04/spotted-toad.jpg 591w, /wp-content/uploads/2022/04/spotted-toad-300x114.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 591px) 85vw, 591px" /></p>
<p><img decoding="async" class="wp-image-574 aligncenter" src="/wp-content/uploads/2022/04/cowen-Copy.jpg" alt="" width="471" height="310" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2022/04/cowen-Copy.jpg 660w, /wp-content/uploads/2022/04/cowen-Copy-300x198.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 471px) 85vw, 471px" /></p>
<p><img decoding="async" class="wp-image-575 aligncenter" src="/wp-content/uploads/2022/04/pink-shift-cover.jpg" alt="" width="364" height="527" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2022/04/pink-shift-cover.jpg 1246w, /wp-content/uploads/2022/04/pink-shift-cover-207x300.jpg 207w, /wp-content/uploads/2022/04/pink-shift-cover-707x1024.jpg 707w, /wp-content/uploads/2022/04/pink-shift-cover-768x1113.jpg 768w, /wp-content/uploads/2022/04/pink-shift-cover-1060x1536.jpg 1060w, /wp-content/uploads/2022/04/pink-shift-cover-1200x1738.jpg 1200w" sizes="(max-width: 364px) 85vw, 364px" /></p>
<p>The idea of cultural feminization became more and more obvious in the wake of the Great Awokening, which appeared to be a heavily female-dominated social phenomenon. One <a href="https://thecritic.co.uk/issues/december-january-2022/new-female-ascendency/">writer</a> after <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2022/01/12/opinion/gender-gap-politics.html">another</a> began to notice and embrace the cultural feminization idea as their own—either not knowing of my (and others’) prior <a href="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/cultural-feminization-a-bibliography/">contributions</a>, or knowing of them but not considering them “big” enough, in terms of readership and public awareness, to acknowledge them.</p>
<p>I may be ultra-sensitive on this topic, because some of my past journalistic work has been used by others with inadequate attribution (or none). I am also aware that this is a very personal kind of pain, one that tends to attract little sympathy from those who have not had a similar experience.</p>
<div style="width: 640px;" class="wp-video"><!--[if lt IE 9]><script>document.createElement('video');</script><![endif]-->
<video class="wp-video-shortcode" id="video-566-1" width="640" height="352" preload="metadata" controls="controls"><source type="video/mp4" src="/wp-content/uploads/2022/04/Dustin-Hoffman-And-Robert-De-Niro-Wag-The-Dog-I-Want-The-Credit-2-1-Copy.mp4?_=1" /><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2022/04/Dustin-Hoffman-And-Robert-De-Niro-Wag-The-Dog-I-Want-The-Credit-2-1-Copy.mp4">/wp-content/uploads/2022/04/Dustin-Hoffman-And-Robert-De-Niro-Wag-The-Dog-I-Want-The-Credit-2-1-Copy.mp4</a></video></div>
<p>Still, I think there is an objective case to be made, wholly apart from my own gripes, that “inadequate credit to originators of ideas” (ICOI?) is a legitimate social problem whose solution would materially benefit society. Why? Simply because denying people credit for developing original ideas effectively disincentivizes them from making the effort to develop those ideas, and in that straightforward sense is likely to retard human progress. Obscuring past expressions of an idea also limits new discussions of that idea when they do occur—people are constantly “reinventing the wheel.”</p>
<p>We acknowledge this logic in other domains of knowledge production. The new ideas of scientists, doctors, English Lit experts, etc. are protected and made accessible by the searchability of their formal papers (via the PubMed system, for example) and the citation custom. New technical ideas also are protected and made accessible by the patent system and its strong judicial backing. Books, musical compositions, movies, TV shows, are protected—albeit weakly—by the copyright system.</p>
<p>Unfortunately, when it comes to ordinary, non-patentable, non-copyrightable ideas that are published in informal, non-academic fora—ideas such as “women’s mass entry into public life has feminized institutions, culture and policy”—there is no legal protection, and no good and searchable repository. Moreover, the principal search engines for web-based material aren’t really designed to uncover the origins and subsequent iterations of ideas. Mainly because of this, there is only a very weak cultural enforcement of priority claims by idea-originators. I observe anecdotally, for example, that Twitter is full of DIY experts who (from lack of knowledge and/or lack of scruples) recycle others’ ideas, framing their contributions as new, though they are unoriginal and are often incomplete/undeveloped compared to the true original. Thus, the true originators are discouraged by not getting credit, and the false ones lead everyone in circles instead of moving the discussion productively forward.</p>
<p><strong>Solutions?</strong></p>
<p>In a broad-brush way, I imagine two complementary solutions to this problem. One is to develop a “registry of ideas.” The other is to develop an “idea history” search engine/bot.</p>
<p>The registry of ideas could have a broad structure like the “<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Motif-Index_of_Folk-Literature">motif index</a>” developed by the anthropologist Stith Thompson in the 1930s to record and categorize folkloric tales according to their different elements or &#8220;motifs.”</p>
<p><img decoding="async" class="wp-image-569 aligncenter" src="/wp-content/uploads/2022/04/motif-index-Copy-2-scaled.jpg" alt="" width="455" height="736" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2022/04/motif-index-Copy-2-scaled.jpg 1584w, /wp-content/uploads/2022/04/motif-index-Copy-2-186x300.jpg 186w, /wp-content/uploads/2022/04/motif-index-Copy-2-633x1024.jpg 633w, /wp-content/uploads/2022/04/motif-index-Copy-2-768x1241.jpg 768w, /wp-content/uploads/2022/04/motif-index-Copy-2-950x1536.jpg 950w, /wp-content/uploads/2022/04/motif-index-Copy-2-1267x2048.jpg 1267w" sizes="(max-width: 455px) 85vw, 455px" /></p>
<p>The Dewey Decimal System, by which librarians decide where to shelve books, and the aborted Google “<a href="https://dbpedia.org/page/Knol">Knol</a>” project, offer other potentially helpful models of topic-categorization.</p>
<p>I imagine that some organization like the Wikimedia Foundation (Wikipedia’s parent) could provide some initial structure and guidelines for such a database, after which it would be assembled and curated by volunteers in a highly distributed manner—like Wikipedia. Idea-originators could directly submit their work for recording in the registry, as they can now for appropriate intellectual property with the patent and copyright systems, or they could just let the curators detect their work (assuming it had been published) with their specially designed web bots and other search tools.</p>
<p>Those tools would be powered by “idea history” search algos, which would parse natural language text to identify ideas being expressed, and categorize them—at least as a “first pass” effort to be checked by human curators of different idea domains, though AI tech may soon be able to handle such tasks on its own.</p>
<p>I suppose one objection to this whole idea—this idea about ideas—would be that ordinary writers, especially casual self-published essayists and social-media posters, won’t submit to a citation system the way academics do. I think, though, that to a great extent, ordinary writers already <em>do</em> follow the custom of citation. These days (unlike, say, 50 years ago) a large majority of young adults in the US have had some college experience, with the exposure to citation rules that entails. More importantly, the internet with its “hypertext” ability that can easily link text to other documents anywhere on the web has made citation of others’ work routine even for the most casual writers. The only things missing, really, are the search engines and repositories that would help to fully routinize the assignment of priority, rewarding creativity appropriately, and plausibly making even our humdrum, everyday dialogue a bit more rigorous and serious.</p>
<p style="text-align: center;">* * *</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		<enclosure url="/wp-content/uploads/2022/04/Dustin-Hoffman-And-Robert-De-Niro-Wag-The-Dog-I-Want-The-Credit-2-1-Copy.mp4" length="1281012" type="video/mp4" />

			</item>
		<item>
		<title>ALWAYS BE CAPTURING</title>
		<link>/always-be-capturing/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[j stone]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 06 Apr 2022 02:36:36 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[psychology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[USA]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[wokeism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[women]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=531</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[The ubiquity of “kulturkampf” &#160; I’ve already written a lot of essays about women’s maternal and other sex-specific traits, and how the mass entry of women into public life, in the last several decades, has brought those feminine traits to bear on culture and politics, driving extensive and ongoing changes in Western societies. I am &#8230; <a href="/always-be-capturing/" class="more-link">Continue reading<span class="screen-reader-text"> "ALWAYS BE CAPTURING"</span></a>]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><em>The ubiquity of “kulturkampf”</em></p>
<p><span id="more-531"></span></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>I’ve already written <a href="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/cultural-feminization-a-bibliography/">a lot of essays</a> about women’s maternal and other sex-specific traits, and how the mass entry of women into public life, in the last several decades, has brought those feminine traits to bear on culture and politics, driving extensive and ongoing changes in Western societies.</p>
<p>I am convinced more than ever that that &#8220;great feminization&#8221; argument is essentially correct. But there is another facet of male/female cultural competition that I have mostly overlooked until now. It’s really something that relates to groups in general, not just to women, but I think it’s especially relevant to the current female-driven social transformations of Western societies.</p>
<p>The idea here is that, when women a few decades ago began to achieve parity/dominance <em>vis-</em><em>à</em><em>-vis</em> men in professions and institutions across the West, they <em>automatically</em> set up a rivalry, a “battle of the sexes,” in each of these professions and institutions. Why? Not because of any particular “female” or “male” trait, but simply because the two sexes are <em>different in general</em>. They have different group identities, different ways of thinking, different group cultures. If only at an instinctive, nonconscious level—and if only to avoid the emotional pain of having to conform to the others’ ways—each has sought dominance over the other.</p>
<p>This certainly seems to be true from women’s perspective. You can hardly open a newspaper or browse news websites these days without encountering lamentations, by female writers, about male workplace behavior—from the mildly irritating to the supposedly traumatizing. These behaviors typically are blamed upon the male domination of the workplace in question, although from my (admittedly biased, male) perspective these complaints often look more like attempts to stamp out the last vestiges of male culture in workplaces that are already significantly feminized.</p>
<p><img decoding="async" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-534" src="/wp-content/uploads/2022/04/toxic-masc.jpg" alt="" width="800" height="458" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2022/04/toxic-masc.jpg 800w, /wp-content/uploads/2022/04/toxic-masc-300x172.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2022/04/toxic-masc-768x440.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 709px) 85vw, (max-width: 909px) 67vw, (max-width: 984px) 61vw, (max-width: 1362px) 45vw, 600px" /></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><img decoding="async" class="alignnone wp-image-533" src="/wp-content/uploads/2022/04/city-lads.jpg" alt="" width="511" height="450" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2022/04/city-lads.jpg 847w, /wp-content/uploads/2022/04/city-lads-300x264.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2022/04/city-lads-768x676.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 511px) 85vw, 511px" /></p>
<p>Women in their workplaces nowadays also—typically with the thinnest of formal rationales—are apt to organize emotional coalitions to oust their male CEOs or other leaders whose ways are insufficiently accommodating to the current female mindset.</p>
<p><img decoding="async" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-537" src="/wp-content/uploads/2022/04/lander.jpg" alt="" width="800" height="518" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2022/04/lander.jpg 800w, /wp-content/uploads/2022/04/lander-300x194.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2022/04/lander-768x497.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 709px) 85vw, (max-width: 909px) 67vw, (max-width: 984px) 61vw, (max-width: 1362px) 45vw, 600px" /></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><img decoding="async" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-540" src="/wp-content/uploads/2022/04/cuomo.jpg" alt="" width="800" height="484" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2022/04/cuomo.jpg 800w, /wp-content/uploads/2022/04/cuomo-300x182.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2022/04/cuomo-768x465.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 709px) 85vw, (max-width: 909px) 67vw, (max-width: 984px) 61vw, (max-width: 1362px) 45vw, 600px" /></p>
<p><img decoding="async" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-559" src="/wp-content/uploads/2022/04/nfl.jpg" alt="" width="800" height="535" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2022/04/nfl.jpg 800w, /wp-content/uploads/2022/04/nfl-300x201.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2022/04/nfl-768x514.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 709px) 85vw, (max-width: 909px) 67vw, (max-width: 984px) 61vw, (max-width: 1362px) 45vw, 600px" /></p>
<p>I suppose that if one ventures into the “manosphere” reaches of the Internet, one will find similar complaints from men trapped in female-dominated institutions. One will strain to find similar victories, though.</p>
<p>On the whole, the institutional battle of the sexes is something that seems to have really crept up on men, creating a challenge for them that they may be unable to surmount. Men, in particular the white, European-derived men who created the institutions of Western civilization, were trying to be progressive and even-handed when they welcomed women into the workplace (they <em>were</em> relatively welcoming, compared to Asians, Arabs, Africans, etc.). They were trying to be meritocratic. Arguably that relatively fair-minded meritocratic mindset was a psychological or cultural trait that helped Western men build their civilization into the powerhouse it was. (Most men also regarded the scaled-up presence of women in the workplace as a colossal and wondrous sexual opportunity.)</p>
<p>What men didn’t reckon with is that women eventually would reach a certain level of presence and power in the institutions and professions where they worked—a critical mass, as it were—and from that point onward would tend to seek not parity but <em>dominance</em>, and by just about any means.</p>
<p>I submit that we are already seeing this reach for (and, frequently, achievement of) female dominance across multiple institutions and professions. While the most visible manifestation is the one I just mentioned&#8212;the noisy cancellation coalition that dislodges a problematic male executive (who is often replaced with a woman)&#8212;women also have been feminizing their institutions, and crowding out men, in much less newsworthy ways, e.g., the practice of “preferred pronouns,” “inclusive,” i.e., non-meritocratic hiring including quotas for female execs and board members, mandatory pro-diversity statements, and feminist/ESG/green constraints on investment and general corporate policy.</p>
<p>The upshot of this organizational capture is, of course, women’s use of these entities to promote the wider feminization of culture and politics—often synonymous with “wokeification”—which, again, I have <a href="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/the-great-feminization/">written about</a> elsewhere.</p>
<p><img decoding="async" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-542" src="/wp-content/uploads/2022/04/disneyexec.jpg" alt="" width="800" height="476" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2022/04/disneyexec.jpg 800w, /wp-content/uploads/2022/04/disneyexec-300x179.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2022/04/disneyexec-768x457.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 709px) 85vw, (max-width: 909px) 67vw, (max-width: 984px) 61vw, (max-width: 1362px) 45vw, 600px" /></p>
<p>Their steamrolling victories suggest that women are much more powerful and effective than men in these institutional struggles, and, in a way, this should be unsurprising: Men presumably have not been under long-term evolutionary or cultural pressure to cope with competition of this kind from women. Women, on the other hand, as the weaker sex, have long had need of “force multiplier” tactics and instincts.</p>
<p>I strongly suspect that women’s greater power derives especially from a set of closely related female traits that include superior emotional sensitivity, superior sociality, superior ability to catch and transmit social contagions, and superior ability to form emotional coalitions—traits that, again, may have evolved not just in support of maternal functions, but also as special weapons in contests with otherwise dominant males. (I have touched on these points in previous essays, e.g., <a href="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/the-day-the-logic-died/">here</a> and <a href="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/girl-power/">here</a>.)</p>
<p>Of course, women also benefit tremendously from the civil rights dogma and legal regime that has gripped the US and some other Western societies for decades now, and often designates women as “traditionally disadvantaged” and thus worthy of favorable treatment, especially <em>vis-à-vis</em> white males.</p>
<p><strong>Other groups</strong></p>
<p>As I suggested at the top of this essay, women’s quest for supremacy within traditionally male institutions/professions is just one specific example of a much more general phenomenon of modernity. In other words, my hypothesis here is that <em>any</em> two (or more) groups that are sufficiently well defined and coherent, with sufficiently distinct group identities and cultures and so on, are bound to vie for control, to some extent, whenever they occupy the same social space.</p>
<p>Ethnic/racial groups are probably the most obvious examples of highly coherent but non-gender-defined groups that we would expect to see in these wars for institutional supremacy. As in the case of women vs. men, some of these ethnic/racial groups, due to their own particular traits, will be better than others in such contests. Immigrants to Western countries, especially those who have to travel from remote parts of the world, already tend to be the smartest, most ambitious, get-up-and-go members of their societies. Moreover, some of those societies are already highly stratified, with highly intelligent, highly entitled, highly ambitious (even ruthless) upper strata—so the immigrants from those upper strata are <em>really</em> going to pose a challenge to Westerners in the context of institutional struggles.</p>
<p>Thus, we are essentially looking at the flip side, the dark side one might say, of the fact that America and other Western countries attract the world’s best: Yes, many of these immigrants are the best, or are at least highly ambitious and sharp-elbowed, but that also means that they may soon have your job—and may even control your organizations.</p>
<p>Additionally, virtually any non-legacy-Western ethnic group is nonwhite, and <em>ipso facto</em> will be granted further strong advantages by contemporary civil rights culture. These advantages, over the past fifty-odd years, have included preferences/quotas in academic admissions, in public and private job hiring, and in government contracting—even when the group’s members have hailed mostly from elite, wealthy castes in the home country, and have not been “disadvantaged” in any sense.</p>
<p>Apart from the very tangible, often windfall-scale benefits of this civil rights regime, there has been, especially in recent decades, a civil rights <em>mindset</em> within organizations, a mindset that provides a further advantage to nonwhite ethnicities. Cloaking themselves in civil rights victimhood, preaching about the need for more diversity and equity, calling out alleged racists and racism, nonwhites can basically activate and direct that mindset as a further, quite powerful tool for displacing legacy Whites, for individual and group benefit.</p>
<p><img decoding="async" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-543" src="/wp-content/uploads/2022/04/apoorvam.jpg" alt="" width="361" height="258" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2022/04/apoorvam.jpg 361w, /wp-content/uploads/2022/04/apoorvam-300x214.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 361px) 85vw, 361px" /></p>
<p><img decoding="async" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-544" src="/wp-content/uploads/2022/04/nytstaffers.jpg" alt="" width="800" height="443" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2022/04/nytstaffers.jpg 800w, /wp-content/uploads/2022/04/nytstaffers-300x166.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2022/04/nytstaffers-768x425.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 709px) 85vw, (max-width: 909px) 67vw, (max-width: 984px) 61vw, (max-width: 1362px) 45vw, 600px" /></p>
<p>I can think of at least several ethnicities that are doing very well in Western societies for the reasons I’ve just described. Indians are probably the most obvious example. They make up only about 1.5 percent of the US population now, and were hardly visible at all in the country half a century ago, but already they are strikingly overrepresented in the ranks of big-company CEOs as well as in other influential professions such as law, medicine, and politics.</p>
<p><img decoding="async" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-545" src="/wp-content/uploads/2022/04/indiansceos.jpg" alt="" width="767" height="860" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2022/04/indiansceos.jpg 767w, /wp-content/uploads/2022/04/indiansceos-268x300.jpg 268w" sizes="(max-width: 709px) 85vw, (max-width: 909px) 67vw, (max-width: 984px) 61vw, (max-width: 1362px) 45vw, 600px" /></p>
<p>Again, according to this general hypothesis, the struggle for control of institutions and professions could involve any other type of group with a significant presence and a sufficiently distinct and coherent identity. I think there are not many good examples beyond gender- and ethnicity-based groupings, but surely the “LGBTQ community” is one that has had some success in influencing big organizations’ policies.</p>
<p><img decoding="async" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-546" src="/wp-content/uploads/2022/04/mcdonalds.jpg" alt="" width="420" height="615" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2022/04/mcdonalds.jpg 420w, /wp-content/uploads/2022/04/mcdonalds-205x300.jpg 205w" sizes="(max-width: 420px) 85vw, 420px" /></p>
<p><strong> </strong><strong>A General Hypothesis of Cultural Struggle</strong></p>
<p>To sum up, then, my hypothesis is that a “collective instinct” to vie for supremacy over institutions/professions is something that occurs to some extent, and more or less automatically, even non-consciously, within <em>all</em> well-defined, cohering groups of significant size within those organizations. Different groups will have different traits that affect the intensity of their participation, their strategies, and their overall chances of success in these struggles. Some will also be advantaged or disadvantaged by the surrounding law and culture, e.g., civil rights law and culture.</p>
<p>I am not sure how original this idea is. Certainly, the idea of group culture is not new; nor is the idea of a struggle between cultures—what the Germans call a <em>kulturkampf</em>—novel. But the idea that such a struggle begins almost automatically when two or more rival cultures share a defined social space—a profession, an organization, a country—is one I don’t think I have encountered before.</p>
<p>I may not have emphasized enough that this “struggle” normally, for most of its participants, would be relatively subtle and even non-conscious. We all have our conscious explanations of, and justifications for, the things we do, but clearly there is a lot of other stuff going on under the hood—under the “limen,” the threshold of consciousness, as psychologists call it. Thus, Sanjay from the IT department may not be consciously plotting to dislodge the white CEO of his corporation; <em>but,</em> if asked to sign a petition decrying overheard off-color remarks by his company’s white CEO at a recent company retreat, he may be, <em>ceteris paribus,</em> much more likely to sign it if he knows the replacement CEO will be one of his countrymen—even if he isn’t consciously aware of that knowledge’s influence on him.</p>
<p>Another point to emphasize is that many, maybe most large organizations and institutions will have more than one group vying for control (e.g., women, assorted nonwhites, LGBTQs) against the legacy group (white males). These factions will coalesce and separate as needed, negotiating power-sharing strategies and arrangements, one faction slipstreaming behind another that has more power, and so on—similar to the workings of political parties in a multiparty system.</p>
<p><strong>The uniqueness of whites</strong></p>
<p>I have hesitated to include the legacy managerial class—white males—as combatants in these ubiquitous struggles, for the simple reason that they seldom seem to put up a fight. It’s downright eerie how some of these guys, no matter how innocent, will grovel, apologize, and plaintively attempt to appease when attacked, instead of showing any kind of defiance. It’s also odd that these men are so easily isolated; they are like those hobbled old wildebeests from the nature documentaries: left behind by the panicked herd for the pursuing, shrieking jackals to surround and kill at their leisure.</p>
<p>As for most of this social-psych territory, I can only speculate about the source of white males’ peculiar weakness and apathy. Maybe just having been on top for so long is enough to erode the mojo needed to stay there; maybe success has made us too soft, as the ascendant Greeks of antiquity said of the descendant Persians. Maybe we also developed psychological tools, such as <a href="https://www.theatlantic.com/magazine/archive/2020/10/joseph-henrich-weird-people/615496/">hyper-individualism</a> and relative cultural openness, that were once highly adaptive in enabling us to build our great civilization, but now leave us vulnerable as our environment becomes more post-patriarchal and multi-ethnic, and the protection and promotion of the “tribe” acquires a renewed importance.</p>
<p>Indeed, we aren’t merely passive in the face of challenges from women and nonwhites. We—a huge number of us anyway—are quick to respond with active self-loathing and self-abasement. Our women are even quicker in this regard, so I guess that this represents not a male trait but a white trait: a guilt/appeasement reflex that is related to emotional sensitivity and social (“virtue”) signaling.</p>
<p><img decoding="async" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-548" src="/wp-content/uploads/2022/04/stewart.jpg" alt="" width="800" height="488" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2022/04/stewart.jpg 800w, /wp-content/uploads/2022/04/stewart-300x183.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2022/04/stewart-768x468.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 709px) 85vw, (max-width: 909px) 67vw, (max-width: 984px) 61vw, (max-width: 1362px) 45vw, 600px" /></p>
<p>Whatever the cause, it is or should be remarkable, not to mention alarming, that <em>nonwhites</em> don’t seem to have this self-abasing, guilt-signaling reflex. Nonwhites have at least many skeletons in their ancestral closets as whites do&#8212;everyone living now is the beneficiary of hundreds of invasions and genocides going back to ape-men times. Yet I&#8217;m sure I&#8217;ve never heard an Indian, a Nigerian, or a Filipino lament his <em>own</em> ongoing, deliberate colonization and exploitation of the countries of the West.</p>
<p><strong>Implications</strong></p>
<p>In principle, some struggles between group cultures will merely simmer, remaining unresolved indefinitely, because the factions that would challenge the incumbent white male faction cannot put together the numbers to prevail, or simply because a certain number of white males are needed to keep the organizational ship afloat. But now in the 2020s, after six decades in which Western women and nonwhites have been crowding into Western professions and institutions (lately empowered by blatantly anti-white-male ideology) they seem to be seriously reaching for supremacy, at least wherever white males and their mindset are less necessary.</p>
<p>In any case, one implication of this hypothesis is that adding &#8220;diversity&#8221; to an organization doesn&#8217;t necessarily bring it closer to some happy, stable equilibrium. It may, instead, disrupt what had been a relatively stable balance of forces, stimulating anew the struggle(s) for dominance in that organization&#8212;and leading to the further marginalization of white males.</p>
<p><img decoding="async" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-561" src="/wp-content/uploads/2022/04/npr.jpg" alt="" width="800" height="768" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2022/04/npr.jpg 800w, /wp-content/uploads/2022/04/npr-300x288.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2022/04/npr-768x737.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 709px) 85vw, (max-width: 909px) 67vw, (max-width: 984px) 61vw, (max-width: 1362px) 45vw, 600px" /></p>
<p>Moreover, struggles among factions within organizations reflect, and also to a great extent add up to, a struggle at the societal level. By this reasoning, increasing demographic diversity in Western societies via mass-nonwhite-immigration is simply adding fuel to the <em>kulturkampf</em> fire, making ethnic factionalism burn hotter to the detriment of most, and increasing the chances that at least in some countries, nonwhites will prevail&#8212;marginalizing whites in their own lands.</p>
<p style="text-align: center;">* * *</p>
<p><em>Author’s note:</em></p>
<p><em>I’d appreciate it, reader, if you would link to my essays on cultural feminization (or otherwise cite them) wherever you see this topic being discussed. I’ve been writing about “cult-fem” for more than a decade—which, as far as I know, is much longer than anyone else. Some of my essays have <a href="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/cultural-feminization-a-bibliography/">circulated widely</a></em><em> in recent years, and I’ve even placed <a href="https://americanmind.org/salvo/pink-shift/">one</a></em><em> in a moderately well-read webzine. I like to think that my contributions have helped seed what is becoming an important public discourse. Yet those contributions of mine are almost never acknowledged by the better-known opinionators who have ventured into this realm in the last year or so. Being pseudonymous and writing principally from a personal website seem to have left me in the unhappy state of being “much read but seldom cited.” (I discuss the general problem of citation in the Internet age in my short essay “<a href="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/the-tree-of-knowledge/">The Tree of Knowledge</a></em><em>.”)</em></p>
<p><em>Also, though I don’t charge a subscription to this website, or put ads on it, or even solicit donations, you could buy a copy of my e-book (see image below, linked to its Amazon page) if you’d like to support my writing.</em></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>I STICK MY NECK OUT FOR NOBODY</title>
		<link>/i-stick-my-neck-out-for-nobody/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[j stone]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 24 Feb 2022 03:14:23 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[fall of the West]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[psychology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Russia]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[The Right]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Ukraine]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[USA]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[wokeism]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=432</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[The West&#8217;s&#8212;and the Right&#8217;s&#8212;shame &#160; World War II ended less than two decades before I was born, yet I&#8217;ve always felt that it belonged to much more distant age&#8212;set off from modern existence by its different ways of thinking and doing, different patterns of speech and dress, grander scale of horrors and heroism, even the &#8230; <a href="/i-stick-my-neck-out-for-nobody/" class="more-link">Continue reading<span class="screen-reader-text"> "I STICK MY NECK OUT FOR NOBODY"</span></a>]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><em>The West&#8217;s&#8212;and the Right&#8217;s&#8212;shame</em></p>
<p><span id="more-432"></span></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>World War II ended less than two decades before I was born, yet I&#8217;ve always felt that it belonged to much more distant age&#8212;set off from modern existence by its different ways of thinking and doing, different patterns of speech and dress, grander scale of horrors and heroism, even the monochrome of its newsreels. The bad things, especially, seemed mostly unrepeatable in the world where I grew up.</p>
<p>American isolationism is a good example. Conservative Americans, for the longest time, didn&#8217;t want to help Britain, or Western Europe, with their struggles against Hitler and Mussolini. The USA had helped out Britain and France in 1917-18, and felt that they shouldn&#8217;t have to do anything like that again. Let Europeans sort out their own problems, they said.</p>
<p>That was <em>part</em> of their public reasoning, anyway. Another part of it seemed much more instinctive and tribal, much more driven by the false logic of &#8220;the enemy-of-my-enemy-is-my-friend&#8221;&#8212;their enemy being FDR, of course, their new friends being the Axis dictators.</p>
<p>It might seem facile to criticize the American isolationists of 1939-41 from our postwar perspective, but really they should have known better just from the information available at the time. In any case, it&#8217;s always striking now to read and hear the things they said. Here, for example, is aviator Charles Lindbergh, on September 11, 1941 (Europe conquered, Britain under siege, Wehrmacht nearing Moscow etc.), blaming the British, Roosevelt, and &#8220;the Jewish,&#8221; for pushing America towards war:</p>
<p><iframe title="Lindbergh &#039; Speech - 1941 | Movietone Moment | 11 September 2020" width="840" height="473" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/xiRYccqVPW0?feature=oembed" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen></iframe></p>
<p>The Pearl Harbor attack, less than three months later, embarrassed the America First movement into silence. Lindbergh himself spent much of the war trying to get into combat to redeem himself, and eventually <a href="http://www.charleslindbergh.com/history/b24.asp">succeeded&#8212;in getting into combat, not at redeeming himself.</a></p>
<p>But anyway, here we are again, with the same kind of geopolitical setup (armed dictator on the prowl abroad, liberal Democrats in control at home), resulting in the same strange mindset on the part of American conservatives.</p>
<p>By the way, in case this is the first essay of mine you&#8217;ve read, I&#8217;m pretty conservative too (notwithstanding David Goldman&#8217;s swipe at me, below, as a &#8220;neocon/GlobLib&#8221;). Yet the fellow conservatives who, in defiance of recent history, have started talking up Putin and talking down Ukraine, the US and the Western alliance, are now as alien to me as DEI consultants.</p>
<p>I&#8217;ve already set down my own anti-isolationist, fight-the-bad-guy <a href="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/aggressors-and-alliances/">thoughts</a> on Putin and Ukraine, a month ago on this site. Here I just want to record, mainly out of sheer amazement and chagrin, some of the sentiments I&#8217;ve been reading in recent days from elsewhere on the American right.</p>
<p>To keep things manageable, I&#8217;ve focused mainly on two prolific and very widely followed commentators, Goldman and Richard Hanania, and I&#8217;ve organized their comments by their major themes.</p>
<p><strong>&#8220;Ukraine is a corrupt and backwards place that isn&#8217;t worth defending&#8212;or invading&#8221;</strong></p>
<p><img decoding="async" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-439" src="/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/dg7.jpg" alt="" width="609" height="167" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/dg7.jpg 609w, /wp-content/uploads/2022/02/dg7-300x82.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 709px) 85vw, (max-width: 909px) 67vw, (max-width: 984px) 61vw, (max-width: 1362px) 45vw, 600px" /></p>
<p><img decoding="async" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-411" src="/wp-content/uploads/2022/01/hanania.jpg" alt="" width="603" height="662" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2022/01/hanania.jpg 603w, /wp-content/uploads/2022/01/hanania-273x300.jpg 273w" sizes="(max-width: 709px) 85vw, (max-width: 909px) 67vw, (max-width: 984px) 61vw, (max-width: 1362px) 45vw, 600px" /></p>
<p><img decoding="async" class="alignnone wp-image-468" src="/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/rh-tuckergood.jpg" alt="" width="558" height="430" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/rh-tuckergood.jpg 614w, /wp-content/uploads/2022/02/rh-tuckergood-300x232.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 558px) 85vw, 558px" /></p>
<p><img decoding="async" class="alignnone wp-image-441" src="/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/dg9.jpg" alt="" width="554" height="449" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/dg9.jpg 614w, /wp-content/uploads/2022/02/dg9-300x243.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 554px) 85vw, 554px" /></p>
<p><img decoding="async" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-442" src="/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/dg10.jpg" alt="" width="640" height="535" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/dg10.jpg 640w, /wp-content/uploads/2022/02/dg10-300x251.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 709px) 85vw, (max-width: 909px) 67vw, (max-width: 984px) 61vw, (max-width: 1362px) 45vw, 600px" /></p>
<p><img decoding="async" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-443" src="/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/dg16.jpg" alt="" width="623" height="310" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/dg16.jpg 623w, /wp-content/uploads/2022/02/dg16-300x149.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 709px) 85vw, (max-width: 909px) 67vw, (max-width: 984px) 61vw, (max-width: 1362px) 45vw, 600px" /></p>
<p><img decoding="async" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-444" src="/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/dg15.jpg" alt="" width="612" height="159" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/dg15.jpg 612w, /wp-content/uploads/2022/02/dg15-300x78.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 709px) 85vw, (max-width: 909px) 67vw, (max-width: 984px) 61vw, (max-width: 1362px) 45vw, 600px" /></p>
<p><img decoding="async" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-445" src="/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/dg17.jpg" alt="" width="617" height="296" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/dg17.jpg 617w, /wp-content/uploads/2022/02/dg17-300x144.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 709px) 85vw, (max-width: 909px) 67vw, (max-width: 984px) 61vw, (max-width: 1362px) 45vw, 600px" /></p>
<p><img decoding="async" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-449" src="/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/dg12.jpg" alt="" width="599" height="493" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/dg12.jpg 599w, /wp-content/uploads/2022/02/dg12-300x247.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 599px) 85vw, 599px" /></p>
<p><img decoding="async" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-451" src="/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/dg25.jpg" alt="" width="618" height="395" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/dg25.jpg 618w, /wp-content/uploads/2022/02/dg25-300x192.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 709px) 85vw, (max-width: 909px) 67vw, (max-width: 984px) 61vw, (max-width: 1362px) 45vw, 600px" /></p>
<p><img decoding="async" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-483" src="/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/rh-usboredw-ukraine.jpg" alt="" width="618" height="230" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/rh-usboredw-ukraine.jpg 618w, /wp-content/uploads/2022/02/rh-usboredw-ukraine-300x112.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 709px) 85vw, (max-width: 909px) 67vw, (max-width: 984px) 61vw, (max-width: 1362px) 45vw, 600px" /></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><strong>&#8220;Ukrainians are So Dumb&#8221;</strong></p>
<p><img decoding="async" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-470" src="/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/rh-ukr-dumb.jpg" alt="" width="612" height="323" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/rh-ukr-dumb.jpg 612w, /wp-content/uploads/2022/02/rh-ukr-dumb-300x158.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 709px) 85vw, (max-width: 909px) 67vw, (max-width: 984px) 61vw, (max-width: 1362px) 45vw, 600px" /></p>
<p><img decoding="async" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-492" src="/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/rh-finland.jpg" alt="" width="583" height="246" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/rh-finland.jpg 583w, /wp-content/uploads/2022/02/rh-finland-300x127.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 583px) 85vw, 583px" /></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><strong>&#8220;It&#8217;s All NATO&#8217;s/Neocons&#8217; Fault for Expanding NATO and Threatening Russia&#8221;</strong></p>
<p><img decoding="async" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-448" src="/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/dg5.jpg" alt="" width="633" height="164" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/dg5.jpg 633w, /wp-content/uploads/2022/02/dg5-300x78.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 709px) 85vw, (max-width: 909px) 67vw, (max-width: 984px) 61vw, (max-width: 1362px) 45vw, 600px" /></p>
<p><img decoding="async" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-463" src="/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/dg24.jpg" alt="" width="612" height="225" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/dg24.jpg 612w, /wp-content/uploads/2022/02/dg24-300x110.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 709px) 85vw, (max-width: 909px) 67vw, (max-width: 984px) 61vw, (max-width: 1362px) 45vw, 600px" /></p>
<p><img decoding="async" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-450" src="/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/dg20.jpg" alt="" width="631" height="401" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/dg20.jpg 631w, /wp-content/uploads/2022/02/dg20-300x191.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 709px) 85vw, (max-width: 909px) 67vw, (max-width: 984px) 61vw, (max-width: 1362px) 45vw, 600px" /></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><strong>&#8220;Putin is Smart and Will Win&#8221;</strong></p>
<p><img decoding="async" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-456" src="/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/dg4.jpg" alt="" width="632" height="316" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/dg4.jpg 632w, /wp-content/uploads/2022/02/dg4-300x150.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 709px) 85vw, (max-width: 909px) 67vw, (max-width: 984px) 61vw, (max-width: 1362px) 45vw, 600px" /></p>
<p><img decoding="async" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-457" src="/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/dg6.jpg" alt="" width="631" height="295" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/dg6.jpg 631w, /wp-content/uploads/2022/02/dg6-300x140.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 709px) 85vw, (max-width: 909px) 67vw, (max-width: 984px) 61vw, (max-width: 1362px) 45vw, 600px" /></p>
<p><img decoding="async" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-458" src="/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/dg-14.jpg" alt="" width="611" height="147" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/dg-14.jpg 611w, /wp-content/uploads/2022/02/dg-14-300x72.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 709px) 85vw, (max-width: 909px) 67vw, (max-width: 984px) 61vw, (max-width: 1362px) 45vw, 600px" /></p>
<p><img decoding="async" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-472" src="/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/rh-putingreat.jpg" alt="" width="607" height="206" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/rh-putingreat.jpg 607w, /wp-content/uploads/2022/02/rh-putingreat-300x102.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 709px) 85vw, (max-width: 909px) 67vw, (max-width: 984px) 61vw, (max-width: 1362px) 45vw, 600px" /></p>
<p><img decoding="async" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-481" src="/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/rh-rus-stronger.jpg" alt="" width="585" height="144" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/rh-rus-stronger.jpg 585w, /wp-content/uploads/2022/02/rh-rus-stronger-300x74.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 585px) 85vw, 585px" /></p>
<p><img decoding="async" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-485" src="/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/putin-69.jpg" alt="" width="607" height="316" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/putin-69.jpg 607w, /wp-content/uploads/2022/02/putin-69-300x156.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 709px) 85vw, (max-width: 909px) 67vw, (max-width: 984px) 61vw, (max-width: 1362px) 45vw, 600px" /></p>
<p><img decoding="async" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-484" src="/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/rh-noinsurgency.jpg" alt="" width="595" height="518" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/rh-noinsurgency.jpg 595w, /wp-content/uploads/2022/02/rh-noinsurgency-300x261.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 595px) 85vw, 595px" /></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><strong>&#8220;The Woke are the Real Enemy&#8212;not Putin&#8221;</strong></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><img decoding="async" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-469" src="/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/tucker1.jpg" alt="" width="527" height="412" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/tucker1.jpg 527w, /wp-content/uploads/2022/02/tucker1-300x235.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 527px) 85vw, 527px" /></p>
<p>(See also &#8220;<a href="https://slate.com/culture/2016/06/did-muhammad-ali-ever-say-no-viet-cong-ever-called-me-nigger.html">No Viet Cong Ever . . .</a>&#8220;)</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><strong>&#8220;You Neocons are So Dumb&#8221;</strong></p>
<p><img decoding="async" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-453" src="/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/dg-v-js1.jpg" alt="" width="620" height="632" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/dg-v-js1.jpg 620w, /wp-content/uploads/2022/02/dg-v-js1-294x300.jpg 294w" sizes="(max-width: 709px) 85vw, (max-width: 909px) 67vw, (max-width: 984px) 61vw, (max-width: 1362px) 45vw, 600px" /></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><strong>&#8220;Love Ukraine = Hate America&#8221;</strong></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><img decoding="async" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-467" src="/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/rh-correlation.jpg" alt="" width="602" height="427" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/rh-correlation.jpg 602w, /wp-content/uploads/2022/02/rh-correlation-300x213.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 709px) 85vw, (max-width: 909px) 67vw, (max-width: 984px) 61vw, (max-width: 1362px) 45vw, 600px" /></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><strong>&#8220;We Should Cut a Deal With Putin&#8221;</strong></p>
<p><img decoding="async" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-459" src="/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/dg21.jpg" alt="" width="616" height="554" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/dg21.jpg 616w, /wp-content/uploads/2022/02/dg21-300x270.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 709px) 85vw, (max-width: 909px) 67vw, (max-width: 984px) 61vw, (max-width: 1362px) 45vw, 600px" /></p>
<p><img decoding="async" class="alignnone wp-image-471" src="/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/rh-ukraineabjurenato.jpg" alt="" width="560" height="699" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/rh-ukraineabjurenato.jpg 597w, /wp-content/uploads/2022/02/rh-ukraineabjurenato-240x300.jpg 240w" sizes="(max-width: 560px) 85vw, 560px" /></p>
<p><img decoding="async" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-477" src="/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/rh-gas.jpg" alt="" width="583" height="161" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/rh-gas.jpg 583w, /wp-content/uploads/2022/02/rh-gas-300x83.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 583px) 85vw, 583px" /></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><strong>&#8220;Our NATO Allies Won&#8217;t Help Us&#8212;In Fact, NATO will collapse&#8221;</strong></p>
<p><img decoding="async" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-460" src="/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/dg8.jpg" alt="" width="609" height="417" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/dg8.jpg 609w, /wp-content/uploads/2022/02/dg8-300x205.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 709px) 85vw, (max-width: 909px) 67vw, (max-width: 984px) 61vw, (max-width: 1362px) 45vw, 600px" /></p>
<p><img decoding="async" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-461" src="/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/dg19.jpg" alt="" width="602" height="170" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/dg19.jpg 602w, /wp-content/uploads/2022/02/dg19-300x85.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 709px) 85vw, (max-width: 909px) 67vw, (max-width: 984px) 61vw, (max-width: 1362px) 45vw, 600px" /></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><strong>&#8220;We&#8217;ll Be Better Off When Russia and China Have More Power&#8221;</strong></p>
<p><img decoding="async" class="alignnone wp-image-473" src="/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/rh-natobad.jpg" alt="" width="562" height="190" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/rh-natobad.jpg 600w, /wp-content/uploads/2022/02/rh-natobad-300x102.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 562px) 85vw, 562px" /></p>
<p><img decoding="async" class="alignnone wp-image-474" src="/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/rh-chinacnstrained.jpg" alt="" width="473" height="461" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/rh-chinacnstrained.jpg 894w, /wp-content/uploads/2022/02/rh-chinacnstrained-300x292.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2022/02/rh-chinacnstrained-768x748.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 473px) 85vw, 473px" /></p>
<p><img decoding="async" class="alignnone wp-image-475" src="/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/rh-chinamorehumane.jpg" alt="" width="476" height="456" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/rh-chinamorehumane.jpg 616w, /wp-content/uploads/2022/02/rh-chinamorehumane-300x288.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 476px) 85vw, 476px" /></p>
<p><img decoding="async" class="alignnone wp-image-479" src="/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/rh-trumpputinsummit.jpg" alt="" width="488" height="230" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/rh-trumpputinsummit.jpg 613w, /wp-content/uploads/2022/02/rh-trumpputinsummit-300x141.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 488px) 85vw, 488px" /></p>
<p><img decoding="async" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-488" src="/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/rh-ivfbabies.jpg" alt="" width="920" height="520" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/rh-ivfbabies.jpg 920w, /wp-content/uploads/2022/02/rh-ivfbabies-300x170.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2022/02/rh-ivfbabies-768x434.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 709px) 85vw, (max-width: 909px) 67vw, (max-width: 1362px) 62vw, 840px" /></p>
<p><img decoding="async" class="alignnone wp-image-489" src="/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/rh-multipolar.jpg" alt="" width="542" height="348" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/rh-multipolar.jpg 779w, /wp-content/uploads/2022/02/rh-multipolar-300x193.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2022/02/rh-multipolar-768x493.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 542px) 85vw, 542px" /></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><strong>&#8220;Enough with the World War II Analogies!&#8221;</strong></p>
<p><img decoding="async" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-491" src="/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/rh-forgethitleranalogies.jpg" alt="" width="591" height="261" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/rh-forgethitleranalogies.jpg 591w, /wp-content/uploads/2022/02/rh-forgethitleranalogies-300x132.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 591px) 85vw, 591px" /></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><strong>&#8220;And Now For Some Other Clever Ideas&#8221;</strong></p>
<p><img decoding="async" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-464" src="/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/dg-asians.jpg" alt="" width="614" height="535" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/dg-asians.jpg 614w, /wp-content/uploads/2022/02/dg-asians-300x261.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 709px) 85vw, (max-width: 909px) 67vw, (max-width: 984px) 61vw, (max-width: 1362px) 45vw, 600px" /></p>
<p><img decoding="async" class="alignnone wp-image-494" src="/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/rh-downs.jpg" alt="" width="535" height="401" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/rh-downs.jpg 608w, /wp-content/uploads/2022/02/rh-downs-300x225.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 535px) 85vw, 535px" /></p>
<p>I&#8217;m aware that, as readers go through all these posts, they might find themselves agreeing with the sentiments expressed. But, as I post this, the long-awaited Russian offensive to conquer (presumably) Ukraine is just starting. It&#8217;s unlikely to be as dramatic for Americans as Pearl Harbor was, especially since it&#8217;s an attack on Ukraine, but modern electronic media, and weaponry, are going to be amplifying factors. I hope it will shock many of the Putin apologists and associated naysayers into rethinking their attitudes.</p>
<p style="text-align: center;">***</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>THE DESPAIR TRAP</title>
		<link>/the-despair-trap/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[j stone]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 31 Jan 2022 16:57:50 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[fall of the West]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[psychology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[science]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=418</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Terminal demoralization, the Fermi Paradox, and the true “end of history” “What is it, then, that this craving and this helplessness proclaim to us, but that there was once in man a true happiness of which there now remain to him only the mark and empty trace, which he in vain tries to fill from &#8230; <a href="/the-despair-trap/" class="more-link">Continue reading<span class="screen-reader-text"> "THE DESPAIR TRAP"</span></a>]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><em>Terminal demoralization, the Fermi Paradox, and the true “end of history”</em></p>
<p><span id="more-418"></span></p>
<hr />
<p style="padding-left: 40px;">“What is it, then, that this craving and this helplessness proclaim to us, but that there was once in man a true happiness of which there now remain to him only the mark and empty trace, which he in vain tries to fill from all his surroundings, seeking from things absent the help he does not obtain in things present? But these are all inadequate, because the infinite abyss can only be filled by an infinite and immutable object, that is to say, only by God Himself. He only is our true good, and since we have forsaken him, it is a strange thing that there is nothing in nature which has not been serviceable in taking His place; the stars, the heavens, earth, the elements, plants, cabbages, leeks, animals, insects, calves, serpents, fever, pestilence, war, famine, vices, adultery, incest. And since man has lost the true good, everything can appear equally good to him, even his own destruction&#8230;”     —Blaise Pascal, <em>Pensées</em> VII (425)</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>For as long as I can remember, people have been asking: <em>what comes next after Christianity? </em>The assumption has been that Christianity is dying, and, as Christianity once replaced the polytheisms of the classical era, so should something new and improved come along and take its place.</p>
<p>In the 1980s and 90s, there was a relatively relaxed discussion about the possibility of a kind of globalistic spiritualism (or spiritual globalism) as a successor to Christianity: a blend of New Age-y, Earth Mother paganism and save-the-whales activism. But for all the allure that body of belief and practice had for some, <a href="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/the-great-feminization/">women especially</a>, it seems to have failed so far to cohere into anything institutionally serious. Certainly there have been potent religion-substitutes, most recently political-correctness/wokeism and the high fever of the Great Awokening, but these have been just substitutes, more about policy preferences and coping with socioeconomic inequalities—what we render unto Caesar, as Christ might have said—than any reach for the infinite.</p>
<p>I suppose many Christians would say that their religion isn’t going to be replaced anytime soon, because it has been renewing itself with more popular views and practices, for example prioritizing personal religious experience over traditional ritual and hierarchy—and moreover has been spreading, or at least holding steady, in Africa and Latin America. The problem with this view is that overall measures of belief and religious participation have continued to <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Decline_of_Christianity_in_the_Western_world">decline in Western countries</a>, especially in the European home of Christianity but even in the relatively Christian United States.</p>
<p><img decoding="async" class="size-full wp-image-419 aligncenter" src="/wp-content/uploads/2022/01/pew.jpg" alt="" width="322" height="661" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2022/01/pew.jpg 322w, /wp-content/uploads/2022/01/pew-146x300.jpg 146w" sizes="(max-width: 322px) 85vw, 322px" /></p>
<p>This clear downtrend among Christianity’s original adherents suggests pretty strongly that this religion in its various forms cannot long survive prosperity, education, and the march of science, and in another few generations will be as defunct, globally, as Zoroastrianism—Islam, Judaism and Buddhism soon following it into the graveyard of theisms.</p>
<p>So again, <em>what comes next? </em>What can fill the proverbial God-shaped hole?</p>
<p>There should be some urgency to the question these days, for it is at least plausible that the decline of Christianity represents the loss of a critical source of vitality for Western societies—and is thus <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2019/09/07/opinion/sunday/the-age-of-american-despair.html">a key factor</a> in their ongoing dissolution. This dissolution is seen in the West’s high rates of mental illness, suicide, drug overdoses, and changing demographics due to immigration; and in falling rates of marriage, household formation, and fertility among those of Western heritage. Indeed, the West now appears to face the usual fate of defeated, devitalized and demoralized peoples throughout history, namely population collapse.</p>
<p><strong>Science as Spiritual Antagonist</strong></p>
<p>Having lived since childhood with the cultural expectation that a religious successor to Christianity is coming, and now in middle age failing to see any sign of such a successor on the cultural horizon, I have to suspect that there won’t be one. Science appears to have been eroding not just one or two particular ideas of God but really any idea of a transcendent being worthy of being worshipped.</p>
<p>From personal experience I expect that this process almost always works only in one direction. A person is baptized and raised in the traditions of one of the big religions, but then in the course of modern education and maturation acquires an alternative, agnostic or even atheistic view of the universe—and when that happens, the person finds it very hard to go back again to embrace religiosity and transcendence. How does one put the toothpaste back in the tube?</p>
<p>Science, in other words, seems to be a potent and broad-acting antagonist with respect to whatever part of the human psyche craves religious transcendence. It embraces the infinite, the cosmos, enough to fill the God-shaped hole, blocking all competitors, but it cannot provide the nourishment, the meaning, the seeds of morality, that one gets from a traditional religion.</p>
<p>Part of the appeal of religion is that it flatters believers with the idea that there is a transcendent Being who considers them important enough to care about. “For God so loved the world” etc. Science obliterates this conceit along with all the other traditional assumptions humans have made about their elevated rank in the universe. “Since Copernicus,” Nietzsche famously wrote, “man seems to have got himself on an inclined plane—now he is slipping faster and faster away from the center into—what? into nothingness? into a ‘penetrating sense of his nothingness?’”</p>
<p>The point here, or the suggested hypothesis, is that science, despite being beneficial to humanity in many ways, is also harmful in a critical psychological way. This is not a new idea, but it and its implications seem to have been underexplored, to say the least. Do science’s malign effects outweigh its benign effects? What if science inevitably sets up a “despair trap” through which any sentient species can pass only with difficulty? Does this putative barrier explain the so-called Fermi Paradox, named for the Nobel-winning physicist Enrico Fermi—who wondered why, if life evolves so easily in the universe, ET civilizations aren’t abundantly evident to us?</p>
<p><strong>Increasingly Toxic Knowledge</strong></p>
<p>Most people are protected from the toxic effects of science by their lack of awareness of, and interest in, the parts of science that deal with the nature of reality and the universe—the parts that blot out the warm sun of the old religions. But, as science takes an ever-larger role in education, in politics, in popular media content and so on, people increasingly will have to confront these toxic parts. Those who absorb such knowledge would not even have to be consciously aware of its toxic effect on them. The pathways and processes connecting learned information to depression and demoralization could work slowly, and entirely “below the limen,” in the unconscious parts of the mind.</p>
<p>In any case, one can easily get the gist of this demoralizing knowledge by skimming through any contemporary popular treatment of cosmology. There one will find laid out, in the weirdly upbeat prose preferred by publishers, cosmologists’ conviction that Earth and its humans make up an infinitesimal speck within a reality comprised of vast, multiple and multiply-dimensioned universes. The acceptance of such a reality raises an obvious and discomfiting question: Would a God that reigns supreme over such a vastness really take notice of an insignificant and presumably backward species such as ours?</p>
<p>The more one reads about the modern scientific understanding of reality, the worse it gets. Arguably the most important scientific advance of the past century is quantum mechanics (QM). The fundamental mathematical equations of this discipline, derived in the 1920s from experimental observations, have been proved accurate again and again, and are the basis for many modern technologies. Yet the physical reality suggested by QM’s equations is severely at odds with the ways in which humans tend to think about themselves and their world. Indeed, the prevailing theory about QM reality is about as cold and nihilistic as any theory could be.</p>
<p>This prevailing theory was originally called the Relative State Formulation by its inventor (a lapsed Catholic named Hugh Everett, who died in relative obscurity in 1982), but is now famously known as the Many Worlds Interpretation (MWI). It suggests that the particles constituting the fabric of “reality” exist naturally not as discrete, individual objects but as what might be called an interconnected multiplicity of states—a ghostly multiplicity that indicates the presence of <em>separate worlds or universes. </em></p>
<p>In other words, while our reality <em>appears</em> to be constructed of discrete particles, and we generally experience only one world or universe that appears to proceed probabilistically along one timeline, there is in fact a wider reality—a “multiverse”—consisting of an infinitude of other universes.</p>
<p>MWI may be hard to understand if one hasn’t had much physics. But its central idea is that, across the multiverse, everything happens that can happen. In other words, at any moment, the particles that make up any object, including a human, have, collectively, a vast number of immediate futures. These are not <em>possible</em> futures&#8212;they all happen/exist, just in different universes. Over short intervals, on the order of seconds or fractions of a second, the differences between these alternate outcomes will be relatively subtle, a matter of slight, seemingly random variations in the positions and other attributes of the subatomic particles making up the object of interest. However, as time goes on—as seconds run to days and years—the differences in outcomes increase dramatically, and of course every branch on this tree of possibility keeps branching again and again, with every femtosecond tick of the cosmic clock. Thus, any person, or any other object, faces at any moment a near-infinitude of futures, and, again, each of these—according to MWI—actually happens in a separate universe within the multiverse.</p>
<p>I&#8217;ve never seen any emphasis of this point in popular treatments of MWI, but the theory suggests that the multiverse&#8212;all Creation&#8212;has a perfect completeness. Its history could be imagined as a closed book on which each page has been inked solid black with the superimposed imprints of innumerable typed and re-typed characters. From the perspective of its godlike author, the book would contain every possible story. From the perspective of an individual human, incapable of perceiving more than one (very brief) timeline, it would contain only the story through which he has lived—though, again, this individual human would really have been only one manifestation of a rather hazily defined collective entity that, from the moment of birth and at every moment thereafter, proliferated into every possible variation of identity and experience.</p>
<p>Whether the ever-branching universes that make up the multiverse are created ex nihil, or already exist—beyond time as it were—in a meta-realm of every possibility (that closed book of over-inked pages) is something that MWI theorists still debate. But the implications for the human self-image are just as dire either way.</p>
<p>In essence, “you” will have been a hero in some of the worlds you have lived through, a villain in others, a nonentity in most. From the perspective of a god who sees all these timelines, do you deserve punishment for your villainy, praise for your heroism, scorn or pity for your nonentity-ness? Wouldn’t such a god understand, instead, that you—far from having any agency in the way that humans instinctively assume—have been fundamentally <em>obliged</em> to be all things, across all your timelines, simply to fill out the full space of possibilities comprising multiversal reality?</p>
<p>And from the perspective of such a god—or of any entity that can apprehend the reality of the multiverse—what are the histories, written or experienced, of myopic humans who think the one universe they perceive is all there is? Do these single-timeline accounts have any more significance than, say, the precise arrangements of handfuls of sand tossed by random children on a beach? These arrangements, these histories, may be influenced by “laws” that relate precedents to outcomes. But the fundamental variability that drives them, collectively, to satisfy every possibility, suggests that their individual significances to an MWI-perceiving god would be nothing—zero.</p>
<p>Does MWI’s final reduction of the “meaning of life” to absolute zero really have dire implications for humanity? Must we believe, with Pascal, that the human psyche has within it an “<em>infinite</em> abyss” that “can <em>only</em> be filled by an <em>infinite</em> and <em>immutable</em> object”? Humans like other animals have evolved, first and foremost, to live and to procreate. Moreover, through medical advances that enable longer and longer lifespans, humans may soon start to see themselves as very godlike.</p>
<p>Yet humans are a contemplative species, and if they can be inspired by contemplating some things, so can they be depressed—even to suicide—by contemplating others. What could be more depressing for them than to become aware of their imprisonment within one tiny solar system, in one vast universe of implicitly zero meaning and significance, inside an infinitely wider multiverse. Hugh Everett himself appears to have felt this conflict and its implications, in the sense that he became an atheist who smoke, drank, and ate to excess—essentially killing himself with a heart attack at the age of only 51—and before he died specified that his remains should be thrown away like garbage.</p>
<p><strong>Beware ETs Bearing Gifts</strong></p>
<p>Humans appear to be bound to confront QM and MWI not only through popular science literature and routine technical education, but also as quantum technology (especially quantum computing) starts to replace conventional technology in many applications&#8212;causing users of the new tech to wonder, <em>how does this really work?</em></p>
<p>Conceivably, modern societies, through some radical cultural shift—perhaps driven by the <a href="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/the-day-the-logic-died/">new and unprecedented cultural power of women</a>—will avoid this confrontation by turning away from science. The elevation of science that we see in the modern West is, after all, a relatively recent cultural choice, one that not every civilization has made. By rejecting that choice, for example as the Amish have, humans could protect themselves from MWI and similar toxic knowledge indefinitely. For now, though, it seems unlikely they will choose such a radical change of direction.</p>
<p>Another possibility we tend to overlook is that humans, whatever their choices, might nevertheless be abruptly <em>forced</em> to confront toxic scientific knowledge, if an extraterrestrial civilization were ever to visit Earth and attempt communication. What is the nature of reality? How is the fabric of existence constructed? Those are among the first questions we would ask visitors from a more advanced, star-faring civilization.</p>
<p>Martin Amis once touched upon this theme in a short story titled “<a href="https://www.newyorker.com/magazine/1998/10/26/the-janitor-on-mars">The Janitor on Mars</a>,” which, suffice it to say, was pretty dark in its view of human morale and morality in the context of an encounter with a superior ET civilization bearing nihilistic cosmological revelations. The least dark element of the story was the impending sudden destruction of the Earth and extinction of humans. In real life, humans probably wouldn’t be granted such a mercy, and would have to die off slowly, one by one in “deaths of despair,” and multitude by multitude in suicide cults and wars.</p>
<p>The fact that craft from ET civilizations are, at least, scarce in Earth’s skies, could thus reflect not only a “despair trap” that strangles most technical civilizations in their cradles, but also the awareness—among those fortunate civilizations that have survived the trap—of the potent effect of the knowledge they carry, on such naïve and primitive species as ours.</p>
<p style="text-align: center;">***</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
