<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>Thoughts of Stone</title>
	<atom:link href="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/</link>
	<description>short essays, usually about humans</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Sat, 01 Jan 2022 22:26:38 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=5.7.4</generator>

<image>
	<url>https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2020/07/cropped-icon-32x32.jpg</url>
	<title>Thoughts of Stone</title>
	<link>https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/</link>
	<width>32</width>
	<height>32</height>
</image> 
	<item>
		<title>SMASH THE FOUR OLDS!</title>
		<link>https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/smash-the-four-olds/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[j stone]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 31 Dec 2021 20:30:59 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[ethnicity]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[fall of the West]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[freedom of speech]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[immigration]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[USA]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[wokeism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[women]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/?p=362</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Four roots of American degeneracy &#160; Americans who watch with dismay the erasure of various symbols of their history and traditions—statues of Robert E. Lee, Theodore Roosevelt, etc.—might take comfort from certain facts about the Chinese Cultural Revolution, which occurred during 1966-76. The CCR was similar in character but vastly greater in its extremism than &#8230; <a href="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/smash-the-four-olds/" class="more-link">Continue reading<span class="screen-reader-text"> "SMASH THE FOUR OLDS!"</span></a>]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><em>Four roots of American degeneracy</em></p>
<p><span id="more-362"></span></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>Americans who watch with dismay the erasure of various symbols of their history and traditions—statues of Robert E. Lee, Theodore Roosevelt, etc.—might take comfort from certain facts about the Chinese Cultural Revolution, which occurred during 1966-76.</p>
<p>The CCR was similar in character but vastly greater in its extremism than what America has been experiencing at the hands of its wokeist mobs. The CCR’s spearpoints were cadres of “Red Guard” fanatics, young people (even teens) whose instability and restlessness, suggestibility, and high susceptibility to fanaticism were probably comparable to what one finds in today’s Antifa brigades.</p>
<p>These howling Maoist minions sought the erasure of whatever competed with Maoism, which in practice meant just about anything predating Maoist China—history books, art, architecture, temples, even genealogical records. Red Guards and their camp followers toppled statues of Confucius, pasted huge banners with their slogans everywhere, and went around attacking intellectuals or anyone even lightly connected to the teaching of pre-Maoist history or philosophy.</p>
<p>There was a strong irrational element in all this—indeed, the CCR was reminiscent of the orgiastic, throw-out-all-inhibitions themes in the old feasts of pagan Europe. It suggests, ironically, that the mostly simple, agrarian Chinese had been chafing under the saddle of Maoist collectivism and needed some release—even if that release served Maoist purposes. There was not only a lot of physical harassment and assault of ordinary people going about their business—there was murder and even cannibalism.</p>
<p style="padding-left: 40px;">At some high schools, students killed their principals in the school courtyard and then cooked and ate the bodies to celebrate a triumph over &#8220;counterrevolutionaries&#8221; . . .  Government-run cafeterias are said to have displayed bodies dangling on meat hooks and to have served human flesh to employees. [<a href="https://www.nytimes.com/1993/01/06/world/a-tale-of-red-guards-and-cannibals.html">NYT</a>]</p>
<p>Not content with attacking living reminders of the old China, Red Guards also broke into cemeteries and dug up the skeletal remains of ancient Chinese emperors and nobles, desecrating them and denouncing the persons these remains had once been.</p>
<p>Amid this hysterical savagery, the Chinese government closed schools and universities, sending tens of millions of urban students, including those who hoped to be scientists and engineers, to do hard labor on collective farms in the countryside. Overall, for as long as its radicalism prevailed, the CCR created a mini Dark Age in China.</p>
<p>So one simple lesson from this is that, however badly Americans think they have suffered under the Great Awokening, it could have been much, much worse.</p>
<p>Another, arguably more important point is that the CCR didn’t last forever. It was so extreme that, like many mass hysteria-type episodes, it became just absurd, dying of its own absurdity—and I guess for many of those caught up in its fervor, it was an emotional storm that ultimately blew over. The CCR also effectively immunized many Chinese, both ordinary and elite, against ideological excesses—which in turn helped pave the way for the liberalization and wealth explosion that occurred in China in the decades that followed.</p>
<p><strong>The Four Olds</strong></p>
<p>There are obvious differences between the dynamics of the CCR on the one hand, and those of the Great Awokening on the other. The Awokening has been less centralized, for example, and has had a weaker connection to government. Moreover, although the Awokening may draw some of its strength from reliably impressionable young people, it also—unlike the CCR, which occurred in a less feminized society—seems particularly well rooted among managerial-class (“elite”) women, whose <a href="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/the-critical-mass-problem/">affinity for wokeness</a> may be much more durable.</p>
<p>Still, the Awokening’s most feverish period of statue-toppling, city-burning, and curriculum-rewriting (“math is racist”) seems to have ended. The supporting regime has failed to entrench itself with new laws, and there are many signs of popular opposition. In short, the Awokening in the United States is running out of steam, and may face reversal even in many states where it has been running rampant.</p>
<p>It therefore makes sense to start thinking about how best to empower and sustain this reversal. In other words, in the long term, in America and presumably other affected countries, how can wokeism be cured and its recurrence suppressed?</p>
<p>My suggestion is to follow an example set by the Red Guards themselves—not an example of their savagery, of course, but of their simplicity of messaging.</p>
<p>One of the CCR’s most enduring slogans was “Smash the Four Olds!” the “Four Olds” being the “customs, cultures, habits, and ideas” of pre-Maoist China. The Chinese, maybe for simple mnemonic reasons, have a thing for <a href="https://apnews.com/article/c1ebc231b1c9c857d64e95581e2eb881">numbered lists</a> in their public slogans—certainly Mao did—and so this particular slogan was crafted accordingly (though they might have said simply “Down With Pre-Maoist Culture”). The Awokening, on the other hand, and I would say American degeneracy in general, really does have distinct conceptual roots, the elimination of which may be a necessary condition for long-term societal health.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><strong>#1        “Diversity is Our Strength”</strong></p>
<p>This idea, a contagious pathogen to which Western societies seem peculiarly prone, may have originated in the “we’re all God’s children” universalism of Christianity—a universalism originally fashioned by St. Paul et al for the multi-ethnic world temporarily united under imperial Rome. The march of technology and science has since weakened other elements of Christianity, but the diversity-worshipping element has been continually stimulated to grow in Western societies, far beyond its original religious context, by the irritant of white-black conflict in the United States, and by flows of non-Western immigrants to Western democracies amid the globalization of trade and labor and declines in Western birthrates. That’s a simplification of what has happened, but not a very wrong one, I think.</p>
<p>Although I’m making a list here, not an extended argument, I think there is ample evidence (including from my own <a href="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/seed-of-destruction/">life experience</a> as an expatriate) that societies with ethnic supermajorities, i.e., some diversity but not much, are not only typical and traditional but also are greatly preferable to societies with high ethnic diversity.</p>
<p>Shared ethnicity is a far more potent source of sociopolitical affinity compared to the thin set of abstract values (“respect for the rule of law!”) that supposedly binds people in multi-ethnic societies. Thus, in multi-ethnic societies, we would expect political factions to form largely along ethnic lines, leading ultimately to ethnic-based conflict or at least a serious divergence of interests. In Western multi-ethnic societies, that divergence of interests already features not only sticks and bricks and guns, but also factionally crafted laws and dogmatic falsehoods designed to harm one side or another.</p>
<p>Mass immigration from ethnically and culturally distant places harms a society in other ways too, involving issues of economics, social trust, and identity. But the fact that it sets up inter-ethnic conflict is already a sufficient reason to put it in the dustbin of history.</p>
<p>Disparate peoples can commingle and ultimately become one people—that is one of the fundamental themes of world history. But the sorry results of Western experiments with multi-ethnicism suggest that this commingling works much better when done at a slower, more natural pace.</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-364" src="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2022/01/ethiopes.jpg" alt="" width="1120" height="682" srcset="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2022/01/ethiopes.jpg 1120w, https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2022/01/ethiopes-300x183.jpg 300w, https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2022/01/ethiopes-1024x624.jpg 1024w, https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2022/01/ethiopes-768x468.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 709px) 85vw, (max-width: 909px) 67vw, (max-width: 1362px) 62vw, 840px" /></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><strong>#2        “The Future is Female”</strong></p>
<p>As I’ve suggested in several <a href="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/cultural-feminization-a-bibliography/">essays</a> over the past decade, women for plausible evo-psych reasons tend to approach issues of culture and policy differently than men do, and thus their ascension to cultural and political power in the USA and other Western countries in recent decades has been accompanied by dramatic cultural and political changes.</p>
<p>I have proposed (good summaries are <a href="https://americanmind.org/salvo/pink-shift/">here</a> and <a href="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/we-need-to-talk-about-women/">here</a>) that the trait that acts as the chief driver of these changes is women’s greater emotional sensitivity, and that this greater sensitivity, now unleashed in the public sphere—presumably having been adapted by evolution for motherhood and home life—is leading to a host of bad outcomes. These bad outcomes include a retreat from traditional Western liberalism (free speech, free scientific inquiry, due process of law), an unthinking embrace of the “diversity is our strength” fallacy, and a generally enhanced proneness to social contagions.</p>
<p>Essentially women, now that they have power, have been remodeling Western civilization to suit their ways of thinking, without fully appreciating what they are doing, let alone acknowledging that they might&#8212;on average compared to men&#8212;have significant shortcomings in this capacity. This problem is exacerbated by the fact that women&#8217;s new cultural/political power, and their apparently greater ability to <a href="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/girl-power/">cohere against perceived enemies</a>—to cancel them or worse—makes the subject of women&#8217;s potential shortcomings unmentionable in mainstream discourse.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><strong>#3        “Governance is Gibs”</strong></p>
<p>Partly as a ratchet-effect holdover of major economic crises (e.g., the Great Depression), partly because politicians in democracies are constantly tempted to buy votes (in effect), and partly because of the feminization (see #2 above) of the elites that shape culture and policy, the provision of “welfare” in one form or another is now the major focus of modern government in the US and other Western countries.</p>
<p>Probably most Americans now don’t even think to question this historic shift. Yet it should be clear that this modern Hyper-Welfarism has inherent inefficiencies and long-term adverse effects, and thus usually worsens the problems it was meant to ameliorate. Its powerful enabling of the centrifugal forces threatening the African American family—resulting in skyrocketing rates of out-of-wedlock births—is one of its most cited adverse effects. But really it weakens individuals and groups across society: by creating dependencies; by taking away traditional disincentives to antisocial behaviors; by vastly increasing the burden on taxpayers; and by displacing (e.g., in the healthcare economy) more local or market-based organizations and forces that would have produced better solutions.</p>
<p>Worst of all, the overwhelming government emphasis on welfare provision gives elites&#8212;wokeified elites in the US&#8217;s case&#8212;enormous power to manipulate society by lavishing rewards on their factional friends and withholding them from their enemies.</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" class="size-full wp-image-381 aligncenter" src="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/bidendiscrim.jpg" alt="" width="600" height="437" srcset="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/bidendiscrim.jpg 600w, https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/bidendiscrim-300x219.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 709px) 85vw, (max-width: 909px) 67vw, (max-width: 984px) 61vw, (max-width: 1362px) 45vw, 600px" /></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><strong>#4        “We’re the Best Because We’re a Democracy”</strong></p>
<p>It became weirdly fashionable at the start of the Great Awokening, when American cities were burning and the stability of the World’s Top Democracy was in question, to exclaim that . . . <a href="https://www.jstor.org/stable/24027184">Fukuyama</a> was right all along! Democracy <em>is</em> the end-stage of political history! These riots and lootings represent only a bumpy patch! Fukuyama specifically warned that there would be bumpy patches!</p>
<p>Maybe it’s just my own bias at work, but I also had the impression that this desperate optimism about democracy went . . . very quiet . . . a few months later, after the US election with its orgies of ballot harvesting and other irregularities, and the follow-on push by the new, woke administration 1) to rejig election laws to enable ballot harvesting forever; and 2) to open the southern border to pack the electorate in their favor.</p>
<p>In any case, it should be obvious that on the subject of democracy these days, someone like <a href="https://www.unqualified-reservations.org/2007/07/democracy-as-adaptive-fiction/">Curtis Yarvin</a> is more relevant than Fukuyama.</p>
<p>My point here is that the USA since its founding has gone from a cautious and relatively rational approach to the problem of political structure to an unthinking worship of &#8220;democracy&#8221;&#8212;a worship that is not merely irrational but also actively <em>harms</em> Americans and their society, mainly by concealing the antidemocratic power of the country&#8217;s out-of-control (and again, wokeified) elites.</p>
<p>The term &#8220;democracy&#8221; as used these days is apt to be misleading. No one really has a democracy in the pure sense. Virtually any government, from monarchical dictatorship to a theoretical rule-by-referendum, involves a certain (at least <em>de facto</em>) allocation of power to the ruling elites, on the one hand, and to “the people” on the other. There may be different factions among the elites, and among the people, and of course different styles of government&#8212;suited for different populations&#8212;which will vary in how they balance elite power and people power. But no large country has ever lacked a political and cultural elite.</p>
<p>Yet democracy-worship in America has encouraged the false belief that one can do without an elite, or even that elites don’t exist in the country anymore. In other words, instead of acknowledging elites, limiting their powers, and inculcating in them a certain level of responsibility toward the people (once called <em>noblesse oblige</em>), the American cultural and political system&#8212;led by elites themselves&#8212;effectively has encouraged elites to believe that they are not elites, and have no special responsibilities. This seems to be a crucial weak point in the American (and more generally Western) political order, and I think it has contributed to the  dissolution of Western societies in many ways, including via the mass immigration that elites embrace, at everyone else&#8217;s cost, because (they think) it benefits themselves.</p>
<p>In short, then, a successful political system probably requires at least some acknowledgment, if not protection, of its elite class, combined with measures to limit elites&#8217; power and curb their selfishness&#8211;above all, to protect ordinary people and their basic way of life from whatever stupid ideology happens to possess elites at a given time. Whether one calls the resulting system a “democracy,” “republic,” “oligarchy” etc. is, <em>per se</em>, less important. And again, from this perspective, formulations such as “democracy is the best” or “we&#8217;re the best because we&#8217;re a democracy” are not merely nonsensical; they are also toxic.</p>
<p style="text-align: center;">***</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>CULTURAL FEMINIZATION: A BIBLIOGRAPHY</title>
		<link>https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/cultural-feminization-a-bibliography/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[j stone]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 14 Dec 2021 06:29:13 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[wokeism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[women]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/?page_id=347</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[An incomplete list, but maybe useful. The idea that women, on average compared to men, think differently, behave differently, and vote differently, is not a new one. What I think has some originality, though—certainly it seems to have been too hot, as recently as a few months ago, for any MSM or MSM-adjacent editor to &#8230; <a href="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/cultural-feminization-a-bibliography/" class="more-link">Continue reading<span class="screen-reader-text"> "CULTURAL FEMINIZATION: A BIBLIOGRAPHY"</span></a>]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><em>An incomplete list, but maybe useful.</em></p>
<p><span id="more-347"></span></p>
<p>The idea that women, on average compared to men, think differently, behave differently, and vote differently, is not a new one. What I think has some originality, though—certainly it seems to have been too hot, as recently as a few months ago, for any MSM or MSM-adjacent editor to handle—is the idea that women, especially by entering culturally influential professions <em>en masse</em> since the 1960s, have transformed Western societies: pulling them leftward and introducing political correctness, etc., but more precisely <em>feminizing</em> them, with arguably dire implications for Western civilization.</p>
<p>In case it’s useful to others writing in this area (and because like most creative people I crave credit), I’ve listed some of my relevant works in this area—and all the ones I’m now aware of from other writers.</p>
<p><strong>From me</strong></p>
<p>2011    “<a href="https://james-the-obscure.github.io/the-demise-of-guythink/">The Demise of Guythink</a>”</p>
<p>An old blog post, and my first and probably briefest expression of the cultural feminization hypothesis. Inspired by something controversial Jeremy Clarkson said, and also by the Larry Summers controversy which I would later write about in more detail.</p>
<p>2014    “<a href="https://james-the-obscure.github.io/motherland/">Motherland</a>”</p>
<p>Also an old blog post but a much longer, more discursive account of the hypothesis. Most of the pieces I’ve written since then have been, for the most part, compressed versions of the ideas expressed here.</p>
<p>2014    “<a href="https://www.returnofkings.com/42976/thanks-to-progressivism-america-is-no-country-for-men">No Country for Men</a>” (<em>Return of Kings</em>)</p>
<p>I got this published on Roosh V’s <em>Return of Kings</em> website (under a pseudonym I no longer use).</p>
<p><a id="set-post-thumbnail" class="thickbox" href="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-admin/media-upload.php?post_id=347&amp;type=image&amp;TB_iframe=1"></a>2017    “[different titles]”</p>
<p>A personal blog post—extremely mild version of the cult-fem theory—I eventually took down because it started costing me professionally.</p>
<p>2019    “<a href="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/the-great-feminization/">The Great Feminization</a>”</p>
<p>Essay on a new website, not using my real name—a relatively brief version of the cult-fem theory, with a bit at the end about testosterone levels and fertility that is probably somewhat relevant, though not really central to the theory. I started the website and placed the essay on it because I had offered a version of the piece to two or three conservative webzines, with no luck.</p>
<p>(Tyler Cowen linked to this essay in his Marginal Revolution blog two and a half years later, prompting a flood of readers.)</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" class="size-full wp-image-348 aligncenter" src="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/cowen.jpg" alt="" width="660" height="435" srcset="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/cowen.jpg 660w, https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/cowen-300x198.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 709px) 85vw, (max-width: 909px) 67vw, (max-width: 984px) 61vw, (max-width: 1362px) 45vw, 600px" /></p>
<p>2019    “<a href="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/the-day-the-logic-died/">The Day the Logic Died</a>”</p>
<p>A fuller account of the 2005 Larry Summers “intrinsic aptitude” controversy/hysteria, with some cult-fem theory. <span style="text-decoration: underline;">If you read just one of my essays, make it this one</span>. A favorable reference to this in a tweet from @toad_spotted, some weeks after it was posted, induced many thousands of people to read it—and the “Great Feminization” piece&#8212;and encouraged me to keep writing.</p>
<p>2020    “<a href="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/girl-power/">Girl Power</a>”</p>
<p>Some cult-fem theory here, touching on women’s greater ability to form networks/coalitions, especially to cancel (or prosecute) men. Mainly, though, this was an examination of #MeToo-type cases against the historical background of hysterias including medieval/early-modern convent hysterias, Salem, modern recovered-memory case epidemics, etc.</p>
<p>2021    “<a href="https://americanmind.org/salvo/pink-shift/">Pink Shift</a>” (<em>The American Mind</em>)</p>
<p>Short piece summarizing the theory&#8212;thanks again to James Poulos &amp; Co. for publishing it.</p>
<p>2021    “<a href="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/the-critical-mass-problem/">The Critical Mass Problem</a>”</p>
<p>More on the apparently superior female ability to form networks and transmit social contagions, as a general source of political/social instability. “The Great Awokening’s transformation of big institutions reflects not only the general fear of personal cancellation within these institutions but also the ‘critical mass’ of susceptible women who work in them.”</p>
<p>2021    “<a href="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/we-need-to-talk-about-women/">We Need to Talk about Women</a>”</p>
<p>Re-emphasis of the key points, including the likely long-term adverse effects of cultural feminization on liberal Western societies.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><strong>Other writers</strong></p>
<p>My initial online searches using keywords like “feminization” were curiously uninformative (a lot of stuff on trans medical issues), but after Tyler Cowen linked to my “Great Feminization” essay two months ago, I started digging again. I’m sure this is still a very incomplete list.</p>
<p>Note that Cowen himself has <a href="https://www.bloomberg.com/opinion/articles/2021-09-19/woke-movement-is-global-and-america-should-be-mostly-proud">written</a> about feminization in occasional columns and blog posts, going back at least a few years.</p>
<p>1985    <a href="https://www.amazon.com/Feminization-America-Womens-Changing-Private/dp/B000R3AQ4A"><em>The Feminization of America</em></a> (Elinor Lenz &amp; Barbara Myerhoff)</p>
<p>The authors “envision the emergence of a new `feminized’ America, a society made more human, less destructive, and more compassionate by women&#8217;s nurturing and integrative influences in all walks of life.”</p>
<p>1987    “<a href="https://www.commentary.org/articles/james-nuechterlein/the-feminization-of-the-american-left/">The Feminization of the American Left</a>” (James Neuchterlein, <em>Commentary</em>)</p>
<p>Contrasts modern leftism with the more masculine leftism of yore. “Feminization, as understood here, suggests the establishment of traditionally feminine virtues (those normally associated with the private realm) as norms of behavior for public life. It indicates an ethic of noncoercion, a preference for emotion over rational analysis and for noncompetitive modes of social interaction, a focus on being rather than doing and on interpersonal relations as the primary preoccupation of the good life.”</p>
<p>1998    <em><a href="https://www.amazon.com/Feminization-American-Culture-Ann-Douglas/dp/0374525587">The Feminization of American Culture</a></em> (Ann Douglas)</p>
<p>Not as relevant as its title suggests. Douglas argues that in the late 19<sup>th</sup> century American literature became “feminized” with “books that idealized the very qualities that kept [women] powerless: timidity, piety, and a disdain for competition.”</p>
<p>2006?  “<a href="https://www.seattleweekly.com/news/when-did-we-all-become-women/">When Did We All Become Women?</a>” (Kathryn Robinson, <em>Seattle Weekly</em>)</p>
<p>“Think of values like nurturing and caring, emotion and sentimentality, connection and community, passivity and submission, vanity and appearance, cooperation and equality, openness and access, manipulation and influence. These are the values on the ascendancy in our public and private lives.” Robinson covers the ground pretty well, and projects the same sense of awe that I had when I started to perceive the significance of this unprecedented cultural development. (Her piece may have been buried in the search rankings until <a href="https://marginalrevolution.com/marginalrevolution/2021/08/when-did-we-all-become-women.html">Cowen linked to it</a> a few months ago. Also, the 2006 date attached to the article may have been the date of uploading to the web, not the original magazine publication date.)</p>
<p style="text-align: center;">***</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>WE NEED TO TALK ABOUT WOMEN</title>
		<link>https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/we-need-to-talk-about-women/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[j stone]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 13 Dec 2021 10:20:02 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[fall of the West]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[immigration]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[USA]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[wokeism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[women]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/?p=331</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Once more unto the breach, dear friends. I’ve written about women and their cultural/political ascendancy so much in recent years, especially the last three, that I worry about sounding like the proverbial broken record if I write any more. But it seems to me that as this idea is accepted more widely—including by commentators who &#8230; <a href="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/we-need-to-talk-about-women/" class="more-link">Continue reading<span class="screen-reader-text"> "WE NEED TO TALK ABOUT WOMEN"</span></a>]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><em>Once more unto the breach, dear friends.</em></p>
<p><span id="more-331"></span></p>
<p>I’ve written about women and their cultural/political ascendancy so much in recent years, especially the last three, that I worry about sounding like the proverbial broken record if I write any more. But it seems to me that as this idea is accepted more widely—including by commentators who see it as their own idea . . .</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" class="size-full wp-image-340 aligncenter" src="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/harrington.jpg" alt="" width="536" height="385" srcset="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/harrington.jpg 536w, https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/harrington-300x215.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 536px) 85vw, 536px" /></p>
<p>. . . there is a tendency to narrow the focus (e.g., “female graduates,” “HR ladies,” or “women explain wokeness”) so that the true extent of the West’s feminization is obscured.</p>
<p>Moreover, the case can be made that feminization is having not only an enormous but also a potentially fatal impact on Western civilization as we have known it. Thus, thumping the tub about this subject may be a good and necessary thing to do now.</p>
<p>To that end, I think at least several key points within this overall hypothesis bear repeating:</p>
<p><strong>Women’s broad cultural/political ascendancy has been reshaping the West for decades</strong></p>
<p>The big idea here is that women have been the principal drivers not only of the creeping wokeism post 2015 or so, and of the ongoing semi-spiritual movement known as the Great Awokening, but also of the general “leftward” (<a href="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/the-day-the-logic-died/">in fact, “feminine”</a>) trends in Western culture and politics over the last six-plus decades. This is the period in which women moved <em>en masse</em> into, and achieved parity or dominance within, culturally and politically influential professions such as journalism, publishing, entertainment, law, academia, politics, even blogging.</p>
<p>It is not just from one or two of those professions but from all of them, and in every circumstance along the way (e.g., university life, engagement with social media, office politics, voting, protest marches), that women have been causing cultural and political change, effectively feminizing the West to a degree never seen before in any large civilization.</p>
<p>Activist women—mostly single, university-educated, and/or young—may be the “shock troops” of feminization, and the most dedicated and effective practitioners of wokeism and cancel culture. But women <em>in general</em> have been driving this social transformation.</p>
<p><strong>Women’s ascension to cultural and political power has had cultural and political consequences because women on average are different than men across a wide range of attitudes and behaviors</strong></p>
<p>Gender differences in attitudes and behaviors were presumably shaped—at a biological level with changes that cannot easily be undone—by men’s and women’s distinct roles during the long period of hominid evolution, roles that for women centered on maternity. Women even now in modern times appear to be markedly more emotionally sensitive than men on average, quicker to form social networks, less interested in abstract and inanimate things, less interested in systems, more personal (including <em>ad hominem</em>) in their thinking, and more fearful—not just of ideas and people they dislike but also of toxins and other putative environmental threats. All these differences have had cultural and policy consequences as women’s power has increased in societies designed and traditionally run by men. One could say that women effectively have been using their new cultural and political power to renovate and redecorate their civilization according to their distinctive tastes. As Virginia Woolf put it in her 1938 essay, “Three Guineas”:</p>
<p style="padding-left: 40px;">Let us never cease from thinking—what is this “civilization” in which we find ourselves?</p>
<p><strong>Cultural/political feminization therefore involves a multitude of changes</strong></p>
<p>Cultural and political changes that have plausibly been driven by the ascendancy of women in Western societies are not limited to the extreme changes associated with “wokeism.” They include also relatively mild and gradual, long-term trends:</p>
<ul>
<li style="list-style-type: none;">
<ul>
<li>more extensive and generous welfare programs;</li>
<li>more rights, often including reverse-discrimination-type rights, for “traditionally disadvantaged” or otherwise marginalized groups (blacks, Hispanics, nonwhite immigrants, women, gays, transsexuals, etc.);</li>
<li>more emphasis generally in culture and policy on “equality of outcomes” over “equal opportunity,” and on guilt and compassion (vs. dispassionate, long-term calculation) as drivers of policy and social change;</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<p><img loading="lazy" class="size-full wp-image-332 aligncenter" src="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/mo.jpg" alt="" width="300" height="168" /></p>
<ul>
<li style="list-style-type: none;">
<ul>
<li>more emphasis on “trauma”—emotional upset—everywhere from journalism to law and medicine, with a related emergence of trauma-memory (PTSD) or otherwise trauma-related syndromes that are strongly contagious and now highly prevalent;</li>
<li>less affinity for traditional, often Constitutionally protected forms of (emotionally painful) confrontation such as free speech and free debate, free scientific inquiry, and due process of law (e.g., the right to face one’s accuser, and the right to cross-examine)—and increasing affinity for systems that suppress and punish “unacceptable” speech;</li>
<li>the acceptance of what amount to special rules for women when they are complainants against men in sex-related court cases, e.g., they can bring cases decades after the alleged crime, and when they claim to have been abused by men they later dated or exchanged love-notes with, their claims are still taken seriously—are simply chalked up to their presumed trauma;</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<p><img loading="lazy" class="wp-image-333 aligncenter" src="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/weinstein1.jpg" alt="" width="391" height="298" srcset="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/weinstein1.jpg 680w, https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/weinstein1-300x228.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 391px) 85vw, 391px" /></p>
<ul>
<li style="list-style-type: none;">
<ul>
<li>the intrusion of distinctively feminine values into the traditionally male-dominated world of sports, such that, for example, athletes putting their “self-care” instincts over their competitive instincts are not derided but celebrated;</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<p><img loading="lazy" class="wp-image-334 aligncenter" src="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/biles.jpg" alt="" width="317" height="418" srcset="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/biles.jpg 414w, https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/biles-227x300.jpg 227w" sizes="(max-width: 317px) 85vw, 317px" /></p>
<ul>
<li style="list-style-type: none;">
<ul>
<li>the alteration of language, including the elimination of upsetting terms and invention of new ones (“safe space”), to reflect the reigning new feminine mindset;</li>
<li>the routine, rapid formation of social <a href="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/the-day-the-logic-died/">networks</a> to exert pressure on corporations or other institutions to “cancel” someone who has fallen afoul of feminist/woke orthodoxies;</li>
<li>strong environmentalism and related advocacies and preferences (anti-vaccine, anti-GMO, anti-nuclear, climate-change alarmism, veganism, “organic” foods and medicines, etc.), stemming plausibly from women’s relatively strong sensitivity to the idea of environmental harms including toxins;</li>
<li>Shifts towards less systematized/hierarchical and rule-based religious forms, from paganism to evangelical/charismatic Christianity.</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>Cultural/political feminization, far from being “progress,” is probably destroying Western liberalism&#8212;the liberalism that emancipated women in the first place<br />
</strong></p>
<p>Yes, men on average have their own ways of thinking and acting—their own stubborn, long-evolved biases. And yes, the traditional male mindset is not necessarily optimized for running human societies in the 21<sup>st</sup> century. But there is an obvious reason why the male mindset, compared to the female mindset, is probably better adapted for managing culture and politics: Men have been managing culture and politics, and getting punished in the harshest ways for failure, for hundreds of millennia. Women, by contrast, have been working on a large scale in public life for not even two generations—and still seem inclined to blame men when things go wrong.</p>
<p>On the flip side of that argument is another obvious point: Women’s mindset is not simply unadapted or insufficiently adapted by evolution for managing public affairs; it is adapted specifically for <em>other</em> tasks, mainly domestic tasks revolving around the bearing and raising of children. In other words, women’s higher emotional sensitivity (compassion, guilt, fear, anxiety/turmoil); their relative indifference to machines and systems and cold, abstract thought; their stronger fear of toxins; their greater tendency to think un-independently and <a href="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/the-critical-mass-problem/">transmit social contagions</a>, etc. are in a fundamental sense <em>out of place</em> in the culture- and policy-making spheres.</p>
<p>I’m not suggesting that women’s traits are totally separate from men’s in this regard—for virtually any trait there would be two highly overlapping distributions, so that there would be lots and lots of women further towards the “male” end of the distribution compared to the average male.</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" class="wp-image-12 aligncenter" src="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2020/07/coulter-twitr.jpg" alt="" width="349" height="99" srcset="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2020/07/coulter-twitr.jpg 578w, https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2020/07/coulter-twitr-300x85.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 349px) 85vw, 349px" /></p>
<p>But there clearly are differences between the means of those distributions, between the <em>average</em> male and the <em>average</em> female in other words; and the central idea here is that those differences, on a population level, are not only meaningful but potentially cataclysmic in their civilizational impact.</p>
<p>That impact is evident not only in the broad cultural and policy shifts since the early 1960s&#8212;the “<a href="https://americanmind.org/salvo/pink-shift/">pink shift</a>” as I have called it&#8212;but in the more recent and extreme policy changes in places where cultural and political feminization is most advanced: “defund the police,” “let violent criminals out on bail,” “open the borders / diversity is our strength,” “let homeless people camp and crap wherever they like,” “give addicts needles,” “math is racist,” “logic is sexist,” etc. Not all of these policies are wildly popular, and obviously specific groups of hardcore activists are to blame for some of them, but I don’t see how these changes, collectively, could have taken root to the extent they have except against a heavily feminized cultural background—they are essentially <em>ad absurdum</em> expressions of the feminine mindset applied to policy.</p>
<p>I don&#8217;t think that every manifestation of feminization will be harmful in the long run. But some will. The move away from free speech towards speech- and thought-policing seems pretty ominous. Even worse, I suspect, is the encouragement of mass non-Western immigration to Western countries. One does not have to “hate” non-Western immigrants to understand that they and the culture they bring with them are . . . non-Western . . . so that the more there are of them, the less Western their host countries become. The women who encourage mass non-Western immigration seem surprisingly indifferent to the fact that non-Western cultures generally are less liberal, and a lot less friendly to the idea of female power, compared to Western cultures even from a few decades ago.</p>
<p>Can liberal Western societies nevertheless avert their impending self-destruction, by&#8212;among other measures&#8212;reining in cultural/political feminization? We&#8217;ll soon see, but I doubt it. I think it could help some to talk more about this cultural feminization hypothesis—“cult-fem theory”—at least as a way of dispelling the holy aura of “progress” that feminization-related social changes have acquired. But could one attack cultural feminization more directly and conclusively? Could one expel women, or even just the “bad apples,” or even persuade them to think and act differently, in all significant Western institutions—legislatures, government offices, universities, corporations, media organizations, philanthropies—where they are now embedded and substantially run things? I don&#8217;t see how. I don&#8217;t think liberal Western societies have any strong defense against this threat, other than by reverting to overt illiberalism.</p>
<p style="text-align: center;">***</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>AN ABANDONED AND MALIGNANT HEART</title>
		<link>https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/an-abandoned-and-malignant-heart/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[j stone]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 30 Nov 2021 21:15:50 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[blacks]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[ethnicity]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[fall of the West]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[USA]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[wokeism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[women]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/?p=284</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Thoughts on another miscarriage of justice in the broken USA &#160; An unpopular cause I feel compelled to stick up for today is the cause of Travis McMichael, his father Gregory McMichael, and their neighbor William “Roddie” Bryan, all of Brunswick, Georgia, USA, who were recently found guilty of murdering Ahmaud Arbery. Rightly or wrongly, &#8230; <a href="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/an-abandoned-and-malignant-heart/" class="more-link">Continue reading<span class="screen-reader-text"> "AN ABANDONED AND MALIGNANT HEART"</span></a>]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><em>Thoughts on another miscarriage of justice in the broken USA</em></p>
<p><span id="more-284"></span></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>An unpopular cause I feel compelled to stick up for today is the cause of Travis McMichael, his father Gregory McMichael, and their neighbor William “Roddie” Bryan, all of Brunswick, Georgia, USA, who were recently found guilty of murdering Ahmaud Arbery. Rightly or wrongly, I am convinced that this verdict is blatantly unjust. I also believe that many Americans, not just the jury and the prosecutor, are complicit in this injustice—an injustice that is much closer to murder (these men are likely to die in prison) than was the actual killing of Arbery.</p>
<p>Grievous miscarriages of justice occur frequently now in the United States, and often arise due to race-related issues that bias prosecutors and jurors. So why am I writing about this particular injustice, and not, say, the travesty of the Derek Chauvin verdict? I think it’s mainly because in the Chauvin case I read a healthy amount of commentary defending Chauvin, whereas in the case of the McMichaels and Bryan I read no defenses, only smug expressions of satisfaction or at least placid acceptance of this verdict, even among people who should know better.</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" class=" wp-image-289 aligncenter" src="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/arbery2.jpg" alt="" width="516" height="421" srcset="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/arbery2.jpg 613w, https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/arbery2-300x245.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 516px) 85vw, 516px" /></p>
<p><img loading="lazy" class=" wp-image-286 aligncenter" src="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/gabbard.jpg" alt="" width="512" height="140" srcset="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/gabbard.jpg 592w, https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/gabbard-300x82.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 512px) 85vw, 512px" /></p>
<p><img loading="lazy" class="wp-image-288 aligncenter" src="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/cheong.jpg" alt="" width="436" height="252" srcset="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/cheong.jpg 607w, https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/cheong-300x173.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 436px) 85vw, 436px" /></p>
<p><img loading="lazy" class=" wp-image-287 aligncenter" src="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/flanagan.jpg" alt="" width="521" height="491" srcset="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/flanagan.jpg 599w, https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/flanagan-300x282.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 521px) 85vw, 521px" /></p>
<p>The guilt of the McMichaels and Bryan is, in other words, part of the contemporary American “conventional wisdom” that I have come to distrust almost reflexively.</p>
<p>Why the McMichaels and Bryan were abandoned to their harsh fate so easily, even willfully and joyously, by their countrymen is something I’ll speculate about later in this essay, but first I want to go over some of the basic facts of the case.</p>
<p><strong>The killing of Ahmaud Arbery</strong></p>
<p>Ahmaud Arbery was a 25-year old African-American man who lived in Brunswick, Georgia. Like many African-American men, he had a police record for at least moderately serious crimes, including bringing a handgun to a high school football game in 2013, and an attempted shoplifting of a TV from a WalMart in 2017. He was still on probation when he died.</p>
<p>In late 2018, apparently based on his own observations as well as those of family members, Arbery’s probation officer recommended that Arbery get a mental health evaluation. At this evaluation—the defense lawyers brought this up at the trial, but the judged ruled it inadmissible—Arbery described to the evaluator (apparently a psychiatric nurse) “auditory delusions sometimes commanding him ‘to rob and steal’ and sometimes telling him ‘to hurt people,’” as well as general difficulties controlling his anger. Arbery was diagnosed with schizoaffective disorder and prescribed olanzapine (Zyprexa), a second-generation antipsychotic that is also used treat schizophrenia and the manic episodes of type 1 bipolar disorder; however, he apparently didn’t take the drug for long, and there was no evidence of it in his system when he died, although there were trace amounts of THC, the active ingredient in marijuana.</p>
<p>The MSM stories after Arbery’s death were heavily biased in the young man’s favor, and tended to omit or downplay anything negative, preferring to show a picture of him looking spiffy in his prom suit . . .</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" class="size-full wp-image-290 aligncenter" src="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/arbery0.jpg" alt="" width="143" height="183" /></p>
<p>. . . and preferring to emphasize that at the time of his death Arbery was “planning” to attend a local technical college to become an electrician, and often went jogging for exercise.</p>
<p>In general, because of this overwhelming bias, it is hard to trust the information about Arbery that was provided by his family and their lawyer and cannot be verified, e.g., with documents. We can’t say with confidence much more about his background than what judicial records show, namely that he had a history of being armed illegally, and of attempting theft, and of showing signs of mental illness including serious impulse-control problems. This shouldn’t necessarily have had any bearing on the jury’s findings, but it does speak to the broader moral picture, and definitely belies the many MSM portraits of Arbery that were designed, in part, to whip up hatred against the men who killed him.</p>
<p>Late in 2019 Arbery had begun taking occasional jogs into a mostly white neighborhood called Satilla Shores, where the McMichaels and Bryan lived. A video camera also had recorded him, in his jogging clothes, walking into a house in the neighborhood that was under construction—this had happened several times, mostly at night.</p>
<p>In the months immediately preceding his fateful encounter with the McMichaels, there also had been several break-ins or thefts in the neighborhood, including the theft of a gun from an unlocked truck—reported by Travis McMichael on January 1.</p>
<p>On the night of February 11, according to Wikipedia:</p>
<p style="padding-left: 40px;">Travis called <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/9-1-1">9-1-1</a> to report a slender 6-foot-tall Black man with short hair, wearing red shorts and a white shirt, who was trespassing on the site of a house under construction. Travis said, &#8220;I&#8217;ve never seen this guy before in the neighborhood.&#8221; The <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dispatcher#Emergency_dispatchers">dispatcher</a> asked whether Travis was OK, and he said, &#8220;Yeah, it just startled me. When I turned around and saw him and backed up, he reached into his pocket and ran into the house. So I don&#8217;t know if he&#8217;s armed or not. But he looked like he was acting like he was.&#8221; &#8220;We&#8217;ve been having a lot of burglaries and break-ins around here lately&#8221;, Travis said on the call. He told the dispatcher that he was out in his truck, and that as many as four neighbors were out looking for the man. His father Gregory was one of the people out searching that night, and Gregory and at least one other neighbor were armed. Police responded and searched the house along with a neighbor, but found no one. However, surveillance video from that evening showed a man who reportedly looked like Arbery, briefly walking in and out of the house under construction. He did not take anything. The under-construction house did not have doors or windows.</p>
<p>While Arbery died before the mystery of the local thefts could be solved, there doesn’t seem to be any evidence that exonerates him in all those thefts, despite the MSM’s implications otherwise. Given his background and the correspondence of his jogging and the local burglaries, it seems at least plausible—and evidently many Satilla Shores residents suspected—that he used his jogging at night as a cover for burglaries, and jogging in daytime to select his night-time targets. (I would be interested to know whether the burglaries continued after Arbery’s death, but haven’t seen any reference to such data.)</p>
<p>On the 23<sup>rd</sup> of February, shortly after one o’clock in the afternoon, Arbery once again ran into Satilla Shores, and into the house under construction, and once again was recorded on video camera.</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-291" src="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/Arbery-in-house.jpg" alt="" width="768" height="453" srcset="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/Arbery-in-house.jpg 768w, https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/Arbery-in-house-300x177.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 709px) 85vw, (max-width: 909px) 67vw, (max-width: 984px) 61vw, (max-width: 1362px) 45vw, 600px" /></p>
<p>A neighbor, Matthew Albenze, also spotted Arbery and called 911 to report the trespass on the building under construction. Wikipedia again:</p>
<p style="padding-left: 40px;">The 9-1-1 dispatcher asked if the man was &#8220;breaking into it right now?&#8221; The caller replied: &#8220;No &#8230; it&#8217;s all open.&#8221; After the caller said the man was now &#8220;running down the street&#8221;, the dispatcher said police would respond. The dispatcher asked at 1:08 p.m., &#8220;I just need to know what he was doing wrong. Was he just on the premises and not supposed to be?&#8221; The caller responded, with some parts garbled, saying: &#8220;And he’s been caught on camera a bunch at night. It&#8217;s kind of an ongoing thing.&#8221;</p>
<p>Why Arbery ran away isn’t clear, but the perception among those who saw him was that he was trying to escape after stealing something from the construction site. Apparently he hadn’t stolen anything, but if he had known that the cops had been called, then, being on probation, he might have wanted to avoid another brush with the law. Then again, if Arbery was mentally ill, it is probably pointless to try to rationalize his actions.</p>
<p>Soon Arbery ran past the McMichaels&#8217; house, where Gregory McMichael, working in the yard, saw him and recognized him as the repeat trespasser the neighborhood was worried about. He and Travis armed themselves and got into their white pickup truck, and gave chase.</p>
<p>The MSM accounts, and the account of the prosecutor, are worded to suggest that the McMichaels were racist good-old-boys who pursued Arbery that day simply because they wanted to hunt down, and snuff out the life of, an innocent black man whose only &#8220;crime&#8221; was “jogging while black.” To say that this is false, and as such represents both journalistic and prosecutorial misconduct, would be putting it very mildly. Both McMichaels had law enforcement experience, and obviously (all the evidence leans this way) were attempting a citizen’s arrest, a procedure that has a long history in the United States and at the time was specifically sanctioned in Georgia law. In other words, they wanted only to detain Arbery so that he could be questioned by police.</p>
<p>Whether they had sufficient reason to attempt a citizen’s arrest is debatable. However, to say that in the heat of the moment someone slightly exceeding his rights under a citizen’s arrest law <em>automatically will be charged with false imprisonment, and then murder for defending his life when the mentally ill arrestee attacks him, </em>is completely absurd. Citizen’s arrest laws are not meant to sanction vigilantism, but they also are not meant to be life-destroying traps for honest citizens who are trying to protect their neighborhoods—in what was here a demonstrable absence of effective policing.</p>
<p>The McMichaels tried unsuccessfully to cut off Arbery as he ran, and, they said later, even asked him to stop and let them talk to him, but he didn’t respond and continued running in an attempt to evade them. They could easily have shot him, if killing him had been their intent, but they did not; they simply kept trying to get him to stop.</p>
<p>At some point Bryan, who had seen the chase go by his own house, joined in with his black pickup truck and tried—again, unsuccessfully—to cut off the running man. Note that Bryan was not a close friend of the McMichaels; he was merely another resident in this neighborhood that was now literally up in arms over the rash of thefts and trespassings, and hoped to put the perp behind bars.</p>
<p>Ultimately the McMichaels gave up pursuing Arbery—apparently the neighborhood had many open yards through which he could always evade them—and simply parked their pickup at a crossing where they thought he was likely to appear in his attempt to get away.</p>
<p>At this point, just several minutes after Albenze’s 911 call, Travis McMichael, standing on the road by the driver’s side door, made his own 911 call—but then saw Arbery coming and handed the phone to his father, who stood in the truck bed:</p>
<p style="padding-left: 40px;">a male caller said: &#8220;I&#8217;m out here at Satilla Shores &#8230;There&#8217;s a Black male running down the street.&#8221; The 9-1-1 dispatcher asked, &#8220;Where at Satilla Shores?&#8221; The caller replied: &#8220;I don&#8217;t know what street we&#8217;re on.&#8221;</p>
<p>Arbery now as he approached apparently saw Travis standing with his shotgun by the open driver&#8217;s door on the left side of the pickup truck. Arbery might have turned around or veered onto either of the lawns beside the narrow road. Instead he kept running towards the truck, though he altered course to the right side of the road, and then ran along the right side of the truck, just a few feet from Gregory McMichael who stood in the truck bed talking to 911. When he reached the front of the truck, Arbery suddenly cut left and charged Travis.</p>
<p>This was the impulse that killed Arbery. You and I, and pretty much every sane person aware of the story, know this, and know that we would never have done what he did. We know that we would have stopped, and we know that if Arbery had stopped, as he&#8217;d been asked, he would still be alive, the McMichaels and Bryan would be free, and none of us would have heard of any of them.</p>
<p>But Arbery charged Travis. Bryan, who had been in pursuit of Arbery, parked his pickup in time to catch most of this tragic encounter on his cellphone camera.</p>
<p>Arbery in his fatal lunge had almost reached Travis when the latter fired his shotgun, catching Arbery in the chest. Arbery kept coming and tried to wrest the gun away from Travis. Meanwhile Gregory McMichael, with the phone still to his ear and the line to the 911 dispatcher still open, screamed at Arbery to stop.</p>
<p style="padding-left: 40px;">The caller shouted, &#8220;Stop! &#8230; Watch that. Stop, damn it! Stop!&#8221;</p>
<p>Why did Gregory McMichael shout at Arbery to stop? Well, obviously because he and his son had never intended to kill Arbery and were astonished that he was making it necessary.</p>
<p>Arbery did not stop. He kept struggling for the shotgun until Travis had shot him with it a total of three times. After the third shot, which went through the left side of his chest, Arbery quickly weakened, staggered, and collapsed to the pavement.</p>
<p><strong>Aftermath<br />
</strong></p>
<p>Alerted by the first 911 call, the police soon arrived. Arbery by then was dead. Travis McMichael was splashed in blood and evidently in shock (“No, I’m not all right,” he told the cop. “I just fucking killed someone.”)</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" class="size-full wp-image-296 aligncenter" src="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/arbery4-1.jpg" alt="" width="800" height="450" srcset="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/arbery4-1.jpg 800w, https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/arbery4-1-300x169.jpg 300w, https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/arbery4-1-768x432.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 709px) 85vw, (max-width: 909px) 67vw, (max-width: 984px) 61vw, (max-width: 1362px) 45vw, 600px" /></p>
<p>But, along with his father, he cooperated. Bryan cooperated too. They freely discussed the events of the preceding minutes, evidently without any sense of having committed a crime. The police did not arrest them, and the local district attorney’s office did not charge them. The Brunswick Circuit DA, Jackie Johnson, saw the case as an unfortunate but not really criminal one involving a mentally ill young man who essentially had brought about his own death through his own impulsive and violent actions.</p>
<p>Johnson had connections to the McMichaels, though, so she recused herself and turned the thing over to a neighboring district, Waycross Judicial Circuit District. The DA there, George Barnhill, felt the same way about the case. According to Wikipedia:</p>
<p style="padding-left: 40px;">On April 2, Barnhill wrote a memorandum to Glynn County police, recommending that no arrests be made. Barnhill wrote that the McMichaels were within their rights to chase &#8220;a burglary suspect, with solid firsthand probable cause&#8221;; that &#8220;Arbery initiated the fight&#8221;; and that Travis McMichael &#8220;was allowed to use deadly force to protect himself&#8221; when &#8220;Arbery grabbed the shotgun&#8221;.</p>
<p>By this time, of course, Arbery’s family had got a lawyer, “leaders of the black community” were getting involved, and there were demands for a prosecution. So the whiff of racial protest, with all that entails for a prosecutor’s career, was already in the air. Soon Barnhill washed his hands of the case, with a rather tenuous excuse:</p>
<p style="padding-left: 40px;">Arbery had previously been prosecuted by his son, a prosecutor for the Brunswick Circuit District Attorney&#8217;s Office, in an earlier case [and] one of the defendants [Gregory McMichael] had served as an investigator on the same prosecution.</p>
<p>And so, on April 13, the Georgia Attorney General&#8217;s Office handed the case to another nearby venue, the Atlantic Judicial Circuit.</p>
<p>It’s unclear what would have happened if the case had simply been left at the Atlantic Judicial Circuit, with no new event to inflame the situation, but presumably its DA, one Tom Durden, would have been under the same political pressures as the two DAs that had passed on the case.</p>
<p>What did happen is this: On May 5 a local defense lawyer who had consulted informally with Gregory and Travis McMichael uploaded Bryan’s cellphone video to the website of a local radio station. Stories were circulating to the effect that Arbery had simply been gunned down while jogging, and the lawyer apparently thought that the video would convince the public of the McMichaels’ innocence. He thought wrong—not because the video shows the McMichaels to be murderers, but simply because it somewhat shockingly depicts a young African-American man’s death at the hands of two fairly stereotypical-looking southern white fellows. This publication of the video was, remember, in one of the hardest, most <a href="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/the-critical-mass-problem/">hysterogenic</a> periods of the COVID-19 pandemic. Just a few weeks later, America would erupt in the Great Awokening after George Floyd’s death—but even now it was clear that this society was becoming very restive under pressure, and its politicians and politically sensitive prosecutors were doing what they could to placate the more restive elements.</p>
<p>From Wikipedia again:</p>
<p style="padding-left: 40px;">Within hours of the video becoming public, Tom Durden, the district attorney for Georgia&#8217;s Atlantic Judicial Circuit, said that he would present the case to &#8220;the next available grand jury in Glynn County&#8221; to decide if charges should be filed. The convening of grand juries had been postponed until after June 12 due to the COVID-19 pandemic. Durden accepted <em>Georgia Governor Brian Kemp&#8217;s offer</em> to bring in the Georgia Bureau of Investigation (GBI) to investigate. [italics mine]</p>
<p>At this point, with the most senior state politician getting involved in what should have been an obscure case, and more or less signaling—virtue-signaling—which way it should go, the McMichaels’ fate was sealed.</p>
<p style="padding-left: 40px;">The GBI found probable cause to charge Gregory and Travis McMichael within 36 hours of taking over jurisdiction of the case, and, on May 7, arrested and charged them with felony murder. The McMichaels were booked into the Glynn County Jail. At an appearance before a judge the following day, the McMichaels were both denied bond.</p>
<p>A few days later, Bryan too was arrested and charged.</p>
<p><strong>Ladies of the Jury</strong></p>
<p>When the case came before a jury, it was widely reported that eleven of the twelve jurors were white. It was much less widely reported that nine of those eleven were women.</p>
<p>Women, as I have been <a href="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/the-great-feminization/">writing</a> for the past decade, “wear the pants” now in most Western societies, i.e., have unprecedented and often dominant influence in many realms of culture. This is important because on average women think about and react to the world differently than men. Compared to men, for example, women seem much more emotionally aroused by stories of white-on-black racial conflict. Women, white women, also appear to have been the<a href="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/the-critical-mass-problem/"> dominant participants</a> in the bizarre BLM frenzy of the summer 2020 Great Awokening.</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" class="size-full wp-image-225 aligncenter" src="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2021/06/bethesdaawokening-1.jpg" alt="" width="800" height="450" srcset="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2021/06/bethesdaawokening-1.jpg 800w, https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2021/06/bethesdaawokening-1-300x169.jpg 300w, https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2021/06/bethesdaawokening-1-768x432.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 709px) 85vw, (max-width: 909px) 67vw, (max-width: 984px) 61vw, (max-width: 1362px) 45vw, 600px" /></p>
<p>If the McMichael/Bryan defense lawyers had read my essays, they would have known this (I write this only half-jokingly—my essays are not <em>that</em> obscure) and accordingly might have tried a different jury-selection strategy—though really, as this and many other examples show, the jury system in the United States is generally unlikely to deliver justice in cases where the forces of Wokeness favor one side.</p>
<p>In any case, the jury members were mostly women, the DA that ultimately charged the three defendants was a black woman (she claimed at the trial, among other things, that the defendants “chased, hunted down and ultimately executed” Arbery), and the lead prosecutor in the trial was a woman. And of course, Al Sharpton sat in the courtroom with Arbery’s family, and a mob of demonstrators camped outside the court building, to remind those sensitive women of the jury what they would face if they delivered the wrong verdict.</p>
<p>The jury, without much deliberation, duly returned a verdict of guilty on most of the charges. These charges included felony murder for all three defendants&#8212;even Bryan who had not been armed and had done nothing more than pursue Arbery in his truck. Travis McMichael, who presumably would have been killed by Arbery had he not defended himself, was additionally found guilty of “malice murder,” which means murder with “express or implied malice.”</p>
<p>These charges bring a minimum 30-year sentence before the possibility of parole, and for Travis McMichael, with the additional malice murder rap, there may be no parole—that will be up to the judge.</p>
<p>The Biden Administration, of course, watched this show trial approvingly.</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" class="size-full wp-image-297 aligncenter" src="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/biden.jpg" alt="" width="604" height="507" srcset="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/biden.jpg 604w, https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/biden-300x252.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 709px) 85vw, (max-width: 909px) 67vw, (max-width: 984px) 61vw, (max-width: 1362px) 45vw, 600px" /></p>
<p>However, it isn&#8217;t going to let it go at that. No, the Biden Administration via its “Justice” Department will try to earn further brownie points in the eyes of its voter base, and at the same time try to crush the spirit of conservative Legacy Americans, by pursuing a federal hate-crime trial of the McMichaels and Bryan—scheduled to convene next year.</p>
<p>Meanwhile the state of Georgia, led by “Republican” Gov. Brian Kemp, will also send a message by prosecuting former Brunswick Circuit DA Jackie Johnson—the first one to recuse herself, remember—for “obstruction of justice.” This will ensure that, the next time a black person in Georgia is killed by whites for any reason whatsoever, local DAs will show the proper Stakhanovite zeal in prosecuting.</p>
<p><strong>Flaws in the Law</strong></p>
<p>Note that Georgia law defines the kind of murder alleged in the case as follows:</p>
<p style="padding-left: 40px;">(a) A person commits the offense of murder when he unlawfully and with malice aforethought, either express or implied, causes the death of another human being.</p>
<p style="padding-left: 40px;">(b) Express malice is that deliberate intention unlawfully to take the life of another human being which is manifested by external circumstances capable of proof. Malice shall be implied where no considerable provocation appears and where all the circumstances of the killing show an abandoned and malignant heart.</p>
<p style="padding-left: 40px;">(c) A person commits the offense of murder when, in the commission of a felony, he or she causes the death of another human being irrespective of malice.</p>
<p>Did “<em>all the circumstances of the killing</em> show an abandoned and malignant heart” on the part of Travis McMichael? The answer is obviously <em>no</em>. He did not shoot Arbery from the window of his truck (or at any time until charged) as he would have done had his intent been murderous; he phoned 911 prior to the fatal encounter; he did not flee the scene of the killing; he showed every sign of having been shaken by that killing because he had not expected it; and he cooperated with the police who came to the scene. If he had an “abandoned and malignant heart” (why are these vague and archaic descriptors even allowed in the legal code?) he would have acted like a typical premeditated killer, shooting Arbery in a way that would not implicate himself, and denying involvement if questioned. I can imagine that a lot of American men who are forced to live with the problem of Black crime will now prefer that option, at least those men who are not totally demoralized by show trials like these.</p>
<p>The bigger problem here is the implied notion, noted above, that even mildly overinterpreting a citizen’s arrest law, as any concerned citizen might easily do without bad intent, can abruptly (by the whim of a biased jury) turn the citizen into a felon, and then a murderer if he has to defend himself against the arrestee’s violence. If such a notion were valid, a citizen’s arrest law would be worse than worthless. It would be as if the government invited motorists to drive across a very long and narrow, guardrail-less bridge over a mile-deep gorge, having positioned the bridge in such a way that it constantly swayed and shimmied in the wind. It effectively would be no bridge at all—only a deathtrap for the unwary.</p>
<p><strong>The Malignant Heart of the Matter<br />
</strong></p>
<p>Is there even any point in arguing over the legal questions at the heart of such cases? I can remember many racially tinged travesties of justice in my adult life, going back at least to the O.J. Simpson trial of 1995. These cases always feel like inversions of the <em>To Kill a Mockingbird </em>setup—either an apparently guilty black man goes free or gets off lightly, or a wrongfully prosecuted white man has his life ruined. More importantly, the process by which these injustices occur is always (as in Harper Lee’s model of 1930s small-town Alabama) a social process involving race-politics pressures as well as a lot of venality, cowardice, and hysteria. Tom Wolfe somehow got away with writing a big novel,<em> Bonfire of the Vanities</em>, about the modern versions of these circuses, a novel that even in 1987 conveyed strongly the message that American society and its judicial system had been irretrievably broken by decades of racial factionalism.</p>
<p>Similarly, what really drew my attention to this case was the evidence of race-politics pressure on DAs and politicians, the jury’s disregard for the basic evidence that should have exonerated the defendants, the MSM&#8217;s wanton mischaracterizations of the case (go back and read their accounts!), and then, above all, the overwhelmingly positive, smug reaction to the verdict by so many Americans.</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" class="wp-image-298 aligncenter" src="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/latimes.jpg" alt="" width="516" height="432" srcset="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/latimes.jpg 598w, https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/latimes-300x251.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 516px) 85vw, 516px" /></p>
<p><img loading="lazy" class=" wp-image-299 aligncenter" src="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/uygur.jpg" alt="" width="510" height="131" srcset="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/uygur.jpg 621w, https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/uygur-300x77.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 510px) 85vw, 510px" /></p>
<p><img loading="lazy" class=" wp-image-300 aligncenter" src="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/king.jpg" alt="" width="434" height="272" srcset="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/king.jpg 610w, https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/king-300x188.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 434px) 85vw, 434px" /></p>
<p>Of course, Twitter and social media generally are full of people who can cheaply virtue-signal while never having to deal with the unhappy realities afflicting ordinary Americans. Stephen King, for example, lives in a humongous complex on a barrier-island beach south of Sarasota—I know because I once lived nearby—at the least-accessible extremity of a wealthy neighborhood that was designed by its residents to keep out the riffraff, including anyone who looks remotely like Ahmaud Arbery. From that fortress King is unlikely ever to have to face the problem of burglary or thievery, and anyway any losses from such property crime would be infinitesimal in their impact on him.</p>
<p>But I think virtue-signaling is only a small and secondary part of this. Over the past few years, and especially since the COVID pandemic started, the more or less diffuse growth of wokeness in American life seems to have cohered into a Salem-like episode of socially sanctioned savagery&#8212;arguably almost as deadly as Salem, and much more broad and durable. I’ve even had the vague imaginative sense (from a distance, as an expatriate) that this mass hysteria has been developing into a kind of cult, presided over by a collectively summoned black perp-god, or purple-haired Gender Studies goddess, who in strident tones demands a constant flow of human sacrifices. (Another <a href="https://vdare.com/articles/john-derbyshire-the-arbery-show-trial-begins-more-human-sacrifices-to-appease-the-blm-gods">writer</a> elaborated this human-sacrifice concept before me, so I will mostly leave that imagery to him.)</p>
<p>The centrality of pictures and videos should give us a clue to how these weird social phenomena arise. If, let us say, a young black man, a man like Ahmaud Arbery, is found dead in the street by gunshot one day, but there is no video evidence of how he was killed, what will be the public reaction? The reader knows the answer already, because such cases occur many times per day across the US, especially in heavily black cities such as Chicago, St. Louis, Detroit and Baltimore. There is generally <em>no</em> reaction, <em>no</em> wider resonance. The man’s family may weep. They may call on the police to solve the crime. But usually only if the cops identify a white suspect (a relatively rare event) will the case make out of the back pages of the papers, and only if the white-on-black killing is caught on video (much rarer) is the case sure to be lifted from the muck of the ordinary criminal court docket into the glare of a Woke Cult show trial.</p>
<p>People in general, and I guess women moreso than men on average, are apt to be distressed when they witness—for example on a video—a violent death. The distress in turn creates a sense of urgency <em>to do something</em>. (Consider how heavily US foreign and immigration policies in recent years have been <a href="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/the-great-feminization/">driven</a> by distressing images in the media, e.g., of wounded children in Syria or refugee children crossing the Rio Grande.) Distress also tends to suppress rational thought, making the mind more susceptible to the beating tom-toms (to paraphrase McLuhan) of mass delusion and madness. And when a killing depicted on a distressing video can be made to seem even remotely consistent with the central wokelore motif of <em>evil whites harming innocent blacks</em>—that very live snarl of wires in the American psyche—the mass delusion and madness will come together and start to lurch in a predictable direction. It will start to be controlled and guided, to do meaningful political work, by a political faction that I would say definitely has “an abandoned and malignant heart.”</p>
<p>It seems to me that there are usually two main group of actors that ignite these episodes: blacks who from basic instinct or family ties support fellow blacks in conflicts with whites, and a certain large stratum of white women who have, in regard to blacks, a powerful guilt and appeasement reflex. Once those two groups start up and gather steam, craven politicians and their judicial minions join in with the rapidity of scurrying rodents, and then the superorganism swells to its maximum size with the additions of journalists and millions of ordinary and celebrity virtue-signalers. This frenzied entity of many voices and noises somehow achieves a certain harmony as it demands “justice,” which is code for: give us a white victim.</p>
<p>One cannot overemphasize how <em>un</em>interested in truth is this entity. In the case of Derek Chauvin, the entity assured us that the smirk on Chauvin’s face as he held down George Floyd was simply his sadist-cop’s delight at the approaching demise of his poor African American victim. Chauvin was a police officer with long experience of having to deal with unruly and bullshitting black perps, and of course did not have the clairvoyance to know that this particular perp, this one unlucky time, was telling the truth—but try explaining that to some vapor-brained leftist millennial or wine-aunt who is caught up in the full guilt-hate-love ecstasy of the Awokening.</p>
<p>In the case of Kyle Rittenhouse, the entity (speaking even through the man who is the current US president) assured us that the defendant was a white supremacist who had gone hunting for innocent protesters. The entity let it be known among the softer minded that Rittenhouse&#8217;s victims were black&#8212;this became a very widespread perception. Rittenhouse avoided becoming the next sacrificial victim mainly because the people he had shot in self defense were actually white. It must have helped too that he, Rittenhouse, was a cherubic-looking lad liable to trigger the protective maternal instincts of many American women—instincts that are normally directed entirely toward the shooting victim in such cases, at least when the victim is black.</p>
<p>In Georgia, of course, the victim was indeed black and the accused were southern whites who drove pickup trucks, carried guns, probably had a few Confederate flags around, and probably held African Americans in low esteem. On the great totem pole of wokeism, these men were the lowest of the low. Thus, the story the entity told of their vile misdeeds, in the MSM, in social media, in the courtroom through the mouths of sworn officers of the court, was a festival of lies and obfuscations, and essentially the defendants had no defenders other than their paid lawyers.</p>
<p>The victims of human sacrifice in ancient times often were drawn from the lowest, most marginalized castes. Is it not plausible that tens of thousands of years of primitive religion have worn certain paths into our minds such that even now we subconsciously act out those rituals&#8212;and perhaps can even experience, every so often, the vivid illusion that an angry god is present and wants to be appeased?</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" class="size-full wp-image-302 aligncenter" src="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/floyd.jpg" alt="" width="529" height="730" srcset="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/floyd.jpg 529w, https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/floyd-217x300.jpg 217w" sizes="(max-width: 529px) 85vw, 529px" /></p>
<p>This particular deity will never stay appeased for long, though, will it? And as evidence accumulates that America’s grand racial experiment has failed, will Americans ever face up to that failure and respond rationally? Or will that failure just drive them crazier and crazier, as they deliver more and more sacrificial victims to a god who will not relent?</p>
<p style="text-align: center;">***</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>WHY YOU CAN’T HAVE NICE THINGS</title>
		<link>https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/why-you-cant-have-nice-things/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[j stone]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 01 Sep 2021 23:48:19 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[ethnicity]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[fall of the West]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[immigration]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[revolution]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[USA]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://thoughtsofstone.com/?p=240</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[You don’t want them badly enough &#160; You want your own decent-sized, reasonably priced house, with a yard big enough for the kids to play, and a bit of space at the back for a garden, or maybe even a pool. You want a neighborhood where the houses are built in a pretty vernacular style, &#8230; <a href="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/why-you-cant-have-nice-things/" class="more-link">Continue reading<span class="screen-reader-text"> "WHY YOU CAN’T HAVE NICE THINGS"</span></a>]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><em>You don’t want them badly enough</em></p>
<p><span id="more-240"></span></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>You want your own decent-sized, reasonably priced house, with a yard big enough for the kids to play, and a bit of space at the back for a garden, or maybe even a pool. You want a neighborhood where the houses are built in a pretty vernacular style, not too close together, and there are sidewalks and lots of trees, and good schools and shops and offices and parks are just a short distance, perhaps even biking or walking distance, away.</p>
<p>You want your neighborhood to be inherently safe—the kind of place where people leave their doors unlocked at night and nothing bad happens. That means you want to be able to trust your neighbors. More than that, you want to have a sense of community and shared identity and culture with them. That in turn means you want them, the vast majority of them anyway, to share at least broadly your own deep roots in the USA and deeper roots in the Old World. You want that sense of shared roots, shared upbringing, shared values and goals, as a reminder and an encouragement, if only a subconscious one, of your collective enterprise as resident citizens, stewards of your children’s future—your nation’s future.</p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><img loading="lazy" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-243" src="https://thoughtsofstone.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/09/6a0d41ae7097f0ae8339073063c4ae87cf6f33e2.jpg" alt="" width="475" height="600" srcset="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2021/09/6a0d41ae7097f0ae8339073063c4ae87cf6f33e2.jpg 475w, https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2021/09/6a0d41ae7097f0ae8339073063c4ae87cf6f33e2-238x300.jpg 238w" sizes="(max-width: 475px) 85vw, 475px" /></p>
<p>You want smaller, less burdensome government at all levels, and having shared roots and a shared culture would mean that you and your neighbors, and the wider community, could safely have a smaller government—could safely dispense with the Leviathan state that is required to keep a semblance of order in diversity-dogma countries.</p>
<p>Your policing needs, for example, might be very modest, on the order of what small American towns used to have in the 1950s. For welfare, you in your tightly knit communities would be able to find most solutions from families, churches, and philanthropists, rather than government bureaucracies. You would not encourage, or even tolerate, chronic welfare dependency among those capable of earning for themselves. Smaller government would in turn mean lower and perhaps greatly simplified taxation, reducing the cost of living and of running businesses, and in general removing considerable stress and uncertainty from economic life.</p>
<p>You want executive branches of government that are not only smaller in general but also more tightly focused on important things that cannot be done effectively through private means. Similarly, you want legislative systems at all levels, federal on down, that are much more limited in the changes they can make to the laws and social structures—systems that can therefore easily withstand the harmful <a href="https://thoughtsofstone.com/the-critical-mass-problem/">thought-contagions</a> that now and then sweep the populace, and can protect important traditions that are necessary for the health of society. You might well favor, for example, a federal congress or parliament that meets for only a few months every year, as the first USA Congress did in 1789.</p>
<p>In keeping with the same goal, you want a more limited and more inherently conservative electorate: citizens of relatively mature age with deep roots in the country, perhaps also with property and children enough to qualify them as having “skin in the game.”</p>
<p>You want neither rightist-socialism (fascism) nor leftist-socialism (communism). You want a traditional, pro-family, moderately pro-business culture that builds up and celebrates Western civilization instead of constantly and acidly trying to dissolve it. In other words, while you want the ordinary, traditional Western freedom to “pursue happiness” in your own way by building a business or professional career, creating wealth for your descendants, etc. you also recognize the need to develop communal spirit, including that high-level communal spirit we call nationalism, through pursuits that are not rooted in mere self-interest. So you would favor, among other measures, some form of national service for young men and women—perhaps two years of military training and service for the former, and two years in non-military service (e.g., charity hospitals, elder care, national parks) for the latter.</p>
<p>On the whole you want bold and imaginative policies and initiatives that retain or reinstate the best of your civilization’s traditions, while also realizing the best possibilities thrown up by rapid technological advances. Should you be building more highways—to take but one example—when flying cars are already flitting about on the horizon? Should you be importing cheap foreign labor when you could automate instead? Should you be investing billions in vast solar- and wind-power farms if fusion-power is just around the corner?</p>
<p>I could go on and on with my own idiosyncratic desiderata: I want medieval-style walled towns in a re-wilded continent where the buffalo, and maybe their indigenous hunters, can once again roam, even as Jetson-style flying cars pepper the airspace. I want education achievement and assessment to be centered on objective standardized tests, not on subjective grades at subjectively ranked and usually overpriced schools. I want insurance mostly banned in the healthcare industry, to <a href="https://www.theatlantic.com/magazine/archive/2009/09/how-american-health-care-killed-my-father/307617/">let the free market do its thing</a> in this very important, yet very broken, realm of American life. I want the decadent, stupid, dangerous American elites—the political class, their media camp-followers, and Big Business execs, who are effectively one of the greatest gangs of villains in human history considering the civilizational damage they’ve done—to be cast down and punished in the most exemplary ways.</p>
<p>My main point here, though, is just the simple one that Americans, while they have lots of nice things and a wide range of choices when it comes to goods, services, careers, and even the sexual/mating marketplace, cannot have nice things—and are in fact afflicted with a growing helplessness and a sense of creeping dystopia—when it comes to their politics, government, and culture. Their politico-cultural system feels hopelessly broken, much in the way that a family you can’t choose can feel broken. It isn’t always much better in other countries, but the contrast in the USA between its potential and its outlook, between the traditional virtues that built it and the perverse, corrosive mindset of its current managerial class, is starker than in any other country with which I’m familiar.</p>
<p><strong>Elites, Population Expansion, and Diversity</strong></p>
<p>This American managerial or “elite” class, now heavily feminized and febrile with wokeism, acts with delusional, totalist conviction in some areas, and with cynicism in others—but the net impact is almost always to benefit itself, in terms of money and power, while making things worse for everyone else.</p>
<p>Safe neighborhoods, good schools, and social harmony? Can’t have those—not if the elites are to succeed in their grand project of assembling a perma-rule electoral coalition from white-loathing nonwhites and self-loathing whites.</p>
<p>Nicely designed, nicely integrated residential and commercial areas in our towns? Oh no! That would disrupt the standard business models of developers and other Big Business types, on whose donations the ruling elites depend.</p>
<p>Sensible healthcare system? Certainly not! For that would benefit mainstream Legacy Americans, who tend to vote for the Deplorable Party, while Elite Party voters would lose their free healthcare and the elites would have to scramble to find another way to own their votes. Plus of course, Big Pharma and Big Healthcare, those esteemed members of the elite (and key donors to the Elite Party), have a very good thing going under the current system—they can charge ludicrously high prices for most of their goods and services without fear of competition.</p>
<p>Just in general, of course—ignoring the distorting role of elites—the chances that you as a citizen will get the policies you want in a democracy have much to do with the size and diversity of the electorate. The greater that size and diversity, the greater the range of things that electorate will want—and thus the chance the resulting USA corresponds to <em>your</em> vision, rather than, say, some African-American’s or Indian-American’s or Chinese-American’s, gets ever smaller. The reader may have noticed the resemblance of the USA I described at the top of this essay, a USA with affordable houses, safer neighborhoods and better schools, to the far smaller and far less diverse USA of the 1960s and 70s. In any case, deliberately enlarging and diversifying your electorate through the mass importation of ethnically and culturally distant peoples seems bound to cause broader “why can’t I have what I want” dissatisfaction with the democratic system, and presumably past a certain point will trigger a shift to authoritarianism and/or ethnic cleansing—the only uncertainty being: who ends up on top?</p>
<p>Maybe (as an expatriate) I don’t have enough contact with other Americans who reside in the US. But even in the news and on Twitter I seldom see my countrymen discussing seriously how their system could be reworked so that they can avoid this bad fate, and can recover the possibility of having good choices in politics, or at any rate can have some of the nice things that better government would bring.</p>
<p>That reticence may be due in part to the difficulty many Americans have in letting go of their Greatest Country of All Time mythology, and all the flag-waving and Constitution-worshipping that goes with it. The USA must have contained very basic, very deep flaws if, after a run of only about 70 years as a true Superpower—combining wealth, reach, and might as no other country ever has—it is already falling apart. It might at first have seemed well designed by its vaunted Founders, but clearly its current crop of elites has learned to game its systems for their own selfish, nation-destroying ends. From such obvious conclusions, though, conservative Americans tend to look away. They seem to prefer distracting themselves with florid <a href="https://thoughtsofstone.com/the-american-way-of-submission/">conspiracy theories</a>, often while retaining a delusional faith in the fundamentals of the existing USA—a distinctly American faith that says, like the narrator at the end of <em>Gatsby</em>, “no matter—tomorrow we will run faster, stretch out our arms farther. . .”</p>
<p>Among the Americans who are, like me, less optimistic about the country’s fate, there also seems to be a pervasive fear of talking openly about the measures that would be necessary to fix the situation—measures that could include the reversal of much of the past half-century’s immigration flow, the creation of a mostly <a href="https://thoughtsofstone.com/the-other-n-word/">autonomous homeland</a> for African Americans, the dramatic narrowing of the voting franchise, extensive government regulation of media/cultural content, and a likely interval of authoritarian government during the transition from old USA to new. Even Americans whose vast wealth could never be removed by social cancellation shy from such notions—such realism, I would call it—and talk instead about making grand new worlds somewhere else, e.g., Thiel’s sea-steading and Musk’s Mars-colonization.</p>
<p>There has been some talk, mostly still on the cultural margins and well outside the Overton Window, of splitting the existing USA into two new countries, red and blue—similar to what might have happened peacefully in 1861. To me, that would fix things a little but not nearly enough. I would imagine the resulting red-USA (led by someone like Ron DeSantis or Tucker Carlson) to have only more muted versions of the same set of problems, the same dystopian trends, stemming from the same false premises that have been drummed into Americans for generations.</p>
<p>In principle, if the aim is to give Americans a wide range of choices so that more of them can live in a political culture that suits them, it would be better to split old-USA into dozens of sovereign micro-states (not necessarily corresponding to existing states), each set up to provide a relatively static demographic mix, governmental and political structure, and culture. Another great advantage of this approach is that it would amount to a vast ongoing experiment, continually teaching Americans and the wider world about the comparative desirability and sustainability of different arrangements. It would also, so to speak, up the ante for those who claim that modern Western countries should be a marketplace of contractual nations (not ethno-nations) for the peoples of the world—it would say: yes, let’s make it a real marketplace with real choices, including conservative, pro-family homelands for legacy Americans.</p>
<p>The big disadvantage of the micro-state idea, of course, is that such states are inherently weak and probably could not survive for long in a world where Great Power hegemons like China and Russia are constantly seeking to conquer and expand. Even wokeism and its variants—like so many American faiths before them—are hegemonic creeds, jealous gods bent on conquest.</p>
<p>More generally, Americans today seem disinclined and ill-equipped to think and act to the depth necessary to bring about such rational solutions. Perhaps there aren’t enough recent examples with which Americans can identify—in contrast to 1861 when proponents of secession readily cited the logic of the original American Revolution in justifying their cause. There also seems to be a certain intellectual inertia left over from the Union’s victory in the Civil War. Even the late Antonin Scalia <a href="https://www.politico.com/blogs/ben-smith/2010/02/scalia-no-to-secession-025119">wrote</a>: “If there was any constitutional issue resolved by the Civil War, it is that there is no right to secede.” But of course the right of self-government should be considered an innate and “inalienable” right, not established in or modifiable by any formal agreement—just as the inalienable right of personal liberty should prevent one from contracting legally to be a slave.</p>
<p>In any case, my overall impression (and I think <a href="https://dailyvoice.com/new-york/whiteplains/politics/new-poll-reveals-percentages-of-americans-who-want-to-secede-by-region/812724/">polls</a> generally back this) is that most Americans now would reject the idea even of a simple red/blue split—I guess mostly because of that mental inertia and the thought of the inconvenience. In other words, Americans for now, though they might want a nicer country, just haven’t reached the point where they collectively want it badly enough to make it happen.</p>
<p style="text-align: center;">***</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>THE &#8216;CRITICAL MASS&#8217; PROBLEM</title>
		<link>https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/the-critical-mass-problem/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[j stone]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 03 Jun 2021 02:19:28 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[fall of the West]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[women]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://thoughtsofstone.com/?p=222</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[What if Western societies are now inherently unstable? &#160; There have been slow social changes over the past century, but there have been fast ones too. A recent one, the year-old outbreak of extreme wokeness called the Great Awokening, has spread with wildfire velocity through US and even foreign institutions, raising the basic question: why &#8230; <a href="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/the-critical-mass-problem/" class="more-link">Continue reading<span class="screen-reader-text"> "THE &#8216;CRITICAL MASS&#8217; PROBLEM"</span></a>]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><em>What if Western societies are now inherently unstable?</em></p>
<p><span id="more-222"></span></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>There have been slow social changes over the past century, but there have been fast ones too. A recent one, the year-old outbreak of extreme wokeness called the Great Awokening, has spread with wildfire velocity through US and even foreign institutions, raising the basic question: why did this happen?</p>
<p>Part of the answer is in the term itself. The Great Awakenings were several distinct episodes of intense religious fervor, chiefly in North America, in the 1700s and 1800s, and arguably in the 1960s-80s. They were social contagions, and spread, like viruses, within populations that had for various social and economic reasons been made peculiarly vulnerable to them. They included mass gatherings to hear highly charismatic—one might say hypnotic—preachers, and mass conversions, amid fainting and weeping, to less hierarchical, more personal and emotional forms of Christianity. Contagions of guilt over sinfulness were followed by outbreaks of ecstasy over salvation. But while the Awakenings were, most vividly, mass psychosocial disturbances, they also led to durable changes, in affected Christian churches, in theology and ordinary practice.</p>
<p>The Great Awokening has shown at least a superficial resemblance to its Christian forbears, in its weepy mass gatherings, its heavy inculcations of guilt, its pressure to embrace radically new ways of thinking—whiteness as a sin—and in its swift march through the media and other important institutions. Above all it looks like a social contagion.</p>
<p>Some factors that made America susceptible to this contagion are plain enough. At the time the Great Awokening started there was a deadly pandemic of a real virus, and, for many, an associated, highly stressful interruption of normal life. There were also unnerving riots, lootings, and other social disturbances in US cities, due to some unhappy police/perp encounters that were amplified by activists and politicians in the run-up to a fateful presidential election. As for the themes of the Great Awokening, they were not really new—most had been around since the 1960s, usually on the radical fringes. In general, white American guilt and perplexity over the chronic low status of the average black American has been an unassuageable stressor on the country from the time of slavery.</p>
<p>But I think there is another big piece in this puzzle of why the wokeist gospel, with its hatred of white American heroes and hagiologies of black ne&#8217;er-do-wells, ripped so easily and swiftly through the country and its key institutions, including corporations, and even now mostly retains all these conquests.</p>
<p>As readers of previous essays of mine (especially <a href="https://thoughtsofstone.com/the-great-feminization/">this</a>, <a href="https://thoughtsofstone.com/the-day-the-logic-died/">this</a>, <a href="https://thoughtsofstone.com/girl-power/">this</a>, and <a href="https://americanmind.org/salvo/pink-shift/">this</a>) may have guessed already, this missing piece is the involvement of women—women as ordinary citizens, and as members of affected institutions. And although I’ve touched on this theme in these previous essays, I’m coming at it here from a slightly different, cultural dynamics angle.</p>
<p><strong>A Feminine Susceptibility</strong></p>
<p>If history has taught us anything about social contagions, it is that women, on average, are more susceptible to them than men. Women have been the key instigators and transmitters of all the most famous mass-hysterias, including the many medieval and early modern convent hysterias and witch-hunts, but also all the modern, medicalized mass-hysterias&#8211;among them Charcot’s neuroses (which kicked off modern psychiatry), multiple personality disorder and other “recovered memory” syndromes, the ongoing child gender dysphoria hysteria, and ordinary schoolyard hysterias of the “children overcome by mysterious gas leak” type. This relative susceptibility to emotional contagion is one of those feminine traits that is sort of obvious anecdotally, and occasionally is given weight by an experimental psychology study, though the idea of it runs against the prevailing pro-feminine orthodoxy in media and academia, so it isn’t mentioned much.</p>
<p>Why are women this way? To me the likeliest, if necessarily tentative, explanation is that the two sexes, with their distinct traditional roles, have evolved distinct sets of psychological leanings and behaviors, and the typical feminine set of behaviors includes a superior emotional sensitivity and sociability as a broad adaptation that facilitates, e.g., child-rearing. The fact that this “enhanced connectedness” makes women more susceptible to harmful social contagions may have been an acceptable side-effect in times when women were mostly restricted to home and hearth. Women’s <a href="https://thoughtsofstone.com/girl-power/">greater ability to align among themselves</a> may even have ended up as part of an adaptive female defense mechanism against the physically stronger sex.</p>
<p>If we consider just this trait, or trait-set, and ask what its social impact should have been as women entered public life <em>en masse</em> over the past half-century or so, I think we end up making sense of a lot of otherwise puzzling social phenomena. In regard to the Great Awokening, we can hypothesize at least that this has been primarily a contagion among women, especially young women with high feminine energies that are not absorbed by husbands and children and need some outlet.</p>
<p>I would suggest too that the Great Awokening’s transformation of big institutions reflects not only the general fear of personal cancellation within these institutions but also the “critical mass” of susceptible women who work in them. In other words, for example, a male executive at a big corporation might only pay lip service to wokeism to preserve his status, while a female executive would be more likely to enforce it from conviction.</p>
<p>As Orwell once said through his <em>1984</em> character Winston Smith:</p>
<p style="padding-left: 40px;">It was always the women, and above all the young ones, who were the most bigoted adherents of the Party, the swallowers of slogans, the amateur spies and nosers-out of unorthodoxy.</p>
<p>I don&#8217;t think that women are equally susceptible to any orthodoxy&#8212;I don&#8217;t expect them to spawn variants of Nazism, or, say, jihadist Islamic ideology. But I think there is a broad range of stuff they go for that comports with the feminine, weaker-sex, caregiving mindset and includes themes of trauma, the loss of agency, the need for inclusivity, and protection from environmental threats. Wokeism ticks most of those boxes, but may also be appealing to women, at least subconsciously, because it is very much an anti-male ideology&#8211;so that women have inherently less to fear from it, and may even find it a useful tool for dislodging men, especially white men, who somehow stand in their way.</p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><img loading="lazy" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-224" src="https://thoughtsofstone.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/06/ursula-1.jpg" alt="" width="700" height="612" srcset="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2021/06/ursula-1.jpg 700w, https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2021/06/ursula-1-300x262.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 709px) 85vw, (max-width: 909px) 67vw, (max-width: 984px) 61vw, (max-width: 1362px) 45vw, 600px" /></p>
<p><strong>Silent but Deadly</strong></p>
<p>Like all the other aspects of women’s cultural ascendancy in the West, this one seems to lie there in plain sight while remaining officially unmentionable. How often do we hear of petitions against insufficiently woke persons, usually white males, by students at a university, or reporters at a newspaper, or employees at some publishing house, in which the feminine sentiment of the complaint (“we feel unsafe”) is unmistakable, and yet no one—in a media increasingly controlled by women—mentions the striking preponderance of females among the petitioners? How often do we see images in the media of Great Awokening mass gatherings whose participants are mostly female though there is nothing in the caption or the story text to explain or even acknowledge that interesting fact? It would seem that a big part of female power, even of the modern, feminist, you-go-girl variety, still comes from feigning powerlessness.</p>
<p>In any case, if the entry of women into public life over the past few decades has now reached a “critical mass” that makes Western institutions and culture highly susceptible to runaway ideological fevers and contagions, then the West obviously has a much bigger problem than wokeness itself.</p>
<p>As noted, I’m assuming that these contagions will be broadly limited to those whose themes are consonant with female sensibilities. But, as the experience so far with wokeism suggests—and the quote from Orwell suggests too—female sensibilities may be no less likely than male sensibilities to support the establishment of totalitarian or otherwise inhumane regimes.</p>
<p>Arguably an even worse outcome is to have no regime at all—to have the chaos of anarchy. Is it far-fetched to suggest that anarchy is where the ascendancy of women is taking the West? The feminized elites of Western, especially Anglosphere, countries now promote influxes of ethnically distant foreigners, and official favoritism towards these newcomers, while preaching hatred and suppression of white legacy populations. Propaganda along these lines has become deafening over the past two decades, and it&#8217;s now hard to imagine that it could ever be reversed fully. But the long-term outcome of demeaning and replacing a dominant legacy population with a mix of very different, often half-civilized foreigners is almost by definition going to be a civilizational collapse. Another, perhaps mostly Asian-flavored civilization may arise from those ruins, but there is no guarantee that it will be better&#8212;in any sense&#8212;than the Western civilization that is now swiftly fading.</p>
<p>I want to emphasize that I don’t wish to demean women in putting forward this set of suggestions. Many women are more resistant to the wokeism nonsense than the average male—and, as females, have better insight into the quirks of the female mindset.</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-12" src="https://thoughtsofstone.com/wp-content/uploads/2020/07/coulter-twitr.jpg" alt="" width="578" height="164" srcset="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2020/07/coulter-twitr.jpg 578w, https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2020/07/coulter-twitr-300x85.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 578px) 85vw, 578px" /></p>
<p>But the key idea here is that there is a difference between the <em>average</em> female and <em>average</em> male. In other words, for traits relating to social contagion susceptibility, men and women can be scored along two bell curves which mostly overlap, though they have different means. That difference in the means makes a big difference on its own. In addition, those women out on the more “extreme feminine” tail of the female curve—who I expect are mostly young, single, fertile, with passion and compassion to burn—may have an outsized impact through their particularly strong ability to align emotionally and transmit contagions.</p>
<p>I think this sex difference is also a good example of a relatively subtle average difference measured at the individual level adding up to a striking difference in collective behavior and culture.</p>
<p>All that said, I am not dogmatic about any of this. I’m broadly aware that we as modern humans, with our fixation on the individual, know too little about how our individual traits relate to the shapes and dynamics of our societies. Essentially, we don’t know the recipe for making civilizations that are good but also <em>sustainable</em>. Again and again, across history, we are born to civilizational riches and then ignorantly squander them.</p>
<p style="text-align: center;">***</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>THE OTHER N-WORD</title>
		<link>https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/the-other-n-word/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[j stone]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 14 May 2021 02:23:55 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[blacks]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[ethnicity]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[fall of the West]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[human ecology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[USA]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://thoughtsofstone.com/?p=212</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Who&#8217;s afraid of black nationalism? &#160; America’s leftist elites regard white American nationalism as their principal ideological adversary. But they have another adversary that is often overlooked: black American nationalism. Black American nationalism is very easy to overlook, here in the third decade of the new millennium. Although it has had its day in the &#8230; <a href="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/the-other-n-word/" class="more-link">Continue reading<span class="screen-reader-text"> "THE OTHER N-WORD"</span></a>]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><em>Who&#8217;s afraid of black nationalism?</em></p>
<p><span id="more-212"></span></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>America’s leftist elites regard white American nationalism as their principal ideological adversary. But they have another adversary that is often overlooked: <em>black</em> American nationalism.</p>
<p>Black American nationalism is very easy to overlook, here in the third decade of the new millennium. Although it has had its day in the sun—even Lincoln was in favor of it, once upon a time—its best-known proponent since the Civil Rights Era, Malcolm X, died 56 years ago, at the hands of rival black nationalists, and the movement seems to have gone only downhill since. Already by the mid 1970s Richard Pryor was mocking the “Back to Africa Movement” in his stand-up routines. Black American nationalism also has been tainted (or so one is supposed to think) by the moral support it has occasionally received from overtly white supremacist organizations. In any case, although there must still be millions of black Americans of the nationalist persuasion out there, their movement has by now been relegated to the fringes—the black nationalists who make the news these days seem mostly <a href="https://www.nbcdfw.com/news/local/dallas-shooting-suspect-was-leader-in-black-nationalist-group/19317/">violent, deranged</a> and disorganized.</p>
<p>By contrast, black American activism that is <em>not</em> nationalist seems to have been doing pretty well lately, judging by the recent wildfire contagions of enthusiasm for BLM, the 1619 Project, the George Floyd hagiology, and Critical Race Theory. Last year, leading Democrats actually donned kente cloth stoles and bent a knee on the US Capitol’s marble floor during the announcement of police reform legislation, as if genuflecting to a Justifiably Angry Black God.</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" class="size-full wp-image-214 aligncenter" src="https://thoughtsofstone.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/05/kente.jpg" alt="" width="700" height="467" srcset="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2021/05/kente.jpg 700w, https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2021/05/kente-300x200.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 709px) 85vw, (max-width: 909px) 67vw, (max-width: 984px) 61vw, (max-width: 1362px) 45vw, 600px" /></p>
<p>Non-nationalist black activists also seem to have been doing pretty well for themselves personally. Consider <a href="https://www.the-sun.com/news/2675013/na-patrisse-khan-cullors-houses/">Patrisse Khan-Cullors</a>, a co-founder of BLM, whose income as an activist has enabled her recently to purchase several homes collectively worth several millions of dollars. Or Nikole Hannah-Jones, of the 1619 Project, with her consulting, if that’s what one should call it, for <a href="https://www.theamericanconservative.com/dreher/the-woke-capitalism-grift-shell-oil-nikole-hannah-jones-live-not-by-lies/">Shell</a> and other large corporations, and her remarkable habit of <a href="https://spectator.us/life/1619-project-nikole-hannah-jones-products/">promoting products</a> in interviews and speeches. Or the so-called family of George Floyd, with their $27 million <a href="https://www.npr.org/2021/03/13/976785212/minneapolis-agrees-to-pay-27-million-to-family-of-george-floyd">payout</a> from the city of Minneapolis. Or Stacey Abrams with <a href="https://www.hollywoodreporter.com/tv/tv-news/nbc-stacey-abrams-while-justice-sleeps-1234951195/">her novel and its lucrative adaptation for TV</a>. Or Ta-Nehisi Coates with his <a href="https://ta-nehisicoates.com/graphic-novels/">comic books</a> and <a href="https://www.latimes.com/entertainment-arts/story/2021-02-26/ta-nehisi-coates-writing-the-script-for-next-superman-movie">film scripts</a>. Or reparations-demander Ibram X. Kendi with the <a href="https://reason.com/2020/08/20/jack-dorsey-ibram-x-kendi-twitter-ceo-racism-center/">miraculous largesse</a> he attracts from wealthy whites.</p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><img loading="lazy" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-69" src="https://thoughtsofstone.com/wp-content/uploads/2020/10/huckster.png" alt="" width="385" height="376" srcset="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2020/10/huckster.png 385w, https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2020/10/huckster-300x293.png 300w" sizes="(max-width: 385px) 85vw, 385px" /></p>
<p>Now, granted, some of this flow of wealth to activists could be framed as prudent purchases of insurance by white-run organizations—inoculations against the cooties of “racism” and “white supremacy” that can afflict, and cancel, <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2020/06/09/books/poetry-foundation-black-lives-matter.html">any</a> <a href="https://www.usatoday.com/story/entertainment/tv/2021/05/10/golden-globes-2022-ceremony-dropped-nbc-after-hfpa-scandal/5026394001/">prominent organization</a> if it’s not careful.</p>
<p>But even moreso I think this wealth transfer reflects elites’ desire to <em>reward and incentivize those who tamely do their bidding</em>.</p>
<p>Malcolm X viewed elite-approved “black leaders” in his day with similar skepticism. He famously called Martin Luther King Jr. a chump and a stooge of white liberals for promoting the idea of peaceful integration within white America—an idea that to him was an empty promise, aimed as always at perpetuating white control of blacks.</p>
<p>I think he was basically right about that. And if contemporary America’s leftist elites have banished black nationalists to the fringes, and have instead anointed a bunch of racial-equity grifters as the approved “leaders” of black America, then surely black nationalism is something that Legacy Americans should support as energetically as they can.</p>
<p>I’m not just being enemy-of-my-enemy tribalistic here. I’m trying to be coldly logical. The leftist elites of the US, which is to say the leaders of the Democratic Party and their allies and henchwomen in academia, media, entertainment, big business, etc., <em>need</em> to keep American blacks in the country and on their side for the most basic electoral reasons. They cannot abide a black separatism that would lead to a new, black nationalist political party or—the elites’ ultimate nightmare—a substantial black exodus from the US to a new homeland, even an internal one. Obviously, such an exodus would, among its many consequences, fatally weaken those leftist elites, in part by removing most of the radioactive core that powers their racial-factionalist ideology.</p>
<p>There is also a strong moral argument here. African-Americans of today are descendants of West Africans who were brought to the New World against their will. Theirs is a population that was literally enslaved for a long time, and then was oppressed for a long time after that. Even as their oppression has eased it has become clear that they are, for the most part, trapped in a world not of their making. In other words, for all this time they have been denied the basic rights of ethnic nationhood and self-determination that most peoples around the world have traditionally enjoyed. The fact that European-derived whites, with their hyperverbal brains and their sentimental, empire-adapted ideology, have overwritten ancient wisdom about the primacy of ethnic nationhood and self-determination, and no longer consider it important, is—American blacks might say, with some heat—not their problem.</p>
<p>It <em>shouldn’t</em> be their problem, anyway. And yet it is. And it’s not just their problem, is it? This idea that nations should be substantially multi-racial/ethnic (“multicultural”), bound merely by civic nationalism, economic opportunism, and kumbayah songs, is really the ur-problem, the most deeply planted seed of destruction, in the United States and most other Western countries. This idea seems essentially Christian in origin, but was also elaborated in response to the circumstances of the modern West, including colonialism and the globalization of trade and labor. In the US, it was shaped <em>inter alia</em> by the issues surrounding the Civil War, and was used, e.g., to justify turning African slaves into Union soldiers and then Republican voters in the Reconstruction South.</p>
<p>Despite multiculturalism&#8217;s clash with traditional ways of organizing societies, and its century and a half of failure in the US, it persists—persists even as racial/ethnic factionalism ravages the country, burns its cities, corrupts its democracy, and ruins its quality of life.</p>
<p>Even worse, multiculturalism’s elite proponents have become ever more suppressive of traditional ethnonationalism—declaring it “white supremacy” if favored by whites—even as they openly stoke nonwhites’ racial/ethnic grievances to build their political factions.</p>
<p>So black American nationalism is really only one of a thousand notions rendered unacceptable by America’s multiculturalist cult—whose mindset has managed to colonize both of the major political factions, and has successfully compensated for its evidentiary shortcomings with an hysterical, Inquisitionist crushing of dissent.</p>
<p>Nevertheless, black American nationalism does have advantages that make it a more practical aim amid this woke, antinationalist Inquisition. For one thing, it’s about what American blacks want, and if they declare they want to live apart and self-governing, the elites have no good alternative to the granting of that wish. Again and again those elites have declared American blacks holy and inviolable. Even if the elites’ motive in saying so has been only political and expedient, many blacks, and liberal whites, have taken the assertion at face value.</p>
<p>Another practical advantage that should make black nationalism more viable as a white cause is that American whites, I guess for reasons relating to their Christian backgrounds, prefer to think of themselves as helping others, not as acting selfishly for their own benefit. What could be more unselfish than to carve out thousands of square miles from their fair land, and donate it to their black brothers and sisters, to give them a new and truer freedom?</p>
<p>Would the blacks who lived in such a country experience a decline in living standards? I expect that they would, at least initially and in material terms. But as naïve as it may seem for me to say so, the issue here really goes deeper than material considerations: It’s about self-determination and human dignity. There are about fifty million black descendants of slaves living in the United States, enough to form one of the world’s most populous countries, and in many ways they have made clear that they are a distinctive people who prefer their own kind to others. The claim that they must nevertheless be the permanent captives and pawns of one political faction or another, in a society of European origin that is majority nonblack—a society that also jails them at sky-high rates—is actually ludicrous. It is one of the many toxic lies Americans foolishly think they can continue to live with.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p style="text-align: center;">***</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>THE AMERICAN WAY OF SUBMISSION</title>
		<link>https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/the-american-way-of-submission/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[j stone]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 11 Jan 2021 12:04:59 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[ethnicity]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[immigration]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[revolution]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[USA]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://thoughtsofstone.com/?p=113</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Americans&#8217; conspiracy theories are blue pills Why are Americans on the political Right so drawn to conspiracy theories, from the chemtrails lore and QAnon to the conviction that COVID-19 vaccines are harmful? It’s hard to say anything with certainty about the causes of social trends, societies not being very amenable to the types of experiments &#8230; <a href="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/the-american-way-of-submission/" class="more-link">Continue reading<span class="screen-reader-text"> "THE AMERICAN WAY OF SUBMISSION"</span></a>]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><em>Americans&#8217; conspiracy theories are blue pills</em></p>
<p><span id="more-113"></span></p>
<p>Why are Americans on the political Right so drawn to conspiracy theories, from the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Chemtrail_conspiracy_theory">chemtrails</a> lore and <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/QAnon">QAnon</a> to the conviction that <a href="https://www.newyorker.com/news/q-and-a/the-influence-of-the-anti-vaccine-movement">COVID-19 vaccines are harmful</a>?</p>
<p>It’s hard to say anything with certainty about the causes of social trends, societies not being very amenable to the types of experiments that can settle such issues in other realms of science. But to me a plausible hypothesis is that all this conspiracy-theorizing is a conversion of complex, partly unconscious, and above all inadmissible knowledge concerning existential threats, into a form that the average person can openly express.</p>
<p>In other words, even if this conspiracy stuff seems ridiculous to most educated people, it is stuff that ordinary folks can understand and discuss, and even if the threats are in fact imaginary, they are in principle as salient and alarming as the real threats that are suppressed: Dire threats from the culture and media are converted into dire threats from the water and the air, even from medicines. Similarly, the implicit knowledge that America&#8217;s elite-driven culture corrupts young people is transformed, in the QAnon belief system, into a simpler narrative about a ring of elite pedophiles.</p>
<p>To put it yet another way: on the Right the collective unconscious knows that something has gone terribly wrong and is causing great harm, but it tends not to acknowledge this directly—it tends to acknowledge only imaginary wounds. Psychiatrists call such phenomena, when they occur in individuals, hysterical or somatoform or conversion disorders: For example, a woman’s husband has been cheating on her, but instead of acknowledging this, she develops an ailment with nonspecific and unverifiable symptoms.</p>
<p>Why can’t Americans openly acknowledge what has harmed them? Most obviously because the principal causes of harm over the past half-century are the very things that American cultural and political elites have held up as holy and beyond criticism—indeed, anyone criticizing them is, in the lexicon of America’s new, feminized, despiritualized Puritanism, a <em>hater</em>.</p>
<p>Consider the general reaction if one were to make, on social media or in person in polite company, any of the following assertions (which I regard as essentially true):</p>
<ul>
<li>The permitting of mass immigration to the United States from 3<sup>rd</sup> World countries over the past several decades has been&#8212;in effect, from the perspective of legacy Americans&#8212;a <a href="https://thoughtsofstone.com/seed-of-destruction/">fraudulent </a>and treasonous ploy by the Democratic Party to pack the electorate in their favor.</li>
<li>To further this scheme, Democrats have depicted it as a compassionate, Christian policy that only “racists” would oppose—notwithstanding the fact that ethnically based nationhood is and always has been the norm worldwide.</li>
</ul>
<p><img loading="lazy" class="wp-image-122 aligncenter" src="https://thoughtsofstone.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/01/massimm.jpg" alt="" width="438" height="443" srcset="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2021/01/massimm.jpg 655w, https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2021/01/massimm-296x300.jpg 296w" sizes="(max-width: 438px) 85vw, 438px" /></p>
<ul>
<li>Democratic Party coalition-building over the last half-century has also relied heavily on the stoking of anti-white feelings among American blacks, anti-male feelings among American women (especially single women who are inherently more susceptible to this message), and anti-heterosexual feelings among homosexuals.</li>
<li>To reward the members of its coalition and further divide them from legacy Americans, the Democratic Party has succeeded in establishing policies that significantly discriminate against legacy Americans and in favor of women and non-whites. Incredibly, these policies, including the euphemistically named “affirmative action,” favor even affluent non-white immigrants over legacy Americans. Again, to quash opposition or even debate, Democrats have depicted these discriminatory policies as compassionate and necessary measures that only evil people could oppose.</li>
</ul>
<p><img loading="lazy" class="size-full wp-image-115 aligncenter" src="https://thoughtsofstone.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/01/biden-1.jpg" alt="" width="530" height="474" srcset="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2021/01/biden-1.jpg 530w, https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2021/01/biden-1-300x268.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 530px) 85vw, 530px" /></p>
<ul>
<li>Major news media organizations, the advertising and entertainment industries, academia, Big Business, large segments of the legal profession, and of course most of the pseudo-opposition Republican Party, have for their own selfish reasons enabled and abetted these schemes.</li>
</ul>
<p><img loading="lazy" class="size-full wp-image-68 aligncenter" src="https://thoughtsofstone.com/wp-content/uploads/2020/10/mcdonalds.jpg" alt="woke capital" width="420" height="615" srcset="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2020/10/mcdonalds.jpg 420w, https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2020/10/mcdonalds-205x300.jpg 205w" sizes="(max-width: 420px) 85vw, 420px" /></p>
<ul>
<li>While these schemes have as their inevitable result the destruction of traditional American society and its replacement with a grouping that necessarily will be degraded, unstable, partly atomized, and riven with ethnic conflict, the “new America” in principle will be much easier for these cultural and political elites to control.</li>
<li>Although the Democrats’ latest power-seeking move—large-scale rigging of the presidential election, mostly through ballot-harvesting in key Democrat-controlled areas—has outraged many on the right, the Democrats&#8217; much more harmful method of electorate-packing has been ongoing for decades.</li>
<li>Effectively the USA’s cultural and political elites have ruined a great country in their pursuit of greater power over it. Many of these elites may actually believe that their motives have been pure. Yet the gravity of their crime far exceeds anything that any traitor or indeed any foreign adversary has ever done to the United States.</li>
</ul>
<p>Obviously, for the average American, stating any of these things openly and identifiably, beyond one’s circle of family and close friends, would risk immediate practical consequences such as social ostracism and job loss.</p>
<p>Less obviously, such a declaration would also have an important psychological consequence: To acknowledge awareness of this real and colossal crime while doing nothing about it—continuing one’s normal routines—would be embarrassing; it would amount to a confession of pathetic weakness and cowardice.</p>
<p>For most Americans, such a declaration could invite as well the recognition that for years, even decades, they have effectively collaborated in this crime, by voting for Democrats and Republicans who have furthered it, and perhaps even by participating in ritual denunciations of fellow Americans who have opposed it.</p>
<p>For all these reasons, I suspect, many Americans avert their eyes from the harshest truths about their situation, preferring to embrace fantasies that signal their distress without inviting the labels “racist” or &#8220;white supremacist&#8221; or being otherwise unmentionable. They call these fantasies “red pills,” but they are really only blue pills.</p>
<p>And perhaps the remarkable mass rallies for a president who was always evidently an inept narcissist, the MAGA-themed protests and other gatherings, and even the recent, brief mob occupation of the U.S. Capitol, should be seen in a similar light: as make-believe manifestations of a rage that dare not speak its name—manifestations that in the end are ways of losing, not ways of winning.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>SOME REALITIES OF &#8220;PEOPLE POWER&#8221;</title>
		<link>https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/some-realities-of-people-power/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[j stone]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 13 Nov 2020 22:15:05 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[fall of the West]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[revolution]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[USA]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://thoughtsofstone.com/?p=98</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Stray thoughts on a Red State rebellion. &#160; Almost exactly twenty years ago, on the other side of the world from the USA, the elites and middle classes of the Philippines, with low-key but ample international support, overthrew their country’s elected president, Joseph Estrada, in what was later called a “constitutional coup.” Estrada was in &#8230; <a href="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/some-realities-of-people-power/" class="more-link">Continue reading<span class="screen-reader-text"> "SOME REALITIES OF &#8220;PEOPLE POWER&#8221;"</span></a>]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><em>Stray thoughts on a Red State rebellion.</em></p>
<p><span id="more-98"></span></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>Almost exactly twenty years ago, on the other side of the world from the USA, the elites and middle classes of the Philippines, with low-key but ample international support, overthrew their country’s elected president, Joseph Estrada, in what was later called a “constitutional coup.”</p>
<p>Estrada was in many ways like Donald Trump. He was an older guy with a womanizing past and rough-edged, frat-boy attitude who was widely known through past media exposure (he’d been an action star in Filipino movies, back in the day), and had plenty of mass appeal, but was somewhat repulsive to the more educated classes.</p>
<p>A big difference was that Estrada had been credibly accused of corruption. When, in January 2001, his Senate supporters effectively suppressed key evidence in his impeachment trial, the prosecutors walked out, liberals in the Philippines threw up a hue and cry, foreign diplomats and creditors became nervous, and the idea of simply ousting Estrada spread quickly.</p>
<p>Just a decade and a half before, in 1986, a mass movement that had come to be known as the EDSA Revolution (after an avenue in Manila where the main gathering took place) had resulted in the overthrow of the dictator Ferdinand Marcos. The anti-Estrada opposition followed this obvious model, and when the impeachment trial collapsed, EDSA II took place immediately. The media were for it, the US, a key ally, gave the nod (G.W. Bush, fresh from his own Bush v. Gore court victory, was about to take office), important Philippine cabinet officials including the heads of the police and military abandoned Estrada, and even the Philippine Supreme Court blessed the coup with the airy declaration that “the welfare of the people is the supreme law” (i.e., <em>salus populi suprema lex</em>). Estrada saw that he had lost virtually all support, and resigned, allowing his successor, vice president Gloria Arroyo, to take office.</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-104" src="https://thoughtsofstone.com/wp-content/uploads/2020/11/edsa-revolution-dos.jpg" alt="EDSA II" width="600" height="381" srcset="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2020/11/edsa-revolution-dos.jpg 600w, https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2020/11/edsa-revolution-dos-300x191.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 709px) 85vw, (max-width: 909px) 67vw, (max-width: 984px) 61vw, (max-width: 1362px) 45vw, 600px" /></p>
<p>(Arroyo, who later pardoned Estrada after his corruption trial and conviction, eventually faced corruption allegations herself, concerning a bribe allegedly demanded by her government from a Chinese government-linked telecom company that wanted a contract to install a “national broadband network” linking Philippine government offices. But she was viewed much more favorably by the elites than Estrada had been, and ended up serving out her terms of office.)</p>
<p>Why is any of this of interest now? Well, for one thing, it’s a reminder that presidential transitions in “democracies” are not necessarily constitutional or legal just because the media proclaim them to be. EDSA II also illustrates how Trump’s presidency, if it were restored by court action, could come to an untimely end.</p>
<p>Perhaps more importantly, this two-decade-old “people power” story highlights some of the things that Trump and his supporters, or a post-Trump Red State America, would <em>not</em> have if they were ever to try to achieve political power through a revolt or rebellion:</p>
<ul>
<li>They would not have significant foreign support.</li>
<li>They would not have the support of their country’s elites.</li>
<li>They probably would not have the support of any major media organization, domestic or foreign.</li>
<li>They almost certainly would lack support from the USA’s top military brass.</li>
</ul>
<p>Could they still prevail? Sure. But they would have to overcome all these disadvantages. And since they would not have MSM support they could not simply gather dramatically in one place and hope for a media-induced buildup of pressure on the federal government.</p>
<p><strong>Red States Army</strong></p>
<p>Essentially, Red State America would need to form an army, à la 1776. Although the needed size and firepower of that army would depend on the movement’s ultimate goals, I think that force would have to be at least several hundred thousand strong to contend with Blue States National Guard units and possibly regular army and USAF units. Much of the “Red States Army” total could come from Red State National Guard units, defecting regular military troops, and retired/reserve veterans, though it would probably be able to pad out that core with a larger group of hunters and others who own and know how to use guns.</p>
<p>This rebel movement, to the extent it could control its own territory, would have a grip on most of the former-USA’s food production, so food shouldn’t be a problem. But the movement would need to set up its own banking system, central bank, and currency, much as the Confederate States did in Civil War I. It would need to establish control over the parts of the internet and telecom networks, rail and road networks, and other infrastructure elements within its domain. It would need its own social security system. And so on, and so on.</p>
<p>Moreover, prior to rebellion at state level, this movement would need a network of benefactors who would fund the cause covertly, for example by adding soldiers and support workers to existing businesses’ payrolls, or simply in a low-visibility, cash-based system outside the federally regulated banking system. As many on the right have learned already, US banks ultimately will not (knowingly) do business with those whom the left elites designate as “enemies of the people.”</p>
<p>The goals of a Red State confederacy could be, for example simply to break away and form a sovereign country, taking existing Red States along with any adjacent Blue State rural counties whose inhabitants vote to join. At county level the USA is mostly Republican, so in principle such a Red America would include most of the land area of the lower-48 states and of course all of Alaska. This would leave Blue America with most of the GDP-producing industry of the former USA, but also with most of the long-term social and demographic problems—“vibrancy” I think they call it.</p>
<p>All that vibrancy would be reflected in whatever army the Blue States could muster following the tens or hundreds of thousands of defections by Red State-loyal troops and officers, plus the loss of the many military bases within Red States. And if the Red States’ goal were purely defensive, the Blue States would have the added burden of having to subdue Red State cities, presumably through high-cost urban warfare.</p>
<p>What of the Antifa and BLM brigades we saw in action last summer? Well, their antics don’t strike me as particularly relevant to actual combat—although I can imagine many of them being unwilling to learn that lesson except in the hardest possible way.</p>
<p>In short, when it comes to actual fighting, a Red State army could have substantial advantages. (I&#8217;m assuming that neither side would go nuclear in this conflict.)</p>
<p>My guess is that the hardest task for an independence-seeking Red America would be the political task of convincing Red State governors and legislators to secede in the first place, so that the rebellion could begin to organize at scale. They don’t make US politicians like they used to—certainly not like they did in 1861.</p>
<p>In fact, neither Trump nor any prominent Red State politician, as far as I know, has had the mental clarity and courage even to <em>raise the issue</em> of resolving the USA’s current schism through political separation. That’s despite the Woke Left’s increasingly obvious willingness to tyrannize its domestic enemies, i.e., half of the country, by demonizing, canceling, and disemploying them, silencing their political speech, and, if necessary, imprisoning them in re-education camps.</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" class="size-full wp-image-105 aligncenter" src="https://thoughtsofstone.com/wp-content/uploads/2020/11/reich.jpg" alt="Turd Reich" width="300" height="370" srcset="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2020/11/reich.jpg 300w, https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2020/11/reich-243x300.jpg 243w" sizes="(max-width: 300px) 85vw, 300px" /></p>
<p><img loading="lazy" class="size-full wp-image-106 aligncenter" src="https://thoughtsofstone.com/wp-content/uploads/2020/11/schmidt.jpg" alt="About Schmidt" width="300" height="398" srcset="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2020/11/schmidt.jpg 300w, https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2020/11/schmidt-226x300.jpg 226w" sizes="(max-width: 300px) 85vw, 300px" /></p>
<p>The USA was founded on the principle of self-determination as the ultimate escape from tyranny, and the tyranny of the contemporary, woke Left already threatens to be worse in some ways than what Colonial Americans faced in the run-up to their declaration of independence. So it does seem appropriate at least to start thinking about how contemporary Americans might successfully act on that hallowed principle.</p>
<p style="text-align: center;">**</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>WOKEISM IS AN INTERIM ANTICULTURE</title>
		<link>https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wokeism-is-an-interim-anticulture/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[j stone]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 19 Oct 2020 09:52:05 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[ethnicity]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[fall of the West]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[immigration]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[women]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://thoughtsofstone.com/?p=64</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[The Great Awokening may be catastrophic for the USA but as a cultural phenomenon it is inherently transitory &#160; Is the United States in the process of remaking itself with a new ideology called Wokeism? A lot of people seem to think so, but I don&#8217;t. The idea I sketch out briefly here is that &#8230; <a href="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wokeism-is-an-interim-anticulture/" class="more-link">Continue reading<span class="screen-reader-text"> "WOKEISM IS AN INTERIM ANTICULTURE"</span></a>]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><em>The Great Awokening may be catastrophic for the USA but as a cultural phenomenon it is inherently transitory</em></p>
<p><span id="more-64"></span></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>Is the United States in the process of remaking itself with a new ideology called Wokeism?</p>
<p>A lot of people seem to think so, but I don&#8217;t. The idea I sketch out briefly here is that the recent pandemic spread of Wokeism, a.k.a. The Great Awokening, is really only a transitory cultural phenomenon, more than a mass hysteria but less than the development of a full-fledged successor culture. Wokeism does draw upon trends in Western culture that have been underway for decades. However, as an ideology or culture it is basically incoherent and destructive, and does not offer a viable guide to a sustainable new way of life. Wokeism is chiefly marking a period of cultural upheaval&#8212;and is telling us nothing of how that period of upheaval will end.</p>
<p><strong>The mess of Wokeism</strong></p>
<p>Wokeism lacks a coherent list of do’s and don’ts, of the kind that normally make up a working culture. It shows no sign of having been thought through.</p>
<p>To give one example, the people who run BLM recently published a “manifesto” on their website which included a vaguely Maoist insistence on collective parenting:</p>
<p style="padding-left: 40px;">We disrupt the Western-prescribed nuclear family structure requirement by supporting each other as extended families and ‘villages’ that collectively care for one another, especially our children, to the degree that mothers, parents, and children are comfortable.</p>
<p>Apparently this was embarrassing enough, even for the dedicated banner-carriers and fellow-travelers of BLM, that this provision along with the rest of the manifesto was removed from the website soon after it was posted. When I went to the site address (<a href="https://blacklivesmatter.com/what-we-believe/">https://blacklivesmatter.com/what-we-believe/</a>) as I was composing this essay, I got a simple 404 error—suggesting that BLM lacks not only sense but also basic IT skills.</p>
<p>Other features of Wokeism include demands for radical police reforms—radically weakening police powers—or even the defunding/abolition of police departments. Some municipal governments in the United States have been so well captured by leftists that they really seem willing to adopt such measures. But—to state the obvious—these measures, and the criminality and anarchy they are bound to unleash, are things that a developed society with a large, wealthy, and center-right business-owning class will not tolerate for long.</p>
<p>Further down the Wokeists’ unrealizable/unsustainable wishlist we find radical reforms to education, which have the ultimate goal of bringing about equality of outcomes for different racial and ethnic groups, especially in public schools where the Wokeists’ policy grip is strongest. Standardized tests will be de-emphasized, admissions exclusivity weakened, and discipline more or less abandoned, in order to accommodate more disadvantaged groups. Recitations of <a href="https://www.city-journal.org/rise-of-woke-schools">Woke ideology</a> presumably will start to crowd out traditional subjects such as math and English. To again state the obvious: this cuckoo radicalism will mean only that any family having the means to do so will take their children out of public schools, leaving the unfortunate kids whose parents can’t place them elsewhere to suffer a long nightmare of Woke education.</p>
<p>Then there is the absurd idea of reparations, to be paid somehow to American blacks who, after 155 years of post-slavery systemic racism, have managed to become the world’s richest black population by far. I wonder how serious the Wokeists are about reparations anyway, since actual payment might be construed as an end to the matter, obliging both blacks and Wokeists to move on from all their racial grievance-mongering. (We all know the grievance-mongering will never be put to rest, as it serves an essential partisan-political function.) Actual payment might also do embarrassingly little to alter the essential situation of American blacks, who in many cases would end up worse following their rapid spending of their windfalls.</p>
<p>Open-door immigration appears to be a core policy of Wokeism, though it shouldn’t be, as it obviously harms the interests of American blacks. Even among immigrant groups, the open-door policy is apt to become unpopular to the extent that these groups see further newcomers as a source of unwanted competition for jobs. Of course liberal immigration policies have prevailed anyway in the US over the past few decades, and thus they are sustainable in that retrospective sense. But open-door immigration isn’t a culture or a pillar of a culture—it is effectively an anti-cultural policy, which almost by definition will destroy the host country’s traditional way of life and create a situation in which newcomer cultures will have to duke it out for eventual supremacy. Who seriously thinks that if Chinese-Americans or Indian-Americans take over large parts of the USA, they will continue to permit mass immigration from Africa or Latin America?</p>
<p>Similarly, if the wokeists succeed in making whites second-class citizens in their own country by mandating POC-preferences in jobs and university admissions—which they clearly hope to do—the end-result is unlikely to be a harmonious multiracial/multiethnic USA living under Wokeism. Much more likely will be the outcome seen in multi-ethnic situations elsewhere in the world, namely inter-ethnic strife, followed by the triumph of one or more, presumably nonwhite ethnicities—who may just divide the old USA among themselves and, in their new American country or countries, adopt nationalistic policies favoring their own. To them, the romantic multiracialism of early 21<sup>st</sup> century whites may end up being seen as a tragically maladaptive cultural trait—vaguely reminiscent of the predilection for firewater that helped doom 19<sup>th</sup> century Native Americans.</p>
<p><strong>Wokeists embody the chaos of wokeism</strong></p>
<p>Apart from Wokeism’s specific policy notions, look at the Wokeists themselves—especially the ones at the business end of Wokeism, where ideas are turned into action. Are these activists bustling Bolsheviks, busily setting up farmers’ or manufacturers’ or soldiers’ collectives? Not exactly. They seem like supremely messed-up people, a very high proportion of whom have histories of mental illness and/or severe sexual identity issues. They seem not only fundamentally unhappy but fundamentally set against the world as it is. That is why they burn and break and topple indiscriminately, destroying even statues of <em>Lincoln</em>. They seem to want the outside world to bear a closer resemblance to the disorder they have within. In other words, they don’t seem to be <em>for</em> anything meaningful. Does an Antifa Autonomous Zone look constructive? Is it something Western people could build upon? How about a burning, rubble-strewn downtown Minneapolis?</p>
<p>OK, but what about rich Woke-capitalist billionaires like Zuckerberg and Bezos? Aren’t they formidable enough to sustain Wokeism as a new culture?</p>
<p>Well, certainly, the Zuckerbergs and the Bezoses and their ilk are powerful. But I think they have zero intention of sustaining Wokeism in a form that could be called a new culture. They are primarily businessmen who have got to where they are by adapting rapidly in a dynamic business (and political) environment. They are now adapting to Wokeism, because it is a clear and present danger to anyone with commercial interests. Their adaptation is to feign support—they fear Wokeism and don’t want to be harmed by it, and think they can escape the firebombs and boycotts if they get out in front of the whole thing with various empty gestures.</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" class="size-full wp-image-68 aligncenter" src="https://thoughtsofstone.com/wp-content/uploads/2020/10/mcdonalds.jpg" alt="woke capital" width="420" height="615" srcset="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2020/10/mcdonalds.jpg 420w, https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2020/10/mcdonalds-205x300.jpg 205w" sizes="(max-width: 420px) 85vw, 420px" /></p>
<p>Needless to add, corporations are not about to start hiring obese black trans performers, let alone 75-IQ kids from the &#8216;hood, to do anything substantive. Woke capitalists’ actions will mainly be limited to the patronage of a few, influential, black “public intellectuals,” who are essentially running legal protection rackets.</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" class="size-full wp-image-69 aligncenter" src="https://thoughtsofstone.com/wp-content/uploads/2020/10/huckster.png" alt="" width="385" height="376" srcset="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2020/10/huckster.png 385w, https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2020/10/huckster-300x293.png 300w" sizes="(max-width: 385px) 85vw, 385px" /></p>
<p>Woke capitalism may also encompass a more urgent hiring preference for well educated Asians and Latinos over whites—anyone but whites! But for the most part the corporate version of Wokeism will be symbolic. After all, competitive organizations need competent people, and Wokeism—because of its insistence on equality of outcomes—does almost everything possible to discourage the development of practical competence.</p>
<p>In short, Wokeism on its own can never be a constructive, society-driving ideology or culture. It may seriously damage or even topple the old culture of legacy Americans, and that process may take years and result in terrible destruction, perhaps on the scale of the French Revolution or even the Fall of Rome. But Wokeism is not itself a successor culture that will be around a couple of generations from now.</p>
<p><strong>The importance of demographics and technology</strong></p>
<p>I don’t claim to fully understand wokeism or its origins, but I don’t think <em>anyone</em> can understand it without first understanding how the cultural ground, so to speak, was prepared for it.</p>
<p>To switch to a viral analogy, wokeism was a pathogen that was always around. There is nothing really new about it. It is a mix, a pastiche, of a lot of old, discredited ideas most of which were first put forward by 1960s radicals. Why did it suddenly break out into a pandemic spread? I think the answer is that the big changes that made the outbreak possible were in the susceptibilities of host populations.</p>
<p>One big change was the cultural feminization that followed the mass entry of women into culturally influential professions such as journalism, publishing, law, politics, and science over the past half-century. I’ve written about this in <a href="https://thoughtsofstone.com/the-great-feminization/">earlier</a> <a href="https://thoughtsofstone.com/the-day-the-logic-died/">essays.</a> Among other things, this feminization process appears to have made the culture profoundly more vulnerable to empathy-inducing themes of oppressed minorities, downtrodden refugees, and buzz-phrases like “systemic racism.”</p>
<p>American women have not been doing particularly well under their emancipation—their estimated lifetime prevalence of major depression is now more than 20 percent, to note one adverse mental health trend among many. Marriage and birth rates are falling. More and more women, having followed the dictates of feminism and sexual liberation, are living alone and childless. Amid the anxiety and bleak isolation of the COVID-19 crisis, many of them seem to have embraced Wokeness as a belief system that is almost spiritually sublime in its ambitions, and at the same time satisfyingly engages their maternal instincts to protect the weak. Other basic instincts may be involved as well. In any case it can’t be denied that women, particularly white women, have been enormously overrepresented at woke and BLM marches and protests.</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-70" src="https://thoughtsofstone.com/wp-content/uploads/2020/10/bethesdawomen.jpg" alt="" width="600" height="338" srcset="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2020/10/bethesdawomen.jpg 600w, https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2020/10/bethesdawomen-300x169.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 709px) 85vw, (max-width: 909px) 67vw, (max-width: 984px) 61vw, (max-width: 1362px) 45vw, 600px" /></p>
<p>Women’s cultural influence in America isn’t going away any time soon. Any new culture that takes hold, or any form of cultural reversion, presumably will have to suit them. But a glance around the world tells us that women on the whole are very flexible when it comes to culture, provided that certain basic needs are met—needs that center largely around motherhood. I can&#8217;t believe that Wokeism, in the long run, meets enough of those needs. It seems more like a yearning, a dance, a pose, a fling, than real life.</p>
<p>Apart from cultural feminization and the COVID-19 crisis, two other big factors have obviously been relevant. One is the Internet, and social media in particular, which has boosted in an unprecedented way the potential speed and scale of social contagions. (I think it’s also generally accepted, if not as well studied as it should be, that women tend to transmit social contagions among themselves much more efficiently than men do.)</p>
<p>The other factor is the 2020 presidential election, which has spurred various get-out-the-vote operations and generally has encouraged partisan activists to whip up emotions to energize potential voters. I think various left-wing/Democrat activists did just that in the wake of George Floyd’s death, and that was the spark on dry tinder that flamed into the Great Awokening.</p>
<p>That flame has dimmed considerably in the months since June. It may flare up again if the Democrats sweep on election day. But I think it won’t burn for 70-odd years as Marxism-Leninism did. It doesn’t have the coherence or the minimal connection to human nature that it would need to have. What stable ideology will form on the other side of Wokeism is unclear. But given the ongoing cultural decay of whites and the relative robustness of nationalism among nonwhites, it seems likely that Wokeness will only mark the transition to a new, probably nonwhite-centered culture&#8212;or cultures. Those cultures could, ironically, end up being much more conservative and traditional than the decadent mishmash from which Wokeness emerged.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>SEED OF DESTRUCTION</title>
		<link>https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/seed-of-destruction/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[j stone]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 15 Jun 2020 22:37:05 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[ethnicity]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[fall of the West]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[immigration]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://thoughtsofstone.com/?p=55</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[An expatriate’s perspective on pan-ethnic mass immigration Western societies almost without exception in recent decades have been transformed by the large-scale additions of essentially all foreign ethnicities to their legacy European-stock populations. How this came about is less important than the fact that it happened and now festers as the central problem of Western civilization. &#8230; <a href="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/seed-of-destruction/" class="more-link">Continue reading<span class="screen-reader-text"> "SEED OF DESTRUCTION"</span></a>]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><em>An expatriate’s perspective on pan-ethnic mass immigration</em></p>
<p><span id="more-55"></span></p>
<p>Western societies almost without exception in recent decades have been transformed by the large-scale additions of essentially all foreign ethnicities to their legacy European-stock populations.</p>
<p>How this came about is less important than the fact that it happened and now festers as the central problem of Western civilization. But I think it’s fair to say that this transformation began, several decades ago, principally because Western elites wanted it, at least partly for reasons they could not openly defend. A simplified and somewhat cynical version is that Left-leaning politicians in the US, emboldened by their success in capturing “the black vote,” calculated that they could import other ethnic minorities from abroad <em>en masse</em> and ultimately assemble a permanent electoral majority that way. Businessmen and the rich, seeking a wider range of cheap-labor options, were eager to go along. This basic idea then spread to the elites of other Western countries.</p>
<p>The pan-ethnic flow has continued for those mostly-unacknowledged reasons, and also because recently arrived foreigners and their offspring have by now acquired substantial political power of their own. But the reasons that have been used to publicly justify this change, at least in recent decades, are different. The elites, who now include the mouthpieces of these new ethnic voting blocs, have been assuring the increasingly feminized, compassion-oriented legacy populations of the West that this historic transformation has been necessary as an act of compassion, and a recognition of universal civil rights—huddled masses and all that. For the special case of the USA, they have argued or implied that the country has always been a construct of immigrants, a &#8220;civic&#8221; rather than an ethnic nation, a “promised land” in the words of RFK.</p>
<p>This has always been more than a dry, reasoned argument. The elites have applied to the legacy lower orders a strong emotional and moral pressure to accept that multi-ethnicity, “diversity,” is good, that it sits on the correct side of history, that opposing it is bad and racist. Some European governments have been so successful in their browbeating that they now enforce this new moral code in actual law. But even Western elites that haven’t achieved that level of thought-control have been pretty effective in enforcing diversity dogma through threats of disemployment and social ostracism for dissidents—<em>cancellation</em>.</p>
<p>Diversity dogma as we know it today would not have had as receptive an audience in the 1960s. The cultural ground had not yet been prepared. The average Democrat then would be considered “far right” today. So when the floodgates to pan-ethnic immigration began to be opened around the middle of that decade, people were simply misled. The elites, instead of presenting the coming demographic transformation as a good thing, assured ordinary citizens that it wouldn’t happen. The influx of foreigners would constitute a social ripple rather than a sea change—nothing to worry about! “This bill we sign today”—<a href="https://cis.org/Report/Legacy-1965-Immigration-Act">claimed</a> Lyndon Johnson of the 1965 Hart-Celler Immigration Bill—“is not a revolutionary bill. It does not affect the lives of millions. It will not restructure the shape of our daily lives.”</p>
<p>It did, though. And in the context of those original false assurances, the mass migration of ethnically and culturally distant peoples to the West has been an ongoing fraud, perpetrated by Western elites against their own legacy populations. By the same token, the compassion-based, right-side-of-history argument used to justify mass immigration is mainly window dressing. Still, it has been remarkably effective, and it deserves an effective response. As I organize my own thoughts about this, I don’t suppose that I have anything truly novel to say, but still I think my presentation is a better one than mass immigration opponents in the popular media usually provide.</p>
<p><strong>It’s not about “hate”</strong></p>
<p>I have never been comfortable with arguments against mass immigration that rest heavily on the idea of immigrants as lawless primitives.</p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><img loading="lazy" class="size-full wp-image-26 aligncenter" src="https://thoughtsofstone.com/wp-content/uploads/2020/07/notsendingbest.jpg" alt="" width="592" height="471" srcset="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2020/07/notsendingbest.jpg 592w, https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2020/07/notsendingbest-300x239.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 592px) 85vw, 592px" /></p>
<p>That’s not to say that immigrants never <em>are</em> lawless primitives. It’s probably always been the case that a significant proportion of them belong in that category. But an argument that focuses just on the lowlifes implies that all the lawful, hard-working immigrants are totally OK. And they’re not totally OK, any more than lawful, hard-working white Americans would be, in the eyes of their hosts, if they tried to form a huge expatriate colony within some ethnically and culturally distant society.</p>
<p>I know this because I’ve spent most of my adult life as an expatriate in ethnically and culturally distant societies, and despite being lawful and hard-working I’ve run again and again into the limits of host country tolerance for foreigners. Those limits have been manifest in laws, such as laws limiting the kinds of jobs resident foreigners can do, and the property rights they can enjoy. Those limits have also been apparent in attitudes, such as the presumption that a foreigner opposing a native in court should normally lose, and the widespread belief that foreigners should pay more for things than natives do, or the simple, murmured resentment among locals to the effect that “there are too many foreigners here.”</p>
<p>Locals’ limited tolerance for foreigners like myself has sometimes struck me as too limited, but the fact that it <em>is</em> limited has never seemed fundamentally wrong. Placing bounds on foreign influx and influence in a society has always seemed like obvious common sense—a common sense forged by biological and cultural evolution as a basic human instinct.</p>
<p>Calling this innate in-group preference “hate” is one of the contemporary Left’s most specious and dishonest ploys. <em>Don’t be a hater</em>! My own experience is that countries placing heavy restrictions on foreigners’ residency and influence typically have citizens that are very warmly disposed towards visitors from abroad—probably in part because those restricting laws give locals a measure of security, from which they feel more free to be hospitable.</p>
<p>Nor is my opposition to mass immigration in my own country rooted in hatred of foreigners: I have spent most of my adult life living in far-flung places among ethnically and culturally dissimilar folk, and even married one of them, so that my children are now ethnically and culturally half-American and half-foreign. In other words, it has long been the case that the people dearest to me are foreigners in whole or in part.</p>
<p>From what do the limits of our tolerance spring, if not from hate?</p>
<p>Well, from something more fundamental than a human emotion. An organism is not an organism if it does not have boundaries that separate it from its environment and from other organisms. If it is too permeable, it will not survive. Human societies are not as well defined in this sense, compared to flora and fauna, but clearly they have been shaped by a similar evolutionary logic.</p>
<p>If one needs to invoke an emotion as the force underlying the universally limited human tolerance of foreigners, why not invoke love? As in, love for one’s kin and country—love for one’s national and cultural identity. One can’t have those good things, those fulfilments of basic human needs, <em>and</em> open one’s borders to all the peoples of the world. It would be like opening the doors of one’s house to random strangers. Speaking of which: remember that scene in the film <em>Doctor Zhivago</em> when the doctor returns from the war to find his comfortable Moscow residence filled with several other families—his own wife and children now confined to a single room? It was a wrenchingly effective depiction of the Bolshevik disregard for basic human nature. And for the viewer, as for Zhivago, the proper objects of hatred were not the new tenants but the Bolshevik overlords that had sent them.</p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><img loading="lazy" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-35" src="https://thoughtsofstone.com/wp-content/uploads/2020/07/zhivago-house-divided.jpg" alt="" width="700" height="326" srcset="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2020/07/zhivago-house-divided.jpg 700w, https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2020/07/zhivago-house-divided-300x140.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 709px) 85vw, (max-width: 909px) 67vw, (max-width: 984px) 61vw, (max-width: 1362px) 45vw, 600px" /></p>
<p>Naturally, when a flood of immigrants makes a citizen feel that he has been displaced, his country effectively overrun, a certain amount of hatred toward the foreign displacer is an understandable reaction, and historically has been pretty effective at motivating a reversal of the flood. But hatred in that context is merely a means, and a temporary one, not the end in itself.</p>
<p>Globally, and ideally, the end is a good and positive end: a system of distinct nations—homelands populated by what are, more or less, extended families, each with a dominant ethnicity and culture—in which good fences, fair trade, and moderate amounts of tourism, intermarriage, and urban cosmopolitanism make good neighbors. In principle, at least, a sane and farsighted world can realize that humane goal calmly through policy, rather than through conflict.</p>
<p><strong>Diversity destroys democracy</strong></p>
<p>There are other reasons to oppose the flood of multi-ethnic immigration that has hit the West in recent decades. One set of reasons, largely amounting to a negative version of the argument above, invokes the weakening of social bonds, the dilution of the usual sense of shared culture, neighborliness and trust in an ethnically bound society, the erosion of the usual feeling of belonging (&#8220;this no longer feels like my country&#8221;), with an attendant demoralization that has already been blamed, e.g., for the downturn in white life expectancy in the US.</p>
<p>Another set of reasons involves the economic distortions caused by mass immigration, which include downward pressure on wages, disemployment of the legacy population, and—no less important—a draining away of skilled labor from the countries supplying the immigrants.</p>
<p>Then there is the higher-crime/lower-quality-of-life angle, which is especially relevant when the majority of immigrants come from less wealthy and orderly places.</p>
<p>Lastly, there is an argument that has long seemed to me especially important and yet mostly neglected. This is the argument that heavy multi-ethnicity in a society is incompatible in the long run with democracy—at least, traditional, stable, Western-style democracy—and must in the end produce political dissolution and anarchy or anyway some other-than-democratic outcome.</p>
<p>In part, this is an argument from simple observation: Multi-ethnic states almost never form naturally, and when they have been set up artificially—e.g., by Western colonial powers over the past few centuries—the result usually has been fragmentation or the emergence of a strongman (e.g., Saddam Hussein) with a police state.</p>
<p>This is also an argument from simple logic: Shared ethnicity is a very strong social and political binder, perhaps stronger than any other, particularly when the ethnic group is a political minority and feels, or is told that they should feel, a sense of adversity and oppression. In principle, as left-leaning parties in the USA and elsewhere have recognized, a sizeable political coalition can be built from such aggrieved, bloc-voting minority groups, <em>provided that the faction-building party can manage to keep the flames of grievance alive in them</em>. I think it’s fair to say, and it is maybe self-evident from events ongoing as I write, that those flames must ultimately burn away the mutual respect and trust that a society needs to sustain a democratic style of government. Many of the founders of the U.S. Republic knew that factionalism, in general, would be a constant temptation and a major threat to its survival. Race-based factionalism, which the founders largely failed to anticipate, is arguably on historical grounds—not to mention, evolutionary-biological grounds—the most toxic.</p>
<p>In the US the Democratic Party, previously the party of southern whites, has been shifting towards this mode of racial-minority factionalism (which also encompasses non-ethnically defined marginalized groups such as women and LGBTs) at least since the civil rights era of the 1950s and 60s. Over the decades, powered especially by immigration, this strategy has strengthened the party electorally, and on a superficial analysis would seem to have positioned it now for long-term electoral dominance. But really this strategy has been self-defeating, in the sense that it effectively has destroyed the social fabric of the USA, making democracy itself now untenable as a means of stable governance.</p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><img loading="lazy" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-33" src="https://thoughtsofstone.com/wp-content/uploads/2020/07/whriot.jpg" alt="" width="700" height="459" srcset="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2020/07/whriot.jpg 700w, https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2020/07/whriot-300x197.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 709px) 85vw, (max-width: 909px) 67vw, (max-width: 984px) 61vw, (max-width: 1362px) 45vw, 600px" /></p>
<p>If I’m right that my country—presaging developments elsewhere in the West—is about to see the full collapse of its political system, then the Left’s current pandering claim that slavery was America’s “original sin” may have a grain of truth to it. I would call it not only America’s original sin but also the original seed of America’s destruction: Through slavery, Americans brought a large, racially and developmentally distant minority into the country. That ultimately prompted a massive conflagration before the Republic was even 90 years old. But what came afterwards was arguably worse. The decision <em>not</em> to give ex-slaves their own separate homeland (as Lincoln among others had wanted) but to keep them in the US as citizens led ultimately, perhaps inevitably, to the emergence of civil rights ideology, diversity dogma, pan-ethnic immigration, and the current caustic factionalism that I expect will prove terminal.</p>
<p>The same fatal seed may deserve blame for the fall of the West more generally, since American-style civil rights ideology long ago infected the elites of other Western democracies and at least partly accounts for their post-colonial embraces of pan-ethnic immigration.</p>
<p>Am I too pessimistic? We’ll soon see. In the meantime, I’ll be busy preparing myself and my family for life and work outside the countries of the self-immolating West.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>DON&#8217;T FEED THE ANIMALS</title>
		<link>https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/dont-feed-the-animals/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[j stone]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sun, 16 Feb 2020 23:53:44 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[ethnicity]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[human ecology]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://thoughtsofstone.com/?p=53</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Thoughts on conservation biology for humans ____________________________________________ “Don’t feed the animals” is a concept I didn’t really learn until late childhood, when I traveled one summer to Yellowstone with my family, and saw signs everywhere with that warning. It’s a central concept of wildlife management in wilderness areas where humans intrude. It’s a counterintuitive concept, &#8230; <a href="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/dont-feed-the-animals/" class="more-link">Continue reading<span class="screen-reader-text"> "DON&#8217;T FEED THE ANIMALS"</span></a>]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><em>Thoughts on conservation biology for humans</em></p>
<p><span id="more-53"></span></p>
<p>____________________________________________</p>
<p>“Don’t feed the animals” is a concept I didn’t really learn until late childhood, when I traveled one summer to Yellowstone with my family, and saw signs everywhere with that warning. It’s a central concept of wildlife management in wilderness areas where humans intrude.</p>
<p>It’s a counterintuitive concept, but a crucial one. Many and perhaps most people, especially when motivated by compassion, tend to assume there is no real harm in their feeding an individual elk or bison, particularly one that looks hungry. What wildlife managers know is that such feeding endangers not only the food-bearing humans but, more importantly, the local animal populations that are being fed. Uncontrolled feeding by humans of wild animals makes them dependent on that artificial food source, effectively reducing their adaptation to their wild environment even as their population balloons from the sudden nutrient abundance. It sets up the possibility of a crash of the animal population, perhaps to zero, due to an interruption of the artificial food supply, a nutrient deficiency caused by the new supply, or perhaps an infectious disease that takes advantage of the new density of hosts.</p>
<p>The key point, from a wildlife management or conservation biology perspective, is that doing what seems beneficial at the level of individual animals can, in the long-run, be utterly disastrous at the population level.</p>
<p><strong>It&#8217;s the Population, Stupid</strong></p>
<p>Conservation biology is functionally akin to politics in the human realm. Both aim to manage populations of animals in their natural habitats, the big difference being that politics involves humans managing other humans, which obviously introduces many complications and complexities. When humans manage animal populations they are much more emotionally detached from their charges. They get no direct feedback or pushback from them. They focus on the goals that are most important and most objectively measurable. They would consider it absurd to promote “equality” among the individual animals in a given population, or to strive to eradicate harmful stereotypes, or to do away with patriarchal oppression, or to promote the civil liberties of animals that want to engage in homosexual activity, or to change their sexual identity, or to “increase the diversity” of an animal population by mixing in other populations or subspecies from other habitats.</p>
<p>Conceivably if we could read animals’ thoughts or emotions better than we can now, we would discern greater complexity in their lives and “cultures.” We would more routinely see animals as distinct individuals with individual needs. But for a conservation biologist, the overriding goals wouldn’t change. Those goals center on the idea of conserving animal populations, <em>as populations</em>, at natural, self-sustaining levels in harmony or equilibrium with the habitats for which they are evolutionarily adapted. Implicit here is the notion of an animal population as a distinct group with a distinct lineage and territory, and a relatively small inflow and outflow of genes from and to outsider groups. The survival of that population in its natural, wild state is the essential aim, compared to which the fleeting joys, sufferings and neuroses of individual animals are immaterial. In other words, the biologist “sees the forest, not the trees”—because the forest really is all that history will ever see.</p>
<p>Humans in the ancient world tended to think of themselves in similar terms: as members of distinct populations, extended families really, whose general health, prosperity, fertility—above all, survival—was the proper object of human politics and governance. Even if they focused on other cultural goals as well, they would have regarded an expanding or at least stable population as the ultimate measure of success. As Yahweh is quoted saying to Abraham in Genesis 22:17, “I will multiply thy seed as the stars of the heaven, and as the sand which is upon the sea shore…”</p>
<p>A word here about diversity: Conservation biologists value it highly, but the diversity for which they aim is not the same as the “diversity” that gets so much attention in the human political realm. Diversity in the lexicon of conservation biologists, or what is usually called “biodiversity,” refers to a diversity of <em>distinct, habitat-linked animal populations</em>, many of them representing different species or subspecies. It does <em>not</em> refer to genetic diversity within an animal population. In fact, conservation biologists tend to view a large flow from one population into another, or from one habitat into another, as a negative outcome, a destroyer of biodiversity, i.e., an invasion or conquest—thus the term “invasive species.”</p>
<p><strong>Free-Agent States</strong></p>
<p>Many people in the modern West, especially among the elites, prefer to see themselves as members of populations that are no longer like extended families of one ethnicity and culture. These post-traditional populations are more like modern sports teams, with flexible rosters of free agents whose attachments to the group are merely contractual.</p>
<p>Why has this new notion gained so much currency? The main reason is that it is a <em>fait accompli</em>. Prior to the 1960s virtually all Western societies were essentially ethnostates, and as such had at least mildly and implicitly racist policies in place, including policies on immigration. But the memory of toxic ethno-nationalism in the WW2 era, the post-1950s <a href="http://www.absltzero.com/the-great-feminization/">feminization</a> of culture and policy, and a growing sense that nonwhites represent a relatively untapped source of electoral power, led the West’s political elites to try to expiate their racism with various policy changes, including relaxations of immigration laws. Unsurprisingly, these border openings were followed by ever-increasing inflows of nonwhites from developing countries—nonwhites in search of better standards of living via more generous welfare systems and more prosperous, stable economies. Heavy multi-ethnicity eventually became the status quo that the political system organized itself to benefit from and justify: Immigrant-citizens and the wider political and business-owning class that are favored by this arrangement now say what they must and vote as they must to maintain it. At the same time, the legacy populations that <em>don’t</em> benefit, and might have defended themselves, have been disarmed by threats of being tarred as racists or even “white supremacists.”</p>
<p>There is a long history of thinking about one particular Western country, the United States, not as an ethnostate but as a new type of nation, bound by a single set of beliefs in liberal democracy (“creedal” nation) or, even more loosely, by the mere rule of law (“civic” nation). However, even if one thinks those explanations are valid for the USA, they have never been expressly adopted by other Western countries, which—again—have long had ethnic bases for their nationhoods.</p>
<p>In any case, multi-ethnicity has happened and is here and for the immediate future will remain, because the factors that drove and allowed it still pertain.</p>
<p>But do free-agent states command the allegiance of their citizens sufficiently—are they knit together well enough—to allow them to compete, in the long run, with ethnostates? And anyway does the survival of a “group” with rapidly changing membership and no common culture really mean anything? What do its members have in common, other than possession of the same territory? If we really were to think of societies without attention to underlying changes in their ethnic composition, we would blind ourselves to certain stark realities, such as invasions and conquests, and even the slower national collapses that are maybe just as common and important. If one set of ethnically and culturally distinct people moves into a country, replacing its relatively infertile natives over a few generations, is there any sense in pretending the country has remained the same?</p>
<p><strong>What if Ethnic-Group Survival Were Priority One?</strong></p>
<p><em>Is</em> doesn’t imply <em>ought</em>. People can, and will, practice politics any way they like. For most, being reminded that we in the West think of animal populations in one way and our own human populations in a quite different way would probably draw little more than a bewildered shrug. Others would warn, rightly enough, that the traditional ethnocentric view has its own hazards, on full display in the WW2 era, or in more recent, sometimes very bloody, inter-ethnic conflicts—or even during a relatively peaceful interlude a century or so ago, when many governments adopted eugenics policies including forced sterilization, essentially to “improve their stock” as a farmer might try to improve his herds of cattle or sheep.</p>
<p>But have these past excesses frightened us into running too far in the other direction? It just seems worth considering how our politics and societies would look if we reverted to the usual practice of defining our populations, our “nations,” in ethnic terms, with reasonable allowance for urban cosmopolitanism as well as the ethnic mixing that occurs at the margins of any population. Such a reversion would mean making the maintenance of our Western nations—under the wider goal of human population diversity—our first priority, as is the case, effectively, in traditional societies and even some of the West’s more successful and happy groups (e.g., Jews, Amish, Mormons).</p>
<p>We also would recover traditional, intuitive, easily recorded metrics for our nations’ health, namely their sizes and fertility rates. We would see our present low fertility rates and fast-dropping population numbers (i.e., for people of European ethnicity) as sure signs that something is wrong. Stability, or even rises in a population to fill its undeveloped territory, would be the goals.</p>
<p>This logic has the added virtue that it aligns with our deep sense that things <em>have</em> been bad and <em>are</em> getting worse, and it clearly belies the polyanna <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2018/11/19/science/steven-pinker-future-science.html">pronouncements</a>—based on other, less relevant “data”—that we’ve never had it so good.</p>
<p>Returning to this way of thinking wouldn’t mean abandoning a humane approach to governance. But by making the sustenance of our nations, properly understood, our first priority, we would create a sensible barrier to the kind of social experimentation that tends to harm family formation and fertility. Moreover, thinking of populations in the traditional way, as extended families, should help restore the traditional sense of, and need for, community—that basic higher good that has been increasingly suppressed and lost in the individualistic modern West.</p>
<p>At bottom, thinking of nations in ethnic terms is realism, or at least a lot closer to realism than modern liberalism gets. Much of the energy of modern liberalism is spent in covering up its own irreconcilable contradictions, arguably the worst of which is the promotion, for political purposes, of ethnic identity and cultural separatism among nonwhites despite the implicit (if unrealizable) need to bind these groups, with whites, somehow in a shared sense of nationhood. And of course it is hard to find historical precedents for multiethnic/ multicultural societies that inspire optimism. Multiethnicism may have been tolerable at times amid the growth and wealth-building of empires, but it also seems to have torn its host civilizations apart whenever wider allegiances weakened. In any case, there are all too many, all too convincing historical precedents for population replacement through migration or invasion, aided by the consequent social decay and demoralization among the natives. It may be the way of the world that &#8220;peoples&#8221; and their civilizations don’t last forever; even so, there are fundamental reasons why we—even as conquerors—have been inclined to see such collapses as sad and tragic events.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>GIRL POWER</title>
		<link>https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/girl-power/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[j stone]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 06 Jan 2020 22:36:08 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[women]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://thoughtsofstone.com/?p=50</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Thoughts on trauma-tale and cancellation cascades __________________________________________ From the late Renaissance to the early Industrial Age, it was common for European families to send their adolescent daughters to convents for long periods, in order to educate them, to let them become nuns, or just to keep them out of trouble. The experience must have been &#8230; <a href="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/girl-power/" class="more-link">Continue reading<span class="screen-reader-text"> "GIRL POWER"</span></a>]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><em>Thoughts on trauma-tale and cancellation cascades</em></p>
<p><span id="more-50"></span></p>
<p>__________________________________________</p>
<p style="line-height: 150%; margin: 0in 0in 6.0pt 0in;">From the late Renaissance to the early Industrial Age, it was common for European families to send their adolescent daughters to convents for long periods, in order to educate them, to let them become nuns, or just to keep them out of trouble. The experience must have been something like <em>Girl, Interrupted,</em> but with lots of medieval-style Catholicism, stone walls, and cold baths. Not too surprisingly, the prison-like concentrations of stressed, sexually maturing girls began incubating epidemics of hysteria, often with florid sexual aspects. Also unsurprisingly, given the mystical and demonological themes that were prevalent in Christian cultures of the day, the epidemics generally took the form of “demonic possession.”</p>
<p style="line-height: 150%; margin: 0in 0in 6.0pt 0in;">Sometimes these episodes stayed within convent walls, and either burned out from lack of attention or were broken up by the dispersal of the participants. But in some notable cases recorded in the history books, convent hysterias had significant impacts beyond the convents, namely when the victims blamed their possessions and/or sexual activity on a male priest. Usually this was the priest who said Mass and heard confessions at the convent, and the claims would be that he had either directly debauched his victims, or had done so remotely via priapic demons. These accusations and the acting-out behaviors that went with them could be competitive and contagious among convent girls, resulting in lurid claims even against men they had never met.</p>
<p style="line-height: 150%; margin: 0in 0in 6.0pt 0in;">One of the most notorious of the convent hysterias began in about 1632 when an epidemic of supposed demonic possession swept through an Ursuline convent in Loudoun, France. The affected young women claimed that they had been possessed and sexually abused by demons sent by a local priest, Urbain Grandier. He was not the convent confessor, and could not have done the things alleged, but he was good looking and wealthy, and was rumored to be a ladies’ man, counting women in several prominent local families among his conquests. Later historians and writers, including Aldous Huxley, who novelized the story in <em>The Devils of Loudoun</em>, suggested that the convent’s Mother Superior, the index case in the hysteria, knew of his exploits and had developed a sexual obsession with him.</p>
<p style="line-height: 150%; margin: 0in 0in 6.0pt 0in;">To the initial investigators, there was ample evidence that the “demonic possessions” and associated claims against Grandier amounted to hysterical fantasies. But there was also a political dimension to the case: Grandier on an unrelated matter had recently made an enemy of the powerful Cardinal Richelieu, King Louis XIII’s right-hand man. On Richelieu’s authority, a new investigation was set up to reach the “correct” verdict and suppress contradictory evidence.</p>
<p style="line-height: 150%; margin: 0in 0in 6.0pt 0in;">To this end, there were public exorcisms of the possessed nuns. These were fantastic displays in which the women, reportedly well coached by Richelieu’s minions, mimed sexual acts while loudly accusing Grandier of various demonic crimes. Thousands of townspeople and even tourists attended these spectacles, and, no doubt as Richelieu had hoped, many considered the nuns’ antics to be convincing evidence of Grandier’s guilt.</p>
<p style="line-height: 150%; margin: 0in 0in 6.0pt 0in;">Eventually some of the affected nuns, including the Mother Superior whose antics had set off the whole hysteria, had second thoughts and publicly recanted. Unfortunately for Grandier, the case had acquired too much momentum by then, and he was found guilty, tortured, and burned at the stake in 1634.</p>
<p style="line-height: 150%; margin: 0in 0in 6.0pt 0in;"><strong>The cascade</strong></p>
<p style="line-height: 150%; margin: 0in 0in 6.0pt 0in;">Some might see witchcraft/possession hysterias like the Loudoun case as just historical oddities, of no relevance today. But I think they belong to an ancient, recurring pattern. After all, outbreaks of sexual-victimization claims among women, and the exploitation of those outbreaks by authority figures, seem as prominent now in the West as they have ever been. Think of the recent <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Brett_Kavanaugh">Kavanaugh hearings</a> and the public parade of his accusers with their lurid, weepy tales. Think of the Weinstein, Epstein, and Cosby media/legal circuses. This is hardly ancient history!</p>
<p style="line-height: 150%; margin: 0in 0in 6.0pt 0in;">The idea I sketch out here is that there is a behavioral program, for the most part specific to females, that evolved long ago as an alternative means of empowerment or self-expression but continues to manifest in various ways and indeed accounts for a good deal of contemporary social history.</p>
<p style="line-height: 150%; margin: 0in 0in 6.0pt 0in;">My argument is basically impressionistic and tentative: I perceive, rightly or wrongly, a pattern that underlies seemingly different social phenomena. I am aware that this is not a terrain that has been or is likely ever to be mapped definitively with social psychology experiments. It is too complex, too squirrelly. It is also much too threatening to current orthodoxy to be a subject of truly free scientific inquiry. So I won’t attempt much more here than to point to cases, describe the apparent pattern, and hope the evidence accumulates enough—in the telling, and in readers’ subsequent experiences—to be persuasive, in the usual human, Bayesian, weight-of-evidence sense.</p>
<p style="line-height: 150%; margin: 0in 0in 6.0pt 0in;">To me the most essential feature of these episodes is the <strong>exploitation of victimhood</strong>. Men have a deep instinct to protect women, and some women take advantage of that by claiming to have been harmed or under threat of harm. They do this to gain attention, fame or money, or simply to nullify their shame over something to which they consented but later regretted.</p>
<p style="line-height: 150%; margin: 0in 0in 6.0pt 0in;">The idea that a trauma has occurred—a trauma that continues to victimize the victim—is arguably the central thread in the history of hysteria. It is evident in the old convent possession hysterias, in female-dominated <a href="https://www.amazon.com/Zar-Spirit-Possession-Healing-Rituals/dp/9774166973">spirit possession</a> syndromes that still exist in the Third World, and in all the modern-era, medicalized forms of hysteria, going back to Charcot—whose studies of hysterics in the late 1800s are often credited with having kicked off modern psychiatry.</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" class="size-full wp-image-8 aligncenter" src="https://thoughtsofstone.com/wp-content/uploads/2020/07/400px-Une_leçon_clinique_à_la_Salpêtrière.jpg" alt="" width="400" height="253" srcset="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2020/07/400px-Une_leçon_clinique_à_la_Salpêtrière.jpg 400w, https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2020/07/400px-Une_leçon_clinique_à_la_Salpêtrière-300x190.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 400px) 85vw, 400px" /></p>
<p style="line-height: 150%; margin: 0in 0in 6.0pt 0in;">As I see it, another core feature of these phenomena is their ability to grow and spread as a <strong>social contagion</strong>. Convent hysterias tended to spread infectiously within the walls of individual convents. In some cases, affected young women, sent from one convent to another as part of a dispersal strategy, would seed outbreaks of hysterical behavior in their new institutions. Hysterias in more open settings, such as the one at Salem that began with a group of girls and women acting out “possession” behaviors similar to those seen in European convent episodes, were apt to spread through their communities and into neighboring ones. More modern, medicalized forms of hysteria such as Charcot’s “hysteroepilepsy” of the late 1800s and the “multiple personality disorder” (MPD) that became prominent in the 1980s, also grew in scope as they were publicized and susceptible women learned how to act them out.</p>
<p style="line-height: 150%; margin: 0in 0in 6.0pt 0in;">Now in the age of the Internet there is the potential for near-instant mass contagions of trauma tales. Even one prominent news story about one alleged victim may be enough to trigger the participation of others from around the world. The Epstein, Weinstein, Kavanagh and Cosby cases all seem to have been driven by this “broadcast” effect.</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" class="aligncenter wp-image-16 size-medium" src="https://thoughtsofstone.com/wp-content/uploads/2020/07/epstein-300x203.jpg" alt="" width="300" height="203" srcset="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2020/07/epstein-300x203.jpg 300w, https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2020/07/epstein.jpg 684w" sizes="(max-width: 300px) 85vw, 300px" /></p>
<p>What about the truth of the claims in these episodes? If a man actually has engaged in serial sexual assault, and his victims complain to the police so that charges are brought against him, how is that “hysteria” or anyway a remarkable social phenomenon requiring explanation? My response is that in such cases there may not be a need for an explanation, but that I’m not referring to such cases here. I’m referring to cases where the claims are obviously to some extent false or exaggerated or opportunistic, tend to be used in ways that go beyond mere law enforcement, occur after <strong>delays that may extend for years or decades</strong>, and come in cascades that strongly suggest a social contagion. The vast majority of real sexual assault cases, even those involving repeat offenders, never make it past the back pages of the newspapers and don’t generate social phenomena such as I’m describing here.</p>
<p>Another frequent, though not universal, theme in these stories is the victim’s <strong>loss of agency</strong>—an utter helplessness on her part that implicitly absolves her of any responsibility for her plight, and underscores her urgent need for aid and sympathy. In premodern and early-modern spirit-possession cases the loss of agency was complete by definition and usually <em>was</em> the traumatic event. Late 20<sup>th</sup> century MPD cases worked in almost but not quite the same way: The victim’s “dissociation” into “alter personalities” was not the trauma itself but, rather, a reaction to the trauma. As one prominent pro-MPD <a href="https://books.google.com/books/about/Multiple_Personality_Disorder.html?id=LfprAAAAMAAJ">psychiatrist</a> put it at the time, MPD is the victim imagining that the abuse she is suffering is happening to someone else. However, in both spirit-possession and MPD, the possessing spirits and alters serve as impressive behavioral symbols of the victim’s traumatized state, and often, more literally, act as her authoritative spokespersons—her Gloria Allreds, if you like.</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" class="size-medium wp-image-24 aligncenter" src="https://thoughtsofstone.com/wp-content/uploads/2020/07/mpd-sybil-300x263.jpg" alt="" width="300" height="263" srcset="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2020/07/mpd-sybil-300x263.jpg 300w, https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2020/07/mpd-sybil-768x673.jpg 768w, https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2020/07/mpd-sybil.jpg 839w" sizes="(max-width: 300px) 85vw, 300px" /></p>
<p>Similarly, Charcot’s hysterics of the 1880s, though they were not afflicted by spirits or alters, were seized by mysterious syndromes that mimicked epilepsies or movement disorders and ostensibly robbed them of their will, contorting their bodies and putting them into trance, “hypnotic” states. The theme of hypnosis, of course, runs through virtually all modern forms of hysteria, as a route to the hysterical state of consciousness and the retrieval of buried trauma memories—and as a suspender of ordinary consciousness and agency.</p>
<p>The loss-of-agency theme is less prominent but still present in more modern, matter-of-fact cascades of sex assault claims, where it continues to underscore the victim’s victimhood. In the Cosby case, for example, his accusers typically acknowledged having dined with him, having drunk alcohol with him, having gone to his hotel room at night, or having done other things that hint at some degree of volition. But virtually all of these women claimed or suggested that Cosby had then robbed them of their ability to resist by slipping them tranquilizer or “knock out” pills of one kind or another. Weinstein’s accusers, for their part, have spoken of his coercion and threats, of his menacing bulk, of his power to destroy their careers. Epstein’s accusers have claimed in some cases that he “<a href="https://www.dailymail.co.uk/news/article-7700529/Jeffrey-Epsteins-sex-slave-Virginia-Giuffre-spotted-Prince-Andrew-denied-sex.html">enslaved</a>” them, if not by actually clapping them in chains then by flying them to remote islands from which no escape was possible. I am not suggesting that any of these men is innocent, but I think it’s worth noting that very few of the victims in these cases have claimed simply, let alone promptly, that they fought back against the accused but were overpowered.</p>
<p><strong>Perps and buried memories</strong></p>
<p>Historically the most prominent cascades of trauma tales, such as the witchcraft mass-hysterias of the late medieval and early modern era, and the MPD-related mass-hysterias of the 1980s-90s, have been those featuring accusations against real people—accusations of witchcraft or Satan-worship or sexual assault, or some combination thereof. That the older, pre-20<sup>th</sup>-century subset of these cases resulted in the jailings and executions of hundreds or thousands of innocent people in Europe and America is well known. Less well known is that the MPD/Satanic-ritual-abuse (SRA)/recovered-memory scares of very recent decades harmed similar numbers of people across the Western world, through false accusations, wrongful prosecutions, and in many cases wrongful and lengthy jailings. The latter episode also corrupted, and exposed the deep corruptibility of, the social work and psychotherapy-related professions, not to mention the media.</p>
<p>But cascades of trauma tales are not always dependent on claims against human perpetrators. One of the more prominent recovered-memory variants that arose in the 1980s and 90s featured trauma-tales that were every bit as lurid as those of MPD/SRA, and often seemed to have been tailored to grab public attention, but lacked human perpetrators and almost never involved law enforcement. This was the “alien abduction” epidemic. Like some of the older spirit-possession cases, abduction stories replaced human perps with otherworldly ones—aliens in this case, of all shapes and sizes, though usually they were said to be the huge-eyed, bulge-headed “greys” that were already prominent in the UFO lore.</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" class="size-medium wp-image-9 aligncenter" src="https://thoughtsofstone.com/wp-content/uploads/2020/07/abducted-184x300.jpg" alt="" width="184" height="300" srcset="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2020/07/abducted-184x300.jpg 184w, https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2020/07/abducted.jpg 245w" sizes="(max-width: 184px) 85vw, 184px" /></p>
<p style="line-height: 150%; margin: 0in 0in 6.0pt 0in;">The recovered-memory epidemic in all its major variants burned out by the late 1990s, in part because it made enemies of hundreds of wrongfully charged defendants and their families, and in general clashed with traditional mechanisms of due-process (which had developed partly in reaction to early-modern hysterias). The real tipping point seems to have been the development of a consensus in psychiatry and law-enforcement that many of the claimants were fantasists and hypnosis-recovered memories were mostly or entirely confabulations.</p>
<p style="line-height: 150%; margin: 0in 0in 6.0pt 0in;"><b>Beyond hypnosis</b></p>
<p style="line-height: 150%; margin: 0in 0in 6.0pt 0in;">However, around the time that the recovered-memory craze dissolved, a new and remarkably similar epidemic involving traumatic memories started becoming very common. In this syndrome the patient, usually female, complained of sleeplessness, fibromyalgia, irritable bowels, chronic fatigue, or other selections from the rich lore of psychosomatic illness. Instead of hinting that these symptoms derived from some buried trauma-memory, as in the now-discredited recovered-memory epidemic, the patient attributed them to an <em>accessible</em> trauma-memory, perhaps of a recent car accident or divorce, or even something as common as <a href="https://www.postpartum.net/learn-more/postpartum-post-traumatic-stress-disorder/">childbirth</a>. It was an easy route to victimhood and the tangible and intangible benefits that went along with that status. For women—also men—in the military, who had no shortage of alleged “traumas” to choose from, and could use such claims to get taxpayer-funded <a href="https://www.disabilitysecrets.com/resources/disability/veterans-disability/make-ptsd-claim-va.htm">“disability” benefits</a>, it was almost literally a gold mine.</p>
<p style="line-height: 150%; margin: 0in 0in 6.0pt 0in;">I am describing PTSD, of course—Post Traumatic Stress Disorder. As a clinical entity it was rare in the 1960s/70s world where I grew up. Now it is easily one of the most common psychiatric diagnoses: even in the early 2000s <a href="https://www.nimh.nih.gov/health/statistics/post-traumatic-stress-disorder-ptsd.shtml">NIMH</a> estimated that more than 5 percent of women and almost 2 percent of men in the US “had PTSD” in the past year (“past-year prevalence”). In the US military, where a PTSD diagnosis can be a monetary gift that keeps on giving, the prevalence has been much <a href="https://www.pdhealth.mil/research-analytics/psychological-health-numbers/mental-health-disorder-prevalence-and-incidence#slideshow-6">higher</a>—even among men, now that the benefits of victimhood in this context are monetary, i.e., go beyond the psychological comforts of victimhood that tend to draw women almost exclusively.</p>
<p style="line-height: 150%; margin: 0in 0in 6.0pt 0in;">Despite its alleged roots in World War I and earlier “shell shock” cases, PTSD is essentially a modern, culture-bound syndrome. It first came to prominence as a veterans’ complaint with the help of Vietnam Vet advocacy groups in the aftermath of that war. However, as the recovered-memory epidemic receded in the 1990s, sensitive women and their enablers in the rapidly feminizing medical profession began adopting it as a civilian, primarily female illness. From the perspective of a hysteria-aware skeptic, it was and continues to be almost perfect as a replacement for recovered-memory syndromes. There is no reliance on hypnosis, nor does it require claims against a human perp and resulting scrutiny from the judicial system. In a newly feminized, newly sensitized age, how can it even be questioned? Therapists or psychiatrists who doubt its validity (a validity that is of course enshrined in the latest DSM editions) can lose not only their patients but also their professional reputations, even their licenses to practice. Skepticism from within academia or the medical profession therefore has been <a href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC1119389/">rare</a>. And when doubts have been expressed they usually have been expressed in opaque academese.</p>
<p style="line-height: 150%; margin: 0in 0in 6.0pt .5in;">Nothing that I have written in this book should be construed as trivializing the acts of violence and the terrible personal losses that stand behind many traumatic memories. The suffering is real; PTSD is real. But can one also say that the facts now attached to PTSD are true (timeless) as well as real? Can questions about truth be divorced from the social, cognitive, and technological conditions through which researchers and clinicians come to know their facts and the meaning of facticity…? My answer is no. [in <a href="https://kclpure.kcl.ac.uk/portal/en/persons/allan-young(6bf03185-e533-4ac2-88ba-76349ba04ddf).html">Allan Young</a>’s <a href="https://www.amazon.com/Harmony-Illusions-Inventing-Post-Traumatic-Disorder/dp/0691017239"><em>The Harmony of Illusions</em></a>]</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" class="size-medium wp-image-21 aligncenter" src="https://thoughtsofstone.com/wp-content/uploads/2020/07/grande-mal-300x297.jpg" alt="" width="300" height="297" srcset="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2020/07/grande-mal-300x297.jpg 300w, https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2020/07/grande-mal-150x150.jpg 150w, https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2020/07/grande-mal-768x760.jpg 768w, https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2020/07/grande-mal.jpg 772w" sizes="(max-width: 300px) 85vw, 300px" /></p>
<p><strong>MeToo: Hysteria Lite</strong></p>
<p>In the paragraphs above I’ve touched on the Weinstein, Epstein, Cosby and Kavanagh cases—classic early 21<sup>st</sup> century #MeToo stories that ostensibly are free of traditional hysterical themes such as spirit possession, witchcraft and somatization disorders. They involve trauma claims but are not cases for therapists or priests or witch-doctors to handle—they are criminal cases or at least cases involving allegations of serious personal misconduct. Yet they involve seemingly infectious cascades of claims, and my hypothesis here is that they feature essentially the same behavioral program that drives other, more frankly hysterical trauma-story cascades. The claims against a Weinstein or a Cosby may be more veridical than those of a 16<sup>th</sup> century novice nun who pretends to be possessed by a demon sent by some priest, but they cascade in the same way, and involve at least some degree of exaggeration and falsehood—as should be evident from even a cursory critical analysis of these cases.</p>
<p>Moreover, there seems to be a social aura of intense feeling around these cases. They don’t exist in isolation as civil or criminal matters to be decided by a sober, judicial weighing of facts. Many women are fiercely, often blindly supportive of the plaintiffs, and are ready to punish anyone who is insensitive enough to express skepticism. Some men too have their protective instincts activated and are also strongly supportive. Many of the rest, perhaps a large majority, are skeptical but know better than to draw adverse attention by saying anything. A few, of course, do voice their skepticism and catch hell for it—and though their skepticism may be well founded and perfectly logical, even obvious, we tend to see such people as <a href="https://www.spectator.co.uk/2019/11/prince-andrew-should-have-married-someone-like-my-wife/">foolish</a> rather than honest or brave or perspicacious. An unspoken but widely accepted fact about hysterias and related trauma-tale cascades is that the truth has little power against the mass emotions they harness.</p>
<p><strong>A Peculiarly Feminine Power</strong></p>
<p>“Power” may be an essential concept here. One can speculate almost endlessly about this sort of thing, but an obvious hypothesis is that these female-driven trauma-tale cascades are, at least in part, manifestations of an ancient, instinctive “asymmetrical warfare” tactic—a means by which women can defeat men who are on an individual basis physically and psychologically more powerful. As one well known anthropologist, speaking of female-dominated African possession cults, has put it:</p>
<p style="padding-left: 40px;"><em>zar</em> possession provides women patients (acting consciously or unconsciously) with an opportunity to pursue their interests and demands in a context of male dominance. [I.M. Lewis, <em>Ecstatic Religion</em>, p. 71]</p>
<p style="padding-left: 40px;">Where they are given little domestic security and are otherwise ill-protected from the pressures and exactions of men, women may thus resort to spirit possession as a means both of airing their grievances obliquely, and of gaining some satisfaction. [Lewis, p. 68]</p>
<p>If women have evolved an instinct to use this tactic, or have evolved traits that otherwise favor that behavioral pattern, it’s at least conceivable that men would have evolved their own way of responding. Curiously, though, the way men respond in modern times and cultures seems to be inefficient at best. The accused tend to try to placate the female complainants or otherwise try to avoid the wrath of the furies that have been whipped up against them, yet usually end up facing the mob alone. There is very little of the male banding-together that could provide an effective defense. Perhaps most bystander men in this situation instinctively sense that they are better off not getting involved. In cases where the woman is alleging that a man has victimized her, a certain proportion of men will be sympathetic and protective to her—thus further hindering any male solidarity.</p>
<p>If women have evolved this cascade tactic as a way of evening up the scales against men, it makes sense that they would use it or adapt it for situations in which (a) they can activate the necessary network of claimants, and (b) they can use it to achieve some goal that would otherwise be harder to reach. Conceivably the modern media-driven cascades aimed at “canceling” or “de-platforming” people who have done or said something politically incorrect owe something to this feminine tradition. The complainants who join these cascades usually point to a broader harm committed by the target person, for example against a minority group whom the target has slighted. But they often use terminology reminiscent of older, trauma-tale cascades, i.e., suggesting that they themselves have been victimized and traumatized. In a recent <a href="http://www.absltzero.com/the-day-the-logic-died/">essay</a> on the notorious Larry Summers cancellation in 2005, I noted the language used by one of the prominent complainants in that case, MIT professor Nancy Hopkins.</p>
<p style="padding-left: 40px;">“When he started talking about innate differences in aptitude between men and women, I just couldn’t breathe because this kind of bias makes me physically ill,” Dr. Hopkins said.</p>
<p>Cancellations of people who violate political correctness codes are frequently labeled “witch hunts,” but I think the analogy is not as loose as people tend to assume. Witch-hunts, such as the New England variety, were led by a different and more clearly defined “authority” than the relatively amorphous journalist-activist network that presides over modern p.c.-violation cases. But in both situations, we see a central dynamic in which an initial accusation against a target is followed by a contagious piling-on of claims and vilification until—usually—the miscreant issues a groveling apology, loses his job, or suffers some other adverse outcome. And although there are no data on this, it seems obvious to me from ordinary experience that women are vastly overrepresented among the claimants in these cascades.</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" class="size-medium wp-image-20 aligncenter" src="https://thoughtsofstone.com/wp-content/uploads/2020/07/gilliam-275x300.jpg" alt="" width="275" height="300" srcset="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2020/07/gilliam-275x300.jpg 275w, https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2020/07/gilliam.jpg 660w" sizes="(max-width: 275px) 85vw, 275px" /></p>
<p><strong>Cascade control</strong></p>
<p>Is there any effective response to cascades of this nature? I get the sense that this question tends to be asked most urgently these days about cancellation cascades, which are often unambiguously irrational and unjust. In the Larry Summers cancellation of 2005/06, with which I’m relatively familiar, reasoned argument by high-profile defenders of Summers, including the popular writer Steven Pinker, writing in high-profile publications, counted for remarkably little against the emotional storm conjured up by a handful of feminist academics and their media enablers.</p>
<p>That attack on Summers clearly was aimed at causing him professional harm—he was then the president of Harvard College. Professional harm was the outcome too, for that and countless other cancellations in recent years. Shouldn’t the law provide a remedy in such cases?</p>
<p>It should perhaps, but it doesn’t, and arguably that’s a big part of the problem. In the 1600s and 1700s in Britain and America, tort law actually <a href="https://www.trademarkandcopyrightlawblog.com/2016/10/defamation-takes-a-holiday-slander-and-the-salem-witch-trials/">did provide</a> good remedies, and (with some notable exceptions) increasingly good deterrence, against the very serious slander/defamation of calling someone a witch. Hysterias such as the one at Salem also provided salutary examples of the harm that could be caused when such defamations went uncontested. But beliefs in witchcraft abated in the century or so after Salem, and in general tort law has never adapted to the fact that witchcraft accusations can have modern variants that are despiritualized but still have very serious reputational and economic consequences. That problem would be fixed, at least at the level of conservative-leaning states, if legislators could strengthen laws meant to protect against this sort of harm—in a way that could survive the inevitable First-Amendment-based challenge from federal courts.</p>
<p>Another element of an effective response would be a response that is just as organized and networked and vocal and goal-directed as the attack. Victims of cancellation cascades tend to be isolated and overwhelmed in the mediasphere by howling mobs that intimidate not only the victims but also their employers and would-be supporters, until the victim loses his job and status. One of the more remarkable aspects of the Age of P.C. is the degree to which big corporations have been cowed by such mobs. It’s hard to avoid the conclusion that having a louder, more numerous mob on your side—a mob that brings a credible threat of a mass boycott of any company that crosses it—could make all the difference in such cases. Implementing this strategy would mean organizing the Right to oppose almost instinctively any media-driven cascade aimed at canceling someone for a political-correctness violation.</p>
<p>Organizing the Right to this extent seems problematic at present, though. Broadly speaking, the Right lacks the relatively energizing and binding “religiosity” of the modern progressive Left—lacks the Left’s youthfulness too. There is no right-wing equivalent of Antifa. Contemporary corporations seem to <a href="https://www.bostonherald.com/2019/11/24/no-one-wins-when-chick-fil-a-caves-to-the-left/">sense pretty well</a> that the Left coheres better and thus poses a greater threat to their profits.</p>
<p>On the other hand, considering that hysterias tend to fade out as soon as they are widely seen as such, it might help a lot just to shine a light on this phenomenon—in other words, as I’m trying to do here, by calling attention to cancellation cascades and trauma-tale cascades as putative manifestations of an ancient, hysteria-related behavioral program. To some extent we do this already when we compare cancellation cascades to witch hunts, but we could take it further by arguing that the comparison is more than just metaphorical, and may have ancient roots in female social behavior—behavior that, due to the mass-entry of women into public life in the last half-century, has been more culturally consequential than ever before in history. There must be a <em>reason</em> that feminists, despite their unprecedented grip on Western culture, keep complaining about women’s “powerlessness” with respect to men. Perhaps that illusion of weakness is essential to their actual and ascendant power.</p>
<p style="text-align: center;">***</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>THE DAY THE LOGIC DIED</title>
		<link>https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/the-day-the-logic-died/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[j stone]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 23 Aug 2019 05:14:39 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[women]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://thoughtsofstone.com/?p=40</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[The feminist hysteria that enveloped Harvard President Larry Summers in 2005 marked a shift away from reason and logic in American public discourse __________________________________________ &#160; Roughly a decade ago, returning briefly to the US after a decade living abroad in countries with more traditional cultures, I began to notice something about the USA—something that I &#8230; <a href="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/the-day-the-logic-died/" class="more-link">Continue reading<span class="screen-reader-text"> "THE DAY THE LOGIC DIED"</span></a>]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><em>The feminist hysteria that enveloped Harvard President Larry Summers in 2005 marked a shift away from reason and logic in American public discourse</em></p>
<p><span id="more-40"></span></p>
<p>__________________________________________</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>Roughly a decade ago, returning briefly to the US after a decade living abroad in countries with more traditional cultures, I began to notice something about the USA—something that I sensed I wasn’t supposed to notice. Of course like everyone else I could see that the country had undergone and was still undergoing real changes. Some of them seemed radical, like the then-new push for legalizing same-sex marriage. Some of them, such as the strengthening strictures of environmentalism and political correctness, were intensifications of trends that had been in place for decades. I think that unlike most people, though, I came to see these changes less as changes towards the “Left” and more as changes towards the “Feminine.” For a variety of professional and circumstantial reasons I was probably more aware than the average person that men and women tend to differ in psychological traits and also that women had been steadily amassing cultural power as they had entered the upper reaches of professions such as journalism, law, publishing, science and politics. I perceived that America’s cultural changes—reflected widely in other developed countries, especially the UK—were the changes one would have expected in a society where women were gaining influence.</p>
<p>I was initially inclined to believe that the differences between men and women in behavior and policy preferences were mostly subtle—and mostly small in relation to the human capacity for learning new ways of thinking. But relevant events shifted me towards the stronger view that men and women are apt to differ profoundly in their psychology and cognitive functioning, which implies that the changes in store for the culture must also be profound. The “relevant event” that did more than any other to shape this view of mine occurred way back in 2005, though its message has continued to echo in the present.</p>
<p>The day was January 14. The occasion was a conference on “Diversifying the Science &amp; Engineering Workforce” at the Cambridge, MA facility of the private, nonprofit National Bureau of Economic Research. The speaker was Harvard’s President, Lawrence Summers. The audience consisted of a few dozen, almost entirely female S&amp;E faculty from Harvard and other universities. University administrators such as Summers, then as now, were under pressure from feminist academics and feminist-friendly media to even up the male/female ratio in science and engineering, the presumption being that a persistent deviance from 50:50 was due to unlawful discrimination.</p>
<p>Summers, a prize-winning economist and former Treasury Secretary, was considered a sharp-witted man. He was also the head of a major university, and as such would have known how to soothe feminist faculty with the usual aspirational cant. Instead, he decided on this day that he would basically speak the truth as he saw it. January 14, 2005 was the occasion of an unusual midwinter warm spell in the Boston area, with a high temperature of 63. It was the sort of pleasant climatic surprise that is apt to make a man unduly optimistic. A week later, Boston would be paralyzed by a winter storm—and Summers, a condemned heretic, would be on his way out of Harvard.</p>
<p>What did Summers say? Below is a representative selection from the ~7,000-word total. Craftwise his speech strikes me as unduly verbose, and it contains too many, obviously futile, attempts to appease the hypersensitive feminists before him. But it otherwise seems well reasoned and unobjectionable, and even thoughtful and useful, which is the point of this story: The women who had power over Summers—women who represent the revolutionary new regime in Western culture and politics—signaled on that day that they would never be satisfied with “mansplanations,” however logical, that contradict their dogmas.</p>
<p style="padding-left: 30px;">[emphases mine]</p>
<p style="padding-left: 30px;">I asked Richard, when he invited me to come here and speak, whether he wanted an institutional talk about Harvard’s policies toward diversity or whether he wanted some questions asked and some attempts at provocation, because I was willing to do the second and didn’t feel like doing the first. And so we have agreed that I am speaking unofficially and not using this as an occasion to lay out the many things we’re doing at Harvard to promote the crucial objective of diversity.</p>
<p style="padding-left: 30px;">I am going to, until most of the way through, attempt to adopt an entirely <em>positive, rather than normative approach [i.e., describing things as they are, not how they should be]</em>, and just try to think about and <em>offer some hypotheses as to why we observe what we observe</em> without seeing this through the kind of judgmental tendency that inevitably is connected with all our common goals of equality. It is after all not the case that the role of women in science is the only example of a group that is significantly underrepresented in an important activity and whose underrepresentation contributes to a shortage of role models for others who are considering being in that group. To take a set of diverse examples, the data will, I am confident, reveal that <em>Catholics are substantially underrepresented in investment banking, which is an enormously high-paying profession in our society; that white men are very substantially underrepresented in the National Basketball Association; and that Jews are very substantially underrepresented in farming and in agriculture.</em> These are all phenomena in which one observes underrepresentation, and <em>I think it’s important to try to think systematically and clinically about the reasons for underrepresentation.</em></p>
<p style="padding-left: 30px;">There are three broad hypotheses about the sources of the very substantial disparities that this conference’s papers document and have been documented before with respect to the presence of women in high-end scientific professions. <em>One is what I would call the—I’ll explain each of these in a few moments and comment on how important I think they are—the first is what I call the high-powered job hypothesis. The second is what I would call different availability of aptitude at the high end, and the third is what I would call different socialization and patterns of discrimination in a search.</em> And in my own view, their importance probably ranks in exactly the order that I just described.</p>
<p style="padding-left: 30px;">[#1: high-powered job hypothesis]</p>
<p style="padding-left: 30px;">I’ve had the opportunity to discuss questions like this with chief executive officers at major corporations, the managing partners of large law firms, the directors of prominent teaching hospitals, and with the leaders of other prominent professional service organizations, as well as with colleagues in higher education. In all of those groups, the story is fundamentally the same.</p>
<p style="padding-left: 30px;">… <em>the relatively few women who are in the highest ranking places are disproportionately either unmarried or without children</em>…</p>
<p style="padding-left: 30px;">… it is a fact about our society that <em>[high-powered jobs involve] a level of commitment that a much higher fraction of married men have been historically prepared to make than of married women</em>. That’s not a judgment about how it should be, not a judgment about what they should expect. But it seems to me that <em>it is very hard to look at the data and escape the conclusion</em> that that expectation is meeting with the choices that people make and is contributing substantially to the outcomes that we observe.</p>
<p style="padding-left: 30px;">…So I think in terms of positive understanding, the first very important reality is just what I would call the, who wants to do high-powered intense work?</p>
<p style="padding-left: 30px;">[#2: aptitude hypothesis]</p>
<p style="padding-left: 30px;">It does appear that <em>on many, many different human attributes</em>—height, weight, propensity for criminality, overall IQ, mathematical ability, scientific ability—there is relatively clear evidence that <em>whatever the difference in means</em>—which can be debated—<em>there is a difference in the standard deviation and variability of a male and a female population</em>. And that is true with respect to attributes that are and are not plausibly, culturally determined.</p>
<p style="padding-left: 30px;">If one supposes, as I think is reasonable, that if one is talking about physicists at a top twenty-five research university, one is …<em> talking about people who are three and a half, four standard deviations above the mean in the one in 5,000, one in 10,000 class.</em></p>
<p style="padding-left: 30px;"><em>Even small differences in the standard deviation will translate into very large differences in the available pool substantially out [i.e., at the highest-aptitude end of the long tail]</em>… I looked at … the evidence on the sex ratios in the top 5 percent of twelfth graders. If you look at those—they’re all over the map, depends on which test, whether it’s math, or science, and so forth—but … one woman for every two men would be a high-end estimate from their estimates. From that, you can back out a difference in the implied standard deviations that works out to be about 20 percent. And from that, you can work out the difference out several standard deviations. If you do that calculation—and I have no reason to think that it couldn’t be refined in a hundred ways—<em>you get five to one, at the high end</em>. <em>[i.e., aptitude is so much more variable in men that, e.g., the very-high-aptitude pool of male physicists may be several times larger than the very-high-aptitude pool of female physicists].</em></p>
<p style="padding-left: 30px;">So my sense is that the unfortunate truth—I would far prefer to believe something else, because it would be easier to address what is surely a serious social problem if something else were true—is that <em>the combination of the high-powered job hypothesis and the differing variances probably explains a fair amount of this problem.</em></p>
<p style="padding-left: 30px;">[#3: differential socialization and innate preferences—mostly the latter]</p>
<p style="padding-left: 30px;">[P]articularly <em>in some attributes that bear on engineering, there is reasonably strong evidence of taste differences between little girls and little boys that are not easy to attribute to socialization</em>. I just returned from Israel, where we had the opportunity to visit a kibbutz, and to spend some time talking about the history of the kibbutz movement, and it is really very striking to hear how the movement started with an absolute commitment, of a kind one doesn’t encounter in other places, that everybody was going to do the same jobs. <em>Sometimes the women were going to fix the tractors, and the men were going to work in the nurseries, sometimes the men were going to fix the tractors and the women were going to work in the nurseries, and just under the pressure of what everyone wanted, in a hundred different kibbutzes, each one of which evolved, it all moved in the same direction [i.e., towards males fixing tractors, women working in nurseries]</em>. So, I think, while I would prefer to believe otherwise, I guess my experience with my two and a half year old twin daughters who were not given dolls and who were given trucks, and found themselves saying to each other, look, daddy truck is carrying the baby truck, tells me something. And I think it’s just something that you probably have to recognize.</p>
<p style="padding-left: 30px;">One [hypothesis for this] is socialization. Somehow little girls are all socialized towards nursing and little boys are socialized towards building bridges. No doubt there is some truth in that<em>. I would be hesitant about assigning too much weight to that hypothesis</em> for two reasons. First, most of what we’ve learned from empirical psychology in the last fifteen years has been that people naturally attribute things to socialization that are in fact not attributable to socialization. We’ve been astounded by the results of separated twins studies. The confident assertions that autism was a reflection of parental characteristics that were absolutely supported and that people knew from years of observational evidence have now been proven to be wrong. And so<em>, the human mind has a tendency to grab to the socialization hypothesis when you can see it, and it often turns out not to be true.</em></p>
<p>Summers finished up by noting that discrimination against women in STEM faculty hiring is an unlikely explanation for the present discrepancy, underscoring the likelihood that his own alternative explanations are valid.</p>
<p style="padding-left: 30px;">[T]here are certainly examples of institutions that have focused on increasing their diversity to their substantial benefit, but <em>if there was really a pervasive pattern of discrimination that was leaving an extraordinary number of high-quality potential candidates behind, one suspects that in the highly competitive academic marketplace, there would be more examples of institutions that succeeded substantially by working to fill the gap. And I think one sees relatively little evidence of that.</em> So <em>my best guess, to provoke you, of what’s behind all of this is that the largest phenomenon, by far, is the general clash between people’s legitimate family desires and employers’ current desire for high power and high intensity, that in the special case of science and engineering, there are issues of intrinsic aptitude [the two fatal words, I suspect], and particularly of the variability of aptitude, and that those considerations are reinforced by what are in fact lesser factors involving socialization and continuing discrimination</em>. I would like nothing better than to be proved wrong, because I would like nothing better than for these problems to be addressable simply by everybody understanding what they are, and working very hard to address them.</p>
<p>Audience members questioned him for a while after that. Almost all were polite. None put a dent in the points he had made. Some were childishly long-winded and seemed to miss his points entirely—almost as if, in some unconscious way, they wanted to buttress his suggestion about “intrinsic aptitude” with clear examples of female illogic and mental confusion. Donna Nelson, a chemistry professor from the University of Oklahoma, responded to Summers’ passing mention of twin studies and their revelations about trait heritability by declaring: “One thing that I do sort of disagree with is the use of identical twins that have been separated and their environment followed. I think that the environments that a lot of women and minorities experience would not be something that would be—that a twin would be subjected to if the person knows that their environment is being watched. Because a lot of the things that are done to women and minorities are simply illegal, and so they’ll never experience that.”</p>
<p>But the only strong hint of ruffled feathers came at the end, when Denice Denton, chancellor of UC-Santa Cruz, stood up and said, with some emotion: “You know, in the spirit of speaking truth to power, I’m not an expert in this area but a lot of people in the room are, and they’ve written a lot of papers … and you know a lot of us would disagree with your hypotheses and your premises.” Acting as if Summers had been aggressively asserting truths rather than cautiously elaborating hypotheses, she complained “so it’s not so clear.”</p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><img loading="lazy" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-14" src="https://thoughtsofstone.com/wp-content/uploads/2020/07/denton.jpg" alt="" width="319" height="242" srcset="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2020/07/denton.jpg 319w, https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2020/07/denton-300x228.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 319px) 85vw, 319px" /></p>
<p>(Denton committed suicide a year and a half later by jumping off the roof of her girlfriend’s SF apartment building. According to <a href="https://www.sfgate.com/news/article/UC-Santa-Cruz-chancellor-jumps-to-her-death-in-2517073.php">SFGate</a>, the chancellor, trained as an engineer, “had been named this spring in a series of articles examining UC management compensation. She had been criticized for an expensive [$600K] university-funded renovation on her campus home, and for obtaining a UC administrative job” for her girlfriend.)</p>
<p>A few other women at the conference were upset by Summers’s references to “intrinsic aptitude.” Whether a reporter was present I don’t know, but somehow <em>Boston Globe</em> reporter Marcella Bombardieri, who would later quit journalism to become a paid activist pushing <a href="https://www.americanprogress.org/issues/education-postsecondary/news/2019/04/03/465193/equity-audits-tool-campus-improvement/">progressive, feminist issues</a> in academia, felt this disturbance in the feminist force and ran a story two days later on the 17th.</p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><img loading="lazy" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-10" src="https://thoughtsofstone.com/wp-content/uploads/2020/07/bombard.jpg" alt="" width="270" height="298" /></p>
<p>Bombardieri’s story, headlined “Summers&#8217; remarks on women draw fire,” recast the speech not as the wordy and sedate event it was, but as riotous act of heresy that had traumatized sensitive listeners.</p>
<p style="padding-left: 30px;">The president of Harvard University, Lawrence H. Summers, sparked an uproar at an academic conference Friday when he said that innate differences between men and women might be one reason fewer women succeed in science and math careers. Summers also questioned how much of a role discrimination plays in the dearth of female professors in science and engineering at elite universities.</p>
<p style="padding-left: 30px;">Nancy Hopkins, a biologist at Massachusetts Institute of Technology, walked out on Summers&#8217; talk, saying later that if she hadn&#8217;t left, &#8221;I would&#8217;ve either blacked out or thrown up.&#8221; Five other participants reached by the Globe, including Denice D. Denton, chancellor designate of the University of California, Santa Cruz, also said they were deeply offended, while four other attendees said they were not.</p>
<p>Note the histrionics of Nancy Hopkins, a woman so overwhelmed with indignation that she went right ahead and reinforced all those old stereotypes about women and their preference for drama over reason. Note too Bombardieri’s last sentence, which a careless reader might take as evidence that <em>a majority of attendees</em> were “deeply offended.”</p>
<p>Naturally, other MSM organs picked up this story and amplified it. Denton and Hopkins now had their national megaphone.</p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><img loading="lazy" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-22" src="https://thoughtsofstone.com/wp-content/uploads/2020/07/hopkins.jpg" alt="" width="463" height="328" srcset="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2020/07/hopkins.jpg 463w, https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2020/07/hopkins-300x213.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 463px) 85vw, 463px" /></p>
<p>The NYT on Jan 18:</p>
<p style="text-align: center;">HARVARD CHIEF DEFENDS HIS TALK ON WOMEN</p>
<p style="padding-left: 30px;">The president of Harvard University, Lawrence H. Summers, who offended some women at an academic conference last week by suggesting that innate differences in sex may explain why fewer women succeed in science and math careers, stood by his comments yesterday but said he regretted if they were misunderstood.</p>
<p style="padding-left: 30px;">&#8220;I&#8217;m sorry for any misunderstanding but believe that raising questions, discussing multiple factors that may explain a difficult problem, and seeking to understand how they interrelate is vitally important,&#8221; Dr. Summers said in an interview.</p>
<p style="padding-left: 30px;">Several women who participated in the conference said yesterday that they had been surprised or outraged by Dr. Summers&#8217;s comments, and Denice D. Denton, the chancellor designate of the University of California, Santa Cruz, questioned Dr. Summers sharply during the conference, saying she needed to &#8220;speak truth to power.&#8221;</p>
<p style="padding-left: 30px;">Nancy Hopkins, a professor of biology at the Massachusetts Institute of Technology who once led an investigation of sex discrimination there that led to changes in hiring and promotion, walked out midway through Dr. Summers&#8217;s remarks.</p>
<p style="padding-left: 30px;">&#8220;When he started talking about innate differences in aptitude between men and women, <em>I just couldn&#8217;t breathe</em> because this kind of bias makes me <em>physically ill</em>,&#8221; Dr. Hopkins said. &#8220;Let&#8217;s not forget that people used to say that women couldn&#8217;t drive an automobile.&#8221;</p>
<p>Buried in the NYT’s piece was this interesting fact [emphases mine]:</p>
<p style="padding-left: 30px;">Dr. Summers arrived after a morning session and addressed a working lunch, speaking without notes. No transcript was made because <em>the conference was designed to be off-the-record so that participants could speak candidly without fear of public misunderstanding or disclosure later.</em></p>
<p>Presumably Denton and Hopkins, who with Bombardieri were the ring-leaders of this hysteria, would say that an off-the-record rule such as that is merely a “Man’s Rule,” designed to protect the patriarchy and keep women down—and thus can be flouted by feminists without fear of reproach!</p>
<p>But they didn’t merely flout this rule: They turned it against Summers, exploiting the apparent lack of a transcript by dramatically misrepresenting his speech as a misogynist rant. Their complaints of psychosomatic injury (“I just couldn’t breathe”) were presented as <em>prima facie</em> evidence that they were the traumatized victims of a serious thoughtcrime.</p>
<p>Many women and men had listened to Summers’s talk, or had heard of his arguments second-hand, and had perceived nothing objectionable. Ultimately it would turn out that an official recording <em>had</em> been made. A transcript of that recording emerged, and it indicated that by traditional, commonsense standards, Summers had neither made false, “hurtful” assertions nor even had been guilty of mild insensitivity. To the contrary, the man had spoken sensibly and sensitively—even oversensitively. My own impression is that he had come to the gathering with the view that his audience of feminist academics included some bad apples who were childish and emotionally unstable and might easily fly into a temper. He simply had underestimated how irrational and unstable they were! And as the hysteria blew up, it was clear that Summers’s feminist antagonists were the ones making unsupported assertions. <em>They</em> and not he were the dogmatists who wanted to quash all opposing ideas.</p>
<p>Bombardieri, for her January 17 <a href="http://archive.boston.com/news/education/higher/articles/2005/01/17/summers_remarks_on_women_draw_fire/">piece</a> in the Globe, tried to mute any sense of pushback from defenders of Summers, but clearly had gotten an earful from the organizer of the NBER conference, Harvard economist Richard Freeman:</p>
<p style="padding-left: 30px;">Freeman … described Summers’s critics as activists whose sensibilities might be at odds with intellectual debate.</p>
<p>Exactly! And <a href="https://scholar.harvard.edu/freeman/home">Freeman</a>, who these days probably feels much less free to express such sentiments, defended Summers to the <em>Guardian</em> for their Jan 18 <a href="https://www.theguardian.com/science/2005/jan/18/educationsgendergap.genderissues">piece</a> on the controversy:</p>
<p style="padding-left: 30px;">Richard Freeman, who invited the Harvard president to speak at the conference, said Dr. Summers&#8217;s comments were intended to provoke debate, and some women over-reacted.</p>
<p style="padding-left: 30px;">&#8220;Some people took offence because they were very sensitive,&#8221; said Dr Freeman, an economist at Harvard and the London School of Economics. &#8220;It does not seem to me insane to think that men and women have biological differences.&#8221;</p>
<p>Freeman’s defense of Summers was followed by others’, including that of Hannah Gray, a distinguished member of the Harvard governing body, the Harvard Corporation. Conference participant Paula Stephan, a professor of economics at Georgia State University, also defended Summers, telling the NYT that his “remarks offended some participants, but not her. ‘I think if you come to participate in a research conference,’ Dr. Stephan said, ‘you should expect speakers to present hypotheses that you may not agree with and then discuss them on the basis of research findings.’”</p>
<p>Then there was Harvard colleague Steven Pinker’s reasoned <a href="https://newrepublic.com/article/68044/sex-ed">defense</a> of Summers in <em>The New Republic</em>.</p>
<p style="padding-left: 30px;">Summers did not, of course, say that women are &#8220;natively inferior,&#8221; that &#8220;they just can&#8217;t cut it,&#8221; that they suffer &#8220;an inherent cognitive deficit in the sciences,&#8221; or that men have &#8220;a monopoly on basic math ability,&#8221; as many academics and journalists assumed. Only a madman could believe such things. Summers&#8217;s analysis of why there might be fewer women in mathematics and science is commonplace among economists who study gender disparities in employment….</p>
<p style="padding-left: 30px;">The analysis should have been unexceptionable. Anyone who has fled a cluster of men at a party debating the fine points of flat-screen televisions can appreciate that fewer women than men might choose engineering, even in the absence of arbitrary barriers. (As one female social scientist noted in Science Magazine, &#8220;Reinventing the curriculum will not make me more interested in learning how my dishwasher works.&#8221;) To what degree these and other differences originate in biology must be determined by research, not fatwa. History tells us that how much we want to believe a proposition is not a reliable guide as to whether it is true.</p>
<p>A <a href="https://www.theatlantic.com/magazine/archive/2005/02/why-feminist-careerists-neutered-larry-summers/303795/">defender</a> of Summers in <em>The Atlantic</em> even went so far as to attack his antagonists: “The hysteria about Summers furthers the career agendas of feminists who seek quotas for themselves and their friends.”</p>
<p>But as Larry Summers’s defenders, and Summers himself, must have suspected, reasoning like this was just pissing in the wind. The typhoon of hysteria, deliberately fed by the media and an email-enabled campaign among feminist academics, continued to strengthen. The NYT followed its initial story on Jan 18 with another one the next day, headlined “NO BREAK IN THE STORM OVER HARVARD PRESIDENT’S WORDS.”</p>
<p style="padding-left: 30px;">Members of a Harvard faculty committee that has examined the recruiting of professors who are women sent a protest letter yesterday to Lawrence H. Summers, the university&#8217;s president, saying his recent statements about innate differences between the sexes would only make it harder to attract top candidates.</p>
<p style="padding-left: 30px;">The committee told Mr. Summers that his remarks did not &#8220;serve our institution well.&#8221;</p>
<p style="padding-left: 30px;">&#8220;Indeed,&#8221; the letter said, &#8220;they serve to reinforce an institutional culture at Harvard that erects numerous barriers to improving the representation of women on the faculty, and to impede our current efforts to recruit top women scholars. They also send at best mixed signals to our high-achieving women students in Harvard College and in the graduate and professional schools.&#8221;</p>
<p style="padding-left: 30px;">The letter was one part of an outcry that continued to follow remarks Mr. Summers made Friday suggesting that biological differences between the sexes may be one explanation for why fewer women succeed in mathematic and science careers.</p>
<p style="padding-left: 30px;">…</p>
<p style="padding-left: 30px;">Denice D. Denton, the dean of engineering at the University of Washington who confronted Mr. Summers over his remarks at the conference, said that her phone had not stopped ringing and that she had received scores of e-mail messages on the subject. She said Mr. Summers&#8217;s remarks might have put new energy into a longstanding effort to improve the status of women in the sciences.</p>
<p style="padding-left: 30px;">&#8220;I think they&#8217;ve provoked an intellectual tsunami,&#8221; Dr. Denton said.</p>
<p><em>Emotional</em> tsunami would have been more accurate—but anyway Summers felt the full force of it. He had been a high flier for most of his life; while still in his 30s he had won the prestigious John Bates Clark Medal for his economics research, in his 40s he had been Secretary of the Treasury during the Clinton Administration. Surely other important positions awaited him. But now at the hands of Puritanical feminists he faced the modern equivalent of the stake or the gallows: vilification from every progressive pulpit across the land, followed by professional and social ostracism.</p>
<p>And so, he did what so many victims of witch-hunts, Inquisitions, and ideological purges had done before him: He caved. He confessed his heresy and begged forgiveness. As the NYT <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2005/01/20/education/harvard-president-apologizes-again-for-remarks-on-gender.html">reported</a> on day 4 of the hysteria, Jan 20 [emphases mine]:</p>
<p style="text-align: center;">HARVARD PRESIDENT APOLOGIZES AGAIN FOR REMARKS ON GENDER</p>
<p style="padding-left: 30px;">With the unabated furor over his recent remarks suggesting that women may not have the same innate abilities in math and science as men, Harvard&#8217;s president, Lawrence H. Summers, issued a two-page apology to the Harvard community late last night.</p>
<p style="padding-left: 30px;"><em>&#8220;I was wrong to have spoken in a way that has resulted in an unintended signal of discouragement to talented girls and women,&#8221; Mr. Summers said in a letter that was posted on his Harvard Web site.</em></p>
<p style="padding-left: 30px;">&#8220;Despite reports to the contrary, I did not say, and I do not believe, that girls are intellectually less able than boys, or that women lack the ability to succeed at the highest levels of science,&#8221; Mr. Summers wrote.</p>
<p style="padding-left: 30px;"><em>It was his third public statement in three days about his remarks at a conference on women and minorities in science and engineering last Friday, with each statement becoming stronger and more apologetic.</em> His remarks have dominated the discussion on the Harvard campus and beyond, with female academics, alumni and donors expressing concern over his leadership.</p>
<p style="padding-left: 30px;">Mr. Summers, an economist and a former treasury secretary, acknowledged that he had been hearing plenty of reaction himself. &#8220;I have learned a great deal from all that I have heard in the last few days,&#8221; he wrote in his statement. &#8220;The many compelling e-mails and calls that I have received have made vivid the very real barriers faced by women in pursuing scientific and other academic careers.&#8221;</p>
<p style="padding-left: 30px;">He wrote in the letter that he had attended the conference, held by the National Bureau of Economics, &#8220;with the intention of reinforcing my strong commitment to the advancement of women in science, and offering some informal observations on possibly fruitful avenues for further research.&#8221;</p>
<p style="padding-left: 30px;">However, he added: &#8220;Ensuing media reports on my remarks appear to have had quite the opposite effect. <em>I deeply regret the impact of my comments and apologize for not having weighed them more carefully.</em>&#8220;</p>
<p>It was abject. It was shameful. It was a surrender to the forces of unreason—to the hysterical mob that had already done so much to distort both science and the hiring of scientists. Despite this crawling penitence, or perhaps because of it, Summers lost his job as Harvard President. In March, a majority of the Faculty of Arts and Sciences, including female faculty, of course, but also male faculty fearful of the same whirlwind that had consumed their leader, approved a resolution of “no confidence” in Summers. The NYT <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2005/03/16/education/professors-in-close-vote-censure-harvard-leader.html">reported</a> among things that:</p>
<p style="padding-left: 30px;">J. Lorand Matory, a professor of anthropology and African and African-American studies, told reporters after the meeting that Dr. Summers should step down. &#8220;There is no noble alternative for him but resignation,&#8221; said Professor Matory, who introduced the resolution….</p>
<p style="padding-left: 30px;">Dr. Summers, an economist and a former United States Treasury secretary, has been meeting individually with faculty members throughout the Faculty of Arts and Sciences over the last several weeks, apologizing for his remarks about women and for any other offense he might have given and asking for their support so he could move forward.</p>
<p>Although the resolution was only symbolic, and Summers in the ensuing months continued to try to placate and soothe his antagonists, it eventually became clear that his position was unrecoverable. On February 22, just about 13 months after his fateful utterance of the words “intrinsic aptitude,” the New York Times <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2006/02/22/education/22harvard.html">reported</a>:</p>
<p style="text-align: center;">PRESIDENT OF HARVARD RESIGNS, ENDING STORMY 5-YEAR TENURE</p>
<p style="padding-left: 30px;">Lawrence H. Summers resigned yesterday as president of Harvard University after a relatively brief and turbulent tenure of five years, nudged by Harvard&#8217;s governing corporation and facing a vote of no confidence from the influential Faculty of Arts and Sciences….</p>
<p style="padding-left: 30px;">… advisers and confidants of Dr. Summers said he privately concluded a week ago that he should step down, after members of Harvard&#8217;s governing corporation and friends—particularly from the Clinton administration—made it clear that his presidency was lost.</p>
<p>No one should have shed any tears for Summers. He was offered a university professorship at Harvard, joined a hedge fund, and within a few years became a high-profile economic adviser at the Obama White House. As embarrassing and degrading as it all was, his public confessions and repentance, his surrender to the New Inquisition, apparently were effective in forestalling his full banishment. At the end of the day Summers retained his wealth, his high status, and his potential for moderately high public office.</p>
<p>American civil society, on the other hand, didn’t fare so well. Summers’s high-profile moral cowardice emboldened the unreasoning feminism he had faced, and within another decade Harvard and most universities across the land were quasi-totalitarian in their insistence on conformity with feminist ideology. The same conformity spread as well through the mainstream media and entertainment industries, and even into the executive layers of big corporations. Opponents would use labels like “Progressivism” or “Cultural Marxism” to describe this mindset. But such descriptions seemed incomplete somehow, for this brand of Leftism wasn’t simply a different set of policy prescriptions. It also involved a different attitude towards ways of thinking and behaving that seemed fundamental to Western societies. Such as debating with reason and logic.</p>
<p>Women, not universally but on average compared to men, appear to have less affinity for the verbal swordplay of reasoned argument. Polls and surveys routinely show them to be less supportive of free speech and debate. An obvious hypothesis would be that women are not as comfortable with debating because they are, compared to men, more emotionally sensitive—less able to discourse dispassionately about things that affect them. That emotional sensitivity in turn would appear to be an adaptation for child-bearing and child-rearing, which have been women’s primary responsibilities for 99.99999% of human/primate existence. A woman in maternal mode, particularly when the life or health of her child is at stake, would also have more use for a dictatorial bearing (“because I said so!”) than an open-to-reason approach. In recent decades, as women have been moving out of the home and into public life, becoming journalists and politicians and scientists and other influencers of policy, they have been—<a href="http://www.absltzero.com/the-great-feminization/">I submit</a>—bringing this maternal mindset with them.</p>
<p>The Summers episode arguably highlights an even more important dimension of the female mindset. Women as compared to men appear to have a strong ability to transmit their anger and anxiety to other women or to “catch” it from other women, thus forming what one might call emotional coalitions or outbreaks. That trait-set would seem to follow from the fact that women are relatively emotionally sensitive, and it’s easy to see that in certain circumstances, it could be a powerful weapon with which to oppose male hegemony or otherwise allow women collectively to get their way. That susceptibility to emotional contagion, and the matching propensity for emotionally acting-out, would also explain why women (and girls) have been the chief propagators of hysterias throughout history, from Salem to the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Loudun_possessions">Devils of Loudoun</a> to the defenestration of Larry Summers. A touch of genuine insight and not mere misogyny may therefore have been what led the ancients to link such behavior with the possession of a womb (ὑστέρα – hystera).</p>
<p>But what of men? Why do we, the “stronger” sex, routinely lose to the “weaker” sex in these conflicts? Why have women found it so easy, in recent decades, to achieve ascendancy over us in the most advanced human societies? Here I can only wade more deeply into speculation and suggest that we the males of our species have evolved a set of instinctive but largely passive, placatory strategies for dealing with outbreaks of female hysteria—strategies to which we still automatically resort even though they no longer work well. Consider for example how men cope with a very old form of hysteria: the female-dominated “spirit-possession” syndrome that persists in one form or another in many traditional, patriarchal societies, and is often organized in &#8220;possession cults.&#8221; A woman playing this role typically will adopt the voice/personality of an authoritative male “spirit,” and will use its authority to demand gifts or some other concession from her husband. In principle, a husband in this situation could organize with other husbands, disband the cult, deliver exemplary punishment to his wife, etc. In practice—perhaps because millennia of experience have established this as the better way—he tends to accede to the “spirit’s” demands, or tries to work out some compromise. Similarly, hysterias in developed countries, such as the epidemic of Multiple Personality Disorder and its variants in the 1980s and early 90s, have tended to fade out, often from their own absurdity, and have almost never been successfully and abruptly quashed by direct, organized male opposition. A large part of the explanation, in both cases, is that the women at the cores of these hysterias are quite good at co-opting influential men, making it hard for men to unite against them.</p>
<p>Thus it may be that women through their greater ability to form emotional/hysterical coalitions in pursuit of a goal have much more power over men than meets the eye, and correspondingly have much less interest in, or susceptibility to, traditional male tools of persuasion such as reasoned argument. Moreover, it may be that men such as Larry Summers who encounter this primordial feminine power, and retreat before it, are not just behaving “rationally” but are also unconsciously acting out an ancient appeasement reflex. If so, I suspect this appeasement reflex no longer works for men, collectively and in the long run, because in modern societies the traditional limits on female power no longer exist: Now every surrender to that power increases it.</p>
<p><span style="color: #ff0000;"><em>published 23 Aug 2019</em></span></p>
<p style="text-align: center;">* *</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>THE GREAT FEMINIZATION</title>
		<link>https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/the-great-feminization/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[j stone]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 06 Mar 2019 22:48:58 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[freedom of speech]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[immigration]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[women]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://thoughtsofstone.com/?p=38</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Forget #TheFutureIsFemale—women have already remodeled the Western world &#160; Feminists these days spend a lot of time worrying about male-dominated culture—“patriarchal culture,” “sexual harassment culture,” “rape culture,” “the culture of silence,” and so on. But shouldn’t they be acknowledging the influence that women now have on culture: on workplace culture, on media culture, on campus &#8230; <a href="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/the-great-feminization/" class="more-link">Continue reading<span class="screen-reader-text"> "THE GREAT FEMINIZATION"</span></a>]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>Forget <em>#TheFutureIsFemale</em>—women have already remodeled the Western world</p>



<p><span id="more-38"></span></p>



<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>Feminists these days spend a lot of time worrying about male-dominated culture—“patriarchal culture,” “sexual harassment culture,” “rape culture,” “the culture of silence,” and so on. But shouldn’t they be acknowledging the influence that <em>women</em> now have on culture: on workplace culture, on media culture, on campus culture, on American culture, and on Western culture generally? That feminizing influence may be the greatest single driver of the rapid social changes seen in recent decades.</p>



<p>Consider the following U.S. Bureau of Labor Statistics chart of women’s civilian labor force participation rate.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" class="size-large wp-image-19 aligncenter" src="https://thoughtsofstone.com/wp-content/uploads/2020/07/fredgraph-women-1024x412.jpg" alt="women's labor participation rate" width="840" height="338" srcset="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2020/07/fredgraph-women-1024x412.jpg 1024w, https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2020/07/fredgraph-women-300x121.jpg 300w, https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2020/07/fredgraph-women-768x309.jpg 768w, https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2020/07/fredgraph-women.jpg 1168w" sizes="(max-width: 709px) 85vw, (max-width: 909px) 67vw, (max-width: 1362px) 62vw, 840px" /></p>



<figure class="wp-block-image"></figure>



<p>It shows that in 1950 only about 30 percent of working-age women were in the workforce, but by 2000 that figure had jumped to 60 percent and rivaled the participation rate for men, which had been in decline since the early 1950s. In other words, by 2000 the U.S. workforce had been mostly gender-integrated. On average, workplaces by then had almost as many women as men.</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" class="size-large wp-image-18 aligncenter" src="https://thoughtsofstone.com/wp-content/uploads/2020/07/fredgraph-men-1024x412.jpg" alt="" width="840" height="338" srcset="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2020/07/fredgraph-men-1024x412.jpg 1024w, https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2020/07/fredgraph-men-300x121.jpg 300w, https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2020/07/fredgraph-men-768x309.jpg 768w, https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2020/07/fredgraph-men.jpg 1168w" sizes="(max-width: 709px) 85vw, (max-width: 909px) 67vw, (max-width: 1362px) 62vw, 840px" /></p>



<figure class="wp-block-image"></figure>



<p>The historic significance of this migration on its own appears to have been underappreciated. Women never made such a move, to such a degree, in any large human society in the past. It significantly altered the structure of ordinary life.</p>
<p>But women in the late 20<sup>th</sup> century didn’t just move into the workforce. They moved into its upper ranks, to professions that strongly influence societal culture and policy. They became journalists, public relations specialists, lawyers, academics, novelists, publishers, filmmakers, TV producers, and politicians, all to an unprecedented extent. In some of these culture-making professions, by the 1990s and early 2000s, they had achieved parity or even <a href="https://www.usatoday.com/story/money/careers/employment-trends/2018/08/08/20-jobs-that-have-become-dominated-by-women/37330779/">dominance</a> (e.g., writers, authors, and public relations specialists) with respect to men. Even where they fell short of full parity, they appeared to acquire considerable “veto” power over content. A 2017 <a href="https://www.womensmediacenter.com/reports/the-status-of-women-in-u.s.-media-2017">report</a> by the Women’s Media Center noted evidence that at the vast majority of media companies, at least one woman is among the top three editors.</p>
<p>Why is the greater presence of women in culture-making professions important? Because women, on average, think differently than men on a wide range of subjects. That psychological differentness is well <a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/articles/201711/the-truth-about-sex-differences">established</a> from experiments, and is reflected in the well-known “<a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/the-2018-gender-gap-was-huge/">gender gap</a>” in voting and policy choices—a gap that is even larger when considering women who are maritally independent of men, i.e., <a href="https://prospect.org/article/untapped-voting-power-single-women">single women</a>, one of the fastest-growing demographics in the country.</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" class="size-medium wp-image-12 aligncenter" src="https://thoughtsofstone.com/wp-content/uploads/2020/07/coulter-twitr-300x85.jpg" alt="" width="300" height="85" srcset="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2020/07/coulter-twitr-300x85.jpg 300w, https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2020/07/coulter-twitr.jpg 578w" sizes="(max-width: 300px) 85vw, 300px" /></p>
<p>If one accepts that culture is a strong determinant of behavior, which it is really by definition, it follows that putting a high proportion of women into senior roles in culture-making professions, basically for the first time ever, will have changed the culture and therefore changed how people on average tend to think and act. It won’t have changed everyone absolutely; we are not blank slates. But it will have moved the collective needle—shifted the so-called Overton Window of publicly acceptable opinion, and shifted average behavior as well, even average male behavior. That is, in fact, the underlying logic of organizations like the Women’s Media Center, which have explicitly sought to alter, to <em>feminize</em>, the content of mass media and the resulting attitudes of the public by putting more women into newsrooms.</p>
<p>How would culture and policy have changed as a result of women’s new influence? Presumably in ways that reflect feminine psychological traits.</p>
<p>For example, women appear on average to be more <a href="https://www.sciencedaily.com/releases/2018/11/181112191650.htm">empathetic </a>and compassionate, more <a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/sexual-personalities/201504/are-women-more-emotional-men">emotionally sensitive</a><strong>.</strong> Some of the most striking social changes of the last few decades appear to have been driven by a cultural shift in that direction:</p>
<ul>
<li>More generous welfare programs</li>
<li>Expansion of the concept of welfare to include more types of intervention (affirmative action, etc.) and more groups needing intervention</li>
<li>Expansion of the definitions of “harm,” “offense,” and “trauma” (“microaggressions,” “triggers”)</li>
<li>Increased attention to psychological trauma in law and medicine, leading to a greater acceptance, and thus a higher prevalence, of trauma-related syndromes such as PTSD (and the recovered-trauma-memory syndromes of the 1990s)</li>
<li>Less tolerance of deaths in war; but, ironically, a greater inclination to enter foreign conflicts in response to emotion-evoking atrocities portrayed on television</li>
</ul>



<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="aligncenter"><img loading="lazy" class="size-full wp-image-11 aligncenter" src="https://thoughtsofstone.com/wp-content/uploads/2020/07/boy1.jpg" alt="" width="194" height="259" /></figure>
</div>



<ul>
<li>Less tolerance for <a href="https://www.aclu.org/blog/capital-punishment/innocence-and-death-penalty/death-penalty-2018-punishment-decline">capital punishment</a></li>
<li>Less restrictive <a href="https://qz.com/900416/most-immigration-lawyers-are-women-and-they-are-helping-stranded-immigrants-and-refugees-at-us-airports/">immigration policy</a></li>
<li>More emphasis in media and policy contexts on emotion-evoking stories of individuals (e.g., pitiable <a href="https://www.independent.co.uk/news/world/americas/us-politics/aoc-crying-ice-akelin-caal-maquin-alexandria-ocasio-cortez-protest-tears-washington-dc-a8768831.html">refugee children</a>) rather than dry analyses of long-term outcomes</li>
</ul>



<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="aligncenter"><img loading="lazy" class="size-full wp-image-17 aligncenter" src="https://thoughtsofstone.com/wp-content/uploads/2020/07/family1.jpg" alt="" width="300" height="169" /><br />
<ul>
<li>Suppression of any kind of emotionally disturbing speech (“hate speech,” “mansplaining,” etc.) and even <a href="https://www.journals.uchicago.edu/doi/abs/10.1086/687863">fields of scientific inquiry</a> that are likely to evoke negative emotions;</li>
<li>Less affinity for traditional, constitutionally protected forms of confrontation in the legal and political spheres, i.e., <a href="https://longreads.com/2018/09/18/no-i-will-not-debate-you/">less support for open debate</a>, <a href="https://www.nas.org/articles/from_suffrage_to_suppressing_speech_the_increasing_hostility_of_women_towar">free-speech rights</a>, and “<a href="https://www.theatlantic.com/ideas/archive/2018/10/sexual-assault-has-become-partisan-issue/572893/">due process of law</a>.”</li>
<li>Suppression/replacement of <em>words</em> that evoke emotional discomfort (e.g., “abortion clinic” becomes “women’s health center”)</li>
</ul>
<p>That’s just from one set of closely related traits. Certainly there are others. For example, women for obvious evolutionary reasons appear to have an instinctive fear of dietary and environmental toxins, which can become pronounced during pregnancy (“morning sickness,” nesting reflex, food aversions). Is it just coincidence that women’s cultural ascendancy in Western countries corresponds to a huge rise in diet-, drug-, and environment-related concerns encompassing the Green movement, anti-GMO attitudes, “detox” fads, the “herbal medicine” racket, “organic foods” preferences, and even the <a href="https://www.fatherly.com/health-science/jenny-mccarthy-masked-singer-measles-outbreak-anti-vaxxer/">anti-vaccine</a> movement?</p>
<p>Then there is the issue of systematizing. Experiments by psychologists and everyday observations by parents, etc. suggest that whereas the average “male” brain is <a href="https://www.theguardian.com/education/2003/apr/17/research.highereducation">adapted for understanding and building systems</a>, the average “female” brain is . . . not so much adapted for that. A cultural shift away from traditional “male,” systematizing thinking across society could again explain many specific social changes. One is the great, still-ongoing migration from traditional religions with their managerial hierarchies and highly systematized theologies to new, more loosely structured and personalized spiritual groups, such as Evangelical Christian groups, New Age movements, and neo-pagan groups (e.g., Wicca) which give prominent roles to women. Another plausible reflection of this de-systematizing tendency is the long-term <a href="https://www.worldexpertise.com/Declining_Interest_in_Engineering_Studies_at_a_Time_of_Increased_Business_Needs.htm">decline</a> of interest in engineering among U.S.-born students, who are now <a href="https://www.insidehighered.com/quicktakes/2017/10/11/foreign-students-and-graduate-stem-enrollment">outnumbered</a> by foreign students at U.S. engineering grad schools.</p>
<p>One of the most obvious sex-related differences in human behavior concerns aggression and violence. Women on average are far less violent than men, and consequently make up only about <a href="https://www.bop.gov/about/statistics/statistics_inmate_gender.jsp">7 percent</a> of the U.S. prison population. If women have had an unprecedented feminizing effect on the “public mind” in recent decades, in principle that would have reduced the propensity for aggression and violence even among men. Indeed there has been a <a href="http://www.pewresearch.org/fact-tank/2019/01/03/5-facts-about-crime-in-the-u-s/">striking downward trend in violent crime rates</a> in the U.S. in recent decades—a trend that would be even stronger if all the violent crimes committed by people born and raised in traditional, patriarchal societies, e.g., Mexico, were excluded.</p>
<p>How could men have been feminized to this extent? By having less <a href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/3575604/">testosterone</a>, for example. The ways in which sex hormones rise and fall in response to <a href="https://www.google.com/url?sa=t&amp;rct=j&amp;q=&amp;esrc=s&amp;source=web&amp;cd=4&amp;cad=rja&amp;uact=8&amp;ved=2ahUKEwiR7sXh1IrhAhXIsFQKHemIAM8QFjADegQIBxAB&amp;url=https%3A%2F%2Fonlinelibrary.wiley.com%2Fdoi%2Fpdf%2F10.1002%2Ftre.372&amp;usg=AOvVaw1zWHTeHK_iPcC4nNAIvBCJ">social cues</a> is an <a href="https://www.cell.com/trends/cognitive-sciences/fulltext/S1364-6613(11)00078-7">under-studied area</a>, but two trends stand out alarmingly: Age-adjusted testosterone levels in men <a href="http://thechart.blogs.cnn.com/2011/08/18/modern-life-rough-on-men/">have been falling</a> in Western countries in recent decades, and—as one would expect from that—<a href="https://www.vox.com/science-and-health/2018/9/17/17841518/low-sperm-count-semen-male-fertility">sperm counts have been falling too</a>. Interestingly, those sperm-count studies suggest that whatever is causing the trend in Western societies has been having less effect, or no effect at all, in traditional, i.e., patriarchal societies.</p>
<p>Why is it “alarming” that male testosterone levels and sperm counts have been dropping in Western countries, if one result is less violent crime? Because that’s not the only result. Declining testosterone also means declining fertility and probably also a declining motivation to marry and raise a family. Here again the statistics are consistent with the idea of a Great Feminization. The U.S. in recent decades has seen not only a <a href="http://www.pewresearch.org/fact-tank/2017/09/14/as-u-s-marriage-rate-hovers-at-50-education-gap-in-marital-status-widens/">decline in the marriage rate</a>, but also a <a href="https://www.npr.org/sections/thetwo-way/2018/05/17/611898421/u-s-births-falls-to-30-year-low-sending-fertility-rate-to-a-record-low">collapse of the birth rate</a> for U.S.-born women, to levels below what demographers consider necessary to maintain the population. The &#8220;U.S. population&#8221; now grows chiefly because of open-door immigration and births to immigrant mothers.</p>
<p>Am I crazy to link female emancipation and near-equality in the workforce to all these bad results, including population collapse? Well, no—I’m only putting forward a hypothesis, and one that seems well grounded in the data. Obviously many factors contributed to the social changes that have swept across the West in the past half century or so. But that women were one of those factors seems undeniable. And the possibility that they were, and continue to be, the <em>dominant</em> factor seems worth discussing, not least because of the potential implications for the future. Yet . . . there has been no discussion. I’ve been circulating this idea for years now, in one forum and another, and it gets no traction at all. It isn’t shot down by some fact or logical disproof; it’s just ignored or dismissed without reason. No “respectable” publication will touch it. I can’t help wondering if that response is yet another reflection of women’s new cultural power.</p>
<p><span style="color: #ff0000;">published <em>6 Mar 2019</em></span></p>
</figure>
<p style="text-align: center;">**</p>
<figure class="aligncenter">
<p><em>Postscript (3/25/19): Apparently a similar theory, blaming the West&#8217;s fertility decline on feminism, has been <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2019/03/18/technology/replacement-theory.html">kicking around in &#8220;far-right&#8221; circles</a>. That probably helps explain why doors have tended to shut in my face whenever I&#8217;ve tried (over the past 7+ years) to get a version of this essay published&#8211;and I&#8217;ve been reduced to publishing pseudonymously in <a href="https://www.returnofkings.com/42976/thanks-to-progressivism-america-is-no-country-for-men">fringe publications</a> or on <a href="https://james-the-obscure.github.io/the-demise-of-guythink/">d-i-y websites</a>. In case it&#8217;s not already clear, my &#8220;great feminization&#8221; idea is mainly about cultural feminization, doesn&#8217;t have anything directly to do with the formal &#8220;feminist&#8221; movement, and doesn&#8217;t require any dire prediction about population decline/replacement. Also, though it should be <a href="https://rationalwiki.org/wiki/Genetic_fallacy">irrelevant</a>, I&#8217;m not some woman-hating incel; I&#8217;m happily married, etc. My interest in the topic of sex differences in culture and policy attitudes developed from the fact that I, a male, work in a profession that is increasingly female-dominated.<br /></em></p>
</figure>
</div>














]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
