<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>wokeism &#8211; Thoughts of Stone</title>
	<atom:link href="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/category/wokeism/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/</link>
	<description>short essays, usually about humans</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Sat, 01 Jan 2022 22:26:38 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=5.7.4</generator>

<image>
	<url>https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2020/07/cropped-icon-32x32.jpg</url>
	<title>wokeism &#8211; Thoughts of Stone</title>
	<link>https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/</link>
	<width>32</width>
	<height>32</height>
</image> 
	<item>
		<title>SMASH THE FOUR OLDS!</title>
		<link>https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/smash-the-four-olds/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[j stone]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 31 Dec 2021 20:30:59 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[ethnicity]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[fall of the West]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[freedom of speech]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[immigration]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[USA]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[wokeism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[women]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/?p=362</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Four roots of American degeneracy &#160; Americans who watch with dismay the erasure of various symbols of their history and traditions—statues of Robert E. Lee, Theodore Roosevelt, etc.—might take comfort from certain facts about the Chinese Cultural Revolution, which occurred during 1966-76. The CCR was similar in character but vastly greater in its extremism than &#8230; <a href="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/smash-the-four-olds/" class="more-link">Continue reading<span class="screen-reader-text"> "SMASH THE FOUR OLDS!"</span></a>]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><em>Four roots of American degeneracy</em></p>
<p><span id="more-362"></span></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>Americans who watch with dismay the erasure of various symbols of their history and traditions—statues of Robert E. Lee, Theodore Roosevelt, etc.—might take comfort from certain facts about the Chinese Cultural Revolution, which occurred during 1966-76.</p>
<p>The CCR was similar in character but vastly greater in its extremism than what America has been experiencing at the hands of its wokeist mobs. The CCR’s spearpoints were cadres of “Red Guard” fanatics, young people (even teens) whose instability and restlessness, suggestibility, and high susceptibility to fanaticism were probably comparable to what one finds in today’s Antifa brigades.</p>
<p>These howling Maoist minions sought the erasure of whatever competed with Maoism, which in practice meant just about anything predating Maoist China—history books, art, architecture, temples, even genealogical records. Red Guards and their camp followers toppled statues of Confucius, pasted huge banners with their slogans everywhere, and went around attacking intellectuals or anyone even lightly connected to the teaching of pre-Maoist history or philosophy.</p>
<p>There was a strong irrational element in all this—indeed, the CCR was reminiscent of the orgiastic, throw-out-all-inhibitions themes in the old feasts of pagan Europe. It suggests, ironically, that the mostly simple, agrarian Chinese had been chafing under the saddle of Maoist collectivism and needed some release—even if that release served Maoist purposes. There was not only a lot of physical harassment and assault of ordinary people going about their business—there was murder and even cannibalism.</p>
<p style="padding-left: 40px;">At some high schools, students killed their principals in the school courtyard and then cooked and ate the bodies to celebrate a triumph over &#8220;counterrevolutionaries&#8221; . . .  Government-run cafeterias are said to have displayed bodies dangling on meat hooks and to have served human flesh to employees. [<a href="https://www.nytimes.com/1993/01/06/world/a-tale-of-red-guards-and-cannibals.html">NYT</a>]</p>
<p>Not content with attacking living reminders of the old China, Red Guards also broke into cemeteries and dug up the skeletal remains of ancient Chinese emperors and nobles, desecrating them and denouncing the persons these remains had once been.</p>
<p>Amid this hysterical savagery, the Chinese government closed schools and universities, sending tens of millions of urban students, including those who hoped to be scientists and engineers, to do hard labor on collective farms in the countryside. Overall, for as long as its radicalism prevailed, the CCR created a mini Dark Age in China.</p>
<p>So one simple lesson from this is that, however badly Americans think they have suffered under the Great Awokening, it could have been much, much worse.</p>
<p>Another, arguably more important point is that the CCR didn’t last forever. It was so extreme that, like many mass hysteria-type episodes, it became just absurd, dying of its own absurdity—and I guess for many of those caught up in its fervor, it was an emotional storm that ultimately blew over. The CCR also effectively immunized many Chinese, both ordinary and elite, against ideological excesses—which in turn helped pave the way for the liberalization and wealth explosion that occurred in China in the decades that followed.</p>
<p><strong>The Four Olds</strong></p>
<p>There are obvious differences between the dynamics of the CCR on the one hand, and those of the Great Awokening on the other. The Awokening has been less centralized, for example, and has had a weaker connection to government. Moreover, although the Awokening may draw some of its strength from reliably impressionable young people, it also—unlike the CCR, which occurred in a less feminized society—seems particularly well rooted among managerial-class (“elite”) women, whose <a href="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/the-critical-mass-problem/">affinity for wokeness</a> may be much more durable.</p>
<p>Still, the Awokening’s most feverish period of statue-toppling, city-burning, and curriculum-rewriting (“math is racist”) seems to have ended. The supporting regime has failed to entrench itself with new laws, and there are many signs of popular opposition. In short, the Awokening in the United States is running out of steam, and may face reversal even in many states where it has been running rampant.</p>
<p>It therefore makes sense to start thinking about how best to empower and sustain this reversal. In other words, in the long term, in America and presumably other affected countries, how can wokeism be cured and its recurrence suppressed?</p>
<p>My suggestion is to follow an example set by the Red Guards themselves—not an example of their savagery, of course, but of their simplicity of messaging.</p>
<p>One of the CCR’s most enduring slogans was “Smash the Four Olds!” the “Four Olds” being the “customs, cultures, habits, and ideas” of pre-Maoist China. The Chinese, maybe for simple mnemonic reasons, have a thing for <a href="https://apnews.com/article/c1ebc231b1c9c857d64e95581e2eb881">numbered lists</a> in their public slogans—certainly Mao did—and so this particular slogan was crafted accordingly (though they might have said simply “Down With Pre-Maoist Culture”). The Awokening, on the other hand, and I would say American degeneracy in general, really does have distinct conceptual roots, the elimination of which may be a necessary condition for long-term societal health.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><strong>#1        “Diversity is Our Strength”</strong></p>
<p>This idea, a contagious pathogen to which Western societies seem peculiarly prone, may have originated in the “we’re all God’s children” universalism of Christianity—a universalism originally fashioned by St. Paul et al for the multi-ethnic world temporarily united under imperial Rome. The march of technology and science has since weakened other elements of Christianity, but the diversity-worshipping element has been continually stimulated to grow in Western societies, far beyond its original religious context, by the irritant of white-black conflict in the United States, and by flows of non-Western immigrants to Western democracies amid the globalization of trade and labor and declines in Western birthrates. That’s a simplification of what has happened, but not a very wrong one, I think.</p>
<p>Although I’m making a list here, not an extended argument, I think there is ample evidence (including from my own <a href="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/seed-of-destruction/">life experience</a> as an expatriate) that societies with ethnic supermajorities, i.e., some diversity but not much, are not only typical and traditional but also are greatly preferable to societies with high ethnic diversity.</p>
<p>Shared ethnicity is a far more potent source of sociopolitical affinity compared to the thin set of abstract values (“respect for the rule of law!”) that supposedly binds people in multi-ethnic societies. Thus, in multi-ethnic societies, we would expect political factions to form largely along ethnic lines, leading ultimately to ethnic-based conflict or at least a serious divergence of interests. In Western multi-ethnic societies, that divergence of interests already features not only sticks and bricks and guns, but also factionally crafted laws and dogmatic falsehoods designed to harm one side or another.</p>
<p>Mass immigration from ethnically and culturally distant places harms a society in other ways too, involving issues of economics, social trust, and identity. But the fact that it sets up inter-ethnic conflict is already a sufficient reason to put it in the dustbin of history.</p>
<p>Disparate peoples can commingle and ultimately become one people—that is one of the fundamental themes of world history. But the sorry results of Western experiments with multi-ethnicism suggest that this commingling works much better when done at a slower, more natural pace.</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-364" src="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2022/01/ethiopes.jpg" alt="" width="1120" height="682" srcset="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2022/01/ethiopes.jpg 1120w, https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2022/01/ethiopes-300x183.jpg 300w, https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2022/01/ethiopes-1024x624.jpg 1024w, https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2022/01/ethiopes-768x468.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 709px) 85vw, (max-width: 909px) 67vw, (max-width: 1362px) 62vw, 840px" /></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><strong>#2        “The Future is Female”</strong></p>
<p>As I’ve suggested in several <a href="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/cultural-feminization-a-bibliography/">essays</a> over the past decade, women for plausible evo-psych reasons tend to approach issues of culture and policy differently than men do, and thus their ascension to cultural and political power in the USA and other Western countries in recent decades has been accompanied by dramatic cultural and political changes.</p>
<p>I have proposed (good summaries are <a href="https://americanmind.org/salvo/pink-shift/">here</a> and <a href="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/we-need-to-talk-about-women/">here</a>) that the trait that acts as the chief driver of these changes is women’s greater emotional sensitivity, and that this greater sensitivity, now unleashed in the public sphere—presumably having been adapted by evolution for motherhood and home life—is leading to a host of bad outcomes. These bad outcomes include a retreat from traditional Western liberalism (free speech, free scientific inquiry, due process of law), an unthinking embrace of the “diversity is our strength” fallacy, and a generally enhanced proneness to social contagions.</p>
<p>Essentially women, now that they have power, have been remodeling Western civilization to suit their ways of thinking, without fully appreciating what they are doing, let alone acknowledging that they might&#8212;on average compared to men&#8212;have significant shortcomings in this capacity. This problem is exacerbated by the fact that women&#8217;s new cultural/political power, and their apparently greater ability to <a href="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/girl-power/">cohere against perceived enemies</a>—to cancel them or worse—makes the subject of women&#8217;s potential shortcomings unmentionable in mainstream discourse.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><strong>#3        “Governance is Gibs”</strong></p>
<p>Partly as a ratchet-effect holdover of major economic crises (e.g., the Great Depression), partly because politicians in democracies are constantly tempted to buy votes (in effect), and partly because of the feminization (see #2 above) of the elites that shape culture and policy, the provision of “welfare” in one form or another is now the major focus of modern government in the US and other Western countries.</p>
<p>Probably most Americans now don’t even think to question this historic shift. Yet it should be clear that this modern Hyper-Welfarism has inherent inefficiencies and long-term adverse effects, and thus usually worsens the problems it was meant to ameliorate. Its powerful enabling of the centrifugal forces threatening the African American family—resulting in skyrocketing rates of out-of-wedlock births—is one of its most cited adverse effects. But really it weakens individuals and groups across society: by creating dependencies; by taking away traditional disincentives to antisocial behaviors; by vastly increasing the burden on taxpayers; and by displacing (e.g., in the healthcare economy) more local or market-based organizations and forces that would have produced better solutions.</p>
<p>Worst of all, the overwhelming government emphasis on welfare provision gives elites&#8212;wokeified elites in the US&#8217;s case&#8212;enormous power to manipulate society by lavishing rewards on their factional friends and withholding them from their enemies.</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" class="size-full wp-image-381 aligncenter" src="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/bidendiscrim.jpg" alt="" width="600" height="437" srcset="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/bidendiscrim.jpg 600w, https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/bidendiscrim-300x219.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 709px) 85vw, (max-width: 909px) 67vw, (max-width: 984px) 61vw, (max-width: 1362px) 45vw, 600px" /></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><strong>#4        “We’re the Best Because We’re a Democracy”</strong></p>
<p>It became weirdly fashionable at the start of the Great Awokening, when American cities were burning and the stability of the World’s Top Democracy was in question, to exclaim that . . . <a href="https://www.jstor.org/stable/24027184">Fukuyama</a> was right all along! Democracy <em>is</em> the end-stage of political history! These riots and lootings represent only a bumpy patch! Fukuyama specifically warned that there would be bumpy patches!</p>
<p>Maybe it’s just my own bias at work, but I also had the impression that this desperate optimism about democracy went . . . very quiet . . . a few months later, after the US election with its orgies of ballot harvesting and other irregularities, and the follow-on push by the new, woke administration 1) to rejig election laws to enable ballot harvesting forever; and 2) to open the southern border to pack the electorate in their favor.</p>
<p>In any case, it should be obvious that on the subject of democracy these days, someone like <a href="https://www.unqualified-reservations.org/2007/07/democracy-as-adaptive-fiction/">Curtis Yarvin</a> is more relevant than Fukuyama.</p>
<p>My point here is that the USA since its founding has gone from a cautious and relatively rational approach to the problem of political structure to an unthinking worship of &#8220;democracy&#8221;&#8212;a worship that is not merely irrational but also actively <em>harms</em> Americans and their society, mainly by concealing the antidemocratic power of the country&#8217;s out-of-control (and again, wokeified) elites.</p>
<p>The term &#8220;democracy&#8221; as used these days is apt to be misleading. No one really has a democracy in the pure sense. Virtually any government, from monarchical dictatorship to a theoretical rule-by-referendum, involves a certain (at least <em>de facto</em>) allocation of power to the ruling elites, on the one hand, and to “the people” on the other. There may be different factions among the elites, and among the people, and of course different styles of government&#8212;suited for different populations&#8212;which will vary in how they balance elite power and people power. But no large country has ever lacked a political and cultural elite.</p>
<p>Yet democracy-worship in America has encouraged the false belief that one can do without an elite, or even that elites don’t exist in the country anymore. In other words, instead of acknowledging elites, limiting their powers, and inculcating in them a certain level of responsibility toward the people (once called <em>noblesse oblige</em>), the American cultural and political system&#8212;led by elites themselves&#8212;effectively has encouraged elites to believe that they are not elites, and have no special responsibilities. This seems to be a crucial weak point in the American (and more generally Western) political order, and I think it has contributed to the  dissolution of Western societies in many ways, including via the mass immigration that elites embrace, at everyone else&#8217;s cost, because (they think) it benefits themselves.</p>
<p>In short, then, a successful political system probably requires at least some acknowledgment, if not protection, of its elite class, combined with measures to limit elites&#8217; power and curb their selfishness&#8211;above all, to protect ordinary people and their basic way of life from whatever stupid ideology happens to possess elites at a given time. Whether one calls the resulting system a “democracy,” “republic,” “oligarchy” etc. is, <em>per se</em>, less important. And again, from this perspective, formulations such as “democracy is the best” or “we&#8217;re the best because we&#8217;re a democracy” are not merely nonsensical; they are also toxic.</p>
<p style="text-align: center;">***</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>CULTURAL FEMINIZATION: A BIBLIOGRAPHY</title>
		<link>https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/cultural-feminization-a-bibliography/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[j stone]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 14 Dec 2021 06:29:13 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[wokeism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[women]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/?page_id=347</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[An incomplete list, but maybe useful. The idea that women, on average compared to men, think differently, behave differently, and vote differently, is not a new one. What I think has some originality, though—certainly it seems to have been too hot, as recently as a few months ago, for any MSM or MSM-adjacent editor to &#8230; <a href="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/cultural-feminization-a-bibliography/" class="more-link">Continue reading<span class="screen-reader-text"> "CULTURAL FEMINIZATION: A BIBLIOGRAPHY"</span></a>]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><em>An incomplete list, but maybe useful.</em></p>
<p><span id="more-347"></span></p>
<p>The idea that women, on average compared to men, think differently, behave differently, and vote differently, is not a new one. What I think has some originality, though—certainly it seems to have been too hot, as recently as a few months ago, for any MSM or MSM-adjacent editor to handle—is the idea that women, especially by entering culturally influential professions <em>en masse</em> since the 1960s, have transformed Western societies: pulling them leftward and introducing political correctness, etc., but more precisely <em>feminizing</em> them, with arguably dire implications for Western civilization.</p>
<p>In case it’s useful to others writing in this area (and because like most creative people I crave credit), I’ve listed some of my relevant works in this area—and all the ones I’m now aware of from other writers.</p>
<p><strong>From me</strong></p>
<p>2011    “<a href="https://james-the-obscure.github.io/the-demise-of-guythink/">The Demise of Guythink</a>”</p>
<p>An old blog post, and my first and probably briefest expression of the cultural feminization hypothesis. Inspired by something controversial Jeremy Clarkson said, and also by the Larry Summers controversy which I would later write about in more detail.</p>
<p>2014    “<a href="https://james-the-obscure.github.io/motherland/">Motherland</a>”</p>
<p>Also an old blog post but a much longer, more discursive account of the hypothesis. Most of the pieces I’ve written since then have been, for the most part, compressed versions of the ideas expressed here.</p>
<p>2014    “<a href="https://www.returnofkings.com/42976/thanks-to-progressivism-america-is-no-country-for-men">No Country for Men</a>” (<em>Return of Kings</em>)</p>
<p>I got this published on Roosh V’s <em>Return of Kings</em> website (under a pseudonym I no longer use).</p>
<p><a id="set-post-thumbnail" class="thickbox" href="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-admin/media-upload.php?post_id=347&amp;type=image&amp;TB_iframe=1"></a>2017    “[different titles]”</p>
<p>A personal blog post—extremely mild version of the cult-fem theory—I eventually took down because it started costing me professionally.</p>
<p>2019    “<a href="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/the-great-feminization/">The Great Feminization</a>”</p>
<p>Essay on a new website, not using my real name—a relatively brief version of the cult-fem theory, with a bit at the end about testosterone levels and fertility that is probably somewhat relevant, though not really central to the theory. I started the website and placed the essay on it because I had offered a version of the piece to two or three conservative webzines, with no luck.</p>
<p>(Tyler Cowen linked to this essay in his Marginal Revolution blog two and a half years later, prompting a flood of readers.)</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" class="size-full wp-image-348 aligncenter" src="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/cowen.jpg" alt="" width="660" height="435" srcset="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/cowen.jpg 660w, https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/cowen-300x198.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 709px) 85vw, (max-width: 909px) 67vw, (max-width: 984px) 61vw, (max-width: 1362px) 45vw, 600px" /></p>
<p>2019    “<a href="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/the-day-the-logic-died/">The Day the Logic Died</a>”</p>
<p>A fuller account of the 2005 Larry Summers “intrinsic aptitude” controversy/hysteria, with some cult-fem theory. <span style="text-decoration: underline;">If you read just one of my essays, make it this one</span>. A favorable reference to this in a tweet from @toad_spotted, some weeks after it was posted, induced many thousands of people to read it—and the “Great Feminization” piece&#8212;and encouraged me to keep writing.</p>
<p>2020    “<a href="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/girl-power/">Girl Power</a>”</p>
<p>Some cult-fem theory here, touching on women’s greater ability to form networks/coalitions, especially to cancel (or prosecute) men. Mainly, though, this was an examination of #MeToo-type cases against the historical background of hysterias including medieval/early-modern convent hysterias, Salem, modern recovered-memory case epidemics, etc.</p>
<p>2021    “<a href="https://americanmind.org/salvo/pink-shift/">Pink Shift</a>” (<em>The American Mind</em>)</p>
<p>Short piece summarizing the theory&#8212;thanks again to James Poulos &amp; Co. for publishing it.</p>
<p>2021    “<a href="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/the-critical-mass-problem/">The Critical Mass Problem</a>”</p>
<p>More on the apparently superior female ability to form networks and transmit social contagions, as a general source of political/social instability. “The Great Awokening’s transformation of big institutions reflects not only the general fear of personal cancellation within these institutions but also the ‘critical mass’ of susceptible women who work in them.”</p>
<p>2021    “<a href="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/we-need-to-talk-about-women/">We Need to Talk about Women</a>”</p>
<p>Re-emphasis of the key points, including the likely long-term adverse effects of cultural feminization on liberal Western societies.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><strong>Other writers</strong></p>
<p>My initial online searches using keywords like “feminization” were curiously uninformative (a lot of stuff on trans medical issues), but after Tyler Cowen linked to my “Great Feminization” essay two months ago, I started digging again. I’m sure this is still a very incomplete list.</p>
<p>Note that Cowen himself has <a href="https://www.bloomberg.com/opinion/articles/2021-09-19/woke-movement-is-global-and-america-should-be-mostly-proud">written</a> about feminization in occasional columns and blog posts, going back at least a few years.</p>
<p>1985    <a href="https://www.amazon.com/Feminization-America-Womens-Changing-Private/dp/B000R3AQ4A"><em>The Feminization of America</em></a> (Elinor Lenz &amp; Barbara Myerhoff)</p>
<p>The authors “envision the emergence of a new `feminized’ America, a society made more human, less destructive, and more compassionate by women&#8217;s nurturing and integrative influences in all walks of life.”</p>
<p>1987    “<a href="https://www.commentary.org/articles/james-nuechterlein/the-feminization-of-the-american-left/">The Feminization of the American Left</a>” (James Neuchterlein, <em>Commentary</em>)</p>
<p>Contrasts modern leftism with the more masculine leftism of yore. “Feminization, as understood here, suggests the establishment of traditionally feminine virtues (those normally associated with the private realm) as norms of behavior for public life. It indicates an ethic of noncoercion, a preference for emotion over rational analysis and for noncompetitive modes of social interaction, a focus on being rather than doing and on interpersonal relations as the primary preoccupation of the good life.”</p>
<p>1998    <em><a href="https://www.amazon.com/Feminization-American-Culture-Ann-Douglas/dp/0374525587">The Feminization of American Culture</a></em> (Ann Douglas)</p>
<p>Not as relevant as its title suggests. Douglas argues that in the late 19<sup>th</sup> century American literature became “feminized” with “books that idealized the very qualities that kept [women] powerless: timidity, piety, and a disdain for competition.”</p>
<p>2006?  “<a href="https://www.seattleweekly.com/news/when-did-we-all-become-women/">When Did We All Become Women?</a>” (Kathryn Robinson, <em>Seattle Weekly</em>)</p>
<p>“Think of values like nurturing and caring, emotion and sentimentality, connection and community, passivity and submission, vanity and appearance, cooperation and equality, openness and access, manipulation and influence. These are the values on the ascendancy in our public and private lives.” Robinson covers the ground pretty well, and projects the same sense of awe that I had when I started to perceive the significance of this unprecedented cultural development. (Her piece may have been buried in the search rankings until <a href="https://marginalrevolution.com/marginalrevolution/2021/08/when-did-we-all-become-women.html">Cowen linked to it</a> a few months ago. Also, the 2006 date attached to the article may have been the date of uploading to the web, not the original magazine publication date.)</p>
<p style="text-align: center;">***</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>WE NEED TO TALK ABOUT WOMEN</title>
		<link>https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/we-need-to-talk-about-women/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[j stone]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 13 Dec 2021 10:20:02 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[fall of the West]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[immigration]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[USA]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[wokeism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[women]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/?p=331</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Once more unto the breach, dear friends. I’ve written about women and their cultural/political ascendancy so much in recent years, especially the last three, that I worry about sounding like the proverbial broken record if I write any more. But it seems to me that as this idea is accepted more widely—including by commentators who &#8230; <a href="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/we-need-to-talk-about-women/" class="more-link">Continue reading<span class="screen-reader-text"> "WE NEED TO TALK ABOUT WOMEN"</span></a>]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><em>Once more unto the breach, dear friends.</em></p>
<p><span id="more-331"></span></p>
<p>I’ve written about women and their cultural/political ascendancy so much in recent years, especially the last three, that I worry about sounding like the proverbial broken record if I write any more. But it seems to me that as this idea is accepted more widely—including by commentators who see it as their own idea . . .</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" class="size-full wp-image-340 aligncenter" src="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/harrington.jpg" alt="" width="536" height="385" srcset="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/harrington.jpg 536w, https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/harrington-300x215.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 536px) 85vw, 536px" /></p>
<p>. . . there is a tendency to narrow the focus (e.g., “female graduates,” “HR ladies,” or “women explain wokeness”) so that the true extent of the West’s feminization is obscured.</p>
<p>Moreover, the case can be made that feminization is having not only an enormous but also a potentially fatal impact on Western civilization as we have known it. Thus, thumping the tub about this subject may be a good and necessary thing to do now.</p>
<p>To that end, I think at least several key points within this overall hypothesis bear repeating:</p>
<p><strong>Women’s broad cultural/political ascendancy has been reshaping the West for decades</strong></p>
<p>The big idea here is that women have been the principal drivers not only of the creeping wokeism post 2015 or so, and of the ongoing semi-spiritual movement known as the Great Awokening, but also of the general “leftward” (<a href="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/the-day-the-logic-died/">in fact, “feminine”</a>) trends in Western culture and politics over the last six-plus decades. This is the period in which women moved <em>en masse</em> into, and achieved parity or dominance within, culturally and politically influential professions such as journalism, publishing, entertainment, law, academia, politics, even blogging.</p>
<p>It is not just from one or two of those professions but from all of them, and in every circumstance along the way (e.g., university life, engagement with social media, office politics, voting, protest marches), that women have been causing cultural and political change, effectively feminizing the West to a degree never seen before in any large civilization.</p>
<p>Activist women—mostly single, university-educated, and/or young—may be the “shock troops” of feminization, and the most dedicated and effective practitioners of wokeism and cancel culture. But women <em>in general</em> have been driving this social transformation.</p>
<p><strong>Women’s ascension to cultural and political power has had cultural and political consequences because women on average are different than men across a wide range of attitudes and behaviors</strong></p>
<p>Gender differences in attitudes and behaviors were presumably shaped—at a biological level with changes that cannot easily be undone—by men’s and women’s distinct roles during the long period of hominid evolution, roles that for women centered on maternity. Women even now in modern times appear to be markedly more emotionally sensitive than men on average, quicker to form social networks, less interested in abstract and inanimate things, less interested in systems, more personal (including <em>ad hominem</em>) in their thinking, and more fearful—not just of ideas and people they dislike but also of toxins and other putative environmental threats. All these differences have had cultural and policy consequences as women’s power has increased in societies designed and traditionally run by men. One could say that women effectively have been using their new cultural and political power to renovate and redecorate their civilization according to their distinctive tastes. As Virginia Woolf put it in her 1938 essay, “Three Guineas”:</p>
<p style="padding-left: 40px;">Let us never cease from thinking—what is this “civilization” in which we find ourselves?</p>
<p><strong>Cultural/political feminization therefore involves a multitude of changes</strong></p>
<p>Cultural and political changes that have plausibly been driven by the ascendancy of women in Western societies are not limited to the extreme changes associated with “wokeism.” They include also relatively mild and gradual, long-term trends:</p>
<ul>
<li style="list-style-type: none;">
<ul>
<li>more extensive and generous welfare programs;</li>
<li>more rights, often including reverse-discrimination-type rights, for “traditionally disadvantaged” or otherwise marginalized groups (blacks, Hispanics, nonwhite immigrants, women, gays, transsexuals, etc.);</li>
<li>more emphasis generally in culture and policy on “equality of outcomes” over “equal opportunity,” and on guilt and compassion (vs. dispassionate, long-term calculation) as drivers of policy and social change;</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<p><img loading="lazy" class="size-full wp-image-332 aligncenter" src="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/mo.jpg" alt="" width="300" height="168" /></p>
<ul>
<li style="list-style-type: none;">
<ul>
<li>more emphasis on “trauma”—emotional upset—everywhere from journalism to law and medicine, with a related emergence of trauma-memory (PTSD) or otherwise trauma-related syndromes that are strongly contagious and now highly prevalent;</li>
<li>less affinity for traditional, often Constitutionally protected forms of (emotionally painful) confrontation such as free speech and free debate, free scientific inquiry, and due process of law (e.g., the right to face one’s accuser, and the right to cross-examine)—and increasing affinity for systems that suppress and punish “unacceptable” speech;</li>
<li>the acceptance of what amount to special rules for women when they are complainants against men in sex-related court cases, e.g., they can bring cases decades after the alleged crime, and when they claim to have been abused by men they later dated or exchanged love-notes with, their claims are still taken seriously—are simply chalked up to their presumed trauma;</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<p><img loading="lazy" class="wp-image-333 aligncenter" src="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/weinstein1.jpg" alt="" width="391" height="298" srcset="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/weinstein1.jpg 680w, https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/weinstein1-300x228.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 391px) 85vw, 391px" /></p>
<ul>
<li style="list-style-type: none;">
<ul>
<li>the intrusion of distinctively feminine values into the traditionally male-dominated world of sports, such that, for example, athletes putting their “self-care” instincts over their competitive instincts are not derided but celebrated;</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<p><img loading="lazy" class="wp-image-334 aligncenter" src="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/biles.jpg" alt="" width="317" height="418" srcset="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/biles.jpg 414w, https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/biles-227x300.jpg 227w" sizes="(max-width: 317px) 85vw, 317px" /></p>
<ul>
<li style="list-style-type: none;">
<ul>
<li>the alteration of language, including the elimination of upsetting terms and invention of new ones (“safe space”), to reflect the reigning new feminine mindset;</li>
<li>the routine, rapid formation of social <a href="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/the-day-the-logic-died/">networks</a> to exert pressure on corporations or other institutions to “cancel” someone who has fallen afoul of feminist/woke orthodoxies;</li>
<li>strong environmentalism and related advocacies and preferences (anti-vaccine, anti-GMO, anti-nuclear, climate-change alarmism, veganism, “organic” foods and medicines, etc.), stemming plausibly from women’s relatively strong sensitivity to the idea of environmental harms including toxins;</li>
<li>Shifts towards less systematized/hierarchical and rule-based religious forms, from paganism to evangelical/charismatic Christianity.</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>Cultural/political feminization, far from being “progress,” is probably destroying Western liberalism&#8212;the liberalism that emancipated women in the first place<br />
</strong></p>
<p>Yes, men on average have their own ways of thinking and acting—their own stubborn, long-evolved biases. And yes, the traditional male mindset is not necessarily optimized for running human societies in the 21<sup>st</sup> century. But there is an obvious reason why the male mindset, compared to the female mindset, is probably better adapted for managing culture and politics: Men have been managing culture and politics, and getting punished in the harshest ways for failure, for hundreds of millennia. Women, by contrast, have been working on a large scale in public life for not even two generations—and still seem inclined to blame men when things go wrong.</p>
<p>On the flip side of that argument is another obvious point: Women’s mindset is not simply unadapted or insufficiently adapted by evolution for managing public affairs; it is adapted specifically for <em>other</em> tasks, mainly domestic tasks revolving around the bearing and raising of children. In other words, women’s higher emotional sensitivity (compassion, guilt, fear, anxiety/turmoil); their relative indifference to machines and systems and cold, abstract thought; their stronger fear of toxins; their greater tendency to think un-independently and <a href="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/the-critical-mass-problem/">transmit social contagions</a>, etc. are in a fundamental sense <em>out of place</em> in the culture- and policy-making spheres.</p>
<p>I’m not suggesting that women’s traits are totally separate from men’s in this regard—for virtually any trait there would be two highly overlapping distributions, so that there would be lots and lots of women further towards the “male” end of the distribution compared to the average male.</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" class="wp-image-12 aligncenter" src="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2020/07/coulter-twitr.jpg" alt="" width="349" height="99" srcset="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2020/07/coulter-twitr.jpg 578w, https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2020/07/coulter-twitr-300x85.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 349px) 85vw, 349px" /></p>
<p>But there clearly are differences between the means of those distributions, between the <em>average</em> male and the <em>average</em> female in other words; and the central idea here is that those differences, on a population level, are not only meaningful but potentially cataclysmic in their civilizational impact.</p>
<p>That impact is evident not only in the broad cultural and policy shifts since the early 1960s&#8212;the “<a href="https://americanmind.org/salvo/pink-shift/">pink shift</a>” as I have called it&#8212;but in the more recent and extreme policy changes in places where cultural and political feminization is most advanced: “defund the police,” “let violent criminals out on bail,” “open the borders / diversity is our strength,” “let homeless people camp and crap wherever they like,” “give addicts needles,” “math is racist,” “logic is sexist,” etc. Not all of these policies are wildly popular, and obviously specific groups of hardcore activists are to blame for some of them, but I don’t see how these changes, collectively, could have taken root to the extent they have except against a heavily feminized cultural background—they are essentially <em>ad absurdum</em> expressions of the feminine mindset applied to policy.</p>
<p>I don&#8217;t think that every manifestation of feminization will be harmful in the long run. But some will. The move away from free speech towards speech- and thought-policing seems pretty ominous. Even worse, I suspect, is the encouragement of mass non-Western immigration to Western countries. One does not have to “hate” non-Western immigrants to understand that they and the culture they bring with them are . . . non-Western . . . so that the more there are of them, the less Western their host countries become. The women who encourage mass non-Western immigration seem surprisingly indifferent to the fact that non-Western cultures generally are less liberal, and a lot less friendly to the idea of female power, compared to Western cultures even from a few decades ago.</p>
<p>Can liberal Western societies nevertheless avert their impending self-destruction, by&#8212;among other measures&#8212;reining in cultural/political feminization? We&#8217;ll soon see, but I doubt it. I think it could help some to talk more about this cultural feminization hypothesis—“cult-fem theory”—at least as a way of dispelling the holy aura of “progress” that feminization-related social changes have acquired. But could one attack cultural feminization more directly and conclusively? Could one expel women, or even just the “bad apples,” or even persuade them to think and act differently, in all significant Western institutions—legislatures, government offices, universities, corporations, media organizations, philanthropies—where they are now embedded and substantially run things? I don&#8217;t see how. I don&#8217;t think liberal Western societies have any strong defense against this threat, other than by reverting to overt illiberalism.</p>
<p style="text-align: center;">***</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>AN ABANDONED AND MALIGNANT HEART</title>
		<link>https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/an-abandoned-and-malignant-heart/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[j stone]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 30 Nov 2021 21:15:50 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[blacks]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[ethnicity]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[fall of the West]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[USA]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[wokeism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[women]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/?p=284</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Thoughts on another miscarriage of justice in the broken USA &#160; An unpopular cause I feel compelled to stick up for today is the cause of Travis McMichael, his father Gregory McMichael, and their neighbor William “Roddie” Bryan, all of Brunswick, Georgia, USA, who were recently found guilty of murdering Ahmaud Arbery. Rightly or wrongly, &#8230; <a href="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/an-abandoned-and-malignant-heart/" class="more-link">Continue reading<span class="screen-reader-text"> "AN ABANDONED AND MALIGNANT HEART"</span></a>]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><em>Thoughts on another miscarriage of justice in the broken USA</em></p>
<p><span id="more-284"></span></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>An unpopular cause I feel compelled to stick up for today is the cause of Travis McMichael, his father Gregory McMichael, and their neighbor William “Roddie” Bryan, all of Brunswick, Georgia, USA, who were recently found guilty of murdering Ahmaud Arbery. Rightly or wrongly, I am convinced that this verdict is blatantly unjust. I also believe that many Americans, not just the jury and the prosecutor, are complicit in this injustice—an injustice that is much closer to murder (these men are likely to die in prison) than was the actual killing of Arbery.</p>
<p>Grievous miscarriages of justice occur frequently now in the United States, and often arise due to race-related issues that bias prosecutors and jurors. So why am I writing about this particular injustice, and not, say, the travesty of the Derek Chauvin verdict? I think it’s mainly because in the Chauvin case I read a healthy amount of commentary defending Chauvin, whereas in the case of the McMichaels and Bryan I read no defenses, only smug expressions of satisfaction or at least placid acceptance of this verdict, even among people who should know better.</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" class=" wp-image-289 aligncenter" src="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/arbery2.jpg" alt="" width="516" height="421" srcset="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/arbery2.jpg 613w, https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/arbery2-300x245.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 516px) 85vw, 516px" /></p>
<p><img loading="lazy" class=" wp-image-286 aligncenter" src="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/gabbard.jpg" alt="" width="512" height="140" srcset="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/gabbard.jpg 592w, https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/gabbard-300x82.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 512px) 85vw, 512px" /></p>
<p><img loading="lazy" class="wp-image-288 aligncenter" src="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/cheong.jpg" alt="" width="436" height="252" srcset="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/cheong.jpg 607w, https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/cheong-300x173.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 436px) 85vw, 436px" /></p>
<p><img loading="lazy" class=" wp-image-287 aligncenter" src="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/flanagan.jpg" alt="" width="521" height="491" srcset="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/flanagan.jpg 599w, https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/flanagan-300x282.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 521px) 85vw, 521px" /></p>
<p>The guilt of the McMichaels and Bryan is, in other words, part of the contemporary American “conventional wisdom” that I have come to distrust almost reflexively.</p>
<p>Why the McMichaels and Bryan were abandoned to their harsh fate so easily, even willfully and joyously, by their countrymen is something I’ll speculate about later in this essay, but first I want to go over some of the basic facts of the case.</p>
<p><strong>The killing of Ahmaud Arbery</strong></p>
<p>Ahmaud Arbery was a 25-year old African-American man who lived in Brunswick, Georgia. Like many African-American men, he had a police record for at least moderately serious crimes, including bringing a handgun to a high school football game in 2013, and an attempted shoplifting of a TV from a WalMart in 2017. He was still on probation when he died.</p>
<p>In late 2018, apparently based on his own observations as well as those of family members, Arbery’s probation officer recommended that Arbery get a mental health evaluation. At this evaluation—the defense lawyers brought this up at the trial, but the judged ruled it inadmissible—Arbery described to the evaluator (apparently a psychiatric nurse) “auditory delusions sometimes commanding him ‘to rob and steal’ and sometimes telling him ‘to hurt people,’” as well as general difficulties controlling his anger. Arbery was diagnosed with schizoaffective disorder and prescribed olanzapine (Zyprexa), a second-generation antipsychotic that is also used treat schizophrenia and the manic episodes of type 1 bipolar disorder; however, he apparently didn’t take the drug for long, and there was no evidence of it in his system when he died, although there were trace amounts of THC, the active ingredient in marijuana.</p>
<p>The MSM stories after Arbery’s death were heavily biased in the young man’s favor, and tended to omit or downplay anything negative, preferring to show a picture of him looking spiffy in his prom suit . . .</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" class="size-full wp-image-290 aligncenter" src="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/arbery0.jpg" alt="" width="143" height="183" /></p>
<p>. . . and preferring to emphasize that at the time of his death Arbery was “planning” to attend a local technical college to become an electrician, and often went jogging for exercise.</p>
<p>In general, because of this overwhelming bias, it is hard to trust the information about Arbery that was provided by his family and their lawyer and cannot be verified, e.g., with documents. We can’t say with confidence much more about his background than what judicial records show, namely that he had a history of being armed illegally, and of attempting theft, and of showing signs of mental illness including serious impulse-control problems. This shouldn’t necessarily have had any bearing on the jury’s findings, but it does speak to the broader moral picture, and definitely belies the many MSM portraits of Arbery that were designed, in part, to whip up hatred against the men who killed him.</p>
<p>Late in 2019 Arbery had begun taking occasional jogs into a mostly white neighborhood called Satilla Shores, where the McMichaels and Bryan lived. A video camera also had recorded him, in his jogging clothes, walking into a house in the neighborhood that was under construction—this had happened several times, mostly at night.</p>
<p>In the months immediately preceding his fateful encounter with the McMichaels, there also had been several break-ins or thefts in the neighborhood, including the theft of a gun from an unlocked truck—reported by Travis McMichael on January 1.</p>
<p>On the night of February 11, according to Wikipedia:</p>
<p style="padding-left: 40px;">Travis called <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/9-1-1">9-1-1</a> to report a slender 6-foot-tall Black man with short hair, wearing red shorts and a white shirt, who was trespassing on the site of a house under construction. Travis said, &#8220;I&#8217;ve never seen this guy before in the neighborhood.&#8221; The <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dispatcher#Emergency_dispatchers">dispatcher</a> asked whether Travis was OK, and he said, &#8220;Yeah, it just startled me. When I turned around and saw him and backed up, he reached into his pocket and ran into the house. So I don&#8217;t know if he&#8217;s armed or not. But he looked like he was acting like he was.&#8221; &#8220;We&#8217;ve been having a lot of burglaries and break-ins around here lately&#8221;, Travis said on the call. He told the dispatcher that he was out in his truck, and that as many as four neighbors were out looking for the man. His father Gregory was one of the people out searching that night, and Gregory and at least one other neighbor were armed. Police responded and searched the house along with a neighbor, but found no one. However, surveillance video from that evening showed a man who reportedly looked like Arbery, briefly walking in and out of the house under construction. He did not take anything. The under-construction house did not have doors or windows.</p>
<p>While Arbery died before the mystery of the local thefts could be solved, there doesn’t seem to be any evidence that exonerates him in all those thefts, despite the MSM’s implications otherwise. Given his background and the correspondence of his jogging and the local burglaries, it seems at least plausible—and evidently many Satilla Shores residents suspected—that he used his jogging at night as a cover for burglaries, and jogging in daytime to select his night-time targets. (I would be interested to know whether the burglaries continued after Arbery’s death, but haven’t seen any reference to such data.)</p>
<p>On the 23<sup>rd</sup> of February, shortly after one o’clock in the afternoon, Arbery once again ran into Satilla Shores, and into the house under construction, and once again was recorded on video camera.</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-291" src="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/Arbery-in-house.jpg" alt="" width="768" height="453" srcset="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/Arbery-in-house.jpg 768w, https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/Arbery-in-house-300x177.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 709px) 85vw, (max-width: 909px) 67vw, (max-width: 984px) 61vw, (max-width: 1362px) 45vw, 600px" /></p>
<p>A neighbor, Matthew Albenze, also spotted Arbery and called 911 to report the trespass on the building under construction. Wikipedia again:</p>
<p style="padding-left: 40px;">The 9-1-1 dispatcher asked if the man was &#8220;breaking into it right now?&#8221; The caller replied: &#8220;No &#8230; it&#8217;s all open.&#8221; After the caller said the man was now &#8220;running down the street&#8221;, the dispatcher said police would respond. The dispatcher asked at 1:08 p.m., &#8220;I just need to know what he was doing wrong. Was he just on the premises and not supposed to be?&#8221; The caller responded, with some parts garbled, saying: &#8220;And he’s been caught on camera a bunch at night. It&#8217;s kind of an ongoing thing.&#8221;</p>
<p>Why Arbery ran away isn’t clear, but the perception among those who saw him was that he was trying to escape after stealing something from the construction site. Apparently he hadn’t stolen anything, but if he had known that the cops had been called, then, being on probation, he might have wanted to avoid another brush with the law. Then again, if Arbery was mentally ill, it is probably pointless to try to rationalize his actions.</p>
<p>Soon Arbery ran past the McMichaels&#8217; house, where Gregory McMichael, working in the yard, saw him and recognized him as the repeat trespasser the neighborhood was worried about. He and Travis armed themselves and got into their white pickup truck, and gave chase.</p>
<p>The MSM accounts, and the account of the prosecutor, are worded to suggest that the McMichaels were racist good-old-boys who pursued Arbery that day simply because they wanted to hunt down, and snuff out the life of, an innocent black man whose only &#8220;crime&#8221; was “jogging while black.” To say that this is false, and as such represents both journalistic and prosecutorial misconduct, would be putting it very mildly. Both McMichaels had law enforcement experience, and obviously (all the evidence leans this way) were attempting a citizen’s arrest, a procedure that has a long history in the United States and at the time was specifically sanctioned in Georgia law. In other words, they wanted only to detain Arbery so that he could be questioned by police.</p>
<p>Whether they had sufficient reason to attempt a citizen’s arrest is debatable. However, to say that in the heat of the moment someone slightly exceeding his rights under a citizen’s arrest law <em>automatically will be charged with false imprisonment, and then murder for defending his life when the mentally ill arrestee attacks him, </em>is completely absurd. Citizen’s arrest laws are not meant to sanction vigilantism, but they also are not meant to be life-destroying traps for honest citizens who are trying to protect their neighborhoods—in what was here a demonstrable absence of effective policing.</p>
<p>The McMichaels tried unsuccessfully to cut off Arbery as he ran, and, they said later, even asked him to stop and let them talk to him, but he didn’t respond and continued running in an attempt to evade them. They could easily have shot him, if killing him had been their intent, but they did not; they simply kept trying to get him to stop.</p>
<p>At some point Bryan, who had seen the chase go by his own house, joined in with his black pickup truck and tried—again, unsuccessfully—to cut off the running man. Note that Bryan was not a close friend of the McMichaels; he was merely another resident in this neighborhood that was now literally up in arms over the rash of thefts and trespassings, and hoped to put the perp behind bars.</p>
<p>Ultimately the McMichaels gave up pursuing Arbery—apparently the neighborhood had many open yards through which he could always evade them—and simply parked their pickup at a crossing where they thought he was likely to appear in his attempt to get away.</p>
<p>At this point, just several minutes after Albenze’s 911 call, Travis McMichael, standing on the road by the driver’s side door, made his own 911 call—but then saw Arbery coming and handed the phone to his father, who stood in the truck bed:</p>
<p style="padding-left: 40px;">a male caller said: &#8220;I&#8217;m out here at Satilla Shores &#8230;There&#8217;s a Black male running down the street.&#8221; The 9-1-1 dispatcher asked, &#8220;Where at Satilla Shores?&#8221; The caller replied: &#8220;I don&#8217;t know what street we&#8217;re on.&#8221;</p>
<p>Arbery now as he approached apparently saw Travis standing with his shotgun by the open driver&#8217;s door on the left side of the pickup truck. Arbery might have turned around or veered onto either of the lawns beside the narrow road. Instead he kept running towards the truck, though he altered course to the right side of the road, and then ran along the right side of the truck, just a few feet from Gregory McMichael who stood in the truck bed talking to 911. When he reached the front of the truck, Arbery suddenly cut left and charged Travis.</p>
<p>This was the impulse that killed Arbery. You and I, and pretty much every sane person aware of the story, know this, and know that we would never have done what he did. We know that we would have stopped, and we know that if Arbery had stopped, as he&#8217;d been asked, he would still be alive, the McMichaels and Bryan would be free, and none of us would have heard of any of them.</p>
<p>But Arbery charged Travis. Bryan, who had been in pursuit of Arbery, parked his pickup in time to catch most of this tragic encounter on his cellphone camera.</p>
<p>Arbery in his fatal lunge had almost reached Travis when the latter fired his shotgun, catching Arbery in the chest. Arbery kept coming and tried to wrest the gun away from Travis. Meanwhile Gregory McMichael, with the phone still to his ear and the line to the 911 dispatcher still open, screamed at Arbery to stop.</p>
<p style="padding-left: 40px;">The caller shouted, &#8220;Stop! &#8230; Watch that. Stop, damn it! Stop!&#8221;</p>
<p>Why did Gregory McMichael shout at Arbery to stop? Well, obviously because he and his son had never intended to kill Arbery and were astonished that he was making it necessary.</p>
<p>Arbery did not stop. He kept struggling for the shotgun until Travis had shot him with it a total of three times. After the third shot, which went through the left side of his chest, Arbery quickly weakened, staggered, and collapsed to the pavement.</p>
<p><strong>Aftermath<br />
</strong></p>
<p>Alerted by the first 911 call, the police soon arrived. Arbery by then was dead. Travis McMichael was splashed in blood and evidently in shock (“No, I’m not all right,” he told the cop. “I just fucking killed someone.”)</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" class="size-full wp-image-296 aligncenter" src="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/arbery4-1.jpg" alt="" width="800" height="450" srcset="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/arbery4-1.jpg 800w, https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/arbery4-1-300x169.jpg 300w, https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/arbery4-1-768x432.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 709px) 85vw, (max-width: 909px) 67vw, (max-width: 984px) 61vw, (max-width: 1362px) 45vw, 600px" /></p>
<p>But, along with his father, he cooperated. Bryan cooperated too. They freely discussed the events of the preceding minutes, evidently without any sense of having committed a crime. The police did not arrest them, and the local district attorney’s office did not charge them. The Brunswick Circuit DA, Jackie Johnson, saw the case as an unfortunate but not really criminal one involving a mentally ill young man who essentially had brought about his own death through his own impulsive and violent actions.</p>
<p>Johnson had connections to the McMichaels, though, so she recused herself and turned the thing over to a neighboring district, Waycross Judicial Circuit District. The DA there, George Barnhill, felt the same way about the case. According to Wikipedia:</p>
<p style="padding-left: 40px;">On April 2, Barnhill wrote a memorandum to Glynn County police, recommending that no arrests be made. Barnhill wrote that the McMichaels were within their rights to chase &#8220;a burglary suspect, with solid firsthand probable cause&#8221;; that &#8220;Arbery initiated the fight&#8221;; and that Travis McMichael &#8220;was allowed to use deadly force to protect himself&#8221; when &#8220;Arbery grabbed the shotgun&#8221;.</p>
<p>By this time, of course, Arbery’s family had got a lawyer, “leaders of the black community” were getting involved, and there were demands for a prosecution. So the whiff of racial protest, with all that entails for a prosecutor’s career, was already in the air. Soon Barnhill washed his hands of the case, with a rather tenuous excuse:</p>
<p style="padding-left: 40px;">Arbery had previously been prosecuted by his son, a prosecutor for the Brunswick Circuit District Attorney&#8217;s Office, in an earlier case [and] one of the defendants [Gregory McMichael] had served as an investigator on the same prosecution.</p>
<p>And so, on April 13, the Georgia Attorney General&#8217;s Office handed the case to another nearby venue, the Atlantic Judicial Circuit.</p>
<p>It’s unclear what would have happened if the case had simply been left at the Atlantic Judicial Circuit, with no new event to inflame the situation, but presumably its DA, one Tom Durden, would have been under the same political pressures as the two DAs that had passed on the case.</p>
<p>What did happen is this: On May 5 a local defense lawyer who had consulted informally with Gregory and Travis McMichael uploaded Bryan’s cellphone video to the website of a local radio station. Stories were circulating to the effect that Arbery had simply been gunned down while jogging, and the lawyer apparently thought that the video would convince the public of the McMichaels’ innocence. He thought wrong—not because the video shows the McMichaels to be murderers, but simply because it somewhat shockingly depicts a young African-American man’s death at the hands of two fairly stereotypical-looking southern white fellows. This publication of the video was, remember, in one of the hardest, most <a href="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/the-critical-mass-problem/">hysterogenic</a> periods of the COVID-19 pandemic. Just a few weeks later, America would erupt in the Great Awokening after George Floyd’s death—but even now it was clear that this society was becoming very restive under pressure, and its politicians and politically sensitive prosecutors were doing what they could to placate the more restive elements.</p>
<p>From Wikipedia again:</p>
<p style="padding-left: 40px;">Within hours of the video becoming public, Tom Durden, the district attorney for Georgia&#8217;s Atlantic Judicial Circuit, said that he would present the case to &#8220;the next available grand jury in Glynn County&#8221; to decide if charges should be filed. The convening of grand juries had been postponed until after June 12 due to the COVID-19 pandemic. Durden accepted <em>Georgia Governor Brian Kemp&#8217;s offer</em> to bring in the Georgia Bureau of Investigation (GBI) to investigate. [italics mine]</p>
<p>At this point, with the most senior state politician getting involved in what should have been an obscure case, and more or less signaling—virtue-signaling—which way it should go, the McMichaels’ fate was sealed.</p>
<p style="padding-left: 40px;">The GBI found probable cause to charge Gregory and Travis McMichael within 36 hours of taking over jurisdiction of the case, and, on May 7, arrested and charged them with felony murder. The McMichaels were booked into the Glynn County Jail. At an appearance before a judge the following day, the McMichaels were both denied bond.</p>
<p>A few days later, Bryan too was arrested and charged.</p>
<p><strong>Ladies of the Jury</strong></p>
<p>When the case came before a jury, it was widely reported that eleven of the twelve jurors were white. It was much less widely reported that nine of those eleven were women.</p>
<p>Women, as I have been <a href="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/the-great-feminization/">writing</a> for the past decade, “wear the pants” now in most Western societies, i.e., have unprecedented and often dominant influence in many realms of culture. This is important because on average women think about and react to the world differently than men. Compared to men, for example, women seem much more emotionally aroused by stories of white-on-black racial conflict. Women, white women, also appear to have been the<a href="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/the-critical-mass-problem/"> dominant participants</a> in the bizarre BLM frenzy of the summer 2020 Great Awokening.</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" class="size-full wp-image-225 aligncenter" src="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2021/06/bethesdaawokening-1.jpg" alt="" width="800" height="450" srcset="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2021/06/bethesdaawokening-1.jpg 800w, https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2021/06/bethesdaawokening-1-300x169.jpg 300w, https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2021/06/bethesdaawokening-1-768x432.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 709px) 85vw, (max-width: 909px) 67vw, (max-width: 984px) 61vw, (max-width: 1362px) 45vw, 600px" /></p>
<p>If the McMichael/Bryan defense lawyers had read my essays, they would have known this (I write this only half-jokingly—my essays are not <em>that</em> obscure) and accordingly might have tried a different jury-selection strategy—though really, as this and many other examples show, the jury system in the United States is generally unlikely to deliver justice in cases where the forces of Wokeness favor one side.</p>
<p>In any case, the jury members were mostly women, the DA that ultimately charged the three defendants was a black woman (she claimed at the trial, among other things, that the defendants “chased, hunted down and ultimately executed” Arbery), and the lead prosecutor in the trial was a woman. And of course, Al Sharpton sat in the courtroom with Arbery’s family, and a mob of demonstrators camped outside the court building, to remind those sensitive women of the jury what they would face if they delivered the wrong verdict.</p>
<p>The jury, without much deliberation, duly returned a verdict of guilty on most of the charges. These charges included felony murder for all three defendants&#8212;even Bryan who had not been armed and had done nothing more than pursue Arbery in his truck. Travis McMichael, who presumably would have been killed by Arbery had he not defended himself, was additionally found guilty of “malice murder,” which means murder with “express or implied malice.”</p>
<p>These charges bring a minimum 30-year sentence before the possibility of parole, and for Travis McMichael, with the additional malice murder rap, there may be no parole—that will be up to the judge.</p>
<p>The Biden Administration, of course, watched this show trial approvingly.</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" class="size-full wp-image-297 aligncenter" src="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/biden.jpg" alt="" width="604" height="507" srcset="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/biden.jpg 604w, https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/biden-300x252.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 709px) 85vw, (max-width: 909px) 67vw, (max-width: 984px) 61vw, (max-width: 1362px) 45vw, 600px" /></p>
<p>However, it isn&#8217;t going to let it go at that. No, the Biden Administration via its “Justice” Department will try to earn further brownie points in the eyes of its voter base, and at the same time try to crush the spirit of conservative Legacy Americans, by pursuing a federal hate-crime trial of the McMichaels and Bryan—scheduled to convene next year.</p>
<p>Meanwhile the state of Georgia, led by “Republican” Gov. Brian Kemp, will also send a message by prosecuting former Brunswick Circuit DA Jackie Johnson—the first one to recuse herself, remember—for “obstruction of justice.” This will ensure that, the next time a black person in Georgia is killed by whites for any reason whatsoever, local DAs will show the proper Stakhanovite zeal in prosecuting.</p>
<p><strong>Flaws in the Law</strong></p>
<p>Note that Georgia law defines the kind of murder alleged in the case as follows:</p>
<p style="padding-left: 40px;">(a) A person commits the offense of murder when he unlawfully and with malice aforethought, either express or implied, causes the death of another human being.</p>
<p style="padding-left: 40px;">(b) Express malice is that deliberate intention unlawfully to take the life of another human being which is manifested by external circumstances capable of proof. Malice shall be implied where no considerable provocation appears and where all the circumstances of the killing show an abandoned and malignant heart.</p>
<p style="padding-left: 40px;">(c) A person commits the offense of murder when, in the commission of a felony, he or she causes the death of another human being irrespective of malice.</p>
<p>Did “<em>all the circumstances of the killing</em> show an abandoned and malignant heart” on the part of Travis McMichael? The answer is obviously <em>no</em>. He did not shoot Arbery from the window of his truck (or at any time until charged) as he would have done had his intent been murderous; he phoned 911 prior to the fatal encounter; he did not flee the scene of the killing; he showed every sign of having been shaken by that killing because he had not expected it; and he cooperated with the police who came to the scene. If he had an “abandoned and malignant heart” (why are these vague and archaic descriptors even allowed in the legal code?) he would have acted like a typical premeditated killer, shooting Arbery in a way that would not implicate himself, and denying involvement if questioned. I can imagine that a lot of American men who are forced to live with the problem of Black crime will now prefer that option, at least those men who are not totally demoralized by show trials like these.</p>
<p>The bigger problem here is the implied notion, noted above, that even mildly overinterpreting a citizen’s arrest law, as any concerned citizen might easily do without bad intent, can abruptly (by the whim of a biased jury) turn the citizen into a felon, and then a murderer if he has to defend himself against the arrestee’s violence. If such a notion were valid, a citizen’s arrest law would be worse than worthless. It would be as if the government invited motorists to drive across a very long and narrow, guardrail-less bridge over a mile-deep gorge, having positioned the bridge in such a way that it constantly swayed and shimmied in the wind. It effectively would be no bridge at all—only a deathtrap for the unwary.</p>
<p><strong>The Malignant Heart of the Matter<br />
</strong></p>
<p>Is there even any point in arguing over the legal questions at the heart of such cases? I can remember many racially tinged travesties of justice in my adult life, going back at least to the O.J. Simpson trial of 1995. These cases always feel like inversions of the <em>To Kill a Mockingbird </em>setup—either an apparently guilty black man goes free or gets off lightly, or a wrongfully prosecuted white man has his life ruined. More importantly, the process by which these injustices occur is always (as in Harper Lee’s model of 1930s small-town Alabama) a social process involving race-politics pressures as well as a lot of venality, cowardice, and hysteria. Tom Wolfe somehow got away with writing a big novel,<em> Bonfire of the Vanities</em>, about the modern versions of these circuses, a novel that even in 1987 conveyed strongly the message that American society and its judicial system had been irretrievably broken by decades of racial factionalism.</p>
<p>Similarly, what really drew my attention to this case was the evidence of race-politics pressure on DAs and politicians, the jury’s disregard for the basic evidence that should have exonerated the defendants, the MSM&#8217;s wanton mischaracterizations of the case (go back and read their accounts!), and then, above all, the overwhelmingly positive, smug reaction to the verdict by so many Americans.</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" class="wp-image-298 aligncenter" src="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/latimes.jpg" alt="" width="516" height="432" srcset="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/latimes.jpg 598w, https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/latimes-300x251.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 516px) 85vw, 516px" /></p>
<p><img loading="lazy" class=" wp-image-299 aligncenter" src="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/uygur.jpg" alt="" width="510" height="131" srcset="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/uygur.jpg 621w, https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/uygur-300x77.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 510px) 85vw, 510px" /></p>
<p><img loading="lazy" class=" wp-image-300 aligncenter" src="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/king.jpg" alt="" width="434" height="272" srcset="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/king.jpg 610w, https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/king-300x188.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 434px) 85vw, 434px" /></p>
<p>Of course, Twitter and social media generally are full of people who can cheaply virtue-signal while never having to deal with the unhappy realities afflicting ordinary Americans. Stephen King, for example, lives in a humongous complex on a barrier-island beach south of Sarasota—I know because I once lived nearby—at the least-accessible extremity of a wealthy neighborhood that was designed by its residents to keep out the riffraff, including anyone who looks remotely like Ahmaud Arbery. From that fortress King is unlikely ever to have to face the problem of burglary or thievery, and anyway any losses from such property crime would be infinitesimal in their impact on him.</p>
<p>But I think virtue-signaling is only a small and secondary part of this. Over the past few years, and especially since the COVID pandemic started, the more or less diffuse growth of wokeness in American life seems to have cohered into a Salem-like episode of socially sanctioned savagery&#8212;arguably almost as deadly as Salem, and much more broad and durable. I’ve even had the vague imaginative sense (from a distance, as an expatriate) that this mass hysteria has been developing into a kind of cult, presided over by a collectively summoned black perp-god, or purple-haired Gender Studies goddess, who in strident tones demands a constant flow of human sacrifices. (Another <a href="https://vdare.com/articles/john-derbyshire-the-arbery-show-trial-begins-more-human-sacrifices-to-appease-the-blm-gods">writer</a> elaborated this human-sacrifice concept before me, so I will mostly leave that imagery to him.)</p>
<p>The centrality of pictures and videos should give us a clue to how these weird social phenomena arise. If, let us say, a young black man, a man like Ahmaud Arbery, is found dead in the street by gunshot one day, but there is no video evidence of how he was killed, what will be the public reaction? The reader knows the answer already, because such cases occur many times per day across the US, especially in heavily black cities such as Chicago, St. Louis, Detroit and Baltimore. There is generally <em>no</em> reaction, <em>no</em> wider resonance. The man’s family may weep. They may call on the police to solve the crime. But usually only if the cops identify a white suspect (a relatively rare event) will the case make out of the back pages of the papers, and only if the white-on-black killing is caught on video (much rarer) is the case sure to be lifted from the muck of the ordinary criminal court docket into the glare of a Woke Cult show trial.</p>
<p>People in general, and I guess women moreso than men on average, are apt to be distressed when they witness—for example on a video—a violent death. The distress in turn creates a sense of urgency <em>to do something</em>. (Consider how heavily US foreign and immigration policies in recent years have been <a href="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/the-great-feminization/">driven</a> by distressing images in the media, e.g., of wounded children in Syria or refugee children crossing the Rio Grande.) Distress also tends to suppress rational thought, making the mind more susceptible to the beating tom-toms (to paraphrase McLuhan) of mass delusion and madness. And when a killing depicted on a distressing video can be made to seem even remotely consistent with the central wokelore motif of <em>evil whites harming innocent blacks</em>—that very live snarl of wires in the American psyche—the mass delusion and madness will come together and start to lurch in a predictable direction. It will start to be controlled and guided, to do meaningful political work, by a political faction that I would say definitely has “an abandoned and malignant heart.”</p>
<p>It seems to me that there are usually two main group of actors that ignite these episodes: blacks who from basic instinct or family ties support fellow blacks in conflicts with whites, and a certain large stratum of white women who have, in regard to blacks, a powerful guilt and appeasement reflex. Once those two groups start up and gather steam, craven politicians and their judicial minions join in with the rapidity of scurrying rodents, and then the superorganism swells to its maximum size with the additions of journalists and millions of ordinary and celebrity virtue-signalers. This frenzied entity of many voices and noises somehow achieves a certain harmony as it demands “justice,” which is code for: give us a white victim.</p>
<p>One cannot overemphasize how <em>un</em>interested in truth is this entity. In the case of Derek Chauvin, the entity assured us that the smirk on Chauvin’s face as he held down George Floyd was simply his sadist-cop’s delight at the approaching demise of his poor African American victim. Chauvin was a police officer with long experience of having to deal with unruly and bullshitting black perps, and of course did not have the clairvoyance to know that this particular perp, this one unlucky time, was telling the truth—but try explaining that to some vapor-brained leftist millennial or wine-aunt who is caught up in the full guilt-hate-love ecstasy of the Awokening.</p>
<p>In the case of Kyle Rittenhouse, the entity (speaking even through the man who is the current US president) assured us that the defendant was a white supremacist who had gone hunting for innocent protesters. The entity let it be known among the softer minded that Rittenhouse&#8217;s victims were black&#8212;this became a very widespread perception. Rittenhouse avoided becoming the next sacrificial victim mainly because the people he had shot in self defense were actually white. It must have helped too that he, Rittenhouse, was a cherubic-looking lad liable to trigger the protective maternal instincts of many American women—instincts that are normally directed entirely toward the shooting victim in such cases, at least when the victim is black.</p>
<p>In Georgia, of course, the victim was indeed black and the accused were southern whites who drove pickup trucks, carried guns, probably had a few Confederate flags around, and probably held African Americans in low esteem. On the great totem pole of wokeism, these men were the lowest of the low. Thus, the story the entity told of their vile misdeeds, in the MSM, in social media, in the courtroom through the mouths of sworn officers of the court, was a festival of lies and obfuscations, and essentially the defendants had no defenders other than their paid lawyers.</p>
<p>The victims of human sacrifice in ancient times often were drawn from the lowest, most marginalized castes. Is it not plausible that tens of thousands of years of primitive religion have worn certain paths into our minds such that even now we subconsciously act out those rituals&#8212;and perhaps can even experience, every so often, the vivid illusion that an angry god is present and wants to be appeased?</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" class="size-full wp-image-302 aligncenter" src="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/floyd.jpg" alt="" width="529" height="730" srcset="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/floyd.jpg 529w, https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/floyd-217x300.jpg 217w" sizes="(max-width: 529px) 85vw, 529px" /></p>
<p>This particular deity will never stay appeased for long, though, will it? And as evidence accumulates that America’s grand racial experiment has failed, will Americans ever face up to that failure and respond rationally? Or will that failure just drive them crazier and crazier, as they deliver more and more sacrificial victims to a god who will not relent?</p>
<p style="text-align: center;">***</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
