<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>wokeism &#8211; Thoughts of Stone</title>
	<atom:link href="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/category/wokeism/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/</link>
	<description>short essays, usually about humans</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Wed, 01 Dec 2021 05:04:25 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=5.7.4</generator>

<image>
	<url>https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2020/07/cropped-icon-32x32.jpg</url>
	<title>wokeism &#8211; Thoughts of Stone</title>
	<link>https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/</link>
	<width>32</width>
	<height>32</height>
</image> 
	<item>
		<title>AN ABANDONED AND MALIGNANT HEART</title>
		<link>https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/an-abandoned-and-malignant-heart/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[j stone]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 30 Nov 2021 21:15:50 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[blacks]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[ethnicity]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[fall of the West]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[USA]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[wokeism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[women]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/?p=284</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Thoughts on another miscarriage of justice in the broken USA &#160; An unpopular cause I feel compelled to stick up for today is the cause of Travis McMichael, his father Gregory McMichael, and their neighbor William “Roddie” Bryan, all of Brunswick, Georgia, USA, who were recently found guilty of murdering Ahmaud Arbery. Rightly or wrongly, &#8230; <a href="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/an-abandoned-and-malignant-heart/" class="more-link">Continue reading<span class="screen-reader-text"> "AN ABANDONED AND MALIGNANT HEART"</span></a>]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><em>Thoughts on another miscarriage of justice in the broken USA</em></p>
<p><span id="more-284"></span></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>An unpopular cause I feel compelled to stick up for today is the cause of Travis McMichael, his father Gregory McMichael, and their neighbor William “Roddie” Bryan, all of Brunswick, Georgia, USA, who were recently found guilty of murdering Ahmaud Arbery. Rightly or wrongly, I am convinced that this verdict is wrongful and basically irrational. I also believe that many Americans, not just the jury and the prosecutor, are complicit in this injustice—an injustice that is closer to murder (these men are likely to die in prison) than was the actual killing of Arbery.</p>
<p>Grievous miscarriages of justice occur frequently now in the United States, and often arise due to race-related issues that bias prosecutors and jurors. So why am I writing about this particular injustice, and not, say, the travesty of the Derek Chauvin verdict? I think it’s mainly because in the Chauvin case I read a healthy amount of commentary defending Chauvin, whereas in the case of the McMichaels and Bryan I read no defenses, only smug expressions of satisfaction or at least placid acceptance of this verdict, even among people who should know better.</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" class=" wp-image-289 aligncenter" src="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/arbery2.jpg" alt="" width="516" height="421" srcset="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/arbery2.jpg 613w, https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/arbery2-300x245.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 516px) 85vw, 516px" /></p>
<p><img loading="lazy" class=" wp-image-286 aligncenter" src="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/gabbard.jpg" alt="" width="512" height="140" srcset="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/gabbard.jpg 592w, https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/gabbard-300x82.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 512px) 85vw, 512px" /></p>
<p><img loading="lazy" class="wp-image-288 aligncenter" src="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/cheong.jpg" alt="" width="436" height="252" srcset="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/cheong.jpg 607w, https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/cheong-300x173.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 436px) 85vw, 436px" /></p>
<p><img loading="lazy" class=" wp-image-287 aligncenter" src="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/flanagan.jpg" alt="" width="521" height="491" srcset="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/flanagan.jpg 599w, https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/flanagan-300x282.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 521px) 85vw, 521px" /></p>
<p>The guilt of the McMichaels and Bryan is, in other words, part of the contemporary American “conventional wisdom” that I have come to distrust almost reflexively.</p>
<p>Why the McMichaels and Bryan were abandoned to their harsh fate so easily, even willfully, by their countrymen is something I’ll speculate about later in this essay, but first I want to go over some of the basic facts of the case.</p>
<p><strong>The killing of Ahmaud Arbery</strong></p>
<p>Ahmaud Arbery was a 25-year old African-American man who lived in Brunswick, Georgia. Like many African-American men, he had a police record for at least moderately serious crimes, including bringing a handgun to a high school football game in 2013, and an attempted shoplifting of a TV from a WalMart in 2017. He was still on probation when he died.</p>
<p>In late 2018, apparently based on his own observations as well as those of family members, Arbery’s probation officer recommended that Arbery get a mental health evaluation. At this evaluation—the defense lawyers brought this up at the trial, but the judged ruled it inadmissible—Arbery described to the evaluator (apparently a psychiatric nurse) “auditory delusions sometimes commanding him ‘to rob and steal’ and sometimes telling him ‘to hurt people,’” as well as general difficulties controlling his anger. Arbery was diagnosed with schizoaffective disorder and prescribed olanzapine (Zyprexa), a second-generation antipsychotic that is also used treat schizophrenia and the manic episodes of type 1 bipolar disorder; however, he apparently didn’t take the drug for long, and there was no evidence of it in his system when he died, although there were trace amounts of THC, the active ingredient in marijuana.</p>
<p>The MSM stories after Arbery’s death were heavily biased in the young man’s favor, and tended to omit or downplay anything negative, preferring to show a picture of him looking spiffy in his prom suit . . .</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" class="size-full wp-image-290 aligncenter" src="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/arbery0.jpg" alt="" width="143" height="183" /></p>
<p>. . . and preferring to emphasize that at the time of his death Arbery was “planning” to attend a local technical college to become an electrician, and often went jogging for exercise.</p>
<p>In general, because of this overwhelming bias, it is hard to trust the information about Arbery that was provided by his family and their lawyer and cannot be verified, e.g., with documents. We can’t say with confidence much more about him than what judicial records show, namely that he had a history of being armed illegally, and of attempting theft, and of showing signs of mental illness including serious impulse-control problems. This shouldn’t necessarily have had any bearing on the jury’s findings, but it does speak to the broader moral picture, and definitely belies the many MSM portraits of Arbery that were designed, in part, to whip up hatred against the men who killed him.</p>
<p>As of early 2020, Arbery had begun occasional jogs into a mostly white neighborhood called Satilla Shores, where the McMichaels and Bryan lived. A video camera also had recorded him, in his jogging clothes, walking into a house in the neighborhood that was under construction—this had happened several times, mostly at night.</p>
<p>In the months immediately preceding his fateful encounter with the McMichaels, there also had been several break-ins or thefts in the neighborhood, including the theft of a gun from an unlocked truck—reported by Travis McMichael on January 1.</p>
<p>On the night of February 11, according to Wikipedia:</p>
<p style="padding-left: 40px;">Travis called <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/9-1-1">9-1-1</a> to report a slender 6-foot-tall Black man with short hair, wearing red shorts and a white shirt, who was trespassing on the site of a house under construction. Travis said, &#8220;I&#8217;ve never seen this guy before in the neighborhood.&#8221; The <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dispatcher#Emergency_dispatchers">dispatcher</a> asked whether Travis was OK, and he said, &#8220;Yeah, it just startled me. When I turned around and saw him and backed up, he reached into his pocket and ran into the house. So I don&#8217;t know if he&#8217;s armed or not. But he looked like he was acting like he was.&#8221; &#8220;We&#8217;ve been having a lot of burglaries and break-ins around here lately&#8221;, Travis said on the call. He told the dispatcher that he was out in his truck, and that as many as four neighbors were out looking for the man. His father Gregory was one of the people out searching that night, and Gregory and at least one other neighbor were armed. Police responded and searched the house along with a neighbor, but found no one. However, surveillance video from that evening showed a man who reportedly looked like Arbery, briefly walking in and out of the house under construction. He did not take anything. The under-construction house did not have doors or windows.</p>
<p>While Arbery died before the mystery of the local thefts could be solved, there doesn’t seem to be any evidence that exonerates him in all those thefts, despite the MSM’s misleading implications otherwise. Given his background and the correspondence of his jogging and the local burglaries, it seems at least plausible—and evidently many Satilla Shores residents suspected—that he used his jogging at night as a cover for burglaries, and jogging in daytime to select his night-time targets. (I would be interested to know whether the burglaries continued after Arbery’s death, but haven’t seen any reference to such data.)</p>
<p>On the 23<sup>rd</sup> of February, shortly after one o’clock in the afternoon, Arbery once again ran into Satilla Shores, and into the house under construction, and once again was recorded on video camera.</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-291" src="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/Arbery-in-house.jpg" alt="" width="768" height="453" srcset="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/Arbery-in-house.jpg 768w, https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/Arbery-in-house-300x177.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 709px) 85vw, (max-width: 909px) 67vw, (max-width: 984px) 61vw, (max-width: 1362px) 45vw, 600px" /></p>
<p>A neighbor, Matthew Albenze, also spotted Arbery and called 911 to report the trespass on the building under construction. Wikipedia again:</p>
<p style="padding-left: 40px;">The 9-1-1 dispatcher asked if the man was &#8220;breaking into it right now?&#8221; The caller replied: &#8220;No &#8230; it&#8217;s all open.&#8221; After the caller said the man was now &#8220;running down the street&#8221;, the dispatcher said police would respond. The dispatcher asked at 1:08 p.m., &#8220;I just need to know what he was doing wrong. Was he just on the premises and not supposed to be?&#8221; The caller responded, with some parts garbled, saying: &#8220;And he’s been caught on camera a bunch at night. It&#8217;s kind of an ongoing thing.&#8221;</p>
<p>Why Arbery ran away isn’t clear, but the perception among those who saw him was that he was trying to escape after stealing something from the construction site. Apparently he hadn’t stolen anything, but if he had known that the cops had been called, then, being on probation, he might have wanted to avoid another brush with the law. Then again, if Arbery was mentally ill, it is probably pointless to try to rationalize his actions.</p>
<p>Soon Arbery ran past the McMichaels&#8217; house, where Gregory McMichael, working in the yard, saw him and recognized him as the repeat trespasser the neighborhood was worried about. He and Travis armed themselves and got into their white pickup truck, and gave chase.</p>
<p>The MSM accounts, and the account of the prosecutor, are worded to suggest that the McMichaels were racist good-old-boys who pursued Arbery that day simply because they wanted to hunt down, and snuff out the life of, an innocent black man whose only crime was “jogging while black.” To say that this is false, and as such represents both journalistic and prosecutorial misconduct, would be putting it very mildly. Both McMichaels had law enforcement experience, and obviously were attempting a citizen’s arrest, a procedure that has a long history in the United States and at the time was specifically sanctioned in Georgia law. In other words, they wanted only to detain Arbery so that he could be questioned by police.</p>
<p>Whether they had enough evidence to justify attempting a citizen’s arrest is debatable. However, to say that in the heat of the moment someone slightly exceeding his rights under a citizen’s arrest law <em>automatically will be charged with false imprisonment, and then murder for defending his life when the mentally ill arrestee attacks him, </em>is completely absurd. Citizen’s arrest laws are not meant to sanction vigilantism, but they also are not meant to be life-destroying traps for honest citizens who are trying to protect their neighborhoods—in what was here a demonstrable absence of effective policing.</p>
<p>The McMichaels tried unsuccessfully to cut off Arbery as he ran, and, they said later, even asked him to stop and let them talk to him, but he didn’t respond and continued running in an attempt to evade them. They could easily have shot him, if killing him had been their intent, but they did not; they simply kept trying to get him to stop.</p>
<p>At some point Bryan, who had seen the chase go by his own house, joined in with his black pickup truck and tried—again, unsuccessfully—to cut off the running man. Note that Bryan was not a close friend of the McMichaels; he was merely another resident in this neighborhood that was now literally up in arms over the rash of thefts and trespassings, and hoped to put the perp behind bars.</p>
<p>Ultimately the McMichaels gave up pursuing Arbery—apparently the neighborhood had many open yards through which he could always evade them—and simply parked their pickup at a crossing where they thought he was likely to appear in his attempt to get away.</p>
<p>At this point, just several minutes after Albenze’s 911 call, Travis McMichael, standing on the road by the driver’s side door, made his own 911 call—but then saw Arbery coming and handed the phone to his father, who stood in the truck bed:</p>
<p style="padding-left: 40px;">a male caller said: &#8220;I&#8217;m out here at Satilla Shores &#8230;There&#8217;s a Black male running down the street.&#8221; The 9-1-1 dispatcher asked, &#8220;Where at Satilla Shores?&#8221; The caller replied: &#8220;I don&#8217;t know what street we&#8217;re on.&#8221;</p>
<p>Arbery now, instead of running away into yards again, ran down the right side of the pickup truck&#8212;Travis McMichael was on the left side&#8212;then cut back across the front of the vehicle and directly attacked Travis, trying to wrest the shotgun from him.</p>
<p>Bryan, who had been in pursuit of Arbery, parked and caught most of this tragic encounter on his cellphone camera: As Arbery struggled with Travis McMichael for the shotgun, Gregory McMichael, with the phone still to his ear and the line to the 911 dispatcher still open, screamed at Arbery to stop.</p>
<p style="padding-left: 40px;">The caller shouted, &#8220;Stop! &#8230; Watch that. Stop, damn it! Stop!&#8221;</p>
<p>He then&#8212;prudently, any sane person would say&#8212;put the cellphone down and picked up a handgun as Arbery attacked his son.</p>
<p>Arbery, as the video showed, did not stop struggling for the shotgun until Travis McMichael had shot him with it three times at point blank range. After the third shot, which went right through the center of his chest, Arbery quickly weakened, staggered, and collapsed to the pavement.</p>
<p><strong>Aftermath<br />
</strong></p>
<p>Having been alerted by the first 911 call, the police soon arrived. Arbery by then was dead. Travis McMichael was covered in blood and in shock (“No, I’m not all right,” he told the cop. “I just fucking killed someone.”)</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" class="size-full wp-image-296 aligncenter" src="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/arbery4-1.jpg" alt="" width="800" height="450" srcset="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/arbery4-1.jpg 800w, https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/arbery4-1-300x169.jpg 300w, https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/arbery4-1-768x432.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 709px) 85vw, (max-width: 909px) 67vw, (max-width: 984px) 61vw, (max-width: 1362px) 45vw, 600px" /></p>
<p>But, along with his father, he cooperated. Bryan cooperated too. They freely discussed the events of the preceding minutes, evidently without any sense of having committed a crime. The police did not arrest them, and the local district attorney’s office did not charge them.</p>
<p>The Brunswick Circuit DA, Jackie Johnson, apparently saw the case as I do, in other words as an unfortunate but not really criminal case involving a mentally ill young man who essentially had brought about his own death through his own impulsive and violent actions.</p>
<p>Johnson had connections to the McMichaels, though, so she recused herself and turned the thing over to a neighboring district, Waycross Judicial Circuit District. The DA there, George Barnhill, felt the same way about the case. According to Wikipedia:</p>
<p style="padding-left: 40px;">On April 2, Barnhill wrote a memorandum to Glynn County police, recommending that no arrests be made. Barnhill wrote that the McMichaels were within their rights to chase &#8220;a burglary suspect, with solid firsthand probable cause&#8221;; that &#8220;Arbery initiated the fight&#8221;; and that Travis McMichael &#8220;was allowed to use deadly force to protect himself&#8221; when &#8220;Arbery grabbed the shotgun&#8221;.</p>
<p>By this time, of course, Arbery’s family had got a lawyer, “leaders of the black community” were getting involved, and there were demands for a prosecution. So the whiff of racial protest, with all that entails for a prosecutor’s career, was already in the air. Soon Barnhill washed his hands of the case, with a rather tenuous excuse:</p>
<p style="padding-left: 40px;">Arbery had previously been prosecuted by his son, a prosecutor for the Brunswick Circuit District Attorney&#8217;s Office, in an earlier case [and] one of the defendants [Gregory McMichael] had served as an investigator on the same prosecution.</p>
<p>And so, on April 13, the Georgia Attorney General&#8217;s Office handed the case to another nearby venue, the Atlantic Judicial Circuit.</p>
<p>It’s unclear what would have happened if the case had simply been left at the Atlantic Judicial Circuit, with no new event to inflame the situation, but presumably its DA, one Tom Durden, would have been under the same political pressures as the two DAs that had passed on the case.</p>
<p>In any case, on May 5 a local defense lawyer who had consulted informally with Gregory and Travis McMichael uploaded Bryan’s cellphone video to the website of a local radio station. Stories were circulating to the effect that Arbery had simply been gunned down while jogging, and the lawyer apparently thought that the video would convince the public of the McMichaels’ innocence. He thought wrong—not because the video shows the McMichaels to be murderers, but simply because it somewhat shockingly depicts a young African-American man’s death at the hands of two fairly stereotypical-looking southern white fellows. This publication of the video was, remember, in one of the hardest, most <a href="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/the-critical-mass-problem/">hysterogenic</a> periods of the COVID-19 pandemic. Just a few weeks later, America would erupt in the Great Awokening after George Floyd’s death—but even now it was clear that this society was becoming very restive under pressure, and its politicians and politically sensitive prosecutors were doing what they could to placate the more restive elements.</p>
<p>From Wikipedia again:</p>
<p style="padding-left: 40px;">Within hours of the video becoming public, Tom Durden, the district attorney for Georgia&#8217;s Atlantic Judicial Circuit, said that he would present the case to &#8220;the next available grand jury in Glynn County&#8221; to decide if charges should be filed. The convening of grand juries had been postponed until after June 12 due to the COVID-19 pandemic. Durden accepted <em>Georgia Governor Brian Kemp&#8217;s offer</em> to bring in the Georgia Bureau of Investigation (GBI) to investigate. [italics mine]</p>
<p>At this point, with the most senior state politician getting involved in what should have been an obscure case, and more or less signaling—virtue-signaling—which way it should go, the McMichaels’ fate was sealed.</p>
<p style="padding-left: 40px;">The GBI found probable cause to charge Gregory and Travis McMichael within 36 hours of taking over jurisdiction of the case, and, on May 7, arrested and charged them with felony murder. The McMichaels were booked into the Glynn County Jail. At an appearance before a judge the following day, the McMichaels were both denied bond.</p>
<p>A few days later, Bryan was arrested and charged too.</p>
<p><strong>Ladies of the Jury</strong></p>
<p>When the case came before a jury, it was widely reported that eleven of the twelve jurors were white. It was much less widely reported that nine of those eleven were women.</p>
<p>Women, as I have been <a href="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/the-great-feminization/">writing</a> for the past decade, “wear the pants” now in most Western societies, i.e., have unprecedented and often dominant influence in many realms of culture. This is important because on average women think about and react to the world differently than men. Compared to men, for example, women seem much more emotionally aroused by stories of white-on-black racial conflict. Women, white women, also appear to have been the<a href="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/the-critical-mass-problem/"> dominant participants</a> in the bizarre BLM frenzy of the summer 2020 Great Awokening.</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" class="size-full wp-image-225 aligncenter" src="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2021/06/bethesdaawokening-1.jpg" alt="" width="800" height="450" srcset="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2021/06/bethesdaawokening-1.jpg 800w, https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2021/06/bethesdaawokening-1-300x169.jpg 300w, https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2021/06/bethesdaawokening-1-768x432.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 709px) 85vw, (max-width: 909px) 67vw, (max-width: 984px) 61vw, (max-width: 1362px) 45vw, 600px" /></p>
<p>If the McMichael/Bryan defense lawyers had read my essays, they would have known this (I write this only half-jokingly—my essays are not <em>that</em> obscure) and accordingly might have tried a different jury-selection strategy—though really, as this and many other examples show, the jury system in the United States is generally unlikely to deliver justice in cases where the Woke Inquisition backs one side.</p>
<p>In any case, the jury members were mostly women, the DA that ultimately charged the three defendants was a black woman (she claimed at the trial, among other things, that the defendants “chased, hunted down and ultimately executed” Arbery), and the lead prosecutor in the trial was a woman. And of course, Al Sharpton sat in the courtroom with Arbery’s family, and a mob of demonstrators camped outside the court building, to remind those sensitive women of the jury what they would face if they delivered the wrong verdict.</p>
<p>The jury predictably and without much deliberation returned a verdict of guilty on most of the charges. These charges included felony murder, for all three defendants&#8212;even Bryan who had not been armed and had done nothing more than pursue Arbery in his truck. Travis McMichael, who presumably would have been killed by Arbery had he not defended himself, was additionally found guilty of “malice murder,” which means murder with “express or implied malice.”</p>
<p>These charges bring a minimum 30-year sentence before the possibility of parole, and for Travis McMichael, with the additional malice murder rap, there may be no parole—that will be up to the judge.</p>
<p>The Biden Administration, of course, watched this show trial approvingly.</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" class="size-full wp-image-297 aligncenter" src="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/biden.jpg" alt="" width="604" height="507" srcset="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/biden.jpg 604w, https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/biden-300x252.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 709px) 85vw, (max-width: 909px) 67vw, (max-width: 984px) 61vw, (max-width: 1362px) 45vw, 600px" /></p>
<p>However, it won&#8217;t let it go at that. No, the Biden Administration via its “Justice” Department will try to earn further brownie points in the eyes of its voter base, and at the same time crush the spirit of conservative Legacy Americans, by pursuing a federal hate-crime trial of the McMichaels and Bryan—scheduled to convene next year.</p>
<p>Meanwhile the state of Georgia, led by “Republican” Gov. Brian Kemp, will also send a message by prosecuting former Brunswick Circuit DA Jackie Johnson—the first one to recuse herself, remember—for “obstruction of justice.” This will ensure that, the next time a black person in Georgia is killed by whites for any reason whatsoever, local DAs will show the proper Stakhanovite zeal in prosecuting.</p>
<p><strong>Flaws in the Law</strong></p>
<p>Note that Georgia law defines the kind of murder alleged in the case as follows:</p>
<p style="padding-left: 40px;">(a) A person commits the offense of murder when he unlawfully and with malice aforethought, either express or implied, causes the death of another human being.</p>
<p style="padding-left: 40px;">(b) Express malice is that deliberate intention unlawfully to take the life of another human being which is manifested by external circumstances capable of proof. Malice shall be implied where no considerable provocation appears and where all the circumstances of the killing show an abandoned and malignant heart.</p>
<p style="padding-left: 40px;">(c) A person commits the offense of murder when, in the commission of a felony, he or she causes the death of another human being irrespective of malice.</p>
<p>Did “<em>all the circumstances of the killing</em> show an abandoned and malignant heart” on the part of Travis McMichael? The answer is obviously <em>no</em>. He did not shoot Arbery from the window of his truck as he would have done had his intent been murderous; he phoned 911 prior to the fatal encounter; he did not flee the scene of the killing; he was shaken by that killing because he had not expected it; and he cooperated with the police who came to the scene. If he had an “abandoned and malignant heart” (why are these vague and archaic descriptors even allowed in the legal code?) he would have acted like a typical premeditated killer, shooting Arbery in a way that would not implicate himself, and denying involvement if questioned. I can imagine that a lot of American men who are forced to live with the problem of Black crime will now prefer that option, at least those men who are not totally demoralized by show trials like these.</p>
<p>The bigger problem here is the implied notion, noted above, that even mildly overinterpreting a citizen’s arrest law, as any concerned citizen might easily do without bad intent, can abruptly (by the whim of a biased jury) turn the citizen into a felon, and then a murderer if he has to defend himself against the arrestee’s violence. If such a notion were valid, a citizen’s arrest law would be worse than worthless. It would be as if the government invited motorists to drive across a very long and narrow, guardrail-less bridge over a mile-deep gorge, having positioned it in such a way that the bridge constantly swayed and shimmied in the wind. It effectively would be no bridge at all—only a deathtrap for the unwary.</p>
<p><strong>The Malignant Heart of the Matter<br />
</strong></p>
<p>Is there even any point in arguing over the legal questions at the heart of such cases? I can remember many racially tinged travesties of justice in my adult life, going back at least to the O.J. Simpson trial of 1995. These cases always feel like inversions of the <em>To Kill a Mockingbird </em>setup—either an apparently guilty black man goes free or gets off lightly, or a wrongfully prosecuted white man has his life ruined. More importantly, the process by which these injustices occur is always (as in Harper Lee’s model of 1930s small-town Alabama) a social process involving race politics and the venality and cowardice of witnesses, prosecutors, jurors, politicians and reporters. Tom Wolfe somehow got away with writing a big novel,<em> Bonfire of the Vanities</em>, about the modern versions of these circuses, a novel that even in 1987 conveyed strongly the message that American society and its judicial system had been irretrievably broken by decades of racial factionalism in its politics.</p>
<p>Similarly, what really drew my attention to this case was the evidence of race-politics pressure on DAs and politicians, the jury’s disregard for the basic evidence that should have exonerated the defendants, and then, above all, the overwhelmingly positive, smug reaction to the verdict by so many Americans.</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" class="wp-image-298 aligncenter" src="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/latimes.jpg" alt="" width="516" height="432" srcset="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/latimes.jpg 598w, https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/latimes-300x251.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 516px) 85vw, 516px" /></p>
<p><img loading="lazy" class=" wp-image-299 aligncenter" src="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/uygur.jpg" alt="" width="510" height="131" srcset="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/uygur.jpg 621w, https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/uygur-300x77.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 510px) 85vw, 510px" /></p>
<p><img loading="lazy" class=" wp-image-300 aligncenter" src="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/king.jpg" alt="" width="434" height="272" srcset="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/king.jpg 610w, https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/king-300x188.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 434px) 85vw, 434px" /></p>
<p>Of course, Twitter and social media generally are full of people who can cheaply virtue-signal while never having to deal with the unhappy realities afflicting ordinary Americans. Stephen King, for example, lives in a humongous complex on a barrier-island beach south of Sarasota—I know because I once lived nearby—at the least accessible extremity of a wealthy neighborhood that was designed by its residents to keep out the riffraff, including anyone who looks remotely like Ahmaud Arbery. From that fortress King is unlikely ever to have to face the problem of burglary or thievery, and anyway any losses from such property crime would be infinitesimal in their impact on him.</p>
<p>But I think virtue-signaling is only a small and secondary part of this. Over the past few years, and especially since the COVID pandemic started, the more or less diffuse growth of wokeness in American life seems to have cohered into a Salem-like mass hysteria&#8212;arguably almost as deadly as Salem, and much more durable. I’ve even had the vague sense (from a distance, as an expatriate) that this hysteria has developed into a kind of cult, the cult of Woke, presided over by an imagined black demon-god, or purple-haired Gender Studies goddess, who in strident tones demands a constant flow of human sacrifices. (Another <a href="https://vdare.com/articles/john-derbyshire-the-arbery-show-trial-begins-more-human-sacrifices-to-appease-the-blm-gods">writer</a> elaborated this human-sacrifice concept before me, so I will mostly leave that imagery to him.)</p>
<p>The centrality of pictures and videos in such cases should give us a clue to how these weird social phenomen arise. If, let us say, a young black man, a man like Ahmaud Arbery, is found dead in the street by gunshot one day, but there is no video evidence of how he was killed, what will be the public reaction? The reader knows the answer already, because such cases occur many times per day across the US, especially in heavily black cities such as Chicago, St. Louis, Detroit and Baltimore. There is generally <em>no</em> reaction, <em>no</em> wider resonance. The man’s family may weep. They may call on the police to solve the crime. But only if the cops identify a white suspect (a relatively rare event) will the case make out of the back pages of the papers, and only if the white-on-black killing is caught on video (much rarer) will the case be lifted from the muck of the ordinary criminal court docket into the glare of a Woke Cult show trial.</p>
<p>People in general, and I guess women moreso than men on average, are apt to be distressed when they witness—for example on a video—a violent death. The distress in turn creates a sense of urgency <em>to do something</em>. (Consider how heavily US foreign and immigration policies in recent years have been <a href="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/the-great-feminization/">driven</a> by distressing images in the media, e.g., of wounded children in Syria.) Distress also tends to suppress rational thought, making the mind more susceptible to the beating tom-toms (to paraphrase McLuhan) of mass delusion and madness. And when a killing depicted on a distressing video can be made to seem even remotely consistent with the central wokelore motif of <em>evil whites harming innocent blacks</em>—that very live snarl of wires in the American psyche—the mass delusion and madness will come together and start to lurch in a predictable direction. It will start to be controlled and guided, to do meaningful political work, by a political faction that I would say definitely has “an abandoned and malignant heart.”</p>
<p>It seems to me that there are usually two main group of actors in such cases: blacks who from basic instinct or family ties support fellow blacks in conflicts with whites, and a certain large stratum of white women who have, in regard to blacks, a powerful guilt and appeasement reflex. Once those two groups start up and gather steam, craven politicians and their judicial minions join in with the rapidity of scurrying rodents, and then the superorganism swells to its maximum size with the additions of journalists and millions of ordinary and celebrity virtue-signalers. This frenzied entity of many voices and noises somehow achieves a certain harmony as it demands “justice,” which is code for: give us a white victim.</p>
<p>One cannot overemphasize how uninterested in truth is this entity. In the case of Derek Chauvin, the entity assured us that the smirk on Chauvin’s face as he held down George Floyd was simply his sadist-cop’s delight at the approaching demise of his poor African American victim. Chauvin was a police officer with long experience of having to deal with unruly and bullshitting black perps, and of course did not have the clairvoyance to know that this particular perp, this one unlucky time, was telling the truth—but try explaining that to some vapor-brained leftist millennial or wine-aunt who is caught up in the full guilt-hate-love ecstasy of the Awokening.</p>
<p>Incidentally, what about Kyle Rittenhouse? How did he avoid becoming a sacrificial victim like Chauvin and the McMichaels? Well, obviously, the facts of that case favored Rittenhouse very strongly. But perhaps more importantly, Rittenhouse is a cherubic boy who probably aroused the protective maternal instincts of many American women—instincts that are normally directed toward the shooting victim in such cases, especially when the victim is black. (A common theme among anti-Rittenhouse partisans was that the men he shot <em>were</em> black, though in fact they were all white.)</p>
<p>In Georgia, of course, the victim was indeed black and the accused were mostly middle-aged southern whites who drove pickup trucks, carried guns, probably had a few Confederate flags around, and probably held African Americans in low esteem. On the great totem pole of wokeism, these men were the lowest of the low.</p>
<p>Speaking of which, I still think there is something instructive in the resemblance of these contemporary orgies of human destruction to ancient religious ceremonies in which sacrifices (often of people from the lowest, most marginalized castes) were made to some higher being. Certainly it is plausible that tens of thousands of years of primitve religion have worn such paths into our minds, such that both the willing participants in the Great Awokening and their appalled opponents (like me) may sometimes experience the illusion that an angry god is present and wants to be appeased.</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" class="size-full wp-image-302 aligncenter" src="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/floyd.jpg" alt="" width="529" height="730" srcset="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/floyd.jpg 529w, https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/floyd-217x300.jpg 217w" sizes="(max-width: 529px) 85vw, 529px" /></p>
<p>It will never stay appeased for long, though, will it? And one wonders: as evidence accumulates that America’s grand racial experiment has failed,  will Americans ever face up to that failure and respond rationally? Or will that failure just drive them crazier and crazier, as it drives more victims into the maw of the Woke god?</p>
<p style="text-align: center;">***</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>WHAT TO DO ABOUT WOKEISM</title>
		<link>https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/what-to-do-about-wokeism/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[j stone]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sat, 20 Nov 2021 23:44:06 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[fall of the West]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[USA]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[wokeism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[women]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://thoughtsofstone.com/?p=253</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[If you must do something, do this one thing &#160; Wokeism with its inversions and distortions of normal humane thinking, and its ability to spread rapidly among susceptible minds, is a mental and cultural plague, pandemically infectious and harmful. What can we do about it? One option, of course, is to hunker down and do &#8230; <a href="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/what-to-do-about-wokeism/" class="more-link">Continue reading<span class="screen-reader-text"> "WHAT TO DO ABOUT WOKEISM"</span></a>]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><em>If you must do something, do this one thing</em></p>
<p><span id="more-253"></span></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>Wokeism with its inversions and distortions of normal humane thinking, and its ability to spread rapidly among susceptible minds, is a mental and cultural plague, pandemically infectious and harmful. What can we do about it?</p>
<p>One option, of course, is to hunker down and do nothing, in the hope that wokeism resolves on its own, as a plague usually does—becoming less extreme as it adapts better to its hosts, or staying extreme until everyone who hasn’t been driven nuts by it has developed strong defenses against it.</p>
<p>Doing nothing probably seems a plausible option to many. In the United States, the Democratic Party’s recent wholehearted embrace of wokeism seems to have made it markedly less popular among voters than it would have been otherwise. Conceivably, the party is now so dominated by this ideology in its leadership, its elite donors, its media enablers, and its city-burning activists, that it can’t change direction, and in future elections will run full-speed off an electoral cliff.</p>
<p>I’m skeptical, though, about the wisdom of doing nothing. When a new and dangerous disease arises, the proper response is to look for its cause and then find ways to block or otherwise neutralize that cause. Wokeism also strikes me as being too robust and malignant to leave alone.</p>
<p>Wokeism is robust because, for all its absurdity as an ideology (at least, to some of us who oppose it), it offers material benefits to many people, especially those who are not what we might call Legacy Americans. These people, these non-Legacy-Americans, occupy, for obvious reasons, an increasing share of the American electorate. Even when wokeism offends them, for example by imposing “critical race theory” (CRT) or wokeist sexual degeneracy on their children in school, they recognize this mindset as a force that promotes their advancement over Legacy Americans—and probably for many of them that “pro” is more important than the “cons.” Did you think the recent GOP victory in the Virginia governor’s race spelled the end of wokeism? It didn’t—the margin of victory was very thin. The wokeists may need only to dial down the ferocity of their attack on Legacy America to start winning again.</p>
<p>There is also the problem of <a href="https://thoughtsofstone.com/the-critical-mass-problem/">women’s susceptibility to wokeism</a>—especially those women who help run major US industries and institutions, including media, government, science, medicine, law, and education, and thus have an outsized impact on the culture. This inter-institutional gynocracy is arguably the true “Deep State”—maybe we should call it the Deep Pink State—and isn’t going away any time soon, given that the current US political and legal system offers no formal or informal mechanism for getting rid of it. Conservative white males <em>can</em> be gotten rid of by the informal Inquisitional network known as Cancel Culture; but white females are still mostly untouchable, especially if they are woke—they are the Cancellers, not the cancelled.</p>
<p>Even if its membership cannot be uprooted, can the Deep Pink State be somehow controlled? For example, at present, the legislatures of various conservative-leaning states are passing laws banning CRT, 1619 Project nonsense, or other specific elements of wokeism from classrooms or state and local government offices. Can this work?</p>
<p>Well, think about it. In places where the education system, the administrative structures of government, corporate HR departments, etc.  are substantially infiltrated by the women—especially single women—that make up wokeism’s religious hard core, isn’t it likely that any legislated “ban” of wokeism is going to be effectively nullified by these institutionally embedded believers? It’s pretty easy to imagine them continuing to teach, preach, propagandize, evangelize, and catechize, using the same wokeist gospels but now with different labels—or with those labels but with more stealth and indirection. It’s also easy to imagine these wokeistas banding together with even more solidarity, seeing themselves, of course, as history’s heroines, freedom fighters, eager martyrs for the glorious cause. There will be no end to the drama.</p>
<p>So, if “banning CRT” or other elements of wokeism is unlikely to work as intended, and if the average soft-hearted American recoils in horror from the idea of more direct and definitive measures, e.g., banning wokeists from culturally influential professions, or even exiling them to hopelessly wokeified countries such as Canada, what is there to be done?</p>
<p><strong>Try Just This One Thing</strong></p>
<p>I’ve proposed in a long series of essays (e.g., <a href="https://thoughtsofstone.com/the-great-feminization/">here</a> and <a href="https://thoughtsofstone.com/the-day-the-logic-died/">here</a>) that the spread of wokeism and many other striking cultural shifts of recent decades is due largely to the new and unprecedented cultural and political power of women. Put simply, this putative “pink shift” in Western societies has resulted from the essentially maternal mindset of women being brought out of its traditional domain of the home into the wider world of public affairs, a realm for which it was not adapted by biological/cultural evolution.</p>
<p>In other words, women’s maternal instincts—and I would guess that the instincts of single and/or empty-nest women are especially ungrounded or unhinged in this sense—are now at work in cultural and policy realms and bias women towards what are often faulty solutions. These include the sentimental encouragement of mass-immigration, overgenerous welfare, and discrimination in favor of the “traditionally disadvantaged,” as well as aversions to freedom of speech, free scientific inquiry, and due process of law. While such policies and attitudes wouldn’t necessarily be problematic in a home setting, I think are bound to be ruinous at the level of public policy.</p>
<p>As I’ve also written, one of the most striking things about this “great feminization” is the effective suppression of mentions of it in the mainstream media. I suspect that this is part of the whole feminization process. In other words, the female editors who now gatekeep mainstream cultural information from Hollywood to Madison Ave. and toe the women-are-oppressed feminist line, aren’t about to allow the portrayal of themselves as having real political and cultural power&#8212;let alone as having used that power to wreck the civilization that empowered them.</p>
<p>For their part, male writers and editors, having seen too many of their brethren thrown on the breadlines already, generally don’t want to cross their female colleagues by writing or publishing something that could draw the label “misogynist screed” and get them sent to the stake. Remember NYT science writer <a href="https://www.thewrap.com/ny-times-newsroom-in-chaos-over-departures-fears-of-cancel-culture/">Donald McNeil Jr.</a>? How about NYT editor <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2020/06/07/business/media/james-bennet-resigns-nytimes-op-ed.html">James Bennett</a>? Every man in Western MSM journalism knows that he could be next, and for the airiest of reasons.</p>
<p>I should add that, having tried and failed to get even very softened versions of my hypothesis published in many conservative venues, I have glimpsed a similar dynamic—I think partly rooted in worries over losing female subscribers and contributors—that serves to suppress this idea even on the right.</p>
<p>On the other hand, we still have an Internet, on which ideas still circulate relatively widely and freely, including ideas rejected by the MSM—and things that get big on the Internet usually make their way into the MSM eventually. The “great feminization” idea hasn’t quite made it to the big time yet, but thanks to some popular <a href="https://marginalrevolution.com/marginalrevolution/2021/10/wednesday-assorted-links-316.html">linkers</a>, <a href="https://americanmind.org/salvo/pink-shift/"><em>The American Mind</em></a>, and some behind-the-scenes assistance from other (female as well as male) writers, it has been getting many tens of thousands of views, including by some potentially very influential people.</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" class="size-full wp-image-266 aligncenter" src="https://thoughtsofstone.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/11/senate-1.jpg" alt="" width="491" height="94" srcset="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2021/11/senate-1.jpg 491w, https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2021/11/senate-1-300x57.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 491px) 85vw, 491px" /></p>
<p>Anyhow, what I suggest is that people can combat wokeism simply by encouraging the circulation and discussion, on the Internet or wherever else they can, of this hypothesis that wokeism and related cultural shifts are only the downstream effects of cultural/elite feminization&#8212;i.e., of a maternal mindset that is dangerously out of its depth. If, having that hypothesis to guide them, people start to see supporting examples every day and become convinced of the peril to their civilization—then wokeism will be undermined, and I think that at least in its most excessive forms it ultimately must collapse.</p>
<p><em>Collapse</em> is one metaphor, although <em>melt</em>—from the dissolving effects of better knowledge—may be more apt.</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" class="size-full wp-image-256 aligncenter" src="https://thoughtsofstone.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/11/melting.jpg" alt="" width="631" height="486" srcset="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2021/11/melting.jpg 631w, https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2021/11/melting-300x231.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 709px) 85vw, (max-width: 909px) 67vw, (max-width: 984px) 61vw, (max-width: 1362px) 45vw, 600px" /></p>
<p><em>To what end?</em> the wokeists cry! Do we want to silence women? Do we want to declare them unfit for public life, turning the clock back 200 years and confining them to the home?</p>
<p>Well, no—anyway <em>I</em> don’t want that. I think there is room for some rollback of women’s employment in very important professions, such as the military and police, in which men have certain innate advantages and women are apt to cause unhelpful distraction by their presence. But on the whole I think the solution to the “pink shift” problem is to limit the damage that <em>any</em> demographic group can do when it is captured by some infectious ideology to which it is especially susceptible.</p>
<p>In other words, I think the solution is broadly to limit the power of government, corporations, media, etc. to suppress or to alter the essentials of a sustainable and relatively liberal Western civilization, including the traditional virtues, structures and drives relating to family formation, free-ish markets, due process of law, and free scientific inquiry. No one has benefited more from this liberal civilization than women! And perhaps as women look around at all the burning, looting, anarchy and madness that wokeism promotes, they may start to agree&#8212;like the many female refugees from the similar excesses of the 1960s&#8212;that in a tough world where women are still the weaker sex, wokeism ultimately isn&#8217;t going to be good for them.</p>
<p style="text-align: center;">***</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
