<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>wokeism &#8211; Thoughts of Stone</title>
	<atom:link href="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/category/wokeism/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/</link>
	<description>short essays, usually about humans</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Sat, 09 Jul 2022 21:46:57 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=6.0.1</generator>

<image>
	<url>https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2020/07/cropped-icon-32x32.jpg</url>
	<title>wokeism &#8211; Thoughts of Stone</title>
	<link>https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/</link>
	<width>32</width>
	<height>32</height>
</image> 
	<item>
		<title>A SPIRALING FRENZY</title>
		<link>https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/a-spiraling-frenzy/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[j stone]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 07 Jul 2022 23:44:52 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[ethnicity]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[fall of the West]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[human ecology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[immigration]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[psychology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[USA]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[wokeism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[women]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/?p=590</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[The Great Awokening as a social mania In prior essays on this site and elsewhere, I’ve argued that the spread of wokeness and its recent marked intensification (the &#8220;Great Awokening&#8221;) is best seen as a social contagion—of feelings and sociocultural ideas that broadly reflect women’s maternal instincts, and are much more transmissible among women than &#8230; <a href="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/a-spiraling-frenzy/" class="more-link">Continue reading<span class="screen-reader-text"> "A SPIRALING FRENZY"</span></a>]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><em>The Great Awokening as a social mania<br />
</em></p>
<p><span id="more-590"></span></p>
<p>In prior essays on this <a href="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/the-critical-mass-problem/">site</a> and <a href="https://americanmind.org/salvo/pink-shift/">elsewhere</a>, I’ve argued that the spread of wokeness and its recent marked intensification (the &#8220;Great Awokening&#8221;) is best seen as a social contagion—of feelings and sociocultural ideas that broadly reflect women’s maternal instincts, and are much more transmissible among women than among men.</p>
<p>I’ve also suggested that wokeness is apt to be ultra-transmissible among females whose feminine, maternal energies aren’t absorbed by husbands and children and may seek another outlet. The terms “cat lady” and “wine aunt” refer to a subset of these individuals, but many unmarried girls and young women, as well as successful career women, also fit this description.</p>
<p>I’ve proposed, moreover, that wokeness is driven into institutions not just by the conversion of (especially female) workers already in place but also by the <a href="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/always-be-capturing/"><em>takeover</em> </a>of those institutions by women and tamed males, via biased hiring.</p>
<p>I’m more certain now than ever that all these hypotheses are correct, as far as they go. But I think there is one more aspect of wokeness that requires an explanation. I’m referring to what could be called wokeness’s <em>spiraling frenzy</em>—its tendency to move away from norms of belief and behavior and towards extremes, wherever it takes hold.</p>
<p>To put it another way: The woke women and their enablers who in the past decade or two have effectively taken control of virtually all major American institutions and professions have not been content to implement a modest set of reforms and leave it at that. As their power has grown, they have increasingly attacked the core values of Western civilization: everything from due process of law to meritocracy to the shielding of children from sexual deviants and predators. As their policies have become extreme, so have their methods. They have made it clear that they don’t want sober deliberations—they want emotional shock and awe!</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" class="size-full wp-image-597 aligncenter" src="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2022/07/femen2-1.jpg" alt="" width="800" height="595" srcset="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2022/07/femen2-1.jpg 800w, https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2022/07/femen2-1-300x223.jpg 300w, https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2022/07/femen2-1-768x571.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 709px) 85vw, (max-width: 909px) 67vw, (max-width: 984px) 61vw, (max-width: 1362px) 45vw, 600px" /></p>
<p><img loading="lazy" class="size-full wp-image-594 aligncenter" src="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2022/07/femen1.jpg" alt="" width="800" height="451" srcset="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2022/07/femen1.jpg 800w, https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2022/07/femen1-300x169.jpg 300w, https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2022/07/femen1-768x433.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 709px) 85vw, (max-width: 909px) 67vw, (max-width: 984px) 61vw, (max-width: 1362px) 45vw, 600px" /></p>
<p><img loading="lazy" class="size-full wp-image-601 aligncenter" src="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2022/07/bloodprotest1.jpg" alt="" width="700" height="357" srcset="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2022/07/bloodprotest1.jpg 700w, https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2022/07/bloodprotest1-300x153.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 709px) 85vw, (max-width: 909px) 67vw, (max-width: 984px) 61vw, (max-width: 1362px) 45vw, 600px" /></p>
<p><img loading="lazy" class="size-full wp-image-604 aligncenter" src="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2022/07/6611fddd-8ba3-49ac-8eec-43537e9c4aa5-12__AP_Senate_Supreme_Court.3.jpg" alt="" width="800" height="529" srcset="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2022/07/6611fddd-8ba3-49ac-8eec-43537e9c4aa5-12__AP_Senate_Supreme_Court.3.jpg 800w, https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2022/07/6611fddd-8ba3-49ac-8eec-43537e9c4aa5-12__AP_Senate_Supreme_Court.3-300x198.jpg 300w, https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2022/07/6611fddd-8ba3-49ac-8eec-43537e9c4aa5-12__AP_Senate_Supreme_Court.3-768x508.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 709px) 85vw, (max-width: 909px) 67vw, (max-width: 984px) 61vw, (max-width: 1362px) 45vw, 600px" /></p>
<p><img loading="lazy" class="size-full wp-image-599 aligncenter" src="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2022/07/crazy-teacher.jpg" alt="" width="800" height="457" srcset="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2022/07/crazy-teacher.jpg 800w, https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2022/07/crazy-teacher-300x171.jpg 300w, https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2022/07/crazy-teacher-768x439.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 709px) 85vw, (max-width: 909px) 67vw, (max-width: 984px) 61vw, (max-width: 1362px) 45vw, 600px" /></p>
<p><img loading="lazy" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-606" src="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2022/07/crazy1.jpg" alt="" width="800" height="530" srcset="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2022/07/crazy1.jpg 800w, https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2022/07/crazy1-300x199.jpg 300w, https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2022/07/crazy1-768x509.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 709px) 85vw, (max-width: 909px) 67vw, (max-width: 984px) 61vw, (max-width: 1362px) 45vw, 600px" /></p>
<p><img loading="lazy" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-607" src="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2022/07/crazy2.jpg" alt="" width="600" height="607" srcset="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2022/07/crazy2.jpg 600w, https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2022/07/crazy2-297x300.jpg 297w" sizes="(max-width: 709px) 85vw, (max-width: 909px) 67vw, (max-width: 984px) 61vw, (max-width: 1362px) 45vw, 600px" /></p>
<p><img loading="lazy" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-608" src="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2022/07/crazy3.jpg" alt="" width="800" height="449" srcset="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2022/07/crazy3.jpg 800w, https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2022/07/crazy3-300x168.jpg 300w, https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2022/07/crazy3-768x431.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 709px) 85vw, (max-width: 909px) 67vw, (max-width: 984px) 61vw, (max-width: 1362px) 45vw, 600px" /></p>
<p>One could argue that there is a counter-cultural logic to this movement—that it wants to collapse the existing order as completely as those hijacked planes collapsed the Twin Towers on 9/11.</p>
<p>But is the Great Awokening replacing the old culture with a new one that can bind society sustainably&#8212;a &#8220;successor ideology&#8221;?</p>
<p>Wokeness and the Great Awokening are driven chiefly by women, who have their own ways of thinking and persuading&#8212;ways that typically seem more emotional and less rational than men&#8217;s. So one might suppose that there <em>is</em> a genuine ideology being built here, albeit a feminine one that seems alien to the average male, and that the Great Awokening is just the final, dramatic dash in this &#8220;<a href="https://americanmind.org/salvo/pink-shift/">pink shift</a>&#8221; takeover of Western culture.</p>
<p>However, to me, that&#8217;s not the full story. To me, the Great Awokening&#8217;s spiraling frenzy, and its attraction for people who are evidently mentally ill, suggest that it is for the most part only a temporary and reactive social phenomenon: a social &#8220;mania.&#8221;</p>
<p><strong>Logic and Madness</strong></p>
<p>As many have noted, the Great Awokening bears a strong resemblance to the Chinese Cultural Revolution of 1966-76.</p>
<p>The CCR’s spearpoints were cadres of “Red Guard” fanatics, young people (even teens) whose instability and restlessness, suggestibility, and high susceptibility to fanaticism were probably comparable to what one finds in today’s millennial Antifa brigades. These howling Maoist minions sought the erasure of whatever competed with Maoism, which in practice meant just about anything predating Maoist China—history books, art, architecture, temples, even genealogical records. Red Guards and their camp followers toppled statues of Confucius, pasted huge banners with their slogans everywhere, and went around attacking intellectuals or anyone even lightly connected to the teaching of pre-Maoist history or philosophy.</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-366" src="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2022/01/fourolds.jpg" alt="" width="1000" height="750" srcset="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2022/01/fourolds.jpg 1000w, https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2022/01/fourolds-300x225.jpg 300w, https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2022/01/fourolds-768x576.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 709px) 85vw, (max-width: 909px) 67vw, (max-width: 1362px) 62vw, 840px" /></p>
<p>That was the counter-cultural logic part of it. But there was also the crazypants part—shocking, obscene, savage stuff, ultimately including murder and even cannibalism.</p>
<p style="padding-left: 40px;">At some high schools, students killed their principals in the school courtyard and then cooked and ate the bodies to celebrate a triumph over &#8220;counterrevolutionaries&#8221; &#8230;  Government-run cafeterias are said to have displayed bodies dangling on meat hooks and to have served human flesh to employees. [<a href="https://www.nytimes.com/1993/01/06/world/a-tale-of-red-guards-and-cannibals.html">NYT</a>]</p>
<p>Not content with attacking living reminders of the old China, Red Guards also broke into cemeteries and dug up the skeletal remains of ancient Chinese emperors and nobles, desecrating them and denouncing the persons these remains had once been.</p>
<p>Other examples of these social frenzies come to mind. In some of the pre-Christian feasts of Rome and northern Europe, open drunkenness and debauchery, and various other intentionally shocking inversions of everyday social norms, were encouraged, at least in part as cathartic but controlled ventings of accumulated stress. (Modern parties, especially the ones teens and young adults have, seem like echoes of these displays.) As Samuel Johnson famously said, “He who makes a beast of himself gets rid of the pain of being a man.”</p>
<p>Or a woman. The infamous <a href="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/girl-power/">convent hysterias</a> of 1500s-1700s Europe supply many illustrations of spiraling frenzies among women, especially sexually frustrated younger ones. In the 1632-34 Loudoun case, for example, at a public exorcism of supposedly demon-possessed Ursuline nuns, a Sister Claire “fell on the ground, blaspheming, in convulsions, lifting up her petticoats and chemise, displaying her privy parts without any shame, and uttering filthy words. Her gestures became so indecent that the audience averted its eyes.” [<a href="https://www.thriftbooks.com/w/the-encyclopedia-of-witchcraft-and-demonology/8811250/">link</a>]</p>
<p>Sexual themes dominated the antics of “possessed” nuns, although there were maternal—or inverted maternal—themes too, for example claims of mystical pregnancy, and stories of secret witch conclaves (“witches’ sabbaths”) at which children were eaten.</p>
<p>Themes of sexual violation and impregnation, theft or killing of unborn babies, and witchcraft, along with the same spiraling of fantastic claims and odd behavior, were also typical in the medicalized versions of possession—&#8221;multiple personality disorder” and “UFO abduction”—that were popular among young women in the 1970-90s, and ended up discrediting many therapists and psychiatrists, as well as the whole idea of &#8220;hypnotically recovered memories.&#8221;</p>
<p>To me, these are examples of social manias&#8212;not just contagions (for even healthy, sustainable behaviors can be contagious) but contagions that spread intense and increasingly bizarre, often counter-cultural activities, and are essentially reactions to excessive stress.</p>
<p><strong>A holiday from stress and inhibition</strong></p>
<p>As the comment by Dr. Johnson implies, human beings in modern civilizations are inhibited and stressed by the social rules they are supposed to obey and the complex social environments they are supposed to navigate—the “pain of being a man.”</p>
<p>It makes sense that women nowadays would be relatively hard-hit by such stresses. Women’s basic lifestyle has shifted dramatically—much more than men’s has—over the past few generations. Women during this interval generally have had to face new stresses from:</p>
<ul>
<li style="list-style-type: none;">
<ul>
<li>higher education and the pressures at higher levels of the working world;</li>
<li>the postponement or abandonment of marriage and child-bearing;</li>
<li>a new (or newly de-civilized) courtship environment in which their natural desire for love and motherhood is taken advantage of again and again without being fulfilled.</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<p>All the while, women have been told (by the most authoritative sources, including Hollywood and feminist activists) that these changes represent &#8220;progress&#8221; and must not be resisted.</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-609" src="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2022/07/sexandthecity1.jpg" alt="" width="800" height="550" srcset="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2022/07/sexandthecity1.jpg 800w, https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2022/07/sexandthecity1-300x206.jpg 300w, https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2022/07/sexandthecity1-768x528.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 709px) 85vw, (max-width: 909px) 67vw, (max-width: 984px) 61vw, (max-width: 1362px) 45vw, 600px" /></p>
<p>Women also, compared to men, appear to have an innately greater desire for “equality” and social harmony. Yet these lofty, sentimental social goals, during the same critical period, have slipped—frustratingly—further and further out of reach, as the West has intensified its effort to remake itself as a highly multi-racial/ethnic civilization.</p>
<p>In addition to having to face these new stresses, women are (on average) more emotionally sensitive than men, and thus are apt to be more affected by the same stressors.</p>
<p>Small wonder, then, that a very large proportion of women and girls in Western societies can now expect to be diagnosed with a mood or anxiety disorder. It probably also should be unsurprising that the essentially feminine notion of “trauma”—a highly stressing psychological injury—has now taken on an <a href="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/the-great-feminization/">outsized role</a> not only in Western medicine but also in the wider culture.</p>
<p>On the whole, then, the recent changes in the standard female lifeway, and the demographic makeovers of Western societies, have created a large and chronic background level of stress for women. But the severe emotional contagion of the Great Awokening was triggered only after additional, more acute stressors appeared in the first half of 2020: the pandemic with its lockdowns, social isolation, and widespread fears of illness/death; and then the inflammatory treatment—by left-leaning media, activists, and politicians—of various police killings of miscreant African Americans.</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-225" src="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2021/06/bethesdaawokening-1.jpg" alt="" width="800" height="450" srcset="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2021/06/bethesdaawokening-1.jpg 800w, https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2021/06/bethesdaawokening-1-300x169.jpg 300w, https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2021/06/bethesdaawokening-1-768x432.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 709px) 85vw, (max-width: 909px) 67vw, (max-width: 984px) 61vw, (max-width: 1362px) 45vw, 600px" /></p>
<p>Thus I think one can fairly easily fit the Great Awokening into the broader category of stress-induced, stress-relieving social manias. Amid the furious revels of such manias, inhibitions are necessarily going to be relaxed (for some more than others, of course) and people who were relatively labile, even frankly nuts, to begin with will also be drawn in, given the camouflage these frenzies provide for their behavioral issues.</p>
<p><strong>The function of boundary-pushing</strong></p>
<p>A social mania—one that is true to the concept of mania—cannot run forever. It must end by depleting its energy source or by inducing resistance, just as an individual with psychiatric mania will become exhausted after many days without adequate sleep, and/or will cause herself to be hospitalized and treated by exhibiting increasingly abnormal behavior. If a social mania’s deep purpose is to relieve accumulated social pressures, then its tendency to be ever more immoderate might even be seen as <em>functional</em>—in the sense that the spiraling further and further away from social norms serves to reduce support and induce opposition, thus limiting the damage while allowing the requisite venting of steam. To put it crudely, a social mania with its spiraling frenzy is a societal “cry for help.”</p>
<p>This is all speculative. It’s also a group-level, forest-not-the-trees view that people with an ordinary individualistic bias might find hard to wrap their heads around. But it’s a novel take that I (obviously) think should be considered. On the whole, it suggests that the Great Awokening should interest us less as a new cultural movement, and more as a <em>signal</em> indicating deep problems with the existing culture and society. In other words, it’s a social version of a seismic tremor, or even earthquake, and its intensity and direction of slip are interesting mainly for what they tell us about the underlying stresses at work—stresses that are unbearable and thus have be relieved, in one way or another.</p>
<p style="text-align: center;">***</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>ALWAYS BE CAPTURING</title>
		<link>https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/always-be-capturing/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[j stone]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 06 Apr 2022 02:36:36 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[psychology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[USA]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[wokeism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[women]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/?p=531</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[The ubiquity of “kulturkampf” &#160; I’ve already written a lot of essays about women’s maternal and other sex-specific traits, and how the mass entry of women into public life, in the last several decades, has brought those feminine traits to bear on culture and politics, driving extensive and ongoing changes in Western societies. I am &#8230; <a href="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/always-be-capturing/" class="more-link">Continue reading<span class="screen-reader-text"> "ALWAYS BE CAPTURING"</span></a>]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><em>The ubiquity of “kulturkampf”</em></p>
<p><span id="more-531"></span></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>I’ve already written <a href="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/cultural-feminization-a-bibliography/">a lot of essays</a> about women’s maternal and other sex-specific traits, and how the mass entry of women into public life, in the last several decades, has brought those feminine traits to bear on culture and politics, driving extensive and ongoing changes in Western societies.</p>
<p>I am convinced more than ever that that &#8220;great feminization&#8221; argument is essentially correct. But there is another facet of male/female cultural competition that I have mostly overlooked until now. It’s really something that relates to groups in general, not just to women, but I think it’s especially relevant to the current female-driven social transformations of Western societies.</p>
<p>The idea here is that, when women a few decades ago began to achieve parity/dominance <em>vis-</em><em>à</em><em>-vis</em> men in professions and institutions across the West, they <em>automatically</em> set up a rivalry, a “battle of the sexes,” in each of these professions and institutions. Why? Not because of any particular “female” or “male” trait, but simply because the two sexes are <em>different in general</em>. They have different group identities, different ways of thinking, different group cultures. If only at an instinctive, nonconscious level—and if only to avoid the emotional pain of having to conform to the others’ ways—each has sought dominance over the other.</p>
<p>This certainly seems to be true from women’s perspective. You can hardly open a newspaper or browse news websites these days without encountering lamentations, by female writers, about male workplace behavior—from the mildly irritating to the supposedly traumatizing. These behaviors typically are blamed upon the male domination of the workplace in question, although from my (admittedly biased, male) perspective these complaints often look more like attempts to stamp out the last vestiges of male culture in workplaces that are already significantly feminized.</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-534" src="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2022/04/toxic-masc.jpg" alt="" width="800" height="458" srcset="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2022/04/toxic-masc.jpg 800w, https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2022/04/toxic-masc-300x172.jpg 300w, https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2022/04/toxic-masc-768x440.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 709px) 85vw, (max-width: 909px) 67vw, (max-width: 984px) 61vw, (max-width: 1362px) 45vw, 600px" /></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" class="alignnone wp-image-533" src="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2022/04/city-lads.jpg" alt="" width="511" height="450" srcset="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2022/04/city-lads.jpg 847w, https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2022/04/city-lads-300x264.jpg 300w, https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2022/04/city-lads-768x676.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 511px) 85vw, 511px" /></p>
<p>Women in their workplaces nowadays also—typically with the thinnest of formal rationales—are apt to organize emotional coalitions to oust their male CEOs or other leaders whose ways are insufficiently accommodating to the current female mindset.</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-537" src="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2022/04/lander.jpg" alt="" width="800" height="518" srcset="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2022/04/lander.jpg 800w, https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2022/04/lander-300x194.jpg 300w, https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2022/04/lander-768x497.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 709px) 85vw, (max-width: 909px) 67vw, (max-width: 984px) 61vw, (max-width: 1362px) 45vw, 600px" /></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-540" src="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2022/04/cuomo.jpg" alt="" width="800" height="484" srcset="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2022/04/cuomo.jpg 800w, https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2022/04/cuomo-300x182.jpg 300w, https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2022/04/cuomo-768x465.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 709px) 85vw, (max-width: 909px) 67vw, (max-width: 984px) 61vw, (max-width: 1362px) 45vw, 600px" /></p>
<p><img loading="lazy" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-559" src="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2022/04/nfl.jpg" alt="" width="800" height="535" srcset="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2022/04/nfl.jpg 800w, https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2022/04/nfl-300x201.jpg 300w, https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2022/04/nfl-768x514.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 709px) 85vw, (max-width: 909px) 67vw, (max-width: 984px) 61vw, (max-width: 1362px) 45vw, 600px" /></p>
<p>I suppose that if one ventures into the “manosphere” reaches of the Internet, one will find similar complaints from men trapped in female-dominated institutions. One will strain to find similar victories, though.</p>
<p>On the whole, the institutional battle of the sexes is something that seems to have really crept up on men, creating a challenge for them that they may be unable to surmount. Men, in particular the white, European-derived men who created the institutions of Western civilization, were trying to be progressive and even-handed when they welcomed women into the workplace (they <em>were</em> relatively welcoming, compared to Asians, Arabs, Africans, etc.). They were trying to be meritocratic. Arguably that relatively fair-minded meritocratic mindset was a psychological or cultural trait that helped Western men build their civilization into the powerhouse it was. (Most men also regarded the scaled-up presence of women in the workplace as a colossal and wondrous sexual opportunity.)</p>
<p>What men didn’t reckon with is that women eventually would reach a certain level of presence and power in the institutions and professions where they worked—a critical mass, as it were—and from that point onward would tend to seek not parity but <em>dominance</em>, and by just about any means.</p>
<p>I submit that we are already seeing this reach for (and, frequently, achievement of) female dominance across multiple institutions and professions. While the most visible manifestation is the one I just mentioned&#8212;the noisy cancellation coalition that dislodges a problematic male executive (who is often replaced with a woman)&#8212;women also have been feminizing their institutions, and crowding out men, in much less newsworthy ways, e.g., the practice of “preferred pronouns,” “inclusive,” i.e., non-meritocratic hiring including quotas for female execs and board members, mandatory pro-diversity statements, and feminist/ESG/green constraints on investment and general corporate policy.</p>
<p>The upshot of this organizational capture is, of course, women’s use of these entities to promote the wider feminization of culture and politics—often synonymous with “wokeification”—which, again, I have <a href="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/the-great-feminization/">written about</a> elsewhere.</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-542" src="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2022/04/disneyexec.jpg" alt="" width="800" height="476" srcset="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2022/04/disneyexec.jpg 800w, https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2022/04/disneyexec-300x179.jpg 300w, https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2022/04/disneyexec-768x457.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 709px) 85vw, (max-width: 909px) 67vw, (max-width: 984px) 61vw, (max-width: 1362px) 45vw, 600px" /></p>
<p>Their steamrolling victories suggest that women are much more powerful and effective than men in these institutional struggles, and, in a way, this should be unsurprising: Men presumably have not been under long-term evolutionary or cultural pressure to cope with competition of this kind from women. Women, on the other hand, as the weaker sex, have long had need of “force multiplier” tactics and instincts.</p>
<p>I strongly suspect that women’s greater power derives especially from a set of closely related female traits that include superior emotional sensitivity, superior sociality, superior ability to catch and transmit social contagions, and superior ability to form emotional coalitions—traits that, again, may have evolved not just in support of maternal functions, but also as special weapons in contests with otherwise dominant males. (I have touched on these points in previous essays, e.g., <a href="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/the-day-the-logic-died/">here</a> and <a href="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/girl-power/">here</a>.)</p>
<p>Of course, women also benefit tremendously from the civil rights dogma and legal regime that has gripped the US and some other Western societies for decades now, and often designates women as “traditionally disadvantaged” and thus worthy of favorable treatment, especially <em>vis-à-vis</em> white males.</p>
<p><strong>Other groups</strong></p>
<p>As I suggested at the top of this essay, women’s quest for supremacy within traditionally male institutions/professions is just one specific example of a much more general phenomenon of modernity. In other words, my hypothesis here is that <em>any</em> two (or more) groups that are sufficiently well defined and coherent, with sufficiently distinct group identities and cultures and so on, are bound to vie for control, to some extent, whenever they occupy the same social space.</p>
<p>Ethnic/racial groups are probably the most obvious examples of highly coherent but non-gender-defined groups that we would expect to see in these wars for institutional supremacy. As in the case of women vs. men, some of these ethnic/racial groups, due to their own particular traits, will be better than others in such contests. Immigrants to Western countries, especially those who have to travel from remote parts of the world, already tend to be the smartest, most ambitious, get-up-and-go members of their societies. Moreover, some of those societies are already highly stratified, with highly intelligent, highly entitled, highly ambitious (even ruthless) upper strata—so the immigrants from those upper strata are <em>really</em> going to pose a challenge to Westerners in the context of institutional struggles.</p>
<p>Thus, we are essentially looking at the flip side, the dark side one might say, of the fact that America and other Western countries attract the world’s best: Yes, many of these immigrants are the best, or are at least highly ambitious and sharp-elbowed, but that also means that they may soon have your job—and may even control your organizations.</p>
<p>Additionally, virtually any non-legacy-Western ethnic group is nonwhite, and <em>ipso facto</em> will be granted further strong advantages by contemporary civil rights culture. These advantages, over the past fifty-odd years, have included preferences/quotas in academic admissions, in public and private job hiring, and in government contracting—even when the group’s members have hailed mostly from elite, wealthy castes in the home country, and have not been “disadvantaged” in any sense.</p>
<p>Apart from the very tangible, often windfall-scale benefits of this civil rights regime, there has been, especially in recent decades, a civil rights <em>mindset</em> within organizations, a mindset that provides a further advantage to nonwhite ethnicities. Cloaking themselves in civil rights victimhood, preaching about the need for more diversity and equity, calling out alleged racists and racism, nonwhites can basically activate and direct that mindset as a further, quite powerful tool for displacing legacy Whites, for individual and group benefit.</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-543" src="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2022/04/apoorvam.jpg" alt="" width="361" height="258" srcset="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2022/04/apoorvam.jpg 361w, https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2022/04/apoorvam-300x214.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 361px) 85vw, 361px" /></p>
<p><img loading="lazy" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-544" src="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2022/04/nytstaffers.jpg" alt="" width="800" height="443" srcset="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2022/04/nytstaffers.jpg 800w, https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2022/04/nytstaffers-300x166.jpg 300w, https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2022/04/nytstaffers-768x425.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 709px) 85vw, (max-width: 909px) 67vw, (max-width: 984px) 61vw, (max-width: 1362px) 45vw, 600px" /></p>
<p>I can think of at least several ethnicities that are doing very well in Western societies for the reasons I’ve just described. Indians are probably the most obvious example. They make up only about 1.5 percent of the US population now, and were hardly visible at all in the country half a century ago, but already they are strikingly overrepresented in the ranks of big-company CEOs as well as in other influential professions such as law, medicine, and politics.</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-545" src="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2022/04/indiansceos.jpg" alt="" width="767" height="860" srcset="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2022/04/indiansceos.jpg 767w, https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2022/04/indiansceos-268x300.jpg 268w" sizes="(max-width: 709px) 85vw, (max-width: 909px) 67vw, (max-width: 984px) 61vw, (max-width: 1362px) 45vw, 600px" /></p>
<p>Again, according to this general hypothesis, the struggle for control of institutions and professions could involve any other type of group with a significant presence and a sufficiently distinct and coherent identity. I think there are not many good examples beyond gender- and ethnicity-based groupings, but surely the “LGBTQ community” is one that has had some success in influencing big organizations’ policies.</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-546" src="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2022/04/mcdonalds.jpg" alt="" width="420" height="615" srcset="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2022/04/mcdonalds.jpg 420w, https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2022/04/mcdonalds-205x300.jpg 205w" sizes="(max-width: 420px) 85vw, 420px" /></p>
<p><strong> </strong><strong>A General Hypothesis of Cultural Struggle</strong></p>
<p>To sum up, then, my hypothesis is that a “collective instinct” to vie for supremacy over institutions/professions is something that occurs to some extent, and more or less automatically, even non-consciously, within <em>all</em> well-defined, cohering groups of significant size within those organizations. Different groups will have different traits that affect the intensity of their participation, their strategies, and their overall chances of success in these struggles. Some will also be advantaged or disadvantaged by the surrounding law and culture, e.g., civil rights law and culture.</p>
<p>I am not sure how original this idea is. Certainly, the idea of group culture is not new; nor is the idea of a struggle between cultures—what the Germans call a <em>kulturkampf</em>—novel. But the idea that such a struggle begins almost automatically when two or more rival cultures share a defined social space—a profession, an organization, a country—is one I don’t think I have encountered before.</p>
<p>I may not have emphasized enough that this “struggle” normally, for most of its participants, would be relatively subtle and even non-conscious. We all have our conscious explanations of, and justifications for, the things we do, but clearly there is a lot of other stuff going on under the hood—under the “limen,” the threshold of consciousness, as psychologists call it. Thus, Sanjay from the IT department may not be consciously plotting to dislodge the white CEO of his corporation; <em>but,</em> if asked to sign a petition decrying overheard off-color remarks by his company’s white CEO at a recent company retreat, he may be, <em>ceteris paribus,</em> much more likely to sign it if he knows the replacement CEO will be one of his countrymen—even if he isn’t consciously aware of that knowledge’s influence on him.</p>
<p>Another point to emphasize is that many, maybe most large organizations and institutions will have more than one group vying for control (e.g., women, assorted nonwhites, LGBTQs) against the legacy group (white males). These factions will coalesce and separate as needed, negotiating power-sharing strategies and arrangements, one faction slipstreaming behind another that has more power, and so on—similar to the workings of political parties in a multiparty system.</p>
<p><strong>The uniqueness of whites</strong></p>
<p>I have hesitated to include the legacy managerial class—white males—as combatants in these ubiquitous struggles, for the simple reason that they seldom seem to put up a fight. It’s downright eerie how some of these guys, no matter how innocent, will grovel, apologize, and plaintively attempt to appease when attacked, instead of showing any kind of defiance. It’s also odd that these men are so easily isolated; they are like those hobbled old wildebeests from the nature documentaries: left behind by the panicked herd for the pursuing, shrieking jackals to surround and kill at their leisure.</p>
<p>As for most of this social-psych territory, I can only speculate about the source of white males’ peculiar weakness and apathy. Maybe just having been on top for so long is enough to erode the mojo needed to stay there; maybe success has made us too soft, as the ascendant Greeks of antiquity said of the descendant Persians. Maybe we also developed psychological tools, such as <a href="https://www.theatlantic.com/magazine/archive/2020/10/joseph-henrich-weird-people/615496/">hyper-individualism</a> and relative cultural openness, that were once highly adaptive in enabling us to build our great civilization, but now leave us vulnerable as our environment becomes more post-patriarchal and multi-ethnic, and the protection and promotion of the “tribe” acquires a renewed importance.</p>
<p>Indeed, we aren’t merely passive in the face of challenges from women and nonwhites. We—a huge number of us anyway—are quick to respond with active self-loathing and self-abasement. Our women are even quicker in this regard, so I guess that this represents not a male trait but a white trait: a guilt/appeasement reflex that is related to emotional sensitivity and social (“virtue”) signaling.</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-548" src="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2022/04/stewart.jpg" alt="" width="800" height="488" srcset="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2022/04/stewart.jpg 800w, https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2022/04/stewart-300x183.jpg 300w, https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2022/04/stewart-768x468.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 709px) 85vw, (max-width: 909px) 67vw, (max-width: 984px) 61vw, (max-width: 1362px) 45vw, 600px" /></p>
<p>Whatever the cause, it is or should be remarkable, not to mention alarming, that <em>nonwhites</em> don’t seem to have this self-abasing, guilt-signaling reflex. Nonwhites have at least many skeletons in their ancestral closets as whites do&#8212;everyone living now is the beneficiary of hundreds of invasions and genocides going back to ape-men times. Yet I&#8217;m sure I&#8217;ve never heard an Indian, a Nigerian, or a Filipino lament his <em>own</em> ongoing, deliberate colonization and exploitation of the countries of the West.</p>
<p><strong>Implications</strong></p>
<p>In principle, some struggles between group cultures will merely simmer, remaining unresolved indefinitely, because the factions that would challenge the incumbent white male faction cannot put together the numbers to prevail, or simply because a certain number of white males are needed to keep the organizational ship afloat. But now in the 2020s, after six decades in which Western women and nonwhites have been crowding into Western professions and institutions (lately empowered by blatantly anti-white-male ideology) they seem to be seriously reaching for supremacy, at least wherever white males and their mindset are less necessary.</p>
<p>In any case, one implication of this hypothesis is that adding &#8220;diversity&#8221; to an organization doesn&#8217;t necessarily bring it closer to some happy, stable equilibrium. It may, instead, disrupt what had been a relatively stable balance of forces, stimulating anew the struggle(s) for dominance in that organization&#8212;and leading to the further marginalization of white males.</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-561" src="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2022/04/npr.jpg" alt="" width="800" height="768" srcset="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2022/04/npr.jpg 800w, https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2022/04/npr-300x288.jpg 300w, https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2022/04/npr-768x737.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 709px) 85vw, (max-width: 909px) 67vw, (max-width: 984px) 61vw, (max-width: 1362px) 45vw, 600px" /></p>
<p>Moreover, struggles among factions within organizations reflect, and also to a great extent add up to, a struggle at the societal level. By this reasoning, increasing demographic diversity in Western societies via mass-nonwhite-immigration is simply adding fuel to the <em>kulturkampf</em> fire, making ethnic factionalism burn hotter to the detriment of most, and increasing the chances that at least in some countries, nonwhites will prevail&#8212;marginalizing whites in their own lands.</p>
<p style="text-align: center;">* * *</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>PUTIN AND THE FALL OF THE WEST</title>
		<link>https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/putin-and-the-fall-of-the-west/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[j stone]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sun, 06 Mar 2022 03:18:55 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[fall of the West]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[immigration]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Russia]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[The Right]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Ukraine]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[USA]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[wokeism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[women]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/?p=501</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[The Right&#8217;s &#8220;sympathy for the devil&#8221; has weakened it at a crucial moment &#160; The sanctions against Russia—both the official economic sanctions and the unofficial, often petty-seeming sanctions such as banning Russian owners from cat shows—arguably represent the first great “geopolitical cancellation” of this new feminized era in the West. This cancellation obviously goes far &#8230; <a href="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/putin-and-the-fall-of-the-west/" class="more-link">Continue reading<span class="screen-reader-text"> "PUTIN AND THE FALL OF THE WEST"</span></a>]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><em>The Right&#8217;s &#8220;sympathy for the devil&#8221; has weakened it at a crucial moment</em><span id="more-501"></span></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>The sanctions against Russia—both the official economic sanctions and the unofficial, often petty-seeming sanctions such as <a href="https://www.npr.org/2022/03/03/1084205316/russian-cats-banned-international-competition">banning Russian owners from cat shows</a>—arguably represent the first great “geopolitical cancellation” of this new feminized era in the West.</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-505" src="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/geopolcancel.jpg" alt="" width="602" height="816" srcset="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/geopolcancel.jpg 602w, https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/geopolcancel-221x300.jpg 221w" sizes="(max-width: 709px) 85vw, (max-width: 909px) 67vw, (max-width: 984px) 61vw, (max-width: 1362px) 45vw, 600px" /></p>
<p>This cancellation obviously goes far beyond the usual diplomatic noises that are made when the blame for conflicts is murkier and the victims more remote from us. It is a public reaction to an outrage that rises explosively above the usual outrages, involves fellow Westerners, and is available to tug at the heartstrings 24/7 on a variety of electronic media.</p>
<p>Moreover, it really does look like a broad translation of the usual domestic cancellation strategies to the geopolitical scene, including economic punishment, censorship, general ostracism, threats of judicial action, and indirect assistance for those who fight the Cancelled One, but of course no direct, overt involvement in that fighting.</p>
<p>Given the scale of this response, the scale of the atrocity that triggered it, and the scale of Russia’s ongoing losses in Ukraine, Putin’s downfall seems inevitable. After killing many thousands of innocent Ukrainians, destroying probably trillions of dollars’ worth of Ukrainian buildings and other infrastructure, utterly breaking Russia&#8217;s army and air force, and of course lying through his teeth about his actions and motives, he does not appear to have any way out—any peaceful “off ramp.” He is our generation’s Hitler, and I suspect he already knows that his days, in office at least, are numbered.</p>
<p>There are many potential pluses to a Putin downfall. One is that Russia again will have a chance to achieve what it could not achieve in the 1990s, namely a more mature form of government and economy, oriented towards and not against the West. Such a transformation of Russia, which I think is somewhat more likely than the alternative, would mean a final unification of all the West’s major powers, and at least a temporary “emboldening” of them. That in turn could usher in one of those periods of history, like 1990-2010, in which the West reigns supreme over all earthly comers. In this scenario, bad actors such as Iran, China, and North Korea would have to watch their step, at the very least, and the world in that sense would be a safer place.</p>
<p>But here’s the bad news. Even if the “best case” scenario happens—including a glorious Russian uprising and overthrow of the dictator, maybe even on Easter Sunday (April 24 in the Russian Orthodox calendar)—the West has suffered a blow in its own ranks that I think is of dire significance.</p>
<p>If you’ve read any of my previous essays on this site, you know that I have taken a generally dim view of the West’s future. Cultural/political feminization; mass immigration, multiculturalism and wokeism; and the lack of political tools for solving these problems, have doomed the West in the most basic ways, as I have seen it. On the other hand, conservatives in the West have been gaining strength and coherence in recent years in reaction to the excesses of Letfism/wokeism. As recently as a month ago, it had seemed plausible to me that a <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/%C3%89ric_Zemmour">Zemmour</a>-ization of the Western Right (Eric Zemmour is explicitly against both cultural feminization and mass-immigration/heavy-multiculturalism) could, eventually and with a lot of luck, restore the situation.</p>
<p>But what Putin’s unprovoked invasion of Ukraine revealed all too clearly is that much of the Right in the West is, well, <em>wrong</em>, and about fundamental things. Sadly, these Wrong Rightists include Zemmour as well as prominent commentators in the US, Tucker Carlson and J.D. Vance among them.</p>
<p>The Wrong Rightists hate, first and foremost, what they call the Globalist American Empire (GAE). Fair enough—I hate it too. The problem is that they view Putin not as a murderous kleptocrat and global troublemaker (as I view him), but rather as a valuable counterweight to the hegemony of the GAE—a counterweight they want to <em>strengthen</em>, not weaken. These pro-Putin rightists have seemed quite willing to nullify the sovereignty of Ukraine (and, since the invasion started, have been willing to let Putin&#8217;s murders of tens of thousands of Ukrainians go unpunished), in order to preserve this counterweight—this bastion of old-fashioned Christian values according to the peculiar delusion afflicting some of them.</p>
<p>Of course, quite a few of the Wrong Rightists are backpedaling now, saying they deplore what Putin did, etc. They understand, at least at some level, the parallels between their sentiments and the discredited sentiments of say, Laval in France and Lindbergh in the USA during 1939-41. They therefore tend to exhibit their distress over the impending collapse of Russia as a Great Power, and the impending destruction of Putin and Putinism, in ways that are more or less indirect. They are peevish about Ukrainian “propaganda.” They lament the “lost opportunity” to have prevented the horrors of this war by barring Ukraine from NATO, thereby calming the nerves of their sensitive hero in the Kremlin. They speak darkly of Ukrainian “Nazis.” They yearn for a swift settlement that preserves Putin in power (and, not incidentally, conceals the fatuity of everything they have claimed or predicted about all this). They emit copious cope about how Russia is still destined to “win.” Above all, they say the West should care less about Ukraine and more about problems at home.</p>
<p>Here are just a few examples of this output (to which I may add soon as time permits):</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" class="wp-image-524 aligncenter" src="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/tc-clientstate.jpg" alt="" width="536" height="396" srcset="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/tc-clientstate.jpg 596w, https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/tc-clientstate-300x221.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 536px) 85vw, 536px" /></p>
<p><img loading="lazy" class="size-full wp-image-469 aligncenter" src="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/tucker1.jpg" alt="" width="527" height="412" srcset="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/tucker1.jpg 527w, https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/tucker1-300x235.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 527px) 85vw, 527px" /></p>
<p><img loading="lazy" class="wp-image-507 aligncenter" src="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/vance1.jpg" alt="" width="491" height="493" srcset="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/vance1.jpg 689w, https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/vance1-300x300.jpg 300w, https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/vance1-150x150.jpg 150w" sizes="(max-width: 491px) 85vw, 491px" /></p>
<p><img loading="lazy" class="size-full wp-image-508 aligncenter" src="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/trumponputin.jpg" alt="" width="506" height="590" srcset="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/trumponputin.jpg 506w, https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/trumponputin-257x300.jpg 257w" sizes="(max-width: 506px) 85vw, 506px" /></p>
<p><img loading="lazy" class="size-full wp-image-509 aligncenter" src="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/gabbard.jpg" alt="" width="524" height="139" srcset="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/gabbard.jpg 524w, https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/gabbard-300x80.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 524px) 85vw, 524px" /></p>
<p><img loading="lazy" class="wp-image-517 aligncenter" src="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/coulter1.jpg" alt="" width="511" height="202" srcset="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/coulter1.jpg 608w, https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/coulter1-300x118.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 511px) 85vw, 511px" /></p>
<p><img loading="lazy" class="size-full wp-image-525 aligncenter" src="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/hanania-thingspplwillbelieve.jpg" alt="" width="614" height="184" srcset="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/hanania-thingspplwillbelieve.jpg 614w, https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/hanania-thingspplwillbelieve-300x90.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 709px) 85vw, (max-width: 909px) 67vw, (max-width: 984px) 61vw, (max-width: 1362px) 45vw, 600px" /></p>
<p><img loading="lazy" class="size-full wp-image-526 aligncenter" src="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/hanania-emotion.jpg" alt="" width="592" height="183" srcset="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/hanania-emotion.jpg 592w, https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/hanania-emotion-300x93.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 592px) 85vw, 592px" /></p>
<p><img loading="lazy" class="wp-image-528 aligncenter" src="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/mcconnell-vietcong.jpg" alt="" width="556" height="363" srcset="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/mcconnell-vietcong.jpg 616w, https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/mcconnell-vietcong-300x196.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 556px) 85vw, 556px" /></p>
<p>What I think all this means is that the Western Right in general now is left with much less credibility in the eyes of the average normie citizen, just as occurred in the aftermath of the Pearl Harbor attack in 1941. In particular, the pro-Putin, &#8220;America First&#8221; sector of the Right, the sector that happens also to be most deeply concerned with the most serious issues, such as mass immigration, has grandly shot itself through the foot—or maybe through the heart. This has left the Left/center-Right “GAE” coalition in a much better position, so that there won’t be a Zemmour-type president in the USA any time soon—and I’m guessing now there won’t be one even in France. Thus the West’s demise will have been hastened at the very moment of its own apparent triumph over its longtime mortal enemy.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p style="text-align: center;">***</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>I STICK MY NECK OUT FOR NOBODY</title>
		<link>https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/i-stick-my-neck-out-for-nobody/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[j stone]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 24 Feb 2022 03:14:23 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[fall of the West]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[psychology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Russia]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[The Right]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Ukraine]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[USA]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[wokeism]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/?p=432</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[The West&#8217;s&#8212;and the Right&#8217;s&#8212;shame &#160; World War II ended less than two decades before I was born, yet I&#8217;ve always felt that it belonged to much more distant age&#8212;set off from modern existence by its different ways of thinking and doing, different patterns of speech and dress, grander scale of horrors and heroism, even the &#8230; <a href="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/i-stick-my-neck-out-for-nobody/" class="more-link">Continue reading<span class="screen-reader-text"> "I STICK MY NECK OUT FOR NOBODY"</span></a>]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><em>The West&#8217;s&#8212;and the Right&#8217;s&#8212;shame</em></p>
<p><span id="more-432"></span></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>World War II ended less than two decades before I was born, yet I&#8217;ve always felt that it belonged to much more distant age&#8212;set off from modern existence by its different ways of thinking and doing, different patterns of speech and dress, grander scale of horrors and heroism, even the monochrome of its newsreels. The bad things, especially, seemed mostly unrepeatable in the world where I grew up.</p>
<p>American isolationism is a good example. Conservative Americans, for the longest time, didn&#8217;t want to help Britain, or Western Europe, with their struggles against Hitler and Mussolini. The USA had helped out Britain and France in 1917-18, and felt that they shouldn&#8217;t have to do anything like that again. Let Europeans sort out their own problems, they said.</p>
<p>That was <em>part</em> of their public reasoning, anyway. Another part of it seemed much more instinctive and tribal, much more driven by the false logic of &#8220;the enemy-of-my-enemy-is-my-friend&#8221;&#8212;their enemy being FDR, of course, their new friends being the Axis dictators.</p>
<p>It might seem facile to criticize the American isolationists of 1939-41 from our postwar perspective, but really they should have known better just from the information available at the time. In any case, it&#8217;s always striking now to read and hear the things they said. Here, for example, is aviator Charles Lindbergh, on September 11, 1941 (Europe conquered, Britain under siege, Wehrmacht nearing Moscow etc.), blaming the British, Roosevelt, and &#8220;the Jewish,&#8221; for pushing America towards war:</p>
<p><iframe loading="lazy" title="Lindbergh &#039; Speech - 1941 | Movietone Moment | 11 September 2020" width="840" height="473" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/xiRYccqVPW0?feature=oembed" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen></iframe></p>
<p>The Pearl Harbor attack, less than three months later, embarrassed the America First movement into silence. Lindbergh himself spent much of the war trying to get into combat to redeem himself, and eventually <a href="http://www.charleslindbergh.com/history/b24.asp">succeeded&#8212;in getting into combat, not at redeeming himself.</a></p>
<p>But anyway, here we are again, with the same kind of geopolitical setup (armed dictator on the prowl abroad, liberal Democrats in control at home), resulting in the same strange mindset on the part of American conservatives.</p>
<p>By the way, in case this is the first essay of mine you&#8217;ve read, I&#8217;m pretty conservative too (notwithstanding David Goldman&#8217;s swipe at me, below, as a &#8220;neocon/GlobLib&#8221;). Yet the fellow conservatives who, in defiance of recent history, have started talking up Putin and talking down Ukraine, the US and the Western alliance, are now as alien to me as DEI consultants.</p>
<p>I&#8217;ve already set down my own anti-isolationist, fight-the-bad-guy <a href="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/aggressors-and-alliances/">thoughts</a> on Putin and Ukraine, a month ago on this site. Here I just want to record, mainly out of sheer amazement and chagrin, some of the sentiments I&#8217;ve been reading in recent days from elsewhere on the American right.</p>
<p>To keep things manageable, I&#8217;ve focused mainly on two prolific and very widely followed commentators, Goldman and Richard Hanania, and I&#8217;ve organized their comments by their major themes.</p>
<p><strong>&#8220;Ukraine is a corrupt and backwards place that isn&#8217;t worth defending&#8212;or invading&#8221;</strong></p>
<p><img loading="lazy" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-439" src="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/dg7.jpg" alt="" width="609" height="167" srcset="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/dg7.jpg 609w, https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/dg7-300x82.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 709px) 85vw, (max-width: 909px) 67vw, (max-width: 984px) 61vw, (max-width: 1362px) 45vw, 600px" /></p>
<p><img loading="lazy" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-411" src="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2022/01/hanania.jpg" alt="" width="603" height="662" srcset="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2022/01/hanania.jpg 603w, https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2022/01/hanania-273x300.jpg 273w" sizes="(max-width: 709px) 85vw, (max-width: 909px) 67vw, (max-width: 984px) 61vw, (max-width: 1362px) 45vw, 600px" /></p>
<p><img loading="lazy" class="alignnone wp-image-468" src="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/rh-tuckergood.jpg" alt="" width="558" height="430" srcset="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/rh-tuckergood.jpg 614w, https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/rh-tuckergood-300x232.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 558px) 85vw, 558px" /></p>
<p><img loading="lazy" class="alignnone wp-image-441" src="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/dg9.jpg" alt="" width="554" height="449" srcset="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/dg9.jpg 614w, https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/dg9-300x243.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 554px) 85vw, 554px" /></p>
<p><img loading="lazy" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-442" src="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/dg10.jpg" alt="" width="640" height="535" srcset="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/dg10.jpg 640w, https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/dg10-300x251.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 709px) 85vw, (max-width: 909px) 67vw, (max-width: 984px) 61vw, (max-width: 1362px) 45vw, 600px" /></p>
<p><img loading="lazy" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-443" src="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/dg16.jpg" alt="" width="623" height="310" srcset="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/dg16.jpg 623w, https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/dg16-300x149.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 709px) 85vw, (max-width: 909px) 67vw, (max-width: 984px) 61vw, (max-width: 1362px) 45vw, 600px" /></p>
<p><img loading="lazy" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-444" src="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/dg15.jpg" alt="" width="612" height="159" srcset="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/dg15.jpg 612w, https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/dg15-300x78.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 709px) 85vw, (max-width: 909px) 67vw, (max-width: 984px) 61vw, (max-width: 1362px) 45vw, 600px" /></p>
<p><img loading="lazy" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-445" src="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/dg17.jpg" alt="" width="617" height="296" srcset="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/dg17.jpg 617w, https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/dg17-300x144.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 709px) 85vw, (max-width: 909px) 67vw, (max-width: 984px) 61vw, (max-width: 1362px) 45vw, 600px" /></p>
<p><img loading="lazy" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-449" src="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/dg12.jpg" alt="" width="599" height="493" srcset="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/dg12.jpg 599w, https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/dg12-300x247.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 599px) 85vw, 599px" /></p>
<p><img loading="lazy" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-451" src="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/dg25.jpg" alt="" width="618" height="395" srcset="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/dg25.jpg 618w, https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/dg25-300x192.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 709px) 85vw, (max-width: 909px) 67vw, (max-width: 984px) 61vw, (max-width: 1362px) 45vw, 600px" /></p>
<p><img loading="lazy" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-483" src="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/rh-usboredw-ukraine.jpg" alt="" width="618" height="230" srcset="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/rh-usboredw-ukraine.jpg 618w, https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/rh-usboredw-ukraine-300x112.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 709px) 85vw, (max-width: 909px) 67vw, (max-width: 984px) 61vw, (max-width: 1362px) 45vw, 600px" /></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><strong>&#8220;Ukrainians are So Dumb&#8221;</strong></p>
<p><img loading="lazy" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-470" src="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/rh-ukr-dumb.jpg" alt="" width="612" height="323" srcset="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/rh-ukr-dumb.jpg 612w, https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/rh-ukr-dumb-300x158.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 709px) 85vw, (max-width: 909px) 67vw, (max-width: 984px) 61vw, (max-width: 1362px) 45vw, 600px" /></p>
<p><img loading="lazy" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-492" src="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/rh-finland.jpg" alt="" width="583" height="246" srcset="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/rh-finland.jpg 583w, https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/rh-finland-300x127.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 583px) 85vw, 583px" /></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><strong>&#8220;It&#8217;s All NATO&#8217;s/Neocons&#8217; Fault for Expanding NATO and Threatening Russia&#8221;</strong></p>
<p><img loading="lazy" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-448" src="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/dg5.jpg" alt="" width="633" height="164" srcset="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/dg5.jpg 633w, https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/dg5-300x78.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 709px) 85vw, (max-width: 909px) 67vw, (max-width: 984px) 61vw, (max-width: 1362px) 45vw, 600px" /></p>
<p><img loading="lazy" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-463" src="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/dg24.jpg" alt="" width="612" height="225" srcset="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/dg24.jpg 612w, https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/dg24-300x110.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 709px) 85vw, (max-width: 909px) 67vw, (max-width: 984px) 61vw, (max-width: 1362px) 45vw, 600px" /></p>
<p><img loading="lazy" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-450" src="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/dg20.jpg" alt="" width="631" height="401" srcset="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/dg20.jpg 631w, https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/dg20-300x191.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 709px) 85vw, (max-width: 909px) 67vw, (max-width: 984px) 61vw, (max-width: 1362px) 45vw, 600px" /></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><strong>&#8220;Putin is Smart and Will Win&#8221;</strong></p>
<p><img loading="lazy" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-456" src="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/dg4.jpg" alt="" width="632" height="316" srcset="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/dg4.jpg 632w, https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/dg4-300x150.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 709px) 85vw, (max-width: 909px) 67vw, (max-width: 984px) 61vw, (max-width: 1362px) 45vw, 600px" /></p>
<p><img loading="lazy" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-457" src="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/dg6.jpg" alt="" width="631" height="295" srcset="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/dg6.jpg 631w, https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/dg6-300x140.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 709px) 85vw, (max-width: 909px) 67vw, (max-width: 984px) 61vw, (max-width: 1362px) 45vw, 600px" /></p>
<p><img loading="lazy" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-458" src="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/dg-14.jpg" alt="" width="611" height="147" srcset="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/dg-14.jpg 611w, https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/dg-14-300x72.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 709px) 85vw, (max-width: 909px) 67vw, (max-width: 984px) 61vw, (max-width: 1362px) 45vw, 600px" /></p>
<p><img loading="lazy" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-472" src="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/rh-putingreat.jpg" alt="" width="607" height="206" srcset="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/rh-putingreat.jpg 607w, https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/rh-putingreat-300x102.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 709px) 85vw, (max-width: 909px) 67vw, (max-width: 984px) 61vw, (max-width: 1362px) 45vw, 600px" /></p>
<p><img loading="lazy" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-481" src="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/rh-rus-stronger.jpg" alt="" width="585" height="144" srcset="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/rh-rus-stronger.jpg 585w, https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/rh-rus-stronger-300x74.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 585px) 85vw, 585px" /></p>
<p><img loading="lazy" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-485" src="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/putin-69.jpg" alt="" width="607" height="316" srcset="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/putin-69.jpg 607w, https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/putin-69-300x156.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 709px) 85vw, (max-width: 909px) 67vw, (max-width: 984px) 61vw, (max-width: 1362px) 45vw, 600px" /></p>
<p><img loading="lazy" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-484" src="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/rh-noinsurgency.jpg" alt="" width="595" height="518" srcset="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/rh-noinsurgency.jpg 595w, https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/rh-noinsurgency-300x261.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 595px) 85vw, 595px" /></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><strong>&#8220;The Woke are the Real Enemy&#8212;not Putin&#8221;</strong></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-469" src="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/tucker1.jpg" alt="" width="527" height="412" srcset="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/tucker1.jpg 527w, https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/tucker1-300x235.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 527px) 85vw, 527px" /></p>
<p>(See also &#8220;<a href="https://slate.com/culture/2016/06/did-muhammad-ali-ever-say-no-viet-cong-ever-called-me-nigger.html">No Viet Cong Ever . . .</a>&#8220;)</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><strong>&#8220;You Neocons are So Dumb&#8221;</strong></p>
<p><img loading="lazy" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-453" src="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/dg-v-js1.jpg" alt="" width="620" height="632" srcset="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/dg-v-js1.jpg 620w, https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/dg-v-js1-294x300.jpg 294w" sizes="(max-width: 709px) 85vw, (max-width: 909px) 67vw, (max-width: 984px) 61vw, (max-width: 1362px) 45vw, 600px" /></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><strong>&#8220;Love Ukraine = Hate America&#8221;</strong></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-467" src="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/rh-correlation.jpg" alt="" width="602" height="427" srcset="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/rh-correlation.jpg 602w, https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/rh-correlation-300x213.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 709px) 85vw, (max-width: 909px) 67vw, (max-width: 984px) 61vw, (max-width: 1362px) 45vw, 600px" /></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><strong>&#8220;We Should Cut a Deal With Putin&#8221;</strong></p>
<p><img loading="lazy" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-459" src="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/dg21.jpg" alt="" width="616" height="554" srcset="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/dg21.jpg 616w, https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/dg21-300x270.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 709px) 85vw, (max-width: 909px) 67vw, (max-width: 984px) 61vw, (max-width: 1362px) 45vw, 600px" /></p>
<p><img loading="lazy" class="alignnone wp-image-471" src="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/rh-ukraineabjurenato.jpg" alt="" width="560" height="699" srcset="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/rh-ukraineabjurenato.jpg 597w, https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/rh-ukraineabjurenato-240x300.jpg 240w" sizes="(max-width: 560px) 85vw, 560px" /></p>
<p><img loading="lazy" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-477" src="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/rh-gas.jpg" alt="" width="583" height="161" srcset="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/rh-gas.jpg 583w, https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/rh-gas-300x83.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 583px) 85vw, 583px" /></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><strong>&#8220;Our NATO Allies Won&#8217;t Help Us&#8212;In Fact, NATO will collapse&#8221;</strong></p>
<p><img loading="lazy" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-460" src="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/dg8.jpg" alt="" width="609" height="417" srcset="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/dg8.jpg 609w, https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/dg8-300x205.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 709px) 85vw, (max-width: 909px) 67vw, (max-width: 984px) 61vw, (max-width: 1362px) 45vw, 600px" /></p>
<p><img loading="lazy" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-461" src="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/dg19.jpg" alt="" width="602" height="170" srcset="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/dg19.jpg 602w, https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/dg19-300x85.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 709px) 85vw, (max-width: 909px) 67vw, (max-width: 984px) 61vw, (max-width: 1362px) 45vw, 600px" /></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><strong>&#8220;We&#8217;ll Be Better Off When Russia and China Have More Power&#8221;</strong></p>
<p><img loading="lazy" class="alignnone wp-image-473" src="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/rh-natobad.jpg" alt="" width="562" height="190" srcset="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/rh-natobad.jpg 600w, https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/rh-natobad-300x102.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 562px) 85vw, 562px" /></p>
<p><img loading="lazy" class="alignnone wp-image-474" src="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/rh-chinacnstrained.jpg" alt="" width="473" height="461" srcset="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/rh-chinacnstrained.jpg 894w, https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/rh-chinacnstrained-300x292.jpg 300w, https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/rh-chinacnstrained-768x748.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 473px) 85vw, 473px" /></p>
<p><img loading="lazy" class="alignnone wp-image-475" src="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/rh-chinamorehumane.jpg" alt="" width="476" height="456" srcset="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/rh-chinamorehumane.jpg 616w, https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/rh-chinamorehumane-300x288.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 476px) 85vw, 476px" /></p>
<p><img loading="lazy" class="alignnone wp-image-479" src="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/rh-trumpputinsummit.jpg" alt="" width="488" height="230" srcset="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/rh-trumpputinsummit.jpg 613w, https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/rh-trumpputinsummit-300x141.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 488px) 85vw, 488px" /></p>
<p><img loading="lazy" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-488" src="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/rh-ivfbabies.jpg" alt="" width="920" height="520" srcset="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/rh-ivfbabies.jpg 920w, https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/rh-ivfbabies-300x170.jpg 300w, https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/rh-ivfbabies-768x434.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 709px) 85vw, (max-width: 909px) 67vw, (max-width: 1362px) 62vw, 840px" /></p>
<p><img loading="lazy" class="alignnone wp-image-489" src="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/rh-multipolar.jpg" alt="" width="542" height="348" srcset="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/rh-multipolar.jpg 779w, https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/rh-multipolar-300x193.jpg 300w, https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/rh-multipolar-768x493.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 542px) 85vw, 542px" /></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><strong>&#8220;Enough with the World War II Analogies!&#8221;</strong></p>
<p><img loading="lazy" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-491" src="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/rh-forgethitleranalogies.jpg" alt="" width="591" height="261" srcset="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/rh-forgethitleranalogies.jpg 591w, https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/rh-forgethitleranalogies-300x132.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 591px) 85vw, 591px" /></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><strong>&#8220;And Now For Some Other Clever Ideas&#8221;</strong></p>
<p><img loading="lazy" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-464" src="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/dg-asians.jpg" alt="" width="614" height="535" srcset="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/dg-asians.jpg 614w, https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/dg-asians-300x261.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 709px) 85vw, (max-width: 909px) 67vw, (max-width: 984px) 61vw, (max-width: 1362px) 45vw, 600px" /></p>
<p><img loading="lazy" class="alignnone wp-image-494" src="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/rh-downs.jpg" alt="" width="535" height="401" srcset="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/rh-downs.jpg 608w, https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/rh-downs-300x225.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 535px) 85vw, 535px" /></p>
<p>I&#8217;m aware that, as readers go through all these posts, they might find themselves agreeing with the sentiments expressed. But, as I post this, the long-awaited Russian offensive to conquer (presumably) Ukraine is just starting. It&#8217;s unlikely to be as dramatic for Americans as Pearl Harbor was, especially since it&#8217;s an attack on Ukraine, but modern electronic media, and weaponry, are going to be amplifying factors. I hope it will shock many of the Putin apologists and associated naysayers into rethinking their attitudes.</p>
<p style="text-align: center;">***</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>THE LAW EMPINKENED</title>
		<link>https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/the-law-empinkened/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[j stone]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sun, 09 Jan 2022 04:30:46 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[fall of the West]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[legal]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[USA]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[wokeism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[women]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://box5257.temp.domains/~houghty5/?p=385</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Giuffre v. Prince Andrew&#8212;yet another egregious example of how wokeism is destroying the US legal system. &#160; Every day, on Twitter and a thousand other media and social-media forums, Americans of a “conservative” or “right-wing” persuasion bemoan and lament the civilizational destruction caused by the crazed, bureaucrat-and-brownshirt armies of wokeness. I bemoan and lament with &#8230; <a href="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/the-law-empinkened/" class="more-link">Continue reading<span class="screen-reader-text"> "THE LAW EMPINKENED"</span></a>]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><em>Giuffre v. Prince Andrew&#8212;yet another egregious example of how wokeism is destroying the US legal system.</em></p>
<p><span id="more-385"></span></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>Every day, on Twitter and a thousand other media and social-media forums, Americans of a “conservative” or “right-wing” persuasion bemoan and lament the civilizational destruction caused by the crazed, bureaucrat-and-brownshirt armies of wokeness.</p>
<p>I bemoan and lament with them. But what distresses me even more is the destruction—serious destruction—caused by trends that ordinary people on the right <em>approve</em> or at least choose to keep silent about.</p>
<p>One of these trends concerns some of the criminal and civil cases inspired by the <em>#MeToo</em> movement—cases that represent the anti-male, <a href="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/girl-power/">pro-histrionic-female</a> theme in the broad wokeist takeover of the American judicial system. (Another prominent theme in that takeover, the <a href="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/an-abandoned-and-malignant-heart/">anti-white-law-abiding-citizen, pro-black-felon theme</a>, I wrote about just over a month ago.)</p>
<p>A particularly striking <em>#MeToo</em> case, still in its early stages but already with prominent media coverage, lies before us now.</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" class="size-full wp-image-386 aligncenter" src="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2022/01/andy1.jpg" alt="" width="672" height="669" srcset="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2022/01/andy1.jpg 672w, https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2022/01/andy1-300x300.jpg 300w, https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2022/01/andy1-150x150.jpg 150w" sizes="(max-width: 709px) 85vw, (max-width: 909px) 67vw, (max-width: 984px) 61vw, (max-width: 1362px) 45vw, 600px" /></p>
<p><img loading="lazy" class="size-full wp-image-387 aligncenter" src="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2022/01/andy2.jpg" alt="" width="600" height="530" srcset="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2022/01/andy2.jpg 600w, https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2022/01/andy2-300x265.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 709px) 85vw, (max-width: 909px) 67vw, (max-width: 984px) 61vw, (max-width: 1362px) 45vw, 600px" /></p>
<p><img loading="lazy" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-390" src="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2022/01/andy3.jpg" alt="" width="803" height="219" srcset="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2022/01/andy3.jpg 803w, https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2022/01/andy3-300x82.jpg 300w, https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2022/01/andy3-768x209.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 709px) 85vw, (max-width: 909px) 67vw, (max-width: 984px) 61vw, (max-width: 1362px) 45vw, 600px" /></p>
<p>This is the case brought by Virginia Roberts Giuffre, the most media-noisy of the sex kittens paid and kept by the late Jeffrey Epstein. She claims that—more than two decades ago, when she was just 17—she slept with the British royal Prince Andrew, and suffered so much harm thereby that she is now entitled to significant monetary damages. According to the complaint filed by her lawyers:</p>
<p style="padding-left: 40px;">Prince Andrew committed sexual assault and battery upon Plaintiff when she was 17 years old. As such, Prince Andrew is responsible for battery and intentional infliction of emotional distress pursuant to New York common law. The damage to Plaintiff has been severe and lasting . . . .</p>
<p style="padding-left: 40px;">The below photograph depicts Prince Andrew, Plaintiff, and Maxwell at Maxwell’s home prior to Prince Andrew sexually abusing Plaintiff.</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" class=" wp-image-388 aligncenter" src="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2022/01/giuff-Copy.jpg" alt="" width="473" height="284" srcset="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2022/01/giuff-Copy.jpg 930w, https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2022/01/giuff-Copy-300x180.jpg 300w, https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2022/01/giuff-Copy-768x461.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 473px) 85vw, 473px" /></p>
<p>The reader is free to peruse the full complaint [<a href="https://www.courthousenews.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/08/Prince-Phillip-sexual-assault-lawsuit.pdf">pdf</a>], to follow the case as it progresses, and to make judgments accordingly. I offer here, as a mere bystander who knows none of the parties, only my own humble, hushed opinions.</p>
<p>Which is to say, I think it’s a shameless fraud that demonstrates the shambles of the American legal system under the pressures of wokeist <a href="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/the-great-feminization/">feminization</a>.</p>
<p>Worse, I think it puts on full display America&#8217;s cultural corruption&#8212;for no media commentator of prominence, as far as I know, has offered even mild skepticism about this outrageous case or others like it.</p>
<p>In other words, while I believe that the stink of this business is more or less universally apparent, the average media person pretends otherwise because the stories generate clicks, and also for fear of cancellation—cancellation by the same hysteria-prone demographic that got people hanged at Salem and other innocents <a href="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/girl-power/">burned at the stake</a> throughout Europe.</p>
<p>Let me clarify that Giuffre’s case against Andrew doesn’t—I mean, logically shouldn’t—have a close connection to the legal cases against Jeffrey Epstein and Ghislaine Maxwell. I happen to think the latter were both obviously guilty of sex trafficking and related offenses, even if the sentence Epstein would have received in New York and the one Maxwell is now set to receive will be excessive (on the Great White Defendant principle) compared to typical trafficking cases, i.e., involving some Nigerian or Honduran who really does enslave and brutalize his victims. But no one has ever presented evidence that Andrew was a party to Epstein’s trafficking scheme, or that he was anything other than a gentle fool who, like other fools (Bill Gates and Bill Clinton among them) hung out with his friend Epstein from time to time. (How Epstein generated the charisma to gather such people in his orbit is to me a significant mystery, albeit not relevant here.)</p>
<p>Giuffre&#8217;s case rests on the simple allegation that Andrew, in cahoots with Epstein and Maxwell, somehow “forced” Giuffre to sleep with him&#8212;which seems not just an unsupported allegation but a preposterous one. Assuming Giuffre and Andrew even did have sex, we have been given no reason to picture it as any less volitional on her part than her demeanor in the photograph would suggest. And I think it&#8217;s safe to say that Andrew, whatever his other failings, has never shown a propensity for treating women in the manner alleged.</p>
<p>At the same time, it appears that Giuffre, having partied and traveled widely and gotten to know various men, all on Epstein’s nickel, has been, since E&#8217;s legal troubles began, squeezing him or his estate (also Ghislaine Maxwell and Alan Dershowitz) for further money; and the suit against Andrew represents one of the continuations of that broader effort; all of which speaks clearly to the issue of her motive.</p>
<p>In short, the case has the <em>prima facie</em> appearance of being no more than a shakedown: an attempt essentially to extort money with the threat of an embarrassing civil trial if the money is not paid.</p>
<p>Despite this, there is a good chance Giuffre will prevail&#8212;her blue-chip lawyers, who probably stand to get around a third of any award or settlement, would not have taken the case otherwise. Most likely she will prevail because Andrew and his family will decide to settle rather than endure the pain of a trial. Even if they are willing to endure that pain, the corruption the <em>#MeToo</em> strain of wokeness has caused in the American legal system, including juries, makes any such case a roll of the dice, at least. The judge in the case also may not be an even-handed Myron Kovitsky type (<em>Bonfire of the Vanities</em>); he is Lewis Kaplan, a Clinton appointee and a <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lewis_A._Kaplan">paid-up member of the New York liberal elite</a>, whose demeanor in an <a href="https://nypost.com/2022/01/04/judge-appears-to-let-prince-andrew-sex-abuse-suit-move-forward/">early hearing</a> does not bode well for the prince.</p>
<p>Shakedowns occur all the time, among highlifes and lowlifes, but this one is so prominent, so front-and-center, and yet apparently so untouchable by simple reason and skepticism. No disinterested observer can question it! Everybody <em>loves</em> Empress Virginia’s new clothes! Little wonder that Dershowitz, target of another one of Giuffre’s suits, has come across as almost apoplectic when talking about her to reporters.</p>
<p style="padding-left: 40px;">certified, complete, total liar [<a href="https://nypost.com/2020/07/01/epstein-sex-slave-giuffre-dershowitz-lose-in-court-ruling/">link</a>]</p>
<p style="padding-left: 40px;">I’m not neutral on this, because [Giuffre] also accused me of having sex with her, and I proved conclusively — through her own diaries, through her own lawyer, through our own emails — that it would be impossible for me to have ever met her. [<a href="https://www.breitbart.com/radio/2021/12/21/alan-dershowitz-prosecution-hid-main-witness-at-ghislaine-maxwell-trial/">link</a>]</p>
<p>Anyway, I hope my writing this emboldens some of you out there to speak up—quixotically, I know, but so be it—and state what is obvious about cases like this, namely that they need to be strongly discouraged somehow, and the men targeted by them need to be better protected. The US and other Western legal systems already make many concessions to women, including protection from incidental reputational harm in rape cases. Why can&#8217;t men receive a similar level of protection from the <em>deliberate</em> reputational harm of shakedown cases?</p>
<p>Well, of course, you know why—because women essentially are now in charge, and are <a href="https://americanmind.org/salvo/pink-shift/">remodeling the institutions of Western life to suit themselves</a>. With essentially zero pushback from men. I begin to tire of pointing this out.</p>
<p style="text-align: center;">***</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>CULTURAL FEMINIZATION: A BIBLIOGRAPHY</title>
		<link>https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/cultural-feminization-a-bibliography/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[j stone]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 14 Dec 2021 06:29:13 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[wokeism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[women]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://box5257.temp.domains/~houghty5/?page_id=347</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[An incomplete list, but maybe useful. The idea that women, on average compared to men, think differently, behave differently, and vote differently, is not a new one. What I think has some originality, though—certainly it seems to have been too hot, as recently as a few months ago, for any MSM or MSM-adjacent editor to &#8230; <a href="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/cultural-feminization-a-bibliography/" class="more-link">Continue reading<span class="screen-reader-text"> "CULTURAL FEMINIZATION: A BIBLIOGRAPHY"</span></a>]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><em>An incomplete list, but maybe useful.</em></p>
<p><span id="more-347"></span></p>
<p>The idea that women, on average compared to men, think differently, behave differently, and vote differently, is not a new one. What I think has some originality, though—certainly it seems to have been too hot, as recently as a few months ago, for any MSM or MSM-adjacent editor to handle—is the idea that women, especially by entering culturally influential professions <em>en masse</em> since the 1960s, have transformed Western societies: pulling them leftward and introducing political correctness, etc., but more precisely <em>feminizing</em> them, with arguably dire implications for Western civilization.</p>
<p>In case it’s useful to others writing in this area (and because like most creative people I crave credit), I’ve listed some of my relevant works in this area—and all the ones I’m now aware of from other writers.</p>
<p><strong>From me</strong></p>
<p>2011    “<a href="https://james-the-obscure.github.io/the-demise-of-guythink/">The Demise of Guythink</a>”</p>
<p>An old blog post, and my first and probably briefest expression of the cultural feminization hypothesis. Inspired by something controversial Jeremy Clarkson said, and also by the Larry Summers controversy which I would later write about in more detail.</p>
<p>2014    “<a href="https://james-the-obscure.github.io/motherland/">Motherland</a>”</p>
<p>Also an old blog post but a much longer, more discursive account of the hypothesis. Most of the pieces I’ve written since then have been, for the most part, compressed versions of the ideas expressed here.</p>
<p>2014    “<a href="https://www.returnofkings.com/42976/thanks-to-progressivism-america-is-no-country-for-men">No Country for Men</a>” (<em>Return of Kings</em>)</p>
<p>I got this published on Roosh V’s <em>Return of Kings</em> website (under a pseudonym I no longer use).</p>
<p>2019    “<a href="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/the-great-feminization/">The Great Feminization</a>”</p>
<p>Essay on a new website, not using my real name—a relatively brief version of the cult-fem theory, with a bit at the end about testosterone levels and fertility that is probably somewhat relevant, though not really central to the theory. I started the website and placed the essay on it because I had offered a version of the piece to two or three conservative webzines, with no luck.</p>
<p>(Tyler Cowen linked to this essay in his Marginal Revolution blog two and a half years later, prompting a flood of readers.)</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" class="size-full wp-image-348 aligncenter" src="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/cowen.jpg" alt="" width="660" height="435" srcset="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/cowen.jpg 660w, https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/cowen-300x198.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 709px) 85vw, (max-width: 909px) 67vw, (max-width: 984px) 61vw, (max-width: 1362px) 45vw, 600px" /></p>
<p>2019    “<a href="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/the-day-the-logic-died/">The Day the Logic Died</a>”</p>
<p>A fuller account of the 2005 Larry Summers “intrinsic aptitude” controversy/hysteria, with some cult-fem theory. <span style="text-decoration: underline;">If you read just one of my essays, make it this one</span>. A favorable reference to this in a tweet from @toad_spotted, some weeks after it was posted, induced many thousands of people to read it—and the “Great Feminization” piece&#8212;and encouraged me to keep writing.</p>
<p>2020    “<a href="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/girl-power/">Girl Power</a>”</p>
<p>Some cult-fem theory here, touching on women’s greater ability to form networks/coalitions, especially to cancel (or prosecute) men. Mainly, though, this was an examination of #MeToo-type cases against the historical background of hysterias including medieval/early-modern convent hysterias, Salem, modern recovered-memory case epidemics, etc.</p>
<p>2021    “<a href="https://americanmind.org/salvo/pink-shift/">Pink Shift</a>” (<em>The American Mind</em>)</p>
<p>Short piece summarizing the theory&#8212;thanks again to James Poulos &amp; Co. for publishing it.</p>
<p>2021    “<a href="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/the-critical-mass-problem/">The Critical Mass Problem</a>”</p>
<p>More on the apparently superior female ability to form networks and transmit social contagions, as a general source of political/social instability. “The Great Awokening’s transformation of big institutions reflects not only the general fear of personal cancellation within these institutions but also the ‘critical mass’ of susceptible women who work in them.”</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><strong>Other writers</strong></p>
<p>My initial online searches using keywords like “feminization” were curiously uninformative (a lot of stuff on trans medical issues), but after Tyler Cowen linked to my “Great Feminization” essay two months ago, I started digging again. I’m sure this is still a very incomplete list.</p>
<p>Note that Cowen himself has <a href="https://www.bloomberg.com/opinion/articles/2021-09-19/woke-movement-is-global-and-america-should-be-mostly-proud">written</a> about feminization in occasional columns and blog posts, going back at least a few years.</p>
<p>1985    <a href="https://www.amazon.com/Feminization-America-Womens-Changing-Private/dp/B000R3AQ4A"><em>The Feminization of America</em></a> (Elinor Lenz &amp; Barbara Myerhoff)</p>
<p>The authors “envision the emergence of a new `feminized’ America, a society made more human, less destructive, and more compassionate by women&#8217;s nurturing and integrative influences in all walks of life.”</p>
<p>1987    “<a href="https://www.commentary.org/articles/james-nuechterlein/the-feminization-of-the-american-left/">The Feminization of the American Left</a>” (James Neuchterlein, <em>Commentary</em>)</p>
<p>Contrasts modern leftism with the more masculine leftism of yore. “Feminization, as understood here, suggests the establishment of traditionally feminine virtues (those normally associated with the private realm) as norms of behavior for public life. It indicates an ethic of noncoercion, a preference for emotion over rational analysis and for noncompetitive modes of social interaction, a focus on being rather than doing and on interpersonal relations as the primary preoccupation of the good life.”</p>
<p>1990—present  <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sexual_Personae"><em>Sexual Personae</em></a> and other works (Camille Paglia)</p>
<p>Though never really in a systematic way, as far as I know, Paglia has frequently made references to issues that relate to cultural feminization. For example, in a short <a href="https://www.hollywoodreporter.com/lifestyle/lifestyle-news/camille-paglia-movies-metoo-modern-sexuality-endless-bitter-rancor-lies-1088450/">essay</a> on #MeToo in 2018: “The big question is whether the present wave of revelations, often consisting of unsubstantiated allegations from decades ago, will aid women’s ambitions in the long run or whether it is already creating further problems by reviving ancient stereotypes of women as hysterical, volatile and vindictive.”</p>
<p>1998    <em><a href="https://www.amazon.com/Feminization-American-Culture-Ann-Douglas/dp/0374525587">The Feminization of American Culture</a></em> (Ann Douglas)</p>
<p>Not as relevant as its title suggests. Douglas argues that in the late 19<sup>th</sup> century American literature became “feminized” with “books that idealized the very qualities that kept [women] powerless: timidity, piety, and a disdain for competition.”</p>
<p>2006?  “<a href="https://www.seattleweekly.com/news/when-did-we-all-become-women/">When Did We All Become Women?</a>” (Kathryn Robinson, <em>Seattle Weekly</em>)</p>
<p>“Think of values like nurturing and caring, emotion and sentimentality, connection and community, passivity and submission, vanity and appearance, cooperation and equality, openness and access, manipulation and influence. These are the values on the ascendancy in our public and private lives.” Robinson covers the ground pretty well, and projects the same sense of awe that I had when I started to perceive the significance of this unprecedented cultural development. (Her piece may have been buried in the search rankings until <a href="https://marginalrevolution.com/marginalrevolution/2021/08/when-did-we-all-become-women.html">Cowen linked to it</a> a few months ago. Also, the 2006 date attached to the article may have been the date of uploading to the web, not the original magazine publication date.)</p>
<p>2009 “<a href="https://www.cato-unbound.org/2009/04/13/peter-thiel/education-libertarian/">The Education of a Libertarian</a>” (Peter Thiel, <em>CATO Unbound</em>)</p>
<p>Within this essay by the then-not-so-well-known tech billionaire and libertarian evangelist is a recognition of at least one aspect of cultural/political feminization: “. . . I no longer believe that freedom and democracy are compatible,” Thiel wrote. “The 1920s were the last decade in American history during which one could be genuinely optimistic about politics. Since 1920, the vast increase in welfare beneficiaries and the extension of the franchise to women—two constituencies that are notoriously tough for libertarians—have rendered the notion of “capitalist democracy” into an oxymoron.”</p>
<p style="text-align: center;">***</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>WE NEED TO TALK ABOUT WOMEN</title>
		<link>https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/we-need-to-talk-about-women/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[j stone]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 13 Dec 2021 10:20:02 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[fall of the West]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[immigration]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[USA]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[wokeism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[women]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://box5257.temp.domains/~houghty5/?p=331</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Once more unto the breach, dear friends. I’ve written about women and their cultural/political ascendancy so much in recent years, especially the last three, that I worry about sounding like the proverbial broken record if I write any more. But it seems to me that as this idea is accepted more widely—including by commentators who &#8230; <a href="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/we-need-to-talk-about-women/" class="more-link">Continue reading<span class="screen-reader-text"> "WE NEED TO TALK ABOUT WOMEN"</span></a>]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><em>Once more unto the breach, dear friends.</em></p>
<p><span id="more-331"></span></p>
<p>I’ve written about women and their cultural/political ascendancy so much in recent years, especially the last three, that I worry about sounding like the proverbial broken record if I write any more. But it seems to me that as this idea is accepted more widely—including by commentators who see it as their own idea . . .</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" class="size-full wp-image-340 aligncenter" src="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/harrington.jpg" alt="" width="536" height="385" srcset="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/harrington.jpg 536w, https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/harrington-300x215.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 536px) 85vw, 536px" /></p>
<p>. . . there is a tendency to narrow the focus (e.g., “female graduates,” “HR ladies,” or “women explain wokeness”) so that the true extent of the West’s feminization is obscured.</p>
<p>Moreover, the case can be made that feminization is having not only an enormous but also a potentially fatal impact on Western civilization as we have known it. Thus, thumping the tub about this subject may be a good and necessary thing to do now.</p>
<p>To that end, I think at least several key points within this overall hypothesis bear repeating:</p>
<p><strong>Women’s broad cultural/political ascendancy has been reshaping the West for decades</strong></p>
<p>The big idea here is that women have been the principal drivers not only of the creeping wokeism post 2015 or so, and of the ongoing semi-spiritual movement known as the Great Awokening, but also of the general “leftward” (<a href="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/the-day-the-logic-died/">in fact, “feminine”</a>) trends in Western culture and politics over the last six-plus decades. This is the period in which women moved <em>en masse</em> into, and achieved parity or dominance within, culturally and politically influential professions such as journalism, publishing, entertainment, law, academia, politics, even blogging.</p>
<p>It is not just from one or two of those professions but from all of them, and in every circumstance along the way (e.g., university life, engagement with social media, office politics, voting, protest marches), that women have been causing cultural and political change, effectively feminizing the West to a degree never seen before in any large civilization.</p>
<p>Activist women—mostly single, university-educated, and/or young—may be the “shock troops” of feminization, and the most dedicated and effective practitioners of wokeism and cancel culture. But women <em>in general</em> have been driving this social transformation.</p>
<p><strong>Women’s ascension to cultural and political power has had cultural and political consequences because women on average are different than men across a wide range of attitudes and behaviors</strong></p>
<p>Gender differences in attitudes and behaviors were presumably shaped—at a biological level with changes that cannot easily be undone—by men’s and women’s distinct roles during the long period of hominid evolution, roles that for women centered on maternity. Women even now in modern times appear to be markedly more emotionally sensitive than men on average, quicker to form social networks, less interested in abstract and inanimate things, less interested in systems, more personal (including <em>ad hominem</em>) in their thinking, and more fearful—not just of ideas and people they dislike but also of toxins and other putative environmental threats. All these differences have had cultural and policy consequences as women’s power has increased in societies designed and traditionally run by men. One could say that women effectively have been using their new cultural and political power to renovate and redecorate their civilization according to their distinctive tastes. As Virginia Woolf put it in her 1938 essay, “Three Guineas”:</p>
<p style="padding-left: 40px;">Let us never cease from thinking—what is this “civilization” in which we find ourselves?</p>
<p><strong>Cultural/political feminization therefore involves a multitude of changes</strong></p>
<p>Cultural and political changes that have plausibly been driven by the ascendancy of women in Western societies are not limited to the extreme changes associated with “wokeism.” They include also relatively mild and gradual, long-term trends:</p>
<ul>
<li style="list-style-type: none;">
<ul>
<li>more extensive and generous welfare programs;</li>
<li>more rights, often including reverse-discrimination-type rights, for “traditionally disadvantaged” or otherwise marginalized groups (blacks, Hispanics, nonwhite immigrants, women, gays, transsexuals, etc.);</li>
<li>more emphasis generally in culture and policy on “equality of outcomes” over “equal opportunity,” and on guilt and compassion (vs. dispassionate, long-term calculation) as drivers of policy and social change;</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<p><img loading="lazy" class="size-full wp-image-332 aligncenter" src="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/mo.jpg" alt="" width="300" height="168" /></p>
<ul>
<li style="list-style-type: none;">
<ul>
<li>more emphasis on “trauma”—emotional upset—everywhere from journalism to law and medicine, with a related emergence of trauma-memory (PTSD) or otherwise trauma-related syndromes that are strongly contagious and now highly prevalent;</li>
<li>less affinity for traditional, often Constitutionally protected forms of (emotionally painful) confrontation such as free speech and free debate, free scientific inquiry, and due process of law (e.g., the right to face one’s accuser, and the right to cross-examine)—and increasing affinity for systems that suppress and punish “unacceptable” speech;</li>
<li>the acceptance of what amount to special rules for women when they are complainants against men in sex-related court cases, e.g., they can bring cases decades after the alleged crime, and when they claim to have been abused by men they later dated or exchanged love-notes with, their claims are still taken seriously—are simply chalked up to their presumed trauma;</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<p><img loading="lazy" class="wp-image-333 aligncenter" src="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/weinstein1.jpg" alt="" width="391" height="298" srcset="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/weinstein1.jpg 680w, https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/weinstein1-300x228.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 391px) 85vw, 391px" /></p>
<ul>
<li style="list-style-type: none;">
<ul>
<li>the intrusion of distinctively feminine values into the traditionally male-dominated world of sports, such that, for example, athletes putting their “self-care” instincts over their competitive instincts are not derided but celebrated;</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<p><img loading="lazy" class="wp-image-334 aligncenter" src="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/biles.jpg" alt="" width="317" height="418" srcset="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/biles.jpg 414w, https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/biles-227x300.jpg 227w" sizes="(max-width: 317px) 85vw, 317px" /></p>
<ul>
<li style="list-style-type: none;">
<ul>
<li>the alteration of language, including the elimination of upsetting terms and invention of new ones (“safe space”), to reflect the reigning new feminine mindset;</li>
<li>the routine, rapid formation of social <a href="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/the-day-the-logic-died/">networks</a> to exert pressure on corporations or other institutions to “cancel” someone who has fallen afoul of feminist/woke orthodoxies;</li>
<li>strong environmentalism and related advocacies and preferences (anti-vaccine, anti-GMO, anti-nuclear, climate-change alarmism, veganism, “organic” foods and medicines, etc.), stemming plausibly from women’s relatively strong sensitivity to the idea of environmental harms including toxins;</li>
<li>Shifts towards less systematized/hierarchical and rule-based religious forms, from paganism to evangelical/charismatic Christianity.</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>Cultural/political feminization, far from being “progress,” is probably destroying Western liberalism&#8212;the liberalism that emancipated women in the first place<br />
</strong></p>
<p>Yes, men on average have their own ways of thinking and acting—their own stubborn, long-evolved biases. And yes, the traditional male mindset is not necessarily optimized for running human societies in the 21<sup>st</sup> century. But there is an obvious reason why the male mindset, compared to the female mindset, is probably better adapted for managing culture and politics: Men have been managing culture and politics, and getting punished in the harshest ways for failure, for hundreds of millennia. Women, by contrast, have been working on a large scale in public life for not even two generations—and still seem inclined to blame men when things go wrong.</p>
<p>On the flip side of that argument is another obvious point: Women’s mindset is not simply unadapted or insufficiently adapted by evolution for managing public affairs; it is adapted specifically for <em>other</em> tasks, mainly domestic tasks revolving around the bearing and raising of children. In other words, women’s higher emotional sensitivity (compassion, guilt, fear, anxiety/turmoil); their relative indifference to machines and systems and cold, abstract thought; their stronger fear of toxins; their greater tendency to think un-independently and <a href="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/the-critical-mass-problem/">transmit social contagions</a>, etc. are in a fundamental sense <em>out of place</em> in the culture- and policy-making spheres.</p>
<p>I’m not suggesting that women’s traits are totally separate from men’s in this regard—for virtually any trait there would be two highly overlapping distributions, so that there would be lots and lots of women further towards the “male” end of the distribution compared to the average male.</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" class="wp-image-12 aligncenter" src="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2020/07/coulter-twitr.jpg" alt="" width="349" height="99" srcset="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2020/07/coulter-twitr.jpg 578w, https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2020/07/coulter-twitr-300x85.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 349px) 85vw, 349px" /></p>
<p>But there clearly are differences between the means of those distributions, between the <em>average</em> male and the <em>average</em> female in other words; and the central idea here is that those differences, on a population level, are not only meaningful but potentially cataclysmic in their civilizational impact.</p>
<p>That impact is evident not only in the broad cultural and policy shifts since the early 1960s&#8212;the “<a href="https://americanmind.org/salvo/pink-shift/">pink shift</a>” as I have called it&#8212;but in the more recent and extreme policy changes in places where cultural and political feminization is most advanced: “defund the police,” “let violent criminals out on bail,” “open the borders / diversity is our strength,” “let homeless people camp and crap wherever they like,” “give addicts needles,” “math is racist,” “logic is sexist,” etc. Not all of these policies are wildly popular, and obviously specific groups of hardcore activists are to blame for some of them, but I don’t see how these changes, collectively, could have taken root to the extent they have except against a heavily feminized cultural background—they are essentially <em>ad absurdum</em> expressions of the feminine mindset applied to policy.</p>
<p>I don&#8217;t think that every manifestation of feminization will be harmful in the long run. But some will. The move away from free speech towards speech- and thought-policing seems pretty ominous. Even worse, I suspect, is the encouragement of mass non-Western immigration to Western countries. One does not have to “hate” non-Western immigrants to understand that they and the culture they bring with them are . . . non-Western . . . so that the more there are of them, the less Western their host countries become. The women who encourage mass non-Western immigration seem surprisingly indifferent to the fact that non-Western cultures generally are less liberal, and a lot less friendly to the idea of female power, compared to Western cultures even from a few decades ago.</p>
<p>Can liberal Western societies nevertheless avert their impending self-destruction, by&#8212;among other measures&#8212;reining in cultural/political feminization? We&#8217;ll soon see, but I doubt it. I think it could help some to talk more about this cultural feminization hypothesis—“cult-fem theory”—at least as a way of dispelling the holy aura of “progress” that feminization-related social changes have acquired. But could one attack cultural feminization more directly and conclusively? Could one expel women, or even just the “bad apples,” or even persuade them to think and act differently, in all significant Western institutions—legislatures, government offices, universities, corporations, media organizations, philanthropies—where they are now embedded and substantially run things? I don&#8217;t see how. I don&#8217;t think liberal Western societies have any strong defense against this threat, other than by reverting to overt illiberalism.</p>
<p style="text-align: center;">***</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>AN ABANDONED AND MALIGNANT HEART</title>
		<link>https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/an-abandoned-and-malignant-heart/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[j stone]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 30 Nov 2021 21:15:50 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[blacks]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[ethnicity]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[fall of the West]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[USA]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[wokeism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[women]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://box5257.temp.domains/~houghty5/?p=284</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Thoughts on another miscarriage of justice in the broken USA &#160; An unpopular cause I feel compelled to stick up for today is the cause of Travis McMichael, his father Gregory McMichael, and their neighbor William “Roddie” Bryan, all of Brunswick, Georgia, USA, who were recently found guilty of murdering Ahmaud Arbery. Rightly or wrongly, &#8230; <a href="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/an-abandoned-and-malignant-heart/" class="more-link">Continue reading<span class="screen-reader-text"> "AN ABANDONED AND MALIGNANT HEART"</span></a>]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><em>Thoughts on another miscarriage of justice in the broken USA</em></p>
<p><span id="more-284"></span></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>An unpopular cause I feel compelled to stick up for today is the cause of Travis McMichael, his father Gregory McMichael, and their neighbor William “Roddie” Bryan, all of Brunswick, Georgia, USA, who were recently found guilty of murdering Ahmaud Arbery. Rightly or wrongly, I am convinced that this verdict is blatantly unjust. I also believe that many Americans, not just the jury and the prosecutor, are complicit in this injustice—an injustice that is much closer to murder (these men are likely to die in prison) than was the actual killing of Arbery.</p>
<p>Grievous miscarriages of justice occur frequently now in the United States, and often arise due to race-related issues that bias prosecutors and jurors. So why am I writing about this particular injustice, and not, say, the travesty of the Derek Chauvin verdict? I think it’s mainly because in the Chauvin case I read a healthy amount of commentary defending Chauvin, whereas in the case of the McMichaels and Bryan I read no defenses, only smug expressions of satisfaction or at least placid acceptance of this verdict, even among people who should know better.</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" class=" wp-image-289 aligncenter" src="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/arbery2.jpg" alt="" width="516" height="421" srcset="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/arbery2.jpg 613w, https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/arbery2-300x245.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 516px) 85vw, 516px" /></p>
<p><img loading="lazy" class=" wp-image-286 aligncenter" src="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/gabbard.jpg" alt="" width="512" height="140" srcset="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/gabbard.jpg 592w, https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/gabbard-300x82.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 512px) 85vw, 512px" /></p>
<p><img loading="lazy" class="wp-image-288 aligncenter" src="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/cheong.jpg" alt="" width="436" height="252" srcset="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/cheong.jpg 607w, https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/cheong-300x173.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 436px) 85vw, 436px" /></p>
<p><img loading="lazy" class=" wp-image-287 aligncenter" src="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/flanagan.jpg" alt="" width="521" height="491" srcset="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/flanagan.jpg 599w, https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/flanagan-300x282.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 521px) 85vw, 521px" /></p>
<p>The guilt of the McMichaels and Bryan is, in other words, part of the contemporary American “conventional wisdom” that I have come to distrust almost reflexively.</p>
<p>Why the McMichaels and Bryan were abandoned to their harsh fate so easily, even willfully and joyously, by their countrymen is something I’ll speculate about later in this essay, but first I want to go over some of the basic facts of the case.</p>
<p><strong>The killing of Ahmaud Arbery</strong></p>
<p>Ahmaud Arbery was a 25-year old African-American man who lived in Brunswick, Georgia. Like many African-American men, he had a police record for at least moderately serious crimes, including bringing a handgun to a high school football game in 2013, and an attempted shoplifting of a TV from a WalMart in 2017. He was still on probation when he died.</p>
<p>In late 2018, apparently based on his own observations as well as those of family members, Arbery’s probation officer recommended that Arbery get a mental health evaluation. At this evaluation—the defense lawyers brought this up at the trial, but the judged ruled it inadmissible—Arbery described to the evaluator (apparently a psychiatric nurse) “auditory delusions sometimes commanding him ‘to rob and steal’ and sometimes telling him ‘to hurt people,’” as well as general difficulties controlling his anger. Arbery was diagnosed with schizoaffective disorder and prescribed olanzapine (Zyprexa), a second-generation antipsychotic that is also used treat schizophrenia and the manic episodes of type 1 bipolar disorder; however, he apparently didn’t take the drug for long, and there was no evidence of it in his system when he died, although there were trace amounts of THC, the active ingredient in marijuana.</p>
<p>The MSM stories after Arbery’s death were heavily biased in the young man’s favor, and tended to omit or downplay anything negative, preferring to show a picture of him looking spiffy in his prom suit . . .</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" class="size-full wp-image-290 aligncenter" src="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/arbery0.jpg" alt="" width="143" height="183" /></p>
<p>. . . and preferring to emphasize that at the time of his death Arbery was “planning” to attend a local technical college to become an electrician, and often went jogging for exercise.</p>
<p>In general, because of this overwhelming bias, it is hard to trust the information about Arbery that was provided by his family and their lawyer and cannot be verified, e.g., with documents. We can’t say with confidence much more about his background than what judicial records show, namely that he had a history of being armed illegally, and of attempting theft, and of showing signs of mental illness including serious impulse-control problems. This shouldn’t necessarily have had any bearing on the jury’s findings, but it does speak to the broader moral picture, and definitely belies the many MSM portraits of Arbery that were designed, in part, to whip up hatred against the men who killed him.</p>
<p>Late in 2019 Arbery had begun taking occasional jogs into a mostly white neighborhood called Satilla Shores, where the McMichaels and Bryan lived. A video camera also had recorded him, in his jogging clothes, walking into a house in the neighborhood that was under construction—this had happened several times, mostly at night.</p>
<p>In the months immediately preceding his fateful encounter with the McMichaels, there also had been several break-ins or thefts in the neighborhood, including the theft of a gun from an unlocked truck—reported by Travis McMichael on January 1.</p>
<p>On the night of February 11, according to Wikipedia:</p>
<p style="padding-left: 40px;">Travis called <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/9-1-1">9-1-1</a> to report a slender 6-foot-tall Black man with short hair, wearing red shorts and a white shirt, who was trespassing on the site of a house under construction. Travis said, &#8220;I&#8217;ve never seen this guy before in the neighborhood.&#8221; The <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dispatcher#Emergency_dispatchers">dispatcher</a> asked whether Travis was OK, and he said, &#8220;Yeah, it just startled me. When I turned around and saw him and backed up, he reached into his pocket and ran into the house. So I don&#8217;t know if he&#8217;s armed or not. But he looked like he was acting like he was.&#8221; &#8220;We&#8217;ve been having a lot of burglaries and break-ins around here lately&#8221;, Travis said on the call. He told the dispatcher that he was out in his truck, and that as many as four neighbors were out looking for the man. His father Gregory was one of the people out searching that night, and Gregory and at least one other neighbor were armed. Police responded and searched the house along with a neighbor, but found no one. However, surveillance video from that evening showed a man who reportedly looked like Arbery, briefly walking in and out of the house under construction. He did not take anything. The under-construction house did not have doors or windows.</p>
<p>While Arbery died before the mystery of the local thefts could be solved, there doesn’t seem to be any evidence that exonerates him in all those thefts, despite the MSM’s implications otherwise. Given his background and the correspondence of his jogging and the local burglaries, it seems at least plausible—and evidently many Satilla Shores residents suspected—that he used his jogging at night as a cover for burglaries, and jogging in daytime to select his night-time targets. (I would be interested to know whether the burglaries continued after Arbery’s death, but haven’t seen any reference to such data.)</p>
<p>On the 23<sup>rd</sup> of February, shortly after one o’clock in the afternoon, Arbery once again ran into Satilla Shores, and into the house under construction, and once again was recorded on video camera.</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-291" src="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/Arbery-in-house.jpg" alt="" width="768" height="453" srcset="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/Arbery-in-house.jpg 768w, https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/Arbery-in-house-300x177.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 709px) 85vw, (max-width: 909px) 67vw, (max-width: 984px) 61vw, (max-width: 1362px) 45vw, 600px" /></p>
<p>A neighbor, Matthew Albenze, also spotted Arbery and called 911 to report the trespass on the building under construction. Wikipedia again:</p>
<p style="padding-left: 40px;">The 9-1-1 dispatcher asked if the man was &#8220;breaking into it right now?&#8221; The caller replied: &#8220;No &#8230; it&#8217;s all open.&#8221; After the caller said the man was now &#8220;running down the street&#8221;, the dispatcher said police would respond. The dispatcher asked at 1:08 p.m., &#8220;I just need to know what he was doing wrong. Was he just on the premises and not supposed to be?&#8221; The caller responded, with some parts garbled, saying: &#8220;And he’s been caught on camera a bunch at night. It&#8217;s kind of an ongoing thing.&#8221;</p>
<p>Why Arbery ran away isn’t clear, but the perception among those who saw him was that he was trying to escape after stealing something from the construction site. Apparently he hadn’t stolen anything, but if he had known that the cops had been called, then, being on probation, he might have wanted to avoid another brush with the law. Then again, if Arbery was mentally ill, it is probably pointless to try to rationalize his actions.</p>
<p>Soon Arbery ran past the McMichaels&#8217; house, where Gregory McMichael, working in the yard, saw him and recognized him as the repeat trespasser the neighborhood was worried about. He and Travis armed themselves and got into their white pickup truck, and gave chase.</p>
<p>The MSM accounts, and the account of the prosecutor, are worded to suggest that the McMichaels were racist good-old-boys who pursued Arbery that day simply because they wanted to hunt down, and snuff out the life of, an innocent black man whose only &#8220;crime&#8221; was “jogging while black.” To say that this is false, and as such represents both journalistic and prosecutorial misconduct, would be putting it very mildly. Both McMichaels had law enforcement experience, and obviously (all the evidence leans this way) were attempting a citizen’s arrest, a procedure that has a long history in the United States and at the time was specifically sanctioned in Georgia law. In other words, they wanted only to detain Arbery so that he could be questioned by police.</p>
<p>Whether they had sufficient reason to attempt a citizen’s arrest is debatable. However, to say that in the heat of the moment someone slightly exceeding his rights under a citizen’s arrest law <em>automatically will be charged with false imprisonment, and then murder for defending his life when the mentally ill arrestee attacks him, </em>is completely absurd. Citizen’s arrest laws are not meant to sanction vigilantism, but they also are not meant to be life-destroying traps for honest citizens who are trying to protect their neighborhoods—in what was here a demonstrable absence of effective policing.</p>
<p>The McMichaels tried unsuccessfully to cut off Arbery as he ran, and, they said later, even asked him to stop and let them talk to him, but he didn’t respond and continued running in an attempt to evade them. They could easily have shot him, if killing him had been their intent, but they did not; they simply kept trying to get him to stop.</p>
<p>At some point Bryan, who had seen the chase go by his own house, joined in with his black pickup truck and tried—again, unsuccessfully—to cut off the running man. Note that Bryan was not a close friend of the McMichaels; he was merely another resident in this neighborhood that was now literally up in arms over the rash of thefts and trespassings, and hoped to put the perp behind bars.</p>
<p>Ultimately the McMichaels gave up pursuing Arbery—apparently the neighborhood had many open yards through which he could always evade them—and simply parked their pickup at a crossing where they thought he was likely to appear in his attempt to get away.</p>
<p>At this point, just several minutes after Albenze’s 911 call, Travis McMichael, standing on the road by the driver’s side door, made his own 911 call—but then saw Arbery coming and handed the phone to his father, who stood in the truck bed:</p>
<p style="padding-left: 40px;">a male caller said: &#8220;I&#8217;m out here at Satilla Shores &#8230;There&#8217;s a Black male running down the street.&#8221; The 9-1-1 dispatcher asked, &#8220;Where at Satilla Shores?&#8221; The caller replied: &#8220;I don&#8217;t know what street we&#8217;re on.&#8221;</p>
<p>Arbery now as he approached apparently saw Travis standing with his shotgun by the open driver&#8217;s door on the left side of the pickup truck. Arbery might have turned around or veered onto either of the lawns beside the narrow road. Instead he kept running towards the truck, though he altered course to the right side of the road, and then ran along the right side of the truck, just a few feet from Gregory McMichael who stood in the truck bed talking to 911. When he reached the front of the truck, Arbery suddenly cut left and charged Travis.</p>
<p>This was the impulse that killed Arbery. You and I, and pretty much every sane person aware of the story, know this, and know that we would never have done what he did. We know that we would have stopped, and we know that if Arbery had stopped, as he&#8217;d been asked, he would still be alive, the McMichaels and Bryan would be free, and none of us would have heard of any of them.</p>
<p>But Arbery charged Travis. Bryan, who had been in pursuit of Arbery, parked his pickup in time to catch most of this tragic encounter on his cellphone camera.</p>
<p>Arbery in his fatal lunge had almost reached Travis when the latter fired his shotgun, catching Arbery in the chest. Arbery kept coming and tried to wrest the gun away from Travis. Meanwhile Gregory McMichael, with the phone still to his ear and the line to the 911 dispatcher still open, screamed at Arbery to stop.</p>
<p style="padding-left: 40px;">The caller shouted, &#8220;Stop! &#8230; Watch that. Stop, damn it! Stop!&#8221;</p>
<p>Why did Gregory McMichael shout at Arbery to stop? Well, obviously because he and his son had never intended to kill Arbery and were astonished that he was making it necessary.</p>
<p>Arbery did not stop. He kept struggling for the shotgun until Travis had shot him with it a total of three times. After the third shot, which went through the left side of his chest, Arbery quickly weakened, staggered, and collapsed to the pavement.</p>
<p><strong>Aftermath<br />
</strong></p>
<p>Alerted by the first 911 call, the police soon arrived. Arbery by then was dead. Travis McMichael was splashed in blood and evidently in shock (“No, I’m not all right,” he told the cop. “I just fucking killed someone.”)</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" class="size-full wp-image-296 aligncenter" src="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/arbery4-1.jpg" alt="" width="800" height="450" srcset="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/arbery4-1.jpg 800w, https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/arbery4-1-300x169.jpg 300w, https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/arbery4-1-768x432.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 709px) 85vw, (max-width: 909px) 67vw, (max-width: 984px) 61vw, (max-width: 1362px) 45vw, 600px" /></p>
<p>But, along with his father, he cooperated. Bryan cooperated too. They freely discussed the events of the preceding minutes, evidently without any sense of having committed a crime. The police did not arrest them, and the local district attorney’s office did not charge them. The Brunswick Circuit DA, Jackie Johnson, saw the case as an unfortunate but not really criminal one involving a mentally ill young man who essentially had brought about his own death through his own impulsive and violent actions.</p>
<p>Johnson had connections to the McMichaels, though, so she recused herself and turned the thing over to a neighboring district, Waycross Judicial Circuit District. The DA there, George Barnhill, felt the same way about the case. According to Wikipedia:</p>
<p style="padding-left: 40px;">On April 2, Barnhill wrote a memorandum to Glynn County police, recommending that no arrests be made. Barnhill wrote that the McMichaels were within their rights to chase &#8220;a burglary suspect, with solid firsthand probable cause&#8221;; that &#8220;Arbery initiated the fight&#8221;; and that Travis McMichael &#8220;was allowed to use deadly force to protect himself&#8221; when &#8220;Arbery grabbed the shotgun&#8221;.</p>
<p>By this time, of course, Arbery’s family had got a lawyer, “leaders of the black community” were getting involved, and there were demands for a prosecution. So the whiff of racial protest, with all that entails for a prosecutor’s career, was already in the air. Soon Barnhill washed his hands of the case, with a rather tenuous excuse:</p>
<p style="padding-left: 40px;">Arbery had previously been prosecuted by his son, a prosecutor for the Brunswick Circuit District Attorney&#8217;s Office, in an earlier case [and] one of the defendants [Gregory McMichael] had served as an investigator on the same prosecution.</p>
<p>And so, on April 13, the Georgia Attorney General&#8217;s Office handed the case to another nearby venue, the Atlantic Judicial Circuit.</p>
<p>It’s unclear what would have happened if the case had simply been left at the Atlantic Judicial Circuit, with no new event to inflame the situation, but presumably its DA, one Tom Durden, would have been under the same political pressures as the two DAs that had passed on the case.</p>
<p>What did happen is this: On May 5 a local defense lawyer who had consulted informally with Gregory and Travis McMichael uploaded Bryan’s cellphone video to the website of a local radio station. Stories were circulating to the effect that Arbery had simply been gunned down while jogging, and the lawyer apparently thought that the video would convince the public of the McMichaels’ innocence. He thought wrong—not because the video shows the McMichaels to be murderers, but simply because it somewhat shockingly depicts a young African-American man’s death at the hands of two fairly stereotypical-looking southern white fellows. This publication of the video was, remember, in one of the hardest, most <a href="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/the-critical-mass-problem/">hysterogenic</a> periods of the COVID-19 pandemic. Just a few weeks later, America would erupt in the Great Awokening after George Floyd’s death—but even now it was clear that this society was becoming very restive under pressure, and its politicians and politically sensitive prosecutors were doing what they could to placate the more restive elements.</p>
<p>From Wikipedia again:</p>
<p style="padding-left: 40px;">Within hours of the video becoming public, Tom Durden, the district attorney for Georgia&#8217;s Atlantic Judicial Circuit, said that he would present the case to &#8220;the next available grand jury in Glynn County&#8221; to decide if charges should be filed. The convening of grand juries had been postponed until after June 12 due to the COVID-19 pandemic. Durden accepted <em>Georgia Governor Brian Kemp&#8217;s offer</em> to bring in the Georgia Bureau of Investigation (GBI) to investigate. [italics mine]</p>
<p>At this point, with the most senior state politician getting involved in what should have been an obscure case, and more or less signaling—virtue-signaling—which way it should go, the McMichaels’ fate was sealed.</p>
<p style="padding-left: 40px;">The GBI found probable cause to charge Gregory and Travis McMichael within 36 hours of taking over jurisdiction of the case, and, on May 7, arrested and charged them with felony murder. The McMichaels were booked into the Glynn County Jail. At an appearance before a judge the following day, the McMichaels were both denied bond.</p>
<p>A few days later, Bryan too was arrested and charged.</p>
<p><strong>Ladies of the Jury</strong></p>
<p>When the case came before a jury, it was widely reported that eleven of the twelve jurors were white. It was much less widely reported that nine of those eleven were women.</p>
<p>Women, as I have been <a href="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/the-great-feminization/">writing</a> for the past decade, “wear the pants” now in most Western societies, i.e., have unprecedented and often dominant influence in many realms of culture. This is important because on average women think about and react to the world differently than men. Compared to men, for example, women seem much more emotionally aroused by stories of white-on-black racial conflict. Women, white women, also appear to have been the<a href="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/the-critical-mass-problem/"> dominant participants</a> in the bizarre BLM frenzy of the summer 2020 Great Awokening.</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" class="size-full wp-image-225 aligncenter" src="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2021/06/bethesdaawokening-1.jpg" alt="" width="800" height="450" srcset="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2021/06/bethesdaawokening-1.jpg 800w, https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2021/06/bethesdaawokening-1-300x169.jpg 300w, https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2021/06/bethesdaawokening-1-768x432.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 709px) 85vw, (max-width: 909px) 67vw, (max-width: 984px) 61vw, (max-width: 1362px) 45vw, 600px" /></p>
<p>If the McMichael/Bryan defense lawyers had read my essays, they would have known this (I write this only half-jokingly—my essays are not <em>that</em> obscure) and accordingly might have tried a different jury-selection strategy—though really, as this and many other examples show, the jury system in the United States is generally unlikely to deliver justice in cases where the forces of Wokeness favor one side.</p>
<p>In any case, the jury members were mostly women, the DA that ultimately charged the three defendants was a black woman (she claimed at the trial, among other things, that the defendants “chased, hunted down and ultimately executed” Arbery), and the lead prosecutor in the trial was a woman. And of course, Al Sharpton sat in the courtroom with Arbery’s family, and a mob of demonstrators camped outside the court building, to remind those sensitive women of the jury what they would face if they delivered the wrong verdict.</p>
<p>The jury, without much deliberation, duly returned a verdict of guilty on most of the charges. These charges included felony murder for all three defendants&#8212;even Bryan who had not been armed and had done nothing more than pursue Arbery in his truck. Travis McMichael, who presumably would have been killed by Arbery had he not defended himself, was additionally found guilty of “malice murder,” which means murder with “express or implied malice.”</p>
<p>These charges bring a minimum 30-year sentence before the possibility of parole, and for Travis McMichael, with the additional malice murder rap, there may be no parole—that will be up to the judge.</p>
<p>The Biden Administration, of course, watched this show trial approvingly.</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" class="size-full wp-image-297 aligncenter" src="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/biden.jpg" alt="" width="604" height="507" srcset="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/biden.jpg 604w, https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/biden-300x252.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 709px) 85vw, (max-width: 909px) 67vw, (max-width: 984px) 61vw, (max-width: 1362px) 45vw, 600px" /></p>
<p>However, it isn&#8217;t going to let it go at that. No, the Biden Administration via its “Justice” Department will try to earn further brownie points in the eyes of its voter base, and at the same time try to crush the spirit of conservative Legacy Americans, by pursuing a federal hate-crime trial of the McMichaels and Bryan—scheduled to convene next year.</p>
<p>Meanwhile the state of Georgia, led by “Republican” Gov. Brian Kemp, will also send a message by prosecuting former Brunswick Circuit DA Jackie Johnson—the first one to recuse herself, remember—for “obstruction of justice.” This will ensure that, the next time a black person in Georgia is killed by whites for any reason whatsoever, local DAs will show the proper Stakhanovite zeal in prosecuting.</p>
<p><strong>Flaws in the Law</strong></p>
<p>Note that Georgia law defines the kind of murder alleged in the case as follows:</p>
<p style="padding-left: 40px;">(a) A person commits the offense of murder when he unlawfully and with malice aforethought, either express or implied, causes the death of another human being.</p>
<p style="padding-left: 40px;">(b) Express malice is that deliberate intention unlawfully to take the life of another human being which is manifested by external circumstances capable of proof. Malice shall be implied where no considerable provocation appears and where all the circumstances of the killing show an abandoned and malignant heart.</p>
<p style="padding-left: 40px;">(c) A person commits the offense of murder when, in the commission of a felony, he or she causes the death of another human being irrespective of malice.</p>
<p>Did “<em>all the circumstances of the killing</em> show an abandoned and malignant heart” on the part of Travis McMichael? The answer is obviously <em>no</em>. He did not shoot Arbery from the window of his truck (or at any time until charged) as he would have done had his intent been murderous; he phoned 911 prior to the fatal encounter; he did not flee the scene of the killing; he showed every sign of having been shaken by that killing because he had not expected it; and he cooperated with the police who came to the scene. If he had an “abandoned and malignant heart” (why are these vague and archaic descriptors even allowed in the legal code?) he would have acted like a typical premeditated killer, shooting Arbery in a way that would not implicate himself, and denying involvement if questioned. I can imagine that a lot of American men who are forced to live with the problem of Black crime will now prefer that option, at least those men who are not totally demoralized by show trials like these.</p>
<p>The bigger problem here is the implied notion, noted above, that even mildly overinterpreting a citizen’s arrest law, as any concerned citizen might easily do without bad intent, can abruptly (by the whim of a biased jury) turn the citizen into a felon, and then a murderer if he has to defend himself against the arrestee’s violence. If such a notion were valid, a citizen’s arrest law would be worse than worthless. It would be as if the government invited motorists to drive across a very long and narrow, guardrail-less bridge over a mile-deep gorge, having positioned the bridge in such a way that it constantly swayed and shimmied in the wind. It effectively would be no bridge at all—only a deathtrap for the unwary.</p>
<p><strong>The Malignant Heart of the Matter<br />
</strong></p>
<p>Is there even any point in arguing over the legal questions at the heart of such cases? I can remember many racially tinged travesties of justice in my adult life, going back at least to the O.J. Simpson trial of 1995. These cases always feel like inversions of the <em>To Kill a Mockingbird </em>setup—either an apparently guilty black man goes free or gets off lightly, or a wrongfully prosecuted white man has his life ruined. More importantly, the process by which these injustices occur is always (as in Harper Lee’s model of 1930s small-town Alabama) a social process involving race-politics pressures as well as a lot of venality, cowardice, and hysteria. Tom Wolfe somehow got away with writing a big novel,<em> Bonfire of the Vanities</em>, about the modern versions of these circuses, a novel that even in 1987 conveyed strongly the message that American society and its judicial system had been irretrievably broken by decades of racial factionalism.</p>
<p>Similarly, what really drew my attention to this case was the evidence of race-politics pressure on DAs and politicians, the jury’s disregard for the basic evidence that should have exonerated the defendants, the MSM&#8217;s wanton mischaracterizations of the case (go back and read their accounts!), and then, above all, the overwhelmingly positive, smug reaction to the verdict by so many Americans.</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" class="wp-image-298 aligncenter" src="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/latimes.jpg" alt="" width="516" height="432" srcset="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/latimes.jpg 598w, https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/latimes-300x251.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 516px) 85vw, 516px" /></p>
<p><img loading="lazy" class=" wp-image-299 aligncenter" src="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/uygur.jpg" alt="" width="510" height="131" srcset="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/uygur.jpg 621w, https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/uygur-300x77.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 510px) 85vw, 510px" /></p>
<p><img loading="lazy" class=" wp-image-300 aligncenter" src="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/king.jpg" alt="" width="434" height="272" srcset="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/king.jpg 610w, https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/king-300x188.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 434px) 85vw, 434px" /></p>
<p>Of course, Twitter and social media generally are full of people who can cheaply virtue-signal while never having to deal with the unhappy realities afflicting ordinary Americans. Stephen King, for example, lives in a humongous complex on a barrier-island beach south of Sarasota—I know because I once lived nearby—at the least-accessible extremity of a wealthy neighborhood that was designed by its residents to keep out the riffraff, including anyone who looks remotely like Ahmaud Arbery. From that fortress King is unlikely ever to have to face the problem of burglary or thievery, and anyway any losses from such property crime would be infinitesimal in their impact on him.</p>
<p>But I think virtue-signaling is only a small and secondary part of this. Over the past few years, and especially since the COVID pandemic started, the more or less diffuse growth of wokeness in American life seems to have cohered into a Salem-like episode of socially sanctioned savagery&#8212;arguably almost as deadly as Salem, and much more broad and durable. I’ve even had the vague imaginative sense (from a distance, as an expatriate) that this mass hysteria has been developing into a kind of cult, presided over by a collectively summoned black perp-god, or purple-haired Gender Studies goddess, who in strident tones demands a constant flow of human sacrifices. (Another <a href="https://vdare.com/articles/john-derbyshire-the-arbery-show-trial-begins-more-human-sacrifices-to-appease-the-blm-gods">writer</a> elaborated this human-sacrifice concept before me, so I will mostly leave that imagery to him.)</p>
<p>The centrality of pictures and videos should give us a clue to how these weird social phenomena arise. If, let us say, a young black man, a man like Ahmaud Arbery, is found dead in the street by gunshot one day, but there is no video evidence of how he was killed, what will be the public reaction? The reader knows the answer already, because such cases occur many times per day across the US, especially in heavily black cities such as Chicago, St. Louis, Detroit and Baltimore. There is generally <em>no</em> reaction, <em>no</em> wider resonance. The man’s family may weep. They may call on the police to solve the crime. But usually only if the cops identify a white suspect (a relatively rare event) will the case make out of the back pages of the papers, and only if the white-on-black killing is caught on video (much rarer) is the case sure to be lifted from the muck of the ordinary criminal court docket into the glare of a Woke Cult show trial.</p>
<p>People in general, and I guess women moreso than men on average, are apt to be distressed when they witness—for example on a video—a violent death. The distress in turn creates a sense of urgency <em>to do something</em>. (Consider how heavily US foreign and immigration policies in recent years have been <a href="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/the-great-feminization/">driven</a> by distressing images in the media, e.g., of wounded children in Syria or refugee children crossing the Rio Grande.) Distress also tends to suppress rational thought, making the mind more susceptible to the beating tom-toms (to paraphrase McLuhan) of mass delusion and madness. And when a killing depicted on a distressing video can be made to seem even remotely consistent with the central wokelore motif of <em>evil whites harming innocent blacks</em>—that very live snarl of wires in the American psyche—the mass delusion and madness will come together and start to lurch in a predictable direction. It will start to be controlled and guided, to do meaningful political work, by a political faction that I would say definitely has “an abandoned and malignant heart.”</p>
<p>It seems to me that there are usually two main group of actors that ignite these episodes: blacks who from basic instinct or family ties support fellow blacks in conflicts with whites, and a certain large stratum of white women who have, in regard to blacks, a powerful guilt and appeasement reflex. Once those two groups start up and gather steam, craven politicians and their judicial minions join in with the rapidity of scurrying rodents, and then the superorganism swells to its maximum size with the additions of journalists and millions of ordinary and celebrity virtue-signalers. This frenzied entity of many voices and noises somehow achieves a certain harmony as it demands “justice,” which is code for: give us a white victim.</p>
<p>One cannot overemphasize how <em>un</em>interested in truth is this entity. In the case of Derek Chauvin, the entity assured us that the smirk on Chauvin’s face as he held down George Floyd was simply his sadist-cop’s delight at the approaching demise of his poor African American victim. Chauvin was a police officer with long experience of having to deal with unruly and bullshitting black perps, and of course did not have the clairvoyance to know that this particular perp, this one unlucky time, was telling the truth—but try explaining that to some vapor-brained leftist millennial or wine-aunt who is caught up in the full guilt-hate-love ecstasy of the Awokening.</p>
<p>In the case of Kyle Rittenhouse, the entity (speaking even through the man who is the current US president) assured us that the defendant was a white supremacist who had gone hunting for innocent protesters. The entity let it be known among the softer minded that Rittenhouse&#8217;s victims were black&#8212;this became a very widespread perception. Rittenhouse avoided becoming the next sacrificial victim mainly because the people he had shot in self defense were actually white. It must have helped too that he, Rittenhouse, was a cherubic-looking lad liable to trigger the protective maternal instincts of many American women—instincts that are normally directed entirely toward the shooting victim in such cases, at least when the victim is black.</p>
<p>In Georgia, of course, the victim was indeed black and the accused were southern whites who drove pickup trucks, carried guns, probably had a few Confederate flags around, and probably held African Americans in low esteem. On the great totem pole of wokeism, these men were the lowest of the low. Thus, the story the entity told of their vile misdeeds, in the MSM, in social media, in the courtroom through the mouths of sworn officers of the court, was a festival of lies and obfuscations, and essentially the defendants had no defenders other than their paid lawyers.</p>
<p>The victims of human sacrifice in ancient times often were drawn from the lowest, most marginalized castes. Is it not plausible that tens of thousands of years of primitive religion have worn certain paths into our minds such that even now we subconsciously act out those rituals&#8212;and perhaps can even experience, every so often, the vivid illusion that an angry god is present and wants to be appeased?</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" class="size-full wp-image-302 aligncenter" src="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/floyd.jpg" alt="" width="529" height="730" srcset="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/floyd.jpg 529w, https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/floyd-217x300.jpg 217w" sizes="(max-width: 529px) 85vw, 529px" /></p>
<p>This particular deity will never stay appeased for long, though, will it? And as evidence accumulates that America’s grand racial experiment has failed, will Americans ever face up to that failure and respond rationally? Or will that failure just drive them crazier and crazier, as they deliver more and more sacrificial victims to a god who will not relent?</p>
<p style="text-align: center;">***</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
