<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>The Right &#8211; Thoughts of Stone</title>
	<atom:link href="/category/the-right/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>/</link>
	<description>short essays, usually about humans</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Mon, 18 Sep 2023 22:45:25 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=6.2.3</generator>

<image>
	<url>/wp-content/uploads/2020/07/cropped-icon-32x32.jpg</url>
	<title>The Right &#8211; Thoughts of Stone</title>
	<link>/</link>
	<width>32</width>
	<height>32</height>
</image> 
	<item>
		<title>THE IDEA THAT GOT AWAY</title>
		<link>/the-idea-that-got-away/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[j stone]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 30 Aug 2023 20:37:25 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[A.I.]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[ideas]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[psychology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[technology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[The Right]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[wokeism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[women]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=842</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[A cautionary tale, and a plea for change “But are you strong enough now for a truly big fish?” —The Old Man and the Sea &#160; Have you ever had a Big Idea—an idea with the potential to transform the way people think about their society and culture? Imagine that you had such a Big &#8230; <a href="/the-idea-that-got-away/" class="more-link">Continue reading<span class="screen-reader-text"> "THE IDEA THAT GOT AWAY"</span></a>]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><em>A cautionary tale, and a plea for change</em></p>
<p><span id="more-842"></span></p>
<p>“But are you strong enough now for a truly big fish?”</p>
<p>—<em>The Old Man and the Sea</em></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>Have you ever had a Big Idea—an idea with the potential to transform the way people think about their society and culture?</p>
<p>Imagine that you had such a Big Idea, but you weren’t a professional opinionator and didn’t have an easy way of getting your Big Idea “out there” in front of a lot of readers.</p>
<p>Imagine too that your Big Idea was going to be controversial enough, in mainstream circles, that publication under your own name would almost certainly cost you your livelihood.</p>
<p>What would you do?</p>
<p>Here is what I did—and, as they say, don’t try this at home.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><strong>THE BIG IDEA</strong></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>Before getting into the timeline of events, I want to emphasize that I have written this in part for the benefit of other, younger writers, who may read it someday and find it useful&#8212;as an account of a process that is relevant to their ambitions but seldom set forth in detail. More than that, though, I see this as a &#8220;case history&#8221; supporting an argument for changes in how we deal with new ideas (of the non-copyrightable, non-patentable variety) and incentivize their originators.</p>
<p>Now to the what and when: It all started early in the new millennium, after I returned to the US following a decades-long sojourn abroad. As I settled in, certain differences in American culture, compared to what I’d known as a young adult, started becoming apparent. Themes of “trauma” and suffering seemed much more prominent in the culture, from media to medicine. Public policy debates were often competitive exercises in projecting compassion, or “empathy,” in regard to supposed victims. Political correctness, a hypersensitive projection of concern for the disadvantaged, seemed out of control. Even in my own somewhat technical line of work, I noticed similar changes in tone and emphasis.</p>
<p>Eventually the proverbial lightbulb winked on. As I put it in an essay (“<a href="https://james-the-obscure.github.io/the-demise-of-guythink/">The Demise of Guythink</a>”) in late 2011:</p>
<p style="padding-left: 40px;">… these empathy-related changes in public discourse are due in large part to the recent, unprecedented entry of women into public life in Western countries. Women have not only the right to vote but also a presence in key areas of society—science, law, business, politics—as never before, and it would be hard to believe that their influence has not changed the culture, bending it towards their own cognitive style. People now use the jokey phrase “endangered white male” . . . but what may be truly endangered here is the male cognitive style.</p>
<p style="padding-left: 40px;">That may not be a good thing, if the male cognitive style evolved to be optimal for managing societies, while the female cognitive style is tuned for the rearing of children. There is a tendency in our culture now to treat empathy as a trait to be simply maximized. But “understanding and building systems,” as [Simon] Baron-Cohen puts it, is useful, too—and perhaps most if not all of our culture’s greatest failings now come not from a lack of empathy but from a failure to see how complex systems fit together, and how they may fly apart.</p>
<p style="padding-left: 40px;">What also worries me is that too much empathy, or other related aspects of the female cognitive style, may be—we don’t know; probably no scientist would go near this question—less compatible with the reasoned debate and calm analytical thinking that are presumably needed in a healthy democracy, or in any mature society. Several years ago, then-Harvard President Lawrence Summers (who was later a White House adviser) referred rather delicately to the possibility that male/female cognitive differences partly explain the relative lack of female professors in math and science; he was, in effect, shouted down and forced from his post….</p>
<p style="padding-left: 40px;">An inflexible, authoritarian, shout-them-down tendency is often said to be a feature of PC-think generally. PC-driven marches and protests (on campuses for example) typically are meant not to broaden a discourse but, rather, to repel or suppress an unwanted speaker—much as a mother, without any pretense of democracy or debate, would try to protect her children from an unwanted influence or their own innate waywardness. (“Because I said so!”)</p>
<p>There it was: the Big Idea! And it <em>was</em> big! What other theory had the same power to explain the dramatic waves of change that have been sweeping through modern societies in the past few decades? What other theory combined such a simple and compelling framework of understanding with such dark implications for Western civilization?</p>
<p>I posted “The Demise of Guythink” on a website I had set up—of very modest readership—where for several years I had published various short essays on cultural and science-related topics (anonymously, though some readers knew who I was).</p>
<p><img decoding="async" class="aligncenter wp-image-868" src="/wp-content/uploads/2023/08/demise-of-guythink-wayback-1.jpg" alt="" width="416" height="489" /></p>
<p>As time went on, though, and the novelty and importance of this idea grew in my estimation, I increasingly thought of getting it published more prominently.</p>
<p>The problem was that I had no clear path for achieving that. I wasn’t a complete nobody—as a journalist, I had written a few books, and more than a few newspaper and magazine pieces, including op-eds. But that had been in the relatively distant past. Moreover, as the world had grown richer and the Internet had become a supremely powerful tool, the barriers to entry for becoming a “writer” had collapsed to virtually nothing, creating more competition than ever and making the process of big-media publication, from a cold start, harder than it had ever been. I pitched a roughly 600-word version of my thesis to the <em>Wall Street Journal</em>’s op-ed people around that time . . . and, if memory serves, got the same result one would get from dropping a small stone into the darkness of a mile-deep well.</p>
<p>I might have persevered with other newspapers or webzines, but I soon concluded that that could be an uphill, potentially very costly struggle. The standard line set down by feminist activists—<em>de facto</em> thought leaders for Western women—was that the fairer sex was still hindered, harassed and victimized by all the things men did, and thus needed ever more power to achieve full emancipation and equality. Indeed, it seemed to me that women’s ability to influence men had <em>always</em> depended heavily on their claims to be relatively weak, needing special protection, etc. In other words, in the age-old power contest with males, females’ claims of powerlessness and victimization were basically reflexive and relentless. Thus, my observation that women were already moving past parity and achieving real dominance in many key areas of public life, from teaching and publishing to psychiatry . . . was likely to be dismissed as a fantasy, or, worse, suppressed as a heresy.</p>
<p>My further suggestion that women’s new dominance in Western civilization was hazardous to that civilization, because maternal thinking was not suited to the public sphere, would make this a heresy to be suppressed with extreme prejudice. I imagined screams, shouts and ululations until I was well and truly cancelled and silenced—to the extent that feminists and the Left had to take notice of me. So, publishing my Big Idea prominently under my own name didn’t seem wise, at least not before my retirement, which was still a long way off.</p>
<p>I can’t remember whether I received any direct feedback on the piece I posted on my website—I didn’t have the time or energy to maintain a comments section. But the site analytics suggested that it was read by at least thousands of people over the next year or so. A “<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Manosphere">manosphere</a>” writer named Matt Forney linked to it in one of his own blog posts. That’s pretty much all I remember about its impact.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><strong>SCRATCHING THE ITCH</strong></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>Years passed. Other events and interests held my attention. It was not until June of 2014 that the urge to write about cultural feminization rose up in me again.</p>
<p>This time I pitched a piece on the subject to <em>Takimag</em>, a small webzine that, although I didn’t normally read it, struck me as suitably uninhibited. The editor, the daughter of <em>Takimag</em>’s proprietor, said she was potentially interested, but wanted it shortened in a few ways. I complied and re-sent it. She then replied simply that she couldn’t use it after all. I was left with no clear idea of her reason, though naturally it occurred to me that pitching this idea to female editors was not an optimal strategy.</p>
<p>Where else could I send it? I figured that if even <em>Takimag</em>—somewhat fringy, and typically framed by the mainstream media as “far right”—wouldn’t touch this hot potato of an idea, and if female editors were problematic, then I’d have to venture still further out onto the fringe. The obvious place was the manosphere.</p>
<p>As a middle-aged family man, I didn’t have much use for “<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Game:_Penetrating_the_Secret_Society_of_Pickup_Artists">game</a>,” complaints about the contemporary dating scene, or other themes central to that subculture. But the urge to get my idea out there, somehow, anyhow, was strong now. Without much effort (though I again had to shorten my submission by quite a bit), and using a pseudonym as most of their contributors did, I got a new version of my thesis published on Roosh Valizadeh’s <a href="https://www.returnofkings.com/index.html"><em>Return of Kings</em></a> site. If you use the Wayback Machine and check the site as of late 2014, you’ll see that the piece was posted in August of that year. (It has also been archived <a href="https://theredarchive.com/blog/Return-of-Kings/thanks-to-progressivism-america-is-no-country-for.21326">here</a>.) My title was “No Country for Men,” but Roosh or one of his editors, probably for SEO reasons, changed it to “Thanks to Progressivism, America is No Country for Men.”</p>
<p><img decoding="async" class="aligncenter wp-image-854" src="/wp-content/uploads/2023/08/rok-ncfm-top.jpg" alt="" width="506" height="410" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2023/08/rok-ncfm-top.jpg 1016w, /wp-content/uploads/2023/08/rok-ncfm-top-768x622.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 506px) 85vw, 506px" /></p>
<p>It was much read and commented upon, within that circle of readers, and for some years it was easily googleable. However, as the mainstream media became more feminized and &#8220;because-I-said-so&#8221; inflexible, outlets like Roosh’s became less permissible. Ultimately—suppressed by search engines, and with most or all of his monetization routes blocked off—he was forced to shut down. So, although I didn’t see it right away, this was yet another dead-end in my quest.</p>
<p>Posting on <em>Return of Kings</em> did, however, scratch the “get it out there” itch, and another year or so passed before the itch recurred. Using my real name, I pitched a very softened version of my cultural feminization idea to the <em>Washington Post</em>, and surprisingly, the response was not a blank refusal but an invitation to submit my piece for posting in their “PostEverything” section. Looking back, I think I probably should have done that. However, at the time I saw PostEverything as a glorified Letters to the Editor forum, and reasoned that publication there would bring little reward, while leaving me with the usual risk to my livelihood. I guess I also feared that the Post’s editors would alter my thesis in ways I wouldn’t like. So I declined the offer.</p>
<p>I pitched a similar piece to one or two other places around then, and though my records and memories of those efforts have faded, the result was the same. Thus, early in 2017, I reverted once again to self-publication. Using the anti-Trump, pro-feminism <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/2017_Women%27s_March">Women’s March</a> as a peg, I posted a short presentation of my idea to a blog page on my personal, non-pseudonymous, website where I had posted a few other short essays over the years.</p>
<p>I didn’t keep it up on that site for long. A few months after it was posted, a prospective client of my consulting business, a woman with a moderately high position at a prestigious institution, read it (as indicated by my site analytics info) and immediately ghosted me. I assumed that my thesis, even as softened as it was, was the causative factor in this loss of what could have been a lucrative relationship, and immediately took it down.</p>
<p>We’re nearing the fateful Twitter years, but not there yet. In the Spring of 2018, I submitted yet another softened version of my cultural feminization thesis to <em>Quillette</em>, which was then just emerging as a new and interesting venue for non-woke thought. One of the editors, a fellow named Jamie (Palmer, I think), turned it down politely with the comment that: “Your thesis is interesting but, in the end, unpersuasive and feels like a possible correlation/causation confusion.”</p>
<p>A bit less than a year later, in March of 2019, I sent yet another version of the idea to an editor at the conservative public-policy magazine <em>City Journal</em>, but received no reply.</p>
<p>(As the reader may know already, both <em>City Journal</em> and <em>Quillette</em> have since published pieces offering versions of the cultural feminization hypothesis—pieces that make no mention of me or my essays.)</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><strong>TWITTER AND “J. STONE”</strong></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>Once again, failure to get published in other journals led me back to a more D.I.Y. mode of punditry. Later in that month of March 2019, I set up a new pseudonymous website as a home for my essays, and joined Twitter with the idea of using Twitter posts to publicize those essays.</p>
<p>I think my general idea was to be a proponent of “cold logic” over the “hot emotion” of a feminized world, so I used the domain absltzero.com. For my Twitter presence I invented the pseudonym “J. Stone,” which had the merit that it didn’t seem like a pseudonym.</p>
<p><img decoding="async" class="aligncenter wp-image-869" src="/wp-content/uploads/2023/08/j-stone-twitter.jpg" alt="" width="423" height="167" /></p>
<p>Having posted a quick version of my thesis, titled “<a href="/the-great-feminization/">The Great Feminization</a>,” on the new site, I joined Twitter and started using my tweets to advertise the essay.</p>
<p><img decoding="async" class="aligncenter wp-image-874" src="/wp-content/uploads/2023/08/absltzero-tgf-fr-wayback.jpg" alt="" width="415" height="242" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2023/08/absltzero-tgf-fr-wayback.jpg 1238w, /wp-content/uploads/2023/08/absltzero-tgf-fr-wayback-768x448.jpg 768w, /wp-content/uploads/2023/08/absltzero-tgf-fr-wayback-1200x700.jpg 1200w" sizes="(max-width: 415px) 85vw, 415px" /></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><span style="color: #ff0000;"><strong><img decoding="async" class="aligncenter wp-image-877" src="/wp-content/uploads/2023/08/tgf-tweet.jpg" alt="" width="313" height="376" /></strong></span></p>
<p>What happened next? Crickets.</p>
<p>At the time, I didn’t know much about the process of drawing attention and followers on Twitter, and anyway was unable to spend much time on it, given my day-to-day work and family responsibilities. But I did try, at least several times per week, to reply to tweets from prominent Tweeters with relevant quips followed by a link to “The Great Feminization”—in the hope that one, eventually, would read it and recommend it to his or her flock of followers.</p>
<p>“<a href="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/the-great-feminization/">The Great Feminization</a>,” by the way—though it was broadly similar to others I’d written, going all the way back to “The Demise of Guythink” in 2011—did contain a fairly pithy summary of the situation:</p>
<p style="padding-left: 40px;">Feminists these days spend a lot of time worrying about male-dominated culture—“patriarchal culture,” “sexual harassment culture,” “rape culture,” “the culture of silence,” and so on. But shouldn’t they be acknowledging the influence that women now have on culture: on workplace culture, on media culture, on campus culture, on American culture, and on Western culture generally? That feminizing influence may be the greatest single driver of the rapid social changes seen in recent decades.</p>
<p style="padding-left: 40px;">Consider the following U.S. Bureau of Labor Statistics chart of women’s civilian labor force participation rate.</p>
<p><img decoding="async" class="aligncenter wp-image-846" src="/wp-content/uploads/2023/08/fredgraph-women-1024x412-1.jpg" alt="" width="505" height="203" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2023/08/fredgraph-women-1024x412-1.jpg 1024w, /wp-content/uploads/2023/08/fredgraph-women-1024x412-1-768x309.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 505px) 85vw, 505px" /></p>
<p style="padding-left: 40px;">It shows that in 1950 only about 30 percent of working-age women were in the workforce, but by 2000 that figure had jumped to 60 percent and rivaled the participation rate for men, which had been in decline since the early 1950s.</p>
<p><img decoding="async" class="aligncenter wp-image-847" src="/wp-content/uploads/2023/08/fredgraph-men-1024x412-1.jpg" alt="" width="508" height="204" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2023/08/fredgraph-men-1024x412-1.jpg 1024w, /wp-content/uploads/2023/08/fredgraph-men-1024x412-1-768x309.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 508px) 85vw, 508px" /></p>
<p style="padding-left: 40px;">In other words, by 2000 the U.S. workforce had been mostly gender-integrated. On average, workplaces by then had almost as many women as men.</p>
<p style="padding-left: 40px;">The historic significance of this migration on its own appears to have been underappreciated. Women never made such a move, to such a degree, in any large human society in the past. It significantly altered the structure of ordinary life.</p>
<p style="padding-left: 40px;">But women in the late 20th century didn’t just move into the workforce. They moved into its upper ranks, to professions that strongly influence societal culture and policy. They became journalists, public relations specialists, lawyers, academics, novelists, publishers, filmmakers, TV producers, and politicians, all to an unprecedented extent. In some of these culture-making professions, by the 1990s and early 2000s, they had achieved parity or even dominance (e.g., writers, authors, and public relations specialists) with respect to men. Even where they fell short of full parity, they appeared to acquire considerable “veto” power over content. A 2017 report by the Women’s Media Center noted evidence that at the vast majority of media companies, at least one woman is among the top three editors.</p>
<p style="padding-left: 40px;">Why is the greater presence of women in culture-making professions important? Because women, on average, think differently than men on a wide range of subjects….</p>
<p style="padding-left: 40px;">How would culture and policy have changed as a result of women’s new influence? Presumably in ways that reflect feminine psychological traits.</p>
<p style="padding-left: 40px;">For example, women appear on average to be more empathetic and compassionate, more emotionally sensitive. Some of the most striking social changes of the last few decades appear to have been driven by a cultural shift in that direction:</p>
<ul>
<li style="list-style-type: none;">
<ul>
<li style="list-style-type: none;">
<ul>
<li style="list-style-type: none;">
<ul>
<li>More generous welfare programs</li>
<li>Expansion of the concept of welfare to include more types of intervention (affirmative action, etc.) and more groups needing intervention</li>
<li>Expansion of the definitions of “harm,” “offense,” and “trauma” (“microaggressions,” “triggers”)</li>
<li>Increased attention to psychological trauma in law and medicine, leading to a greater acceptance, and thus a higher prevalence, of trauma-related syndromes such as PTSD (and the recovered-trauma-memory syndromes of the 1990s)</li>
<li>Less tolerance of deaths in war; but, ironically, a greater inclination to enter foreign conflicts in response to emotion-evoking atrocities portrayed on television.</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li style="list-style-type: none;"><img decoding="async" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-11" src="/wp-content/uploads/2020/07/boy1.jpg" alt="" width="194" height="259" />
<ul>
<li style="list-style-type: none;">
<ul>
<li style="list-style-type: none;">
<ul>
<li>Less tolerance for capital punishment</li>
<li>Less restrictive immigration policy</li>
<li>More emphasis in media and policy contexts on emotion-evoking stories of individuals (e.g., pitiable refugee children) rather than dry analyses of long-term outcomes.</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li style="list-style-type: none;"><img decoding="async" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-848" src="/wp-content/uploads/2023/08/refugees.jpg" alt="" width="300" height="169" />
<ul>
<li style="list-style-type: none;">
<ul>
<li style="list-style-type: none;">
<ul>
<li>Suppression of any kind of emotionally disturbing speech (“hate speech,” “mansplaining,” etc.) and even fields of scientific inquiry that are likely to evoke negative emotions;</li>
<li>Less affinity for traditional, constitutionally protected forms of confrontation in the legal and political spheres, i.e., less support for open debate, free-speech rights, and “due process of law.”</li>
<li>Suppression/replacement of words that evoke emotional discomfort (e.g., “abortion clinic” becomes “women’s health center”)</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<p style="padding-left: 40px;">That’s just from one set of closely related traits. Certainly there are others. For example, women for obvious evolutionary reasons appear to have an instinctive fear of dietary and environmental toxins, which can become pronounced during pregnancy (“morning sickness,” nesting reflex, food aversions). Is it just coincidence that women’s cultural ascendancy in Western countries corresponds to a huge rise in diet-, drug-, and environment-related concerns encompassing the Green movement, anti-GMO attitudes, “detox” fads, the “herbal medicine” racket, “organic foods” preferences, and even the anti-vaccine movement?</p>
<p>Et cetera. It was a quick, accessible outline of my Big Idea, and I gathered from my website analytics that people who started reading it tended to read it through, and often sent their friends links to it.</p>
<p>Still, the daily reader count seldom got into three digits, and sometimes flatlined in the single digits for days at a time, especially if I was too distracted by work to do my reply-guy thing on Twitter. For weeks, and then months, my interest in the whole thing waned, as it just seemed unrewarding.</p>
<p>But the compulsion to get some recognition for my Big Idea was one of those relapsing/remitting conditions that can never be fully cured. Within six months of posting “The Great Feminization,” I began work on a new cultural feminization essay, centered on a more in-depth account of the aforementioned Larry Summers brouhaha.</p>
<p>I initially conceived of this essay, which came to be titled, “<a href="/the-day-the-logic-died/">The Day the Logic Died</a>,” as something that would be publishable in a respectable conservative venue. But by the time I’d finished it, and weighed its largeish word-count, I knew better, and just posted it to the absltzero.com site.</p>
<p>“The Day the Logic Died” was an exploration of the Larry Summers case as a classic early example of a cancellation hysteria created by activist, anti-rational women in academia and media—a classic demonstration, in other words, of cultural feminization and its unpleasant consequences. I also put in a hypothesis at the end about the deep reasons why men fail, again and again, to hold their own in this new female-controlled cancellation culture. Though it was a long essay, it was probably the most “writerly” one I’ve produced on this topic.</p>
<p><img decoding="async" class="aligncenter wp-image-870" src="/wp-content/uploads/2023/08/TDTLD-fr2019.jpg" alt="" width="498" height="408" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2023/08/TDTLD-fr2019.jpg 907w, /wp-content/uploads/2023/08/TDTLD-fr2019-768x629.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 498px) 85vw, 498px" /></p>
<p>Once again, not much happened in the weeks after I posted it. But a few months later, lightning finally struck, and—using my reply-guy strategy—I succeeded in getting “The Day the Logic Died” noticed by a popular Twitter figure. This was the celebrated “Spotted Toad” (@toad_spotted), who read the essay, liked it, and recommended it to his tens of thousands of followers:</p>
<p><img decoding="async" class="aligncenter wp-image-851" src="/wp-content/uploads/2023/08/spotted-toad.jpg" alt="" width="499" height="189" /></p>
<p>Boom. The essay went “viral,” as they say—Statcounter began registering thousands of hits per day. And as people checked my posts and my bio and saw that Spotted Toad followed me, I began accumulating many more followers. To my surprise, many of these were Twitter-famous or even real-life-famous people with high follower counts of their own. They included Wesley Yang, Walter Kirn, Nick Denton, Marc Andreesen, Helen Andrews, Micah Meadowcroft, and Steve Sailer. One of the best known of these even DM’d me, wanting to know—apropos of the Larry Summers essay—if I was on the faculty at Harvard.</p>
<p>Naturally, this positive reaction encouraged me to spend more time on Twitter, and to keep posting essays on absltzero.com, including essay #3, “<a href="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/girl-power/">Girl Power</a>” (Jan 2020), in which I tried to trace the roots of modern cancel culture back to convent hysterias, Salem, and other female social contagions of yore.</p>
<p><img decoding="async" class="aligncenter wp-image-872" src="/wp-content/uploads/2023/08/girl-power-trunc.jpg" alt="" width="413" height="262" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2023/08/girl-power-trunc.jpg 1274w, /wp-content/uploads/2023/08/girl-power-trunc-768x488.jpg 768w, /wp-content/uploads/2023/08/girl-power-trunc-1200x762.jpg 1200w" sizes="(max-width: 413px) 85vw, 413px" /></p>
<p>Writing more, both in short-form and long, was probably unwise at this point, given how little time I had to spare for it. But anyway I pressed on, publishing additional essays whenever I felt I had something reasonably new to say.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><strong>STONE’S PEAK</strong></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>Early 2020 brought the COVID crisis. Fear of what the pandemic would do, anxiety over the sudden economic shut-down, and stress over lockdown and mask-wearing rules combined to exacerbate the national frazzlement. Then in the approach to the presidential election, Democratic Party operatives’ stoking of black grievance and white guilt—achieved by pumping several police run-ins with recalcitrant African-Americans into national prominence, and organizing marches and riots—was added to this toxic mix. As I pointed out often that year, mostly in tweets and once or twice in essays, stressed American women had reached a sort of breaking point, causing them—in a <a href="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/a-spiraling-frenzy/">social mania</a> akin to the Chinese Cultural Revolution of 1966-76—to shift their society-disrupting activities into a higher gear.</p>
<p>This contagious frenzy, which Sailer aptly called the “Great Awokening,” was essentially female in a way that, I thought, made the concept of cultural feminization increasingly obvious.</p>
<p><img decoding="async" class="aligncenter wp-image-225" src="/wp-content/uploads/2021/06/bethesdaawokening-1.jpg" alt="" width="486" height="274" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2021/06/bethesdaawokening-1.jpg 800w, /wp-content/uploads/2021/06/bethesdaawokening-1-300x169.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2021/06/bethesdaawokening-1-768x432.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 486px) 85vw, 486px" /></p>
<p>Throughout 2020 and early 2021, the COVID-19 pandemic kept me busy professionally. I did find time to change the domain name of my essay website from absltzero.com to thoughtsofstone.com. I also probably made at least one or two further—now-forgotten—efforts to get published more widely. But those too failed, and by April of 2021, I was getting restless again.</p>
<p>At this point, I had enough big-name Twitter mutuals (who were routinely liking and retweeting my stuff, and reading my essays) that I felt I could ask for their help in reaching a wider audience. In April 2021, I contacted Helen Andrews, a young author and editor/writer for <em>The American Conservative</em> magazine, to see if <em>TAC</em> would be interested in running a short piece on my cultural feminization idea. Based on her tweets, Helen had struck me as very sharp-minded and conservative—and she was clearly enthusiastic about my Big Idea.</p>
<p>She was gracious in her response, reiterating her support for my thesis and heaping particular praise  on “The Day the Logic Died.” After making inquiries, she informed me that <em>The American Conservative</em> as a rule would not publish something by a pseudonymous author. As an alternative, though, she suggested <em>The American Mind</em>, a webzine produced by the Claremont Institute, and she helpfully put me in touch with its editors James Poulos and Spencer Klavan. My short piece on cultural feminization, “<a href="https://americanmind.org/salvo/pink-shift/">Pink Shift</a>,” appeared in <em>TAM’</em>s pages in early May.</p>
<p><img decoding="async" class="aligncenter wp-image-856" src="/wp-content/uploads/2023/08/pink-shift-cover.jpg" alt="" width="555" height="986" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2023/08/pink-shift-cover.jpg 1242w, /wp-content/uploads/2023/08/pink-shift-cover-768x1365.jpg 768w, /wp-content/uploads/2023/08/pink-shift-cover-864x1536.jpg 864w, /wp-content/uploads/2023/08/pink-shift-cover-1153x2048.jpg 1153w, /wp-content/uploads/2023/08/pink-shift-cover-1200x2132.jpg 1200w" sizes="(max-width: 555px) 85vw, 555px" /></p>
<p>Naturally, I felt that this was progress, in the sense that I was reaching a wider readership, and was also basically putting down a public marker of my role in advancing the cultural feminization hypothesis. But though I gained a modest number of new Twitter followers and daily readers of my essays, I was still far from my goal.</p>
<p>Months passed, and the familiar, unpleasant sense of futility grew in me. I had made a reasonable effort—especially given my work and time constraints—to get my Big Idea “out there” and noticed. Certainly a lot of people, in a strong position to help, were well aware of it and its provenance. But how could I propel this idea into the public mind strongly enough that it <em>had</em> to be confronted and considered, and never again ignored or suppressed? And what more could I do to get the recognition I felt I deserved? Whatever the true answers to those questions may have been, I did little other than what I had been doing, namely writing to small-ish media organizations and asking them to publish my Big Idea.</p>
<p>That strategy continued to <em>not</em> work, although for a while, things kept happening to prop up my hopes. One day in mid-October 2021, I did a routine check of the analytics for the thoughtsofstone.com website, and saw thousands—soon tens of thousands—of visitors to the “Great Feminization” essay page. It was clear that all these visitors were arriving via a link on a blog called <em>Marginal Revolution</em>.</p>
<p><img decoding="async" class="aligncenter wp-image-858" src="/wp-content/uploads/2023/08/cowen-link-1.jpg" alt="" width="450" height="354" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2023/08/cowen-link-1.jpg 861w, /wp-content/uploads/2023/08/cowen-link-1-768x604.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 450px) 85vw, 450px" /></p>
<p><em>Marginal Revolution</em> is the blog of Tyler Cowen, the economist, Bloomberg columnist, and all-round social media star. I wasn’t entirely surprised that “The Great Feminization” had caught his attention, as I had observed in the past that his ideas and mine sometimes ran in similar (at least marginally heretical) directions. We had even had a brief, cordial email exchange during the 2008-09 financial crisis—when he was already very popular, but far more approachable—in relation to one of my ideas (on my anonymous blog) about the future economy.</p>
<p>In any case, Cowen’s link to “The Great Feminization” widened the essay’s circulation not just for one or two days, but for weeks and months—in which many other bloggers and posters cited it approvingly, and visitor counts at the thoughtsofstone.com site stayed high.</p>
<p><img decoding="async" class="aligncenter wp-image-896" src="/wp-content/uploads/2023/08/saul01a.jpg" alt="" width="445" height="172" /></p>
<p><img decoding="async" class="aligncenter wp-image-860" src="/wp-content/uploads/2023/08/arnoldking-mention-1.jpg" alt="" width="538" height="138" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2023/08/arnoldking-mention-1.jpg 856w, /wp-content/uploads/2023/08/arnoldking-mention-1-768x197.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 538px) 85vw, 538px" /></p>
<p><img decoding="async" class="aligncenter wp-image-878" src="/wp-content/uploads/2023/08/blurb-for-tgf.jpg" alt="" width="445" height="247" /></p>
<p><img decoding="async" class="aligncenter wp-image-879" src="/wp-content/uploads/2023/08/blurb-2-for-tgf.jpg" alt="" width="545" height="334" /></p>
<p><img decoding="async" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-266" src="/wp-content/uploads/2021/11/senate-1.jpg" alt="" width="491" height="94" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2021/11/senate-1.jpg 491w, /wp-content/uploads/2021/11/senate-1-300x57.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 491px) 85vw, 491px" /></p>
<p>Toward the end of that month of October, energized by the Cowen link, I pitched another piece on cultural feminization to Twitter mutual Park MacDougald, a young editor/writer at the <em>Washington Examiner</em>. He told me he was just then bound for a new job at UK’s UnHerd, but would try to get the piece in before he left, if I could get it to him quickly. I did, we did some rapid edits, and on Oct 27 he told me the piece would be online two days later.</p>
<p>The piece—my working title was “Wokeism is a Woman”—didn’t really include anything new compared to what I’d already written on the subject. It started as follows . . .</p>
<p style="padding-left: 40px;">Consider the hypothesis that most of the dramatic social changes sweeping over Western societies in recent decades, including the rise of social justice ideology or “wokeness,” are driven not so much by a specific ideology as they are by a simple demographic shift, namely, the large-scale addition of women to the ranks of the elites.</p>
<p style="padding-left: 40px;">It is curious that this possibility has been overlooked for so long. Since the middle of the last century, women in the West have almost completely departed from their traditional stay-at-home roles. They have moved into the workforce alongside men, and have acquired power, often dominance, within all the culturally and politically influential professions. Women are now managing editors, film producers, CEOs, university presidents, cabinet secretaries, senators and congresswomen. They now help direct the culture and the policies that move all of us—the first time this has happened in a large society.</p>
<p>. . . and it ended (in the last draft I have in my files) this way:</p>
<p style="padding-left: 40px;">In any case, the most important issue about this “great feminization” is where it appears to be taking us. Do we really want to jettison things like due process and free scientific inquiry? Do we really want laws discriminating against America’s legacy population, especially white males, in the name of “equity?”</p>
<p style="padding-left: 40px;">I suspect that a lot of people, men in particular, already sense at least subconsciously that wokeism and related social changes reflect the new power of women—and hope that the worst of these changes are a sort of emotional storm that will blow over eventually if they just ignore it. I think that view overlooks, to put it mildly, wokeism’s sensational recent successes in transforming Western societies, and its strong roots among the women who help run those societies. Wokeism is too incoherent, too contrary to common sense and human nature, to last anywhere near as long as Western liberalism has. But rolling back its excesses is going to require real effort. Step one should be the recognition—as harsh as it may seem—that wokeism, far from being an enlightened vision of human progress, may be only the projection of a maternal mindset that is dangerously out of its depth.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><strong>THE SHARKS</strong></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>The day before the <em>Washington Examiner</em> piece was scheduled to appear, MacDougald DM’d me to let me know it had been put on hold. I knew that I hadn’t pulled my punches in the piece; moreover, I had experienced one or two last-minute cancellations of pieces in my earlier career as a journalist. So I was not especially surprised when, a week later, MacDougal informed me that they weren’t going to run the piece at all—and that he, about to exit, had little say in the matter. (He offered a kill fee, which I declined.)</p>
<p>It soon became clear that that had been my last chance to get my Big Idea out there and get credit for it. The &#8220;Great Awokening&#8221; had made women&#8217;s central role in wokeness and modern progressivism hard to ignore&#8212;and with that (and to some extent the influence of my own essays) other writers with easier paths to high-profile publication were starting to see an opportunity. Other than Cowen with his comment-free linking to “The Great Feminization,” none of them would acknowledge my prior contributions.</p>
<p>Less than a month after my piece on women and wokeness was killed at the <em>Washington Examiner</em>, the writer <strong>Noah Carl</strong> published a short Substack post (“<a href="https://www.noahsnewsletter.com/p/did-women-in-academia-cause-wokeness">Did Women in Academia Cause Wokeness?</a>”) arguing that the roots of wokeness lay in the feminization of academia—essentially a much narrower (and I would say incomplete) version of my own argument.</p>
<p>A very similar piece by <strong>Mary Harrington</strong> appeared on the same day, Nov. 24, in the UK webzine the <em>Critic</em>, about “<a href="https://thecritic.co.uk/issues/december-january-2022/new-female-ascendency/">The New Female Ascendancy</a>” in academia—in the administrative ranks, at least.</p>
<p style="padding-left: 40px;">Less remarked on is the sex breakdown of the growing proportion of administrators. A recent diversity and inclusion report by the University of California indicates that women make up more than 70 per cent of non-academic staff across (among others) nursing, therapeutic services, health, health technicians, communications services roles, and a majority or near majority across all non-manual staff roles. In other words, if men are still over represented in top academic roles, the non-academic supporting ecosystem is overwhelmingly female.</p>
<p style="padding-left: 40px;">And that support system has an increasingly symbiotic relationship with student activism, which over my lifetime has (on both sides of the Atlantic) shifted noticeably away from a focus on material conditions toward something more like the bureaucratic regulation of personal identity and interpersonal interactions.</p>
<p style="padding-left: 40px;">A 2015 look at student protesters across 51 campuses showed the most common demands — alongside greater diversity among faculty — were diversity training and cultural centres. In turn, this focus requires a ballooning staff tasked with managing identities, or variously supporting or disciplining types of relationship, for example via “consent” education: the roles where women predominate.</p>
<p>Overseas at the time, I was alerted to the appearance of Harrington’s piece by a nice Twitter DM from Helen Andrews:</p>
<p><img decoding="async" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-863" src="/wp-content/uploads/2023/08/xtfr34es.jpg" alt="" width="422" height="146" /></p>
<p>Certainly I agreed that I deserved credit! However, as I replied a bit morosely to Helen (after thanking her again for her help and encouragement), I knew that I probably wasn’t going to be given <em>a lot of</em> credit, given that I was a pseudonymous, non-professional essayist with no high-profile publication of my thesis. Again, it would turn out that even a <em>little</em> credit was more than I should have hoped for.</p>
<p>Surprisingly, one of the writers who advanced cultural feminization as his own big idea was <strong>Thomas Edsall</strong>, a writer for the <em>New York Times</em>, who managed to get a stealthily subversive essay on all this (“<a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2022/01/12/opinion/gender-gap-politics.html">The Gender Gap is Taking Us to Unexpected Places</a>,” 12 Jan 2022) into the Gray Lady’s pages. He quoted Tyler Cowen enough to suggest that he read Cowen’s “Marginal Revolution” blog—which to me also suggested that he had read “The Great Feminization” and that his essay might even have been prompted by it. But if one is writing a column for a woke media organ like the <em>New York Times</em>, where young, female and nonwhite activists are always <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2021/02/05/business/media/donald-mcneil-andy-mills-leave-nyt.html">looking for ways to advance by displacing white males</a>, it would be deeply imprudent to cite a pseudonymous essayist who evidently hated wokeism and other leftist  dogmas. Of course, from my perspective it would nevertheless have been the correct, honorable thing to do; but I think it&#8217;s fair to say that in American journalism now those old-fashioned ethics count for very little. Anyway, Edsall mostly stuck to the quoting of relatively dry academic and survey stuff on gender differences in attitudes, which itself was not new.</p>
<p style="padding-left: 40px;">. . . a Knight Foundation survey in 2017 of 3,014 college students asked: “If you had to choose, which do you think is more important, a diverse and inclusive society or protecting free speech rights.”</p>
<p style="padding-left: 40px;">Male students preferred protecting free speech over an inclusive and diverse society by a decisive 61 to 39. Female students took the opposite position, favoring an inclusive, diverse society over free speech by 64 to 35.</p>
<p>I’ll just list briefly a few of the other relatively prominent writers who started posting on cultural feminization, generally with the conceit that they were making an original contribution:</p>
<p><strong>Richard Hanania.</strong> Having discussed cultural feminization as a <a href="https://lnns.co/A1TOvPcmx6z">podcast guest</a> in August 2021, he <a href="https://www.richardhanania.com/p/womens-tears-win-in-the-marketplace">posted</a> one or two Substack pieces on the same topic early in 2022, with arguments very similar to my own. He was already vastly better known than I, but there was a significant overlap in our Twitter mutuals and general interests, so our stuff would have appeared on each other’s timelines quite a lot during 2019-2021.</p>
<p>Some of the commenters on Hanania’s Substack posts also linked to my older cultural feminization essays, which directed at least hundreds of his readers, and I would guess Hanania himself at some point, to my work. I couldn’t help noticing that someone in Southern California (where Hanania lived then), often using an IP address at UCLA (where he had recently been a grad student), was a frequent reader of the essays on my website. Yet as far as I know, Hanania has never acknowledged my prior contributions. (I have previously <a href="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/i-stick-my-neck-out-for-nobody/">criticized Hanania</a> for his promotions of eugenics, Vladimir Putin, the Chinese Communist Party, abortions to prevent Down Syndrome births, etc.)</p>
<p>“<strong>L0m3z.”</strong> This pseudonymous right-wing writer, prominent on Twitter, managed in early 2023 to get a few-hundred-word <a href="https://www.firstthings.com/web-exclusives/2023/02/what-is-the-longhouse">piece</a> published in <em>First Things</em> (one of the many media orgs on whose deaf ears my pitches had fallen) framing the cultural feminization hypothesis as the &#8220;longhouse&#8221; theory&#8212;a reference to longhouse-dwelling primitive societies.</p>
<p>The idea apparently derives from the book <em>Bronze Age Mindset</em> (2018) whose pseudonymous author&#8217;s references to it are pretty cursory.</p>
<p><img decoding="async" class="aligncenter wp-image-886" src="/wp-content/uploads/2023/08/bap01.jpg" alt="" width="354" height="381" /></p>
<p style="text-align: center;"> . . .</p>
<p><img decoding="async" class="aligncenter wp-image-922" src="/wp-content/uploads/2023/08/bap-longhouse-ref-2.jpg" alt="" width="388" height="459" /></p>
<p>None of that is really important anyway, since the invocation of putative longhouse-based societies clearly fails&#8212;or is just unnecessary&#8212;as an explanation for cultural feminization. Western culture has been feminized mainly because women, abandoning their traditional homemaker roles at the behest of feminists and for financial reasons, have moved into public life and have achieved critical masses in all important, culturally and politically influential Western institutions. L0m3z basically admitted this in his short piece, though he referred to other, later writers like Hanania and Edsall as having pointed this out, not to me. Like Hanania, L0m3z had had a lot of Twitter-mutual overlap with me, and, I seem to recall, followed me for a few months after Spotted Toad gave me some publicity in 2019. L0m3z also didn&#8217;t start writing on Twitter about his &#8220;longhouse&#8221; idea (judging by Twitter searches) until late 2021.</p>
<p><strong>Heather MacDonald</strong>. I had always admired MacDonald’s writing, so I was disappointed to see her <a href="https://www.city-journal.org/article/in-loco-masculi">piece</a> in <em>Urban Journal</em> in March 2023 about the feminization of academia. It seemed unoriginal from my perspective&#8212;and, I guess, also would have seemed that way from the perspective of Harrington or Carl. Worse, the initial title appears to have been “The Great Feminization of the American University,” so that, following the publication of her piece (which of course did not cite me) the Google search ranking for my &#8220;Great Feminization&#8221; essay of 2019 was obliterated, and readers searching for those keywords were directed to MacDonald’s piece instead. (The fact that <em>Urban Journal</em> changed the title hints that someone tipped them off to the existence of my essay.)</p>
<p><img decoding="async" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-884" src="/wp-content/uploads/2023/08/macdonald-1.jpg" alt="" width="612" height="565" /></p>
<p><img decoding="async" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-937" src="/wp-content/uploads/2023/08/rufo.jpg" alt="" width="562" height="514" /></p>
<p>There were a number of other pieces discussing this topic, including one in <a href="https://quillette.com/2022/10/08/sex-and-the-academy/"><em>Quillette</em></a>, and even <a href="https://www.theamericanconservative.com/into-the-longhouse/"><em>The American Conservative</em></a>. None of these pieces mentioned me. <em>No one</em> mentioned me, apart from a few tweeters in replies and blog commenters.</p>
<p><img decoding="async" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-935" src="/wp-content/uploads/2023/08/important-2019-essay.jpg" alt="" width="581" height="145" /></p>
<p><img decoding="async" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-881" src="/wp-content/uploads/2023/08/hanania1.jpg" alt="" width="775" height="178" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2023/08/hanania1.jpg 775w, /wp-content/uploads/2023/08/hanania1-768x176.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 709px) 85vw, (max-width: 909px) 67vw, (max-width: 984px) 61vw, (max-width: 1362px) 45vw, 600px" /></p>
<p>As time went on, and tardier but better-known writers&#8217; thoughts on this circulated more widely, even people who definitely knew of my work started referring to me only alongside, sometimes even after, those other writers.</p>
<p><img decoding="async" class="aligncenter wp-image-918" src="/wp-content/uploads/2023/08/kline-ref.jpg" alt="" width="398" height="305" /></p>
<p><img decoding="async" class="aligncenter wp-image-919" src="/wp-content/uploads/2023/08/bay-coaltion-ref.jpg" alt="" width="445" height="545" /></p>
<p>Of course I know that to the ones making these references, this &#8220;inclusivity&#8221; would have seemed perfectly natural, perhaps even generous towards the nobody J. Stone. Nevertheless, I felt at least a twinge of annoyance every time. &#8220;Nothing these other writers are telling you about cultural feminization is original in the slightest!&#8221; I wanted to shout. &#8220;That would become instantly obvious if any of them had the decency to cite my work!&#8221; But I knew that no one cared&#8211;I knew I was dealing with social forces just as inexorable and irrational as the ones I&#8217;d been writing about in my cultural feminization essays.</p>
<p>I continued to post occasional cultural feminization-related thoughts on Twitter . . .</p>
<p><img decoding="async" class="aligncenter wp-image-939" src="/wp-content/uploads/2023/08/virtual-children.jpg" alt="" width="493" height="359" /></p>
<p>. . . but over time I was, as they say, airbrushed from the picture.</p>
<p>It did not help that I was pseudonymous and intent upon remaining so. It also <em>emphatically</em> did not help that, early in 2022, I tweeted/posted in support of Ukraine’s struggle to withstand Russia’s invasion. A large number of my Twitter mutuals, flying flags I had not known they possessed, revealed themselves to be supporters of Putin or at least derisive skeptics about Ukraine’s ambitions to be a free country. I <a href="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/i-stick-my-neck-out-for-nobody/">expressed my own derision</a> in regard to this bizarre, anti-liberty, anti-self-determination attitude, and this resulted in my being unfollowed or muted by many. That the facts on the ground in Ukraine increasingly supported my view probably only hurt me worse in this respect.</p>
<p>In 2022, it was increasingly clear from the dwindling engagement of my tweets that I had essentially lost my audience. In April of that year, less than 12 months after my &#8220;Pink Shift&#8221; piece had appeared in <em>American Mind</em>, I organized my thoughts on cultural feminization into a self-published <a href="https://www.amazon.com/Great-Feminization-drivers-modern-social-ebook/dp/B09Z7MWJ7R/">ebook</a>, as a sort of tombstone for my eleven years of promoting this idea, and then mostly ceased writing about it. I had come to the conclusion that trying to introduce <em>and</em> get credit for an important new idea, from a standing start, on Twitter or a personal website—or on any venue with a small audience—was a mug’s game, little better than shouting to passers-by from a proverbial soap-box.</p>
<p><img decoding="async" class="aligncenter wp-image-907" src="/wp-content/uploads/2023/08/handr1.jpg" alt="" width="473" height="264" /></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>A BETTER WAY?</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>Is this just my own personal gripe—my own self-driven, bad-luck story—without relevance to the wider problems of society? I can easily believe that members of the “opinionator elite,” as I call them, would say so if pressed.</p>
<p>I also think that the vast majority of people, even highly educated people, don’t consider the process I have described significantly problematic. They encounter new ideas all the time, and they generally don’t care about recognizing these ideas’ exact provenance—they don’t see that as affecting their interests. Sure, they’ll pile on the opprobrium if a plagiarist is caught red-handed. But if some pseudonymous nobody complains about his prior work being copied and/or not cited by some mass-followed elite opinionator, the latter and his followers will scoff together at Mr. Nobody’s presumption.</p>
<p>That doesn’t mean they’re right! Consider the distribution of forces here: Firstly, there are the opinionator elites, the gatekeepers of media content and popular intellectual discourse. Obviously, they have no interest in finding fault with a situation that empowers them, and to some extent enriches them. Just as obviously, the great mass of ordinary, non-idea-originator people are not going to see a problem if the elites won’t highlight it for them.</p>
<p>Against this weight of opposition and inertia, we amateur, non-elite idea originators—surprisingly numerous but still constituting only a tiny minority in the grand scheme of things—have little chance.</p>
<p>There is also a general misconception that new ideas of the type I’m referencing here—ideas that appear in media outlets like the ones I’ve mentioned in this story—do not deserve protection because they are of a different nature than the ideas or intellectual works we do normally protect, e.g., with copyright and patent laws.</p>
<p><img decoding="async" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-929" src="/wp-content/uploads/2023/08/patent-idea-1.jpg" alt="" width="501" height="126" /></p>
<p>But while it may be true that the idea “cultural feminization is happening and is caused by women’s entry <em>en masse</em> into culturally influential institutions” is not a patentable invention and is not a book or film that can be copyrighted and sold commercially, nevertheless:</p>
<ul>
<li style="list-style-type: none;">
<ul>
<li>This idea has social value in the sense that it potentially explains many otherwise inexplicable sociocultural changes. It may not (yet) have the same perceived importance, but it belongs to the same broad category as Darwin’s theory of biological evolution, and Dawkins’s theory of <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Selfish_Gene">cultural memetics</a>;</li>
</ul>
<ul>
<li>This idea certainly can have commercial value for writers who successfully negotiate book and/or magazine deals—perhaps even lucrative sinecures at think-tanks—by claiming to have originated it.</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<p>Although I think the mechanism by which non-elite idea originators are disadvantaged is essentially non-rational—a blunt-force social suppression—I can imagine a semi-compelling reasoned case for the status quo, which would go something like this:</p>
<p style="padding-left: 40px;">People won’t believe that a new ‘Big Idea’ is valid unless the author of that idea has plenty of social support, e.g., from a substantial number of authoritative figures (i.e., elite opinionators) and/or a large mass of social media followers. Thus, the introduction of a new idea <em>must be</em>, to some extent, a popularity contest—which means that one <em>must</em> develop a sturdy network of social support before one can expect the idea to spread widely and proper credit to be given. In most cases, gathering such support requires one to write under one’s own name, instead of hiding behind a pseudonym—this is why so many media organizations refuse to publish pseudonymous authors. In short, you can choose to play the game, with a chance of winning, or you can choose to quit and be a loser.</p>
<p>I believe that this would seem reasonable to many people. But really it is not a very good argument.</p>
<p>Firstly, this “social network argument” enmires itself in, or at least fails to take account of, a logical fallacy called the genetic fallacy. This fallacy is the belief that the genesis of an idea has anything to do with the idea’s validity. In other words, if Adolf Hitler had once claimed that two plus two equals four, it would be illogical for us all to disbelieve it merely because Adolf Hitler stated it.</p>
<p>The Hitler example makes the fallaciousness obvious, but in everyday cases it’s not so obvious. In fact (as I would say my own case illustrates) it’s <em>common</em> in public discourse for a good idea to be rejected or ignored, without any consideration of its merits, because the idea-originator is either unknown or—as is true for a lot of conservative thinkers nowadays—somehow intolerably heretical, from the perspective of media gatekeepers.</p>
<p>My guess is that, despite our gatekeepers’ now having more formal education than ever, they are more prone than ever to stray into this fallacy, because there are more women than ever among these gatekeepers, and (for that reason) the culture itself is more feminized than ever. Women, on average compared to men, are drawn more to the personal, less to the abstract, and so they are more likely to consider the character or politics of a person who is voicing an argument before they consider the argument on its merits. In my experience, a shocking number of educated women <em>do not see the genetic fallacy as a real fallacy</em>. Indeed, the modern <a href="https://plato.stanford.edu/Archives/sum2023/entries/feminism-argumentation/">wokeist/feminist contention</a> that gender and ethnic identity determine the validity of one’s ideas and contributions is a bold assertion of this view.</p>
<p>Now, of course I recognize that we can’t all be abstract logicians. We are social animals, only a few million years removed from our tree-dwelling ape ancestors, and we tend to make decisions in crude ways, often involving associations that are practically useful but not necessarily linked by causal mechanisms. We are disinclined to listen or read when some unknown or fringe-y person starts pontificating—yet the same idea, restated by a mainstream thinker, will be much more likely to get our attention. This does seem natural to us.</p>
<p>Natural doesn’t mean optimal, though. Keeping slaves and burning heretics are among the many practices that once seemed natural to us humans. In more traditional, “natural” times, we also had no protection for—or even concept of—intellectual property. The fact is that current social structures and dynamics governing the treatment of new ideas end up suppressing many true idea originators and rewarding fake ones. Who really believes that we <em>can&#8217;t</em> come up with a better, fairer, more modern approach?</p>
<p>It seems worth emphasizing here that one of the great revelations of modern electronic social media platforms, especially Twitter, is that there are surprisingly many amateur but bona fide originators of useful ideas. Obviously it would be good if these people—whether one wants to include me in their ranks or not—had an easier time making their new ideas visible <em>or at least getting credit when their ideas do eventually begin to circulate</em>. This would <em>encourage</em> more new ideas, whereas the present system (as my case is meant to illustrate) <em>discourages</em> them.</p>
<p>Amateur idea originators are, in my opinion, mostly people whose quirks of genetics and life experience cause them to perceive the world a bit differently than the average person does. This doesn&#8217;t necessarily make them smarter than average, but it does allow them to see patterns that others don’t. This cognitive differentness (not the same as autism, though very mild autism sometimes produces a similar phenomenon) often puts them “out of step” with their fellow humans not just intellectually but also socially. Thus, in my estimation, amateur idea originators are often among the <em>least</em> equipped and inclined to climb the greasy pole to win social support.</p>
<p>How to amplify their voices? How to give them credit and thereby encourage their contributions?</p>
<p>The Internet already gives us the basic medium for the essentially costless publication of new ideas. Some of us set up our own websites; others have Substack accounts. It should also be possible to craft search algorithms specifically to find and date instances of a given idea on the searchable web—this would seem an excellent application of current AI technology.</p>
<p>It should be possible, as well, to make an “idea registry,” maybe something like a cross between rXiv.org and Wikpedia, to which anyone can contribute, and where ideas are automatically categorized and time-stamped.</p>
<p>I have two basic models in mind. The most obvious one is the patent system, a modern, logical, merit-based system that does not require inventors to garner social support. And, again, while the commercial potential of technical inventions drove the establishment of the patent system, and political/cultural ideas tend to have less money-making potential, the reality nowadays is that new ideas <em>are</em> more monetizable than ever through books, magazine articles, Substack subscriptions, and so on. I also think most experienced professional journalists and opinionators would admit that it is absolutely routine for better-known writers to “borrow” the reporting and/or ideas of lesser-known writers and monetize them with large publishing contracts. Although, again, the average person doesn’t care, quite a few big-name writers would not have their fame and fat incomes but for opportune appropriations of others’ work.</p>
<p><img decoding="async" class="aligncenter wp-image-880" src="/wp-content/uploads/2023/08/francis.jpg" alt="" width="528" height="118" /></p>
<p>We may not want to treat new cultural/political ideas as protectable intellectual property in the strict sense, by fining violators, requiring licensing, etc. But having an easily searchable record of the originations of these new ideas would, at least, tend to discourage the rampant theft that now takes place.</p>
<p>The other model I have in mind is the “<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Motif-Index_of_Folk-Literature">motif index</a>” made by folklorists. Such an index—somewhat akin to patent examiners’ taxonomies of technologies, and zoologists’ taxonomies of plants and animals—is a hyper-branchiate ordering of folkloric tales according to the functional elements they contain. If such a vast and useful information structure could be built by a few folklorists using pre-Internet, pre-computer technologies, it should be doable much more easily now for new ideas in the Internet age.</p>
<p>I see no downside for this general proposal to &#8220;level the playing field&#8221; for idea-originators. It seems like a no-brainer, really, and my guess is that, as it becomes easy to implement in the AI age, it will happen, overcoming the predictable opposition/suppression by the elite opinionator class. Perhaps I will even get some credit for the idea!</p>
<p style="text-align: center;">* * *</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>&#8220;IF WE DON&#8217;T, WE&#8217;LL DIE&#8221;</title>
		<link>/if-we-dont-well-die/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[j stone]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 28 Dec 2022 21:11:40 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[fall of the West]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[immigration]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[revolution]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[The Right]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[USA]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[wokeism]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=739</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Is the USA in a Flight 93 situation? &#160; United Airlines flight 93 was the one that crashed into a field in Pennsylvania on 9/11/01, instead of being flown into the US Capitol. The reason it crashed into a field in Pennsylvania was that a group of passengers, ordinary peace-loving Americans, put aside their fears &#8230; <a href="/if-we-dont-well-die/" class="more-link">Continue reading<span class="screen-reader-text"> "&#8220;IF WE DON&#8217;T, WE&#8217;LL DIE&#8221;"</span></a>]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><em>Is the USA in a Flight 93 situation?</em></p>
<p><span id="more-739"></span></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>United Airlines flight 93 was the one that crashed into a field in Pennsylvania on 9/11/01, instead of being flown into the US Capitol. The reason it crashed into a field in Pennsylvania was that a group of passengers, ordinary peace-loving Americans, put aside their fears of immediate harm from the edged weapons held by the hijackers and united with one goal: to storm the cockpit, kill the hijackers, and regain control of the plane. Although they didn’t succeed in regaining control of the plane, they did at least induce the hijackers to crash it prematurely.</p>
<p>These passengers had the advantage of knowing, from communications with people on the ground, what was up that morning—and thus, what their hijackers probably intended to do with the plane. So really they knew they had nothing to lose. Among the many sounds the cockpit voice-recorder picked up in the final minutes of the flight, was that of a food cart being rammed against the cockpit door, and a cry from one of the passengers, “In the cockpit! If we don’t, we’ll die!”</p>
<p>According to <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/United_Airlines_Flight_93#Passenger_revolt">Wikipedia</a>, “Vice President Dick Cheney, in the Presidential Emergency Operations Center deep under the White House, authorized Flight 93 to be shot down, but upon learning of the crash, is reported to have said, ‘I think an act of heroism just took place on that plane.’”</p>
<p>He was right. But the heroism of the flight 93 passengers was a different kind of heroism than the lone-actor heroism we’re more used to reading about. It was a heroism involving a coming-together, a coalescence, of people who could accomplish a heroic task only when in a “united state.”</p>
<p>The rarity of that kind of coalescence nowadays points to a basic conundrum of human affairs, especially governance. In other words, even when a large mass of people has ample justification for rebelling against the relatively small group of individuals who control their lives, and ample means to do so—<em>if united</em>—they almost never unite effectively.</p>
<p style="text-align: center;">*</p>
<p>Consider the recent unprecedented popular protests across China, which ultimately involved more than a dozen cities. The background was a general unhappiness concerning national and local “COVID zero” policies, plus an even more general dissatisfaction with one-party rule. The triggers for protests were World Cup broadcasts from Qatar showing fans not wearing masks, and a deadly fire in a residential building in Urumqi that took firefighters hours to extinguish due to extreme local anti-COVID measures—Urumqi had been locked down for months. As for the leadership of the protest movement . . . the movement seems to have been relatively leader<em>less</em> and spontaneous, driven chiefly by the circulation of Internet messages and images. That leaderlessness is unsurprising in China, where any dissident leader visible and vocal enough to shape and direct protests is likely to be swiftly bundled away by police. It also may have been the decisive factor, for these relatively leaderless protests were limited to public gatherings, and did not have clear goals other than the mass voicing of complaints. Ultimately, the Chinese government was able to climb down from their COVID policies without their tight control of the country being threatened significantly.</p>
<p>A popular uprising against the government of Sri Lanka earlier this year was arguably more successful. The government, headed by President Gotabaya Rajapaksa and including some of his family members, was widely viewed as incompetent and corrupt, as Sri Lankans faced out-of-control inflation, power shortages, and other problems. When these stresses worsened and protests began, the government responded with repressive measures such as arrests and social media blackouts, exacerbating the situation. The protest movement eventually developed a leadership structure, including some firebrand student leaders. In July, a very large crowd of protesters stormed the Presidential palace in Colombo and Rajapaksa was forced to flee the country. However, the new government soon cracked down on the protest movement leaders, who apparently didn’t have much support among the country’s elites.</p>
<p>There are also ongoing protest movements in Iran and Russia. The one in Iran is very prominent and broad-based, and has forced the Tehran regime to backpedal somewhat, but so far has failed to result in an overthrow of the theocratic regime—which recently has started publicly executing protesters. The protest movement in Russia, against the Putin government and its Ukraine invasion, is hardly visible and seems to have achieved little if anything—clearly many dissidents have opted to leave the country rather than stay and protest, while some higher-profile dissidents have been <a href="https://www.forbes.com/sites/jonathanponciano/2022/12/27/russian-sausage-tycoon-dies-by-suicide-in-hotel-fall-just-the-latest-russian-elite-including-putin-critics-to-die-mysteriously/">disposed of</a> via the now-classic Russian method of defenestration.</p>
<p>Just looking at these examples, one can postulate that a popular political uprising, to have a decent chance of success, requires:</p>
<ul>
<li style="list-style-type: none;">
<ul>
<li><em>Sufficient popularity</em>, i.e., support from a large, preferably dominant proportion of the population, among whom there is a strong commonality of interest;</li>
<li><em>Strong stressors/triggers</em> that convince ordinary people that regime change is needed and compel them to take action (starting with protest marches and other gatherings);</li>
<li><em>A vision of how things should be different</em>, e.g., more liberal, less corrupt, more aligned with some alternative ideology, etc.</li>
<li><em>Effective leaders </em>who can inspire and direct the movement in ways that achieve regime change;</li>
<li><em>Elite support</em>, boosting the movement’s power by enabling it to control or influence key institutions (e.g., media, academia, police, military).</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<p style="text-align: center;">*</p>
<p>Ticking most or all these boxes is going to be challenging anywhere, particularly so in Western countries. I would say it’s virtually impossible in the United States at present.</p>
<p><em>Popularity</em>: Considering how the current US regime favors nonwhites, and considering how many contemporary white women are content with this anti-in-group discrimination, it seems likely that American dissidents are mostly white males—the principal heirs, as it were, of the country’s founders and builders. I would guess that this putative dissident group, all in all, comprises less than a third of the US population. That is still a very large number of individuals, somewhere between 50 and 100 million. Certainly they would be unbeatable if united as one against disunited foes. But even white American males remain <a href="https://www.pewresearch.org/politics/2021/06/30/behind-bidens-2020-victory/">highly disunited</a>. Moreover, the fact that dissident Americans, as I have defined them, are very much a <em>minority</em> puts them in a weak position culturally. It also would be used (and to some extent is already being used) to justify harsh regime measures against them, since they do not &#8220;represent the average American.&#8221;</p>
<p><em>Stressors/triggers</em>: The level of stress and urgency that would normally compel dissidents to go out onto the streets and protest is so far not very evident among dissident Americans. To be sure, the regime (an entity that is cultural as well as political and extends far beyond formal government) has done great damage to the country, via the wokeification/corruption of education, media, academia, immigration policy, the judiciary, and most other policies and institutions. Their misrule seems much more deserving of a punitive popular reaction than the misrule that prompted the American Revolution. Yet the US, for now, retains relatively high living standards, certainly for white males&#8212;and those living standards are supported by a huge structure of financialization/debt. In short, American dissidents still have much to lose by revolting openly. And so, like the proverbial slow-boiled frog, they still mostly prefer waiting (and complaining ineffectually, often indirectly via <a href="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/the-american-way-of-submission/">conspiracy theories</a>) to real, in-the-streets action. I doubt that they will prefer action until there is much more radical and extensive regime provocation and/or a prolonged economic depression that leaves them with &#8220;nothing to lose.&#8221;</p>
<p><em>Envisioned change:</em> American dissidents are remarkably fragmented in their views of what has gone wrong and what is to be done about it. Many of them, as I just noted, believe in bizarre conspiracies involving things like elite pedophile rings, or &#8220;chemtrails.&#8221; It&#8217;s often hard to tell where the conspiracy-theory fringe ends and the mainstream begins.</p>
<p><img decoding="async" class="aligncenter wp-image-753" src="/wp-content/uploads/2022/12/musk-fauci.jpg" alt="" width="515" height="229" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2022/12/musk-fauci.jpg 960w, /wp-content/uploads/2022/12/musk-fauci-768x342.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 515px) 85vw, 515px" /></p>
<p>The only halfway-cogent explanations for USA&#8217;s predicament that I&#8217;ve ever heard/read are from right wing intellectuals with small followings. The average &#8220;angry white male&#8221; appears to have little or no understanding of, say, the recent cultural and political impact of <a href="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/the-great-feminization/">women</a>, or the history of blacks in the USA and their <a href="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/the-other-n-word/">manipulation</a> by the major political parties. The most popular view now among right-wing American dissidents seems to be that &#8220;<a href="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/its-not-wokeness-its-women/">wokeism is the problem</a>,&#8221; and that things would get better if it could just be toned down a bit. In other words, they have neither a solid grasp of the problems facing the country, nor a positive alternative vision&#8212;let alone one that captures the energy and idealism of young people in the way that progressivism/wokeism does.</p>
<p><em>Inadequate leadership.</em> The American woke regime seems almost as effective at suppressing the leaders of dissident groups (e.g., Proud Boys, Oath Keepers) as the Chinese Communist party’s secret police are at suppressing pro-democracy leaders. In the wake of the regime&#8217;s 1/6/21 prosecutions and hearings, I can’t think of a single person, inside or outside of American politics, who currently has the visibility, stature, energy, intellect, and vision to reverse the adverse trends and put the country on secure footings. A big part of the problem, of course, is that at this late stage of the national disease, saving the country almost certainly would require a revolution-like abandonment, at least temporarily, of its current political framework&#8212;and the regime, understanding this, has begun to treat any opposition as sedition. Given these stakes, many of the right’s most prominent “leaders” have switched to less risky goals, such as enriching themselves—which to me is a clear indicator of organizational defeat/degeneracy, seen also among Democratic Party-controlled <a href="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/the-other-n-word/">African American leaders</a>.</p>
<p><img decoding="async" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-743" src="/wp-content/uploads/2022/12/trumpnft.jpg" alt="" width="600" height="600" /></p>
<p><em>Lack of elite support.</em> Perhaps the most obvious of all its defects is that the American conservative/dissident movement lacks elite and institutional support. This is not a trend that seems likely to be reversed any time soon. The takeovers/makeovers of elites and institutions by anticonservative activists and their ideas (often these begin as conquests by women, who are <a href="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/its-not-wokeness-its-women/">inherently</a> more left-wing and susceptible to wokeism) reflect a process that has been at work for decades, and is now accelerating through its final stages to a state of more or less complete control.</p>
<p>Thus, while the Flight 93 story presents a striking case of group heroism in the face of disaster, it’s more an example of what US <em>isn’t</em> (yet) than what it <a href="https://claremontreviewofbooks.com/digital/the-flight-93-election/"><em>is</em></a>. The legacy population of the United States, though well advanced in their cultural and political <a href="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/the-great-feminization/">emasculation</a>, and in the related, sad handover of their inheritance to foreigners, are still surprisingly comfortable, still quite far from an “if we don’t, we’ll die” moment.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p style="text-align: center;">***</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>PUTIN AND THE FALL OF THE WEST</title>
		<link>/putin-and-the-fall-of-the-west/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[j stone]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sun, 06 Mar 2022 03:18:55 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[fall of the West]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[immigration]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Russia]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[The Right]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Ukraine]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[USA]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[wokeism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[women]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=501</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[The Right&#8217;s &#8220;sympathy for the devil&#8221; has weakened it at a crucial moment &#160; The sanctions against Russia—both the official economic sanctions and the unofficial, often petty-seeming sanctions such as banning Russian owners from cat shows—arguably represent the first great “geopolitical cancellation” of this new feminized era in the West. This cancellation obviously goes far &#8230; <a href="/putin-and-the-fall-of-the-west/" class="more-link">Continue reading<span class="screen-reader-text"> "PUTIN AND THE FALL OF THE WEST"</span></a>]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><em>The Right&#8217;s &#8220;sympathy for the devil&#8221; has weakened it at a crucial moment</em><span id="more-501"></span></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>The sanctions against Russia—both the official economic sanctions and the unofficial, often petty-seeming sanctions such as <a href="https://www.npr.org/2022/03/03/1084205316/russian-cats-banned-international-competition">banning Russian owners from cat shows</a>—arguably represent the first great “geopolitical cancellation” of this new feminized era in the West.</p>
<p><img decoding="async" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-505" src="/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/geopolcancel.jpg" alt="" width="602" height="816" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/geopolcancel.jpg 602w, /wp-content/uploads/2022/03/geopolcancel-221x300.jpg 221w" sizes="(max-width: 709px) 85vw, (max-width: 909px) 67vw, (max-width: 984px) 61vw, (max-width: 1362px) 45vw, 600px" /></p>
<p>This cancellation obviously goes far beyond the usual diplomatic noises that are made when the blame for conflicts is murkier and the victims more remote from us. It is a public reaction to an outrage that rises explosively above the usual outrages, involves fellow Westerners, and is available to tug at the heartstrings 24/7 on a variety of electronic media.</p>
<p>Moreover, it really does look like a broad translation of the usual domestic cancellation strategies to the geopolitical scene, including economic punishment, censorship, general ostracism, threats of judicial action, and indirect assistance for those who fight the Cancelled One, but of course no direct, overt involvement in that fighting.</p>
<p>Given the scale of this response, the scale of the atrocity that triggered it, and the scale of Russia’s ongoing losses in Ukraine, Putin’s downfall seems inevitable. After killing many thousands of innocent Ukrainians, destroying probably trillions of dollars’ worth of Ukrainian buildings and other infrastructure, utterly breaking Russia&#8217;s army and air force, and of course lying through his teeth about his actions and motives, he does not appear to have any way out—any peaceful “off ramp.” He is our generation’s Hitler, and I suspect he already knows that his days, in office at least, are numbered.</p>
<p>There are many potential pluses to a Putin downfall. One is that Russia again will have a chance to achieve what it could not achieve in the 1990s, namely a more mature form of government and economy, oriented towards and not against the West. Such a transformation of Russia, which I think is somewhat more likely than the alternative, would mean a final unification of all the West’s major powers, and at least a temporary “emboldening” of them. That in turn could usher in one of those periods of history, like 1990-2010, in which the West reigns supreme over all earthly comers. In this scenario, bad actors such as Iran, China, and North Korea would have to watch their step, at the very least, and the world in that sense would be a safer place.</p>
<p>But here’s the bad news. Even if the “best case” scenario happens—including a glorious Russian uprising and overthrow of the dictator, maybe even on Easter Sunday (April 24 in the Russian Orthodox calendar)—the West has suffered a blow in its own ranks that I think is of dire significance.</p>
<p>If you’ve read any of my previous essays on this site, you know that I have taken a generally dim view of the West’s future. Cultural/political feminization; mass immigration, multiculturalism and wokeism; and the lack of political tools for solving these problems, have doomed the West in the most basic ways, as I have seen it. On the other hand, conservatives in the West have been gaining strength and coherence in recent years in reaction to the excesses of Letfism/wokeism. As recently as a month ago, it had seemed plausible to me that a <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/%C3%89ric_Zemmour">Zemmour</a>-ization of the Western Right (Eric Zemmour is explicitly against both cultural feminization and mass-immigration/heavy-multiculturalism) could, eventually and with a lot of luck, restore the situation.</p>
<p>But what Putin’s unprovoked invasion of Ukraine revealed all too clearly is that much of the Right in the West is, well, <em>wrong</em>, and about fundamental things. Sadly, these Wrong Rightists include Zemmour as well as prominent commentators in the US, Tucker Carlson and J.D. Vance among them.</p>
<p>The Wrong Rightists hate, first and foremost, what they call the Globalist American Empire (GAE). Fair enough—I hate it too. The problem is that they view Putin not as a murderous kleptocrat and global troublemaker (as I view him), but rather as a valuable counterweight to the hegemony of the GAE—a counterweight they want to <em>strengthen</em>, not weaken. These pro-Putin rightists have seemed quite willing to nullify the sovereignty of Ukraine (and, since the invasion started, have been willing to let Putin&#8217;s murders of tens of thousands of Ukrainians go unpunished), in order to preserve this counterweight—this bastion of old-fashioned Christian values according to the peculiar delusion afflicting some of them.</p>
<p>Of course, quite a few of the Wrong Rightists are backpedaling now, saying they deplore what Putin did, etc. They understand, at least at some level, the parallels between their sentiments and the discredited sentiments of say, Laval in France and Lindbergh in the USA during 1939-41. They therefore tend to exhibit their distress over the impending collapse of Russia as a Great Power, and the impending destruction of Putin and Putinism, in ways that are more or less indirect. They are peevish about Ukrainian “propaganda.” They lament the “lost opportunity” to have prevented the horrors of this war by barring Ukraine from NATO, thereby calming the nerves of their sensitive hero in the Kremlin. They speak darkly of Ukrainian “Nazis.” They yearn for a swift settlement that preserves Putin in power (and, not incidentally, conceals the fatuity of everything they have claimed or predicted about all this). They emit copious cope about how Russia is still destined to “win.” Above all, they say the West should care less about Ukraine and more about problems at home.</p>
<p>Here are just a few examples of this output (to which I may add soon as time permits):</p>
<p><img decoding="async" class="wp-image-524 aligncenter" src="/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/tc-clientstate.jpg" alt="" width="536" height="396" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/tc-clientstate.jpg 596w, /wp-content/uploads/2022/03/tc-clientstate-300x221.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 536px) 85vw, 536px" /></p>
<p><img decoding="async" class="size-full wp-image-469 aligncenter" src="/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/tucker1.jpg" alt="" width="527" height="412" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/tucker1.jpg 527w, /wp-content/uploads/2022/02/tucker1-300x235.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 527px) 85vw, 527px" /></p>
<p><img decoding="async" class="wp-image-507 aligncenter" src="/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/vance1.jpg" alt="" width="491" height="493" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/vance1.jpg 689w, /wp-content/uploads/2022/03/vance1-300x300.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2022/03/vance1-150x150.jpg 150w" sizes="(max-width: 491px) 85vw, 491px" /></p>
<p><img decoding="async" class="size-full wp-image-508 aligncenter" src="/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/trumponputin.jpg" alt="" width="506" height="590" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/trumponputin.jpg 506w, /wp-content/uploads/2022/03/trumponputin-257x300.jpg 257w" sizes="(max-width: 506px) 85vw, 506px" /></p>
<p><img decoding="async" class="size-full wp-image-509 aligncenter" src="/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/gabbard.jpg" alt="" width="524" height="139" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/gabbard.jpg 524w, /wp-content/uploads/2022/03/gabbard-300x80.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 524px) 85vw, 524px" /></p>
<p><img decoding="async" class="wp-image-517 aligncenter" src="/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/coulter1.jpg" alt="" width="511" height="202" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/coulter1.jpg 608w, /wp-content/uploads/2022/03/coulter1-300x118.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 511px) 85vw, 511px" /></p>
<p><img decoding="async" class="size-full wp-image-525 aligncenter" src="/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/hanania-thingspplwillbelieve.jpg" alt="" width="614" height="184" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/hanania-thingspplwillbelieve.jpg 614w, /wp-content/uploads/2022/03/hanania-thingspplwillbelieve-300x90.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 709px) 85vw, (max-width: 909px) 67vw, (max-width: 984px) 61vw, (max-width: 1362px) 45vw, 600px" /></p>
<p><img decoding="async" class="size-full wp-image-526 aligncenter" src="/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/hanania-emotion.jpg" alt="" width="592" height="183" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/hanania-emotion.jpg 592w, /wp-content/uploads/2022/03/hanania-emotion-300x93.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 592px) 85vw, 592px" /></p>
<p><img decoding="async" class="wp-image-528 aligncenter" src="/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/mcconnell-vietcong.jpg" alt="" width="556" height="363" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/mcconnell-vietcong.jpg 616w, /wp-content/uploads/2022/03/mcconnell-vietcong-300x196.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 556px) 85vw, 556px" /></p>
<p>What I think all this means is that the Western Right in general now is left with much less credibility in the eyes of the average normie citizen, just as occurred in the aftermath of the Pearl Harbor attack in 1941. In particular, the pro-Putin, &#8220;America First&#8221; sector of the Right, the sector that happens also to be most deeply concerned with the most serious issues, such as mass immigration, has grandly shot itself through the foot—or maybe through the heart. This has left the Left/center-Right “GAE” coalition in a much better position, so that there won’t be a Zemmour-type president in the USA any time soon—and I’m guessing now there won’t be one even in France. Thus the West’s demise will have been hastened at the very moment of its own apparent triumph over its longtime mortal enemy.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p style="text-align: center;">***</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>I STICK MY NECK OUT FOR NOBODY</title>
		<link>/i-stick-my-neck-out-for-nobody/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[j stone]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 24 Feb 2022 03:14:23 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[fall of the West]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[psychology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Russia]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[The Right]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Ukraine]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[USA]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[wokeism]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=432</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[The West&#8217;s&#8212;and the Right&#8217;s&#8212;shame &#160; World War II ended less than two decades before I was born, yet I&#8217;ve always felt that it belonged to much more distant age&#8212;set off from modern existence by its different ways of thinking and doing, different patterns of speech and dress, grander scale of horrors and heroism, even the &#8230; <a href="/i-stick-my-neck-out-for-nobody/" class="more-link">Continue reading<span class="screen-reader-text"> "I STICK MY NECK OUT FOR NOBODY"</span></a>]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><em>The West&#8217;s&#8212;and the Right&#8217;s&#8212;shame</em></p>
<p><span id="more-432"></span></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>World War II ended less than two decades before I was born, yet I&#8217;ve always felt that it belonged to much more distant age&#8212;set off from modern existence by its different ways of thinking and doing, different patterns of speech and dress, grander scale of horrors and heroism, even the monochrome of its newsreels. The bad things, especially, seemed mostly unrepeatable in the world where I grew up.</p>
<p>American isolationism is a good example. Conservative Americans, for the longest time, didn&#8217;t want to help Britain, or Western Europe, with their struggles against Hitler and Mussolini. The USA had helped out Britain and France in 1917-18, and felt that they shouldn&#8217;t have to do anything like that again. Let Europeans sort out their own problems, they said.</p>
<p>That was <em>part</em> of their public reasoning, anyway. Another part of it seemed much more instinctive and tribal, much more driven by the false logic of &#8220;the enemy-of-my-enemy-is-my-friend&#8221;&#8212;their enemy being FDR, of course, their new friends being the Axis dictators.</p>
<p>It might seem facile to criticize the American isolationists of 1939-41 from our postwar perspective, but really they should have known better just from the information available at the time. In any case, it&#8217;s always striking now to read and hear the things they said. Here, for example, is aviator Charles Lindbergh, on September 11, 1941 (Europe conquered, Britain under siege, Wehrmacht nearing Moscow etc.), blaming the British, Roosevelt, and &#8220;the Jewish,&#8221; for pushing America towards war:</p>
<p><iframe title="Lindbergh &#039; Speech - 1941 | Movietone Moment | 11 September 2020" width="840" height="473" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/xiRYccqVPW0?feature=oembed" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen></iframe></p>
<p>The Pearl Harbor attack, less than three months later, embarrassed the America First movement into silence. Lindbergh himself spent much of the war trying to get into combat to redeem himself, and eventually <a href="http://www.charleslindbergh.com/history/b24.asp">succeeded&#8212;in getting into combat, not at redeeming himself.</a></p>
<p>But anyway, here we are again, with the same kind of geopolitical setup (armed dictator on the prowl abroad, liberal Democrats in control at home), resulting in the same strange mindset on the part of American conservatives.</p>
<p>By the way, in case this is the first essay of mine you&#8217;ve read, I&#8217;m pretty conservative too (notwithstanding David Goldman&#8217;s swipe at me, below, as a &#8220;neocon/GlobLib&#8221;). Yet the fellow conservatives who, in defiance of recent history, have started talking up Putin and talking down Ukraine, the US and the Western alliance, are now as alien to me as DEI consultants.</p>
<p>I&#8217;ve already set down my own anti-isolationist, fight-the-bad-guy <a href="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/aggressors-and-alliances/">thoughts</a> on Putin and Ukraine, a month ago on this site. Here I just want to record, mainly out of sheer amazement and chagrin, some of the sentiments I&#8217;ve been reading in recent days from elsewhere on the American right.</p>
<p>To keep things manageable, I&#8217;ve focused mainly on two prolific and very widely followed commentators, Goldman and Richard Hanania, and I&#8217;ve organized their comments by their major themes.</p>
<p><strong>&#8220;Ukraine is a corrupt and backwards place that isn&#8217;t worth defending&#8212;or invading&#8221;</strong></p>
<p><img decoding="async" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-439" src="/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/dg7.jpg" alt="" width="609" height="167" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/dg7.jpg 609w, /wp-content/uploads/2022/02/dg7-300x82.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 709px) 85vw, (max-width: 909px) 67vw, (max-width: 984px) 61vw, (max-width: 1362px) 45vw, 600px" /></p>
<p><img decoding="async" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-411" src="/wp-content/uploads/2022/01/hanania.jpg" alt="" width="603" height="662" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2022/01/hanania.jpg 603w, /wp-content/uploads/2022/01/hanania-273x300.jpg 273w" sizes="(max-width: 709px) 85vw, (max-width: 909px) 67vw, (max-width: 984px) 61vw, (max-width: 1362px) 45vw, 600px" /></p>
<p><img decoding="async" class="alignnone wp-image-468" src="/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/rh-tuckergood.jpg" alt="" width="558" height="430" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/rh-tuckergood.jpg 614w, /wp-content/uploads/2022/02/rh-tuckergood-300x232.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 558px) 85vw, 558px" /></p>
<p><img decoding="async" class="alignnone wp-image-441" src="/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/dg9.jpg" alt="" width="554" height="449" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/dg9.jpg 614w, /wp-content/uploads/2022/02/dg9-300x243.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 554px) 85vw, 554px" /></p>
<p><img decoding="async" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-442" src="/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/dg10.jpg" alt="" width="640" height="535" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/dg10.jpg 640w, /wp-content/uploads/2022/02/dg10-300x251.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 709px) 85vw, (max-width: 909px) 67vw, (max-width: 984px) 61vw, (max-width: 1362px) 45vw, 600px" /></p>
<p><img decoding="async" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-443" src="/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/dg16.jpg" alt="" width="623" height="310" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/dg16.jpg 623w, /wp-content/uploads/2022/02/dg16-300x149.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 709px) 85vw, (max-width: 909px) 67vw, (max-width: 984px) 61vw, (max-width: 1362px) 45vw, 600px" /></p>
<p><img decoding="async" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-444" src="/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/dg15.jpg" alt="" width="612" height="159" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/dg15.jpg 612w, /wp-content/uploads/2022/02/dg15-300x78.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 709px) 85vw, (max-width: 909px) 67vw, (max-width: 984px) 61vw, (max-width: 1362px) 45vw, 600px" /></p>
<p><img decoding="async" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-445" src="/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/dg17.jpg" alt="" width="617" height="296" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/dg17.jpg 617w, /wp-content/uploads/2022/02/dg17-300x144.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 709px) 85vw, (max-width: 909px) 67vw, (max-width: 984px) 61vw, (max-width: 1362px) 45vw, 600px" /></p>
<p><img decoding="async" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-449" src="/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/dg12.jpg" alt="" width="599" height="493" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/dg12.jpg 599w, /wp-content/uploads/2022/02/dg12-300x247.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 599px) 85vw, 599px" /></p>
<p><img decoding="async" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-451" src="/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/dg25.jpg" alt="" width="618" height="395" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/dg25.jpg 618w, /wp-content/uploads/2022/02/dg25-300x192.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 709px) 85vw, (max-width: 909px) 67vw, (max-width: 984px) 61vw, (max-width: 1362px) 45vw, 600px" /></p>
<p><img decoding="async" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-483" src="/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/rh-usboredw-ukraine.jpg" alt="" width="618" height="230" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/rh-usboredw-ukraine.jpg 618w, /wp-content/uploads/2022/02/rh-usboredw-ukraine-300x112.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 709px) 85vw, (max-width: 909px) 67vw, (max-width: 984px) 61vw, (max-width: 1362px) 45vw, 600px" /></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><strong>&#8220;Ukrainians are So Dumb&#8221;</strong></p>
<p><img decoding="async" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-470" src="/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/rh-ukr-dumb.jpg" alt="" width="612" height="323" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/rh-ukr-dumb.jpg 612w, /wp-content/uploads/2022/02/rh-ukr-dumb-300x158.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 709px) 85vw, (max-width: 909px) 67vw, (max-width: 984px) 61vw, (max-width: 1362px) 45vw, 600px" /></p>
<p><img decoding="async" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-492" src="/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/rh-finland.jpg" alt="" width="583" height="246" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/rh-finland.jpg 583w, /wp-content/uploads/2022/02/rh-finland-300x127.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 583px) 85vw, 583px" /></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><strong>&#8220;It&#8217;s All NATO&#8217;s/Neocons&#8217; Fault for Expanding NATO and Threatening Russia&#8221;</strong></p>
<p><img decoding="async" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-448" src="/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/dg5.jpg" alt="" width="633" height="164" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/dg5.jpg 633w, /wp-content/uploads/2022/02/dg5-300x78.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 709px) 85vw, (max-width: 909px) 67vw, (max-width: 984px) 61vw, (max-width: 1362px) 45vw, 600px" /></p>
<p><img decoding="async" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-463" src="/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/dg24.jpg" alt="" width="612" height="225" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/dg24.jpg 612w, /wp-content/uploads/2022/02/dg24-300x110.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 709px) 85vw, (max-width: 909px) 67vw, (max-width: 984px) 61vw, (max-width: 1362px) 45vw, 600px" /></p>
<p><img decoding="async" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-450" src="/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/dg20.jpg" alt="" width="631" height="401" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/dg20.jpg 631w, /wp-content/uploads/2022/02/dg20-300x191.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 709px) 85vw, (max-width: 909px) 67vw, (max-width: 984px) 61vw, (max-width: 1362px) 45vw, 600px" /></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><strong>&#8220;Putin is Smart and Will Win&#8221;</strong></p>
<p><img decoding="async" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-456" src="/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/dg4.jpg" alt="" width="632" height="316" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/dg4.jpg 632w, /wp-content/uploads/2022/02/dg4-300x150.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 709px) 85vw, (max-width: 909px) 67vw, (max-width: 984px) 61vw, (max-width: 1362px) 45vw, 600px" /></p>
<p><img decoding="async" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-457" src="/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/dg6.jpg" alt="" width="631" height="295" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/dg6.jpg 631w, /wp-content/uploads/2022/02/dg6-300x140.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 709px) 85vw, (max-width: 909px) 67vw, (max-width: 984px) 61vw, (max-width: 1362px) 45vw, 600px" /></p>
<p><img decoding="async" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-458" src="/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/dg-14.jpg" alt="" width="611" height="147" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/dg-14.jpg 611w, /wp-content/uploads/2022/02/dg-14-300x72.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 709px) 85vw, (max-width: 909px) 67vw, (max-width: 984px) 61vw, (max-width: 1362px) 45vw, 600px" /></p>
<p><img decoding="async" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-472" src="/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/rh-putingreat.jpg" alt="" width="607" height="206" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/rh-putingreat.jpg 607w, /wp-content/uploads/2022/02/rh-putingreat-300x102.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 709px) 85vw, (max-width: 909px) 67vw, (max-width: 984px) 61vw, (max-width: 1362px) 45vw, 600px" /></p>
<p><img decoding="async" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-481" src="/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/rh-rus-stronger.jpg" alt="" width="585" height="144" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/rh-rus-stronger.jpg 585w, /wp-content/uploads/2022/02/rh-rus-stronger-300x74.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 585px) 85vw, 585px" /></p>
<p><img decoding="async" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-485" src="/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/putin-69.jpg" alt="" width="607" height="316" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/putin-69.jpg 607w, /wp-content/uploads/2022/02/putin-69-300x156.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 709px) 85vw, (max-width: 909px) 67vw, (max-width: 984px) 61vw, (max-width: 1362px) 45vw, 600px" /></p>
<p><img decoding="async" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-484" src="/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/rh-noinsurgency.jpg" alt="" width="595" height="518" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/rh-noinsurgency.jpg 595w, /wp-content/uploads/2022/02/rh-noinsurgency-300x261.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 595px) 85vw, 595px" /></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><strong>&#8220;The Woke are the Real Enemy&#8212;not Putin&#8221;</strong></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><img decoding="async" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-469" src="/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/tucker1.jpg" alt="" width="527" height="412" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/tucker1.jpg 527w, /wp-content/uploads/2022/02/tucker1-300x235.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 527px) 85vw, 527px" /></p>
<p>(See also &#8220;<a href="https://slate.com/culture/2016/06/did-muhammad-ali-ever-say-no-viet-cong-ever-called-me-nigger.html">No Viet Cong Ever . . .</a>&#8220;)</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><strong>&#8220;You Neocons are So Dumb&#8221;</strong></p>
<p><img decoding="async" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-453" src="/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/dg-v-js1.jpg" alt="" width="620" height="632" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/dg-v-js1.jpg 620w, /wp-content/uploads/2022/02/dg-v-js1-294x300.jpg 294w" sizes="(max-width: 709px) 85vw, (max-width: 909px) 67vw, (max-width: 984px) 61vw, (max-width: 1362px) 45vw, 600px" /></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><strong>&#8220;Love Ukraine = Hate America&#8221;</strong></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><img decoding="async" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-467" src="/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/rh-correlation.jpg" alt="" width="602" height="427" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/rh-correlation.jpg 602w, /wp-content/uploads/2022/02/rh-correlation-300x213.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 709px) 85vw, (max-width: 909px) 67vw, (max-width: 984px) 61vw, (max-width: 1362px) 45vw, 600px" /></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><strong>&#8220;We Should Cut a Deal With Putin&#8221;</strong></p>
<p><img decoding="async" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-459" src="/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/dg21.jpg" alt="" width="616" height="554" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/dg21.jpg 616w, /wp-content/uploads/2022/02/dg21-300x270.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 709px) 85vw, (max-width: 909px) 67vw, (max-width: 984px) 61vw, (max-width: 1362px) 45vw, 600px" /></p>
<p><img decoding="async" class="alignnone wp-image-471" src="/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/rh-ukraineabjurenato.jpg" alt="" width="560" height="699" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/rh-ukraineabjurenato.jpg 597w, /wp-content/uploads/2022/02/rh-ukraineabjurenato-240x300.jpg 240w" sizes="(max-width: 560px) 85vw, 560px" /></p>
<p><img decoding="async" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-477" src="/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/rh-gas.jpg" alt="" width="583" height="161" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/rh-gas.jpg 583w, /wp-content/uploads/2022/02/rh-gas-300x83.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 583px) 85vw, 583px" /></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><strong>&#8220;Our NATO Allies Won&#8217;t Help Us&#8212;In Fact, NATO will collapse&#8221;</strong></p>
<p><img decoding="async" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-460" src="/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/dg8.jpg" alt="" width="609" height="417" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/dg8.jpg 609w, /wp-content/uploads/2022/02/dg8-300x205.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 709px) 85vw, (max-width: 909px) 67vw, (max-width: 984px) 61vw, (max-width: 1362px) 45vw, 600px" /></p>
<p><img decoding="async" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-461" src="/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/dg19.jpg" alt="" width="602" height="170" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/dg19.jpg 602w, /wp-content/uploads/2022/02/dg19-300x85.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 709px) 85vw, (max-width: 909px) 67vw, (max-width: 984px) 61vw, (max-width: 1362px) 45vw, 600px" /></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><strong>&#8220;We&#8217;ll Be Better Off When Russia and China Have More Power&#8221;</strong></p>
<p><img decoding="async" class="alignnone wp-image-473" src="/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/rh-natobad.jpg" alt="" width="562" height="190" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/rh-natobad.jpg 600w, /wp-content/uploads/2022/02/rh-natobad-300x102.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 562px) 85vw, 562px" /></p>
<p><img decoding="async" class="alignnone wp-image-474" src="/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/rh-chinacnstrained.jpg" alt="" width="473" height="461" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/rh-chinacnstrained.jpg 894w, /wp-content/uploads/2022/02/rh-chinacnstrained-300x292.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2022/02/rh-chinacnstrained-768x748.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 473px) 85vw, 473px" /></p>
<p><img decoding="async" class="alignnone wp-image-475" src="/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/rh-chinamorehumane.jpg" alt="" width="476" height="456" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/rh-chinamorehumane.jpg 616w, /wp-content/uploads/2022/02/rh-chinamorehumane-300x288.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 476px) 85vw, 476px" /></p>
<p><img decoding="async" class="alignnone wp-image-479" src="/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/rh-trumpputinsummit.jpg" alt="" width="488" height="230" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/rh-trumpputinsummit.jpg 613w, /wp-content/uploads/2022/02/rh-trumpputinsummit-300x141.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 488px) 85vw, 488px" /></p>
<p><img decoding="async" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-488" src="/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/rh-ivfbabies.jpg" alt="" width="920" height="520" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/rh-ivfbabies.jpg 920w, /wp-content/uploads/2022/02/rh-ivfbabies-300x170.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2022/02/rh-ivfbabies-768x434.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 709px) 85vw, (max-width: 909px) 67vw, (max-width: 1362px) 62vw, 840px" /></p>
<p><img decoding="async" class="alignnone wp-image-489" src="/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/rh-multipolar.jpg" alt="" width="542" height="348" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/rh-multipolar.jpg 779w, /wp-content/uploads/2022/02/rh-multipolar-300x193.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2022/02/rh-multipolar-768x493.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 542px) 85vw, 542px" /></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><strong>&#8220;Enough with the World War II Analogies!&#8221;</strong></p>
<p><img decoding="async" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-491" src="/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/rh-forgethitleranalogies.jpg" alt="" width="591" height="261" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/rh-forgethitleranalogies.jpg 591w, /wp-content/uploads/2022/02/rh-forgethitleranalogies-300x132.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 591px) 85vw, 591px" /></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><strong>&#8220;And Now For Some Other Clever Ideas&#8221;</strong></p>
<p><img decoding="async" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-464" src="/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/dg-asians.jpg" alt="" width="614" height="535" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/dg-asians.jpg 614w, /wp-content/uploads/2022/02/dg-asians-300x261.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 709px) 85vw, (max-width: 909px) 67vw, (max-width: 984px) 61vw, (max-width: 1362px) 45vw, 600px" /></p>
<p><img decoding="async" class="alignnone wp-image-494" src="/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/rh-downs.jpg" alt="" width="535" height="401" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/rh-downs.jpg 608w, /wp-content/uploads/2022/02/rh-downs-300x225.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 535px) 85vw, 535px" /></p>
<p>I&#8217;m aware that, as readers go through all these posts, they might find themselves agreeing with the sentiments expressed. But, as I post this, the long-awaited Russian offensive to conquer (presumably) Ukraine is just starting. It&#8217;s unlikely to be as dramatic for Americans as Pearl Harbor was, especially since it&#8217;s an attack on Ukraine, but modern electronic media, and weaponry, are going to be amplifying factors. I hope it will shock many of the Putin apologists and associated naysayers into rethinking their attitudes.</p>
<p style="text-align: center;">***</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
