<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>ideas &#8211; Thoughts of Stone</title>
	<atom:link href="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/category/ideas/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/</link>
	<description>short essays, usually about humans</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Wed, 12 Oct 2022 19:05:51 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=6.0.2</generator>

<image>
	<url>https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2020/07/cropped-icon-32x32.jpg</url>
	<title>ideas &#8211; Thoughts of Stone</title>
	<link>https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/</link>
	<width>32</width>
	<height>32</height>
</image> 
	<item>
		<title>IT&#8217;S NOT &#8220;WOKENESS&#8221;&#8212;IT&#8217;S WOMEN</title>
		<link>https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/its-not-wokeness-its-women/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[j stone]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 10 Oct 2022 04:49:27 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[ethnicity]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[fall of the West]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[freedom of speech]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[ideas]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[immigration]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[psychology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[science]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[wokeism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[women]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/?p=682</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[The rise of wokeness, ESG, the trans mania, etc. is all due to women&#8217;s new power in institutions The new Western culture, especially the American variety, offers the old-fashioned conservative male dissident many trends to bewail. Discrimination against white males! Promotion of LGBTQ lifestyles! The trans mania with its mutilation of children and destruction of &#8230; <a href="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/its-not-wokeness-its-women/" class="more-link">Continue reading<span class="screen-reader-text"> "IT&#8217;S NOT &#8220;WOKENESS&#8221;&#8212;IT&#8217;S WOMEN"</span></a>]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><em>The rise of wokeness, ESG, the trans mania, etc. is all due to women&#8217;s new power in institutions</em></p>
<p><span id="more-682"></span></p>
<p>The new Western culture, especially the American variety, offers the old-fashioned conservative male dissident many trends to bewail. Discrimination against white males! Promotion of LGBTQ lifestyles! The trans mania with its mutilation of children and destruction of women’s sports! Suppression of meritocracy, free speech, free scientific inquiry, and due process of law! Runaway entitlement spending! Open borders! Critical race theory! The ESG investing fad! No-prosecute policies in violent cities! Proliferation of social contagions and hysterical illnesses, from ROGD and PTSD to Tik-Tok Tourette’s! Cascades of cancellations of perfectly competent white males, e.g., for “<a href="https://www.theguardian.com/us-news/2022/oct/06/nyu-professor-fired-maitland-jones-jr-student-petition">grading too hard in organic chemistry</a>,” or for <a href="https://www.nydailynews.com/news/national/ny-apple-exec-fired-tiktok-arthur-20220930-rdsgzpbzr5anxjyqar5avuiyv4-story.html">cracking an off-color joke</a>! Widespread exclusion (in effect) of males from important professions, including public relations, publishing, and clinical psychology/psychotherapy. “Math is White Supremacy!” “Showing up for work is White Supremacy!!” “Not being a pea-brained slob is White Supremacy!!!”</p>
<p>My argument here is that everybody should <em>stop</em> bewailing these trends as separate phenomena—should stop fighting “wokeness” or “ESG” or the trans mania. They should, instead, focus on the one factor that underlies and causes all of these social developments.</p>
<p>Of course, I mean <em>women</em>—or more precisely, women’s newfound power in organizations and institutions, and in the culture generally.</p>
<p>An assumption everyone seems to have made during the decades of female emancipation is that women see things more or less as men do, and are just as devoted as men to the principles underlying Western civilization. Not so! As some feminist writers, including Virginia Woolf, warned long ago, women when they enter public life in business and government tend to look around and see lots of things they want to change. They’re just not fans, to the extent that men are, of things like free speech, open debate, due process of law, meritocracy, free scientific inquiry, maximizing shareholder value, equality of opportunity, and so on.</p>
<p>It’s not that women have worked things out logically and carefully and comprehensively, and now want to formally enact a scheme they think is better. It’s more that things in Western civ, which was made by men, often go against the emotional grain with women, causing them real discomfort, and compelling them to react. Women’s instincts were shaped by evolution for a maternal and domestic context, and seem to bias them towards short-term, feelgood, nurturing, and protective outcomes—on average compared to men. These instincts seem to be especially aroused by things like persistent racial inequality, discussions of race-based IQ differences, ruthless meritocratic competition unleavened by sympathy for the losers, stern cross-examinations of women making rape claims, medical skepticism over women&#8217;s unverifiable symptoms, and the kind of frat-boy humor that has gotten so many men cancelled. Now that women are largely in charge, they question why we need such things—or peremptorily try to stamp them out.</p>
<p>There are some nuances to this general theory. First, a lot of women are not woke. But the argument here is really about women on average as compared to men on average, and I don’t think it could be reasonably disputed that women, on average and compared to men, are significantly biased in the direction of wokeness. It’s also obviously true that modest average psychological differences between the sexes could translate to big social changes when one sex takes power from the other. I would suggest too that the women who seek power in institutions are less likely to be “average” women and more likely to be childless activist types. There is, moreover, a hell of a lot of depression and anxiety among modern women, especially younger ones, and that as well may push many women to embrace the woke activism mindset as a therapeutic source of meaning and purpose.</p>
<p>Another nuance has to do with women’s apparently superior ability, compared to men, to align themselves emotionally within a group. This means, in effect, that women in an organization will tend to be less independent-minded, with the tradeoff that they can collectively punch above their weight. Among the examples that come to mind is the recent <a href="https://www.tmz.com/2020/03/06/woody-allen-memoir-canceled-hachette-publisher-staff-walkout/">cancellation of Woody Allen</a> from his publisher due to activism among the publishing company’s <em>junior staff</em>. (The publishing industry, like public relations and psychology/psychiatry/psychotherapy, is utterly dominated by women—“junior staff” in publishing generally means millennial women.)</p>
<p>Women, as I’ve suggested in a recent <a href="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/always-be-capturing/">essay</a>, may also have, collectively, a stronger drive to dominate organizations, to eliminate the greater discomfort they experience when exposed to male organizational culture. Certainly the female-to-male ratio in many organizations now is one that would be condemned as discriminatory (by women) were the proportions reversed.</p>
<p>A further nuance, which I think will become increasingly obvious and important as our societal &#8220;<a href="https://americanmind.org/salvo/pink-shift/">pink shift</a>&#8221; advances, is that women, as they align emotionally within groups, and ultimately purge dissenting voices, tend to cause the institutions they control to become unstable. In other words, like hysteria-prone convents of half a millenium ago, female-dominated institutions become relatively susceptible to groupthink contagions that swing them irrationally this way and that. Today these contagions introduce relatively mild new absurdities like pronoun declarations and land acknowledgments. But I expect it&#8217;s all going to get loopier, and more harshly enforced, as time goes on and female control solidifies.</p>
<p>Lastly, somewhat hair-splittingly, I don’t think that women when left to themselves running male-built institutions <em>necessarily</em> become woke in the way that we see now. I see wokeness as a contemporary, contagious mindset (not quite an ideology) that corresponds very well to, and thus easily infects, the average female mind, still moreso the younger, more neurotic, more activist female mind. But in principle, under different circumstances, one could gin up something substantially different that would also spread well among women, provided that it pressed their main buttons. Certainly in the centuries before women took such a large part in public life, thought contagions among them were common and varied, though usually localized and rarely very consequential (rarely but not never—see, for example, the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Salem_witch_trials">Salem Witchcraft Hysteria</a>).</p>
<p>But back to my main argument: If wokeness and its variants are all epiphenomena of the new, historically unprecedented power of women in public life, measures taken against wokeness etc. could be ineffective if there is no acknowledgment of the true source of the problem. Indeed all means short of <em>reducing women’s presence in public life</em> might be futile.</p>
<p>I’m not advocating a specific strategy, but I think it’s important at least to highlight this dilemma, which Western countries obviously have no easy way of resolving. It may be that over time, the current, Cultural Revolution-like surge of wokeness subsides and becomes less radical, as the women pushing wokeness are increasingly forced to acknowledge some of its adverse consequences, such as rising crime from weak law enforcement, social dissolution from uncontrolled immigration, the institutional incompetence that flows inevitably from the abandonment of meritocracy, and the aforementioned institutional instability.</p>
<p>Then again, by the time things get bad enough for women to acknowledge that they aren&#8217;t necessarily better than men at managing our civilization, the process of degeneration might be very, very advanced. Indeed, it&#8217;s plausible that, by then, other, even stronger, less reversible adverse processes—ethnic conflict, for example—will be underway, effectively sealing the West’s fate.</p>
<p style="text-align: center;">***</p>
<p><em>Author’s note:</em></p>
<p><em>I’d appreciate it, reader, if you would link to my essays on cultural feminization (or otherwise cite them) wherever you see this topic being discussed. I’ve been writing about “cult-fem” for more than a decade—which, as far as I know, is much longer than anyone else. Some of my essays have <a href="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/cultural-feminization-a-bibliography/">circulated widely</a></em><em> in recent years, and I’ve even placed <a href="https://americanmind.org/salvo/pink-shift/">one</a></em><em> in a moderately well-read webzine. I like to think that my contributions have, in effect, seeded what is becoming an important public discourse. Yet those contributions of mine are almost never acknowledged by the better-known opinionators who have ventured into this realm in the last year or so. Being pseudonymous and writing principally from a personal website seem to have left me in the unhappy state of being “much read but seldom cited.” (I discuss the general problem of citation in the Internet age in my short essay “<a href="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/the-tree-of-knowledge/">The Tree of Knowledge</a></em><em>.”)</em></p>
<p><em>Also, though I don’t charge a subscription to this website, or put ads on it, or even solicit donations, you could buy a copy of my e-book (see image below, linked to its Amazon page) if you’d like to support my essay-writing.</em></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>THE TREE OF KNOWLEDGE</title>
		<link>https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/the-tree-of-knowledge/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[j stone]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sat, 16 Apr 2022 21:52:30 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[ideas]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[psychology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[technology]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/?p=566</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Encourage new ideas and more productive dialogue by giving idea-originators the credit they’re due &#160; Late in 2011, I first put pen to paper, or fingertips to keyboard, to describe an idea that had been bouncing around in my mind for several years—at least since Larry Summers’s public defenestration from Harvard in 2005. The idea &#8230; <a href="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/the-tree-of-knowledge/" class="more-link">Continue reading<span class="screen-reader-text"> "THE TREE OF KNOWLEDGE"</span></a>]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><em>Encourage new ideas and more productive dialogue by giving idea-originators the credit they’re due</em></p>
<p><span id="more-566"></span></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>Late in 2011, I first put pen to paper, or fingertips to keyboard, to describe an idea that had been bouncing around in my mind for several years—at least since Larry Summers’s public <a href="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/the-day-the-logic-died/">defenestration</a> from Harvard in 2005. The idea was that women’s unprecedented mass entry into public life, in the US and other Western societies, had been “feminizing” public discourse and policy—leading among other things to the rise of political correctness culture, the increasing suppression of free speech, and the decline of capital punishment—due to women’s different way of thinking about the world.</p>
<p>I wasn’t a professional opinionator—just an amateur with a background in journalism. But I did have a website where I published occasional essays, which were read by a few hundreds to thousands of people every month, and there I first set down my thoughts in a <a href="https://james-the-obscure.github.io/the-demise-of-guythink/">short piece</a> about the demise of the male cognitive style. In the ensuing decade, I developed the basic idea in further essays, including in two web magazines with significant readership. I joined Twitter to promote these essays. Eventually I had some recognition as an introducer of this idea.</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" class="size-full wp-image-573 aligncenter" src="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2022/04/spotted-toad.jpg" alt="" width="591" height="224" srcset="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2022/04/spotted-toad.jpg 591w, https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2022/04/spotted-toad-300x114.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 591px) 85vw, 591px" /></p>
<p><img loading="lazy" class="wp-image-574 aligncenter" src="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2022/04/cowen-Copy.jpg" alt="" width="471" height="310" srcset="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2022/04/cowen-Copy.jpg 660w, https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2022/04/cowen-Copy-300x198.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 471px) 85vw, 471px" /></p>
<p><img loading="lazy" class="wp-image-575 aligncenter" src="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2022/04/pink-shift-cover.jpg" alt="" width="364" height="527" srcset="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2022/04/pink-shift-cover.jpg 1246w, https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2022/04/pink-shift-cover-207x300.jpg 207w, https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2022/04/pink-shift-cover-707x1024.jpg 707w, https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2022/04/pink-shift-cover-768x1113.jpg 768w, https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2022/04/pink-shift-cover-1060x1536.jpg 1060w, https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2022/04/pink-shift-cover-1200x1738.jpg 1200w" sizes="(max-width: 364px) 85vw, 364px" /></p>
<p>The idea of cultural feminization became more and more obvious in the wake of the Great Awokening, which appeared to be a heavily female-dominated social phenomenon. One <a href="https://thecritic.co.uk/issues/december-january-2022/new-female-ascendency/">writer</a> after <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2022/01/12/opinion/gender-gap-politics.html">another</a> began to notice and embrace the cultural feminization idea as their own—either not knowing of my (and others’) prior <a href="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/cultural-feminization-a-bibliography/">contributions</a>, or knowing of them but not considering them “big” enough, in terms of readership and public awareness, to acknowledge them.</p>
<p>I may be ultra-sensitive on this topic, because some of my past journalistic work has been used by others with inadequate attribution (or none). I am also aware that this is a very personal kind of pain, one that tends to attract little sympathy from those who have not had a similar experience.</p>
<div style="width: 640px;" class="wp-video"><!--[if lt IE 9]><script>document.createElement('video');</script><![endif]-->
<video class="wp-video-shortcode" id="video-566-1" width="640" height="352" preload="metadata" controls="controls"><source type="video/mp4" src="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2022/04/Dustin-Hoffman-And-Robert-De-Niro-Wag-The-Dog-I-Want-The-Credit-2-1-Copy.mp4?_=1" /><a href="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2022/04/Dustin-Hoffman-And-Robert-De-Niro-Wag-The-Dog-I-Want-The-Credit-2-1-Copy.mp4">https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2022/04/Dustin-Hoffman-And-Robert-De-Niro-Wag-The-Dog-I-Want-The-Credit-2-1-Copy.mp4</a></video></div>
<p>Still, I think there is an objective case to be made, wholly apart from my own gripes, that “inadequate credit to originators of ideas” (ICOI?) is a legitimate social problem whose solution would materially benefit society. Why? Simply because denying people credit for developing original ideas effectively disincentivizes them from making the effort to develop those ideas, and in that straightforward sense is likely to retard human progress. Obscuring past expressions of an idea also limits new discussions of that idea when they do occur—people are constantly “reinventing the wheel.”</p>
<p>We acknowledge this logic in other domains of knowledge production. The new ideas of scientists, doctors, English Lit experts, etc. are protected and made accessible by the searchability of their formal papers (via the PubMed system, for example) and the citation custom. New technical ideas also are protected and made accessible by the patent system and its strong judicial backing. Books, musical compositions, movies, TV shows, are protected—albeit weakly—by the copyright system.</p>
<p>Unfortunately, when it comes to ordinary, non-patentable, non-copyrightable ideas that are published in informal, non-academic fora—ideas such as “women’s mass entry into public life has feminized institutions, culture and policy”—there is no legal protection, and no good and searchable repository. Moreover, the principal search engines for web-based material aren’t really designed to uncover the origins and subsequent iterations of ideas. Mainly because of this, there is only a very weak cultural enforcement of priority claims by idea-originators. I observe anecdotally, for example, that Twitter is full of DIY experts who (from lack of knowledge and/or lack of scruples) recycle others’ ideas, framing their contributions as new, though they are unoriginal and are often incomplete/undeveloped compared to the true original. Thus, the true originators are discouraged by not getting credit, and the false ones lead everyone in circles instead of moving the discussion productively forward.</p>
<p><strong>Solutions?</strong></p>
<p>In a broad-brush way, I imagine two complementary solutions to this problem. One is to develop a “registry of ideas.” The other is to develop an “idea history” search engine/bot.</p>
<p>The registry of ideas could have a broad structure like the “<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Motif-Index_of_Folk-Literature">motif index</a>” developed by the anthropologist Stith Thompson in the 1930s to record and categorize folkloric tales according to their different elements or &#8220;motifs.”</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" class="wp-image-569 aligncenter" src="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2022/04/motif-index-Copy-2-scaled.jpg" alt="" width="455" height="736" srcset="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2022/04/motif-index-Copy-2-scaled.jpg 1584w, https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2022/04/motif-index-Copy-2-186x300.jpg 186w, https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2022/04/motif-index-Copy-2-633x1024.jpg 633w, https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2022/04/motif-index-Copy-2-768x1241.jpg 768w, https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2022/04/motif-index-Copy-2-950x1536.jpg 950w, https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2022/04/motif-index-Copy-2-1267x2048.jpg 1267w" sizes="(max-width: 455px) 85vw, 455px" /></p>
<p>The Dewey Decimal System, by which librarians decide where to shelve books, and the aborted Google “<a href="https://dbpedia.org/page/Knol">Knol</a>” project, offer other potentially helpful models of topic-categorization.</p>
<p>I imagine that some organization like the Wikimedia Foundation (Wikipedia’s parent) could provide some initial structure and guidelines for such a database, after which it would be assembled and curated by volunteers in a highly distributed manner—like Wikipedia. Idea-originators could directly submit their work for recording in the registry, as they can now for appropriate intellectual property with the patent and copyright systems, or they could just let the curators detect their work (assuming it had been published) with their specially designed web bots and other search tools.</p>
<p>Those tools would be powered by “idea history” search algos, which would parse natural language text to identify ideas being expressed, and categorize them—at least as a “first pass” effort to be checked by human curators of different idea domains, though AI tech may soon be able to handle such tasks on its own.</p>
<p>I suppose one objection to this whole idea—this idea about ideas—would be that ordinary writers, especially casual self-published essayists and social-media posters, won’t submit to a citation system the way academics do. I think, though, that to a great extent, ordinary writers already <em>do</em> follow the custom of citation. These days (unlike, say, 50 years ago) a large majority of young adults in the US have had some college experience, with the exposure to citation rules that entails. More importantly, the internet with its “hypertext” ability that can easily link text to other documents anywhere on the web has made citation of others’ work routine even for the most casual writers. The only things missing, really, are the search engines and repositories that would help to fully routinize the assignment of priority, rewarding creativity appropriately, and plausibly making even our humdrum, everyday dialogue a bit more rigorous and serious.</p>
<p style="text-align: center;">* * *</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		<enclosure url="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2022/04/Dustin-Hoffman-And-Robert-De-Niro-Wag-The-Dog-I-Want-The-Credit-2-1-Copy.mp4" length="1281012" type="video/mp4" />

			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
