<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>freedom of speech &#8211; Thoughts of Stone</title>
	<atom:link href="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/category/freedom-of-speech/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/</link>
	<description>short essays, usually about humans</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Sat, 18 Feb 2023 04:06:15 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=6.1.1</generator>

<image>
	<url>https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2020/07/cropped-icon-32x32.jpg</url>
	<title>freedom of speech &#8211; Thoughts of Stone</title>
	<link>https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/</link>
	<width>32</width>
	<height>32</height>
</image> 
	<item>
		<title>IT&#8217;S NOT &#8220;WOKENESS&#8221;&#8212;IT&#8217;S WOMEN</title>
		<link>https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/its-not-wokeness-its-women/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[j stone]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 10 Oct 2022 04:49:27 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[ethnicity]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[fall of the West]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[freedom of speech]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[ideas]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[immigration]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[psychology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[science]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[wokeism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[women]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/?p=682</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[The rise of wokeness, ESG, the trans mania, etc. is all due to women&#8217;s new power in institutions The new Western culture, especially the American variety, offers the old-fashioned conservative male dissident many trends to bewail. Discrimination against white males! Promotion of LGBTQ lifestyles! The trans mania with its mutilation of children and destruction of &#8230; <a href="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/its-not-wokeness-its-women/" class="more-link">Continue reading<span class="screen-reader-text"> "IT&#8217;S NOT &#8220;WOKENESS&#8221;&#8212;IT&#8217;S WOMEN"</span></a>]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><em>The rise of wokeness, ESG, the trans mania, etc. is all due to women&#8217;s new power in institutions</em></p>
<p><span id="more-682"></span></p>
<p>The new Western culture, especially the American variety, offers the old-fashioned conservative male dissident many trends to bewail. Discrimination against white males! Promotion of LGBTQ lifestyles! The trans mania with its mutilation of children and destruction of women’s sports! Suppression of meritocracy, free speech, free scientific inquiry, and due process of law! Runaway entitlement spending! Open borders! Critical race theory! The ESG investing fad! No-prosecute policies in violent cities! Proliferation of social contagions and hysterical illnesses, from ROGD and PTSD to Tik-Tok Tourette’s! Cascades of cancellations of perfectly competent white males, e.g., for “<a href="https://www.theguardian.com/us-news/2022/oct/06/nyu-professor-fired-maitland-jones-jr-student-petition">grading too hard in organic chemistry</a>,” or for <a href="https://www.nydailynews.com/news/national/ny-apple-exec-fired-tiktok-arthur-20220930-rdsgzpbzr5anxjyqar5avuiyv4-story.html">cracking an off-color joke</a>! Widespread exclusion (in effect) of males from important professions, including public relations, publishing, and clinical psychology/psychotherapy. “Math is White Supremacy!” “Showing up for work is White Supremacy!!” “Not being a pea-brained slob is White Supremacy!!!”</p>
<p>My argument here is that everybody should <em>stop</em> bewailing these trends as separate phenomena—should stop fighting “wokeness” or “ESG” or the trans mania. They should, instead, focus on the one factor that underlies and causes all of these social developments.</p>
<p>Of course, I mean <em>women</em>—or more precisely, women’s newfound power in organizations and institutions, and in the culture generally.</p>
<p>An assumption everyone seems to have made during the decades of female emancipation is that women see things more or less as men do, and are just as devoted as men to the principles underlying Western civilization. Not so! As some feminist writers, including Virginia Woolf, warned long ago, women when they enter public life in business and government tend to look around and see lots of things they want to change. They’re just not fans, to the extent that men are, of things like free speech, open debate, due process of law, meritocracy, free scientific inquiry, maximizing shareholder value, equality of opportunity, and so on.</p>
<p>It’s not that women have worked things out logically and carefully and comprehensively, and now want to formally enact a scheme they think is better. It’s more that things in Western civ, which was made by men, often go against the emotional grain with women, causing them real discomfort, and compelling them to react. Women’s instincts were shaped by evolution for a maternal and domestic context, and seem to bias them towards short-term, feelgood, nurturing, and protective outcomes—on average compared to men. These instincts seem to be especially aroused by things like persistent racial inequality, discussions of race-based IQ differences, ruthless meritocratic competition unleavened by sympathy for the losers, stern cross-examinations of women making rape claims, medical skepticism over women&#8217;s unverifiable symptoms, and the kind of frat-boy humor that has gotten so many men cancelled. Now that women are largely in charge, they question why we need such things—or peremptorily try to stamp them out.</p>
<p>There are some nuances to this general theory. First, a lot of women are not woke. But the argument here is really about women on average as compared to men on average, and I don’t think it could be reasonably disputed that women, on average and compared to men, are significantly biased in the direction of wokeness. It’s also obviously true that modest average psychological differences between the sexes could translate to big social changes when one sex takes power from the other. I would suggest too that the women who seek power in institutions are less likely to be “average” women and more likely to be childless activist types. There is, moreover, a hell of a lot of depression and anxiety among modern women, especially younger ones, and that as well may push many women to embrace the woke activism mindset as a therapeutic source of meaning and purpose.</p>
<p>Another nuance has to do with women’s apparently superior ability, compared to men, to align themselves emotionally within a group. This means, in effect, that women in an organization will tend to be less independent-minded, with the tradeoff that they can collectively punch above their weight. Among the examples that come to mind is the recent <a href="https://www.tmz.com/2020/03/06/woody-allen-memoir-canceled-hachette-publisher-staff-walkout/">cancellation of Woody Allen</a> from his publisher due to activism among the publishing company’s <em>junior staff</em>. (The publishing industry, like public relations and psychology/psychiatry/psychotherapy, is utterly dominated by women—“junior staff” in publishing generally means millennial women.)</p>
<p>Women, as I’ve suggested in a recent <a href="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/always-be-capturing/">essay</a>, may also have, collectively, a stronger drive to dominate organizations, to eliminate the greater discomfort they experience when exposed to male organizational culture. Certainly the female-to-male ratio in many organizations now is one that would be condemned as discriminatory (by women) were the proportions reversed.</p>
<p>A further nuance, which I think will become increasingly obvious and important as our societal &#8220;<a href="https://americanmind.org/salvo/pink-shift/">pink shift</a>&#8221; advances, is that women, as they align emotionally within groups, and ultimately purge dissenting voices, tend to cause the institutions they control to become unstable. In other words, like hysteria-prone convents of half a millenium ago, female-dominated institutions become relatively susceptible to groupthink contagions that swing them irrationally this way and that. Today these contagions introduce relatively mild new absurdities like pronoun declarations and land acknowledgments. But I expect it&#8217;s all going to get loopier, and more harshly enforced, as time goes on and female control solidifies.</p>
<p>Lastly, somewhat hair-splittingly, I don’t think that women when left to themselves running male-built institutions <em>necessarily</em> become woke in the way that we see now. I see wokeness as a contemporary, contagious mindset (not quite an ideology) that corresponds very well to, and thus easily infects, the average female mind, still moreso the younger, more neurotic, more activist female mind. But in principle, under different circumstances, one could gin up something substantially different that would also spread well among women, provided that it pressed their main buttons. Certainly in the centuries before women took such a large part in public life, thought contagions among them were common and varied, though usually localized and rarely very consequential (rarely but not never—see, for example, the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Salem_witch_trials">Salem Witchcraft Hysteria</a>).</p>
<p>But back to my main argument: If wokeness and its variants are all epiphenomena of the new, historically unprecedented power of women in public life, measures taken against wokeness etc. could be ineffective if there is no acknowledgment of the true source of the problem. Indeed all means short of <em>reducing women’s presence in public life</em> might be futile.</p>
<p>I’m not advocating a specific strategy, but I think it’s important at least to highlight this dilemma, which Western countries obviously have no easy way of resolving. It may be that over time, the current, Cultural Revolution-like surge of wokeness subsides and becomes less radical, as the women pushing wokeness are increasingly forced to acknowledge some of its adverse consequences, such as rising crime from weak law enforcement, social dissolution from uncontrolled immigration, the institutional incompetence that flows inevitably from the abandonment of meritocracy, and the aforementioned institutional instability.</p>
<p>Then again, by the time things get bad enough for women to acknowledge that they aren&#8217;t necessarily better than men at managing our civilization, the process of degeneration might be very, very advanced. Indeed, it&#8217;s plausible that, by then, other, even stronger, less reversible adverse processes—ethnic conflict, for example—will be underway, effectively sealing the West’s fate.</p>
<p style="text-align: center;">***</p>
<p><em>Author’s note:</em></p>
<p><em>I’d appreciate it, reader, if you would link to my essays on cultural feminization (or otherwise cite them) wherever you see this topic being discussed. I’ve been writing about “cult-fem” for more than a decade—which, as far as I know, is much longer than anyone else. Some of my essays have <a href="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/cultural-feminization-a-bibliography/">circulated widely</a></em><em> in recent years, and I’ve even placed <a href="https://americanmind.org/salvo/pink-shift/">one</a></em><em> in a moderately well-read webzine. I like to think that my contributions have helped seed what is becoming an important public discourse. Yet those contributions of mine are almost never acknowledged by the better-known opinionators who have ventured into this realm in the last year or so. Being pseudonymous and writing principally from a personal website seem to have left me in the unhappy state of being “much read but seldom cited.” (I discuss the general problem of citation in the Internet age in my short essay “<a href="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/the-tree-of-knowledge/">The Tree of Knowledge</a></em><em>.”)</em></p>
<p><em>Also, though I don’t charge a subscription to this website, or put ads on it, or even solicit donations, you could buy a copy of my e-book (see image below, linked to its Amazon page) if you’d like to support my writing.</em></p>
<p style="text-align: center;">*</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>CULTURAL FEMINIZATION: AN INTRODUCTION</title>
		<link>https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/cultural-feminization-an-introduction/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[j stone]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 24 Aug 2022 23:24:31 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[fall of the West]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[freedom of speech]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[psychology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[science]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[testosterone]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[wokeism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[women]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/?p=641</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[&#160; A quick summary for those coming to this for the first time. &#160; I’ve been in the habit of citing one of my 2019 essays, “The Great Feminization” or “The Day the Logic Died,” as an introduction to the idea of cultural feminization. Since those pieces were written, though, I’ve posted other essays on &#8230; <a href="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/cultural-feminization-an-introduction/" class="more-link">Continue reading<span class="screen-reader-text"> "CULTURAL FEMINIZATION: AN INTRODUCTION"</span></a>]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><em>A quick summary for those coming to this for the first time.</em></p>
<p><span id="more-641"></span></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>I’ve been in the habit of citing one of my 2019 essays, “<a href="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/the-great-feminization/">The Great Feminization</a>” or “<a href="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/the-day-the-logic-died/">The Day the Logic Died</a>,” as an introduction to the idea of cultural feminization. Since those pieces were written, though, I’ve posted other essays on this topic, expanding this “idea space” a bit more with each one. So it might be useful now, to those coming to this for the first time, to have an updated short summary of the whole picture as I see it.</p>
<p><strong>In a Nutshell</strong></p>
<p>Women, because of their different ways of thinking and behaving on average, and their new, strong influence over culture and politics, are the principal drivers of modern social change, including all aspects of wokeness.</p>
<p><strong>From Home to Office</strong></p>
<p>American women—whose sociocultural circumstances are very similar to those of other Western women—obtained full equality in voting rights by constitutional amendment more than a century ago. That had significant cultural and political consequences, but it was only a small part of the story of women’s modern empowerment. The big change occurred in the period 1950-2000, when women shifted, <em>en masse</em> and on a durable, peacetime basis, from being dedicated homemakers to participating more or less equally alongside men in the working world and public life. The labor force participation rate charts below (the first for American men, the second for women) clearly show this shift.</p>
<p><img decoding="async" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-652" src="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/fredgraph-men.jpg" alt="" width="1168" height="470" srcset="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/fredgraph-men.jpg 1168w, https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/fredgraph-men-300x121.jpg 300w, https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/fredgraph-men-1024x412.jpg 1024w, https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/fredgraph-men-768x309.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 709px) 85vw, (max-width: 909px) 67vw, (max-width: 1362px) 62vw, 840px" /><img decoding="async" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-653" src="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/fredgraph-women.jpg" alt="" width="1168" height="470" srcset="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/fredgraph-women.jpg 1168w, https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/fredgraph-women-300x121.jpg 300w, https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/fredgraph-women-1024x412.jpg 1024w, https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/fredgraph-women-768x309.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 709px) 85vw, (max-width: 909px) 67vw, (max-width: 1362px) 62vw, 840px" /></p>
<p>As I wrote in “<a href="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/the-great-feminization/">The Great Feminization</a>”:</p>
<p style="padding-left: 40px;">The historic significance of this migration on its own appears to have been underappreciated. Women never made such a move, to such a degree, in any large human society in the past. It significantly altered the structure of ordinary life.</p>
<p style="padding-left: 40px;">But women in the late 20th century didn’t just move into the workforce. They moved into its upper ranks, to professions that strongly influence societal culture and policy. They became journalists, public relations specialists, lawyers, academics, novelists, publishers, filmmakers, TV producers, and politicians, all to an unprecedented extent. In some of these culture-making professions, by the 1990s and early 2000s, they had achieved parity or even dominance (e.g., writers, authors, and public relations specialists) with respect to men. Even where they fell short of full parity, they appeared to acquire considerable “veto” power over content. A 2017 report by the Women’s Media Center noted evidence that at the vast majority of media companies, at least one woman is among the top three editors.</p>
<p><strong>Women Think Differently About Cultural and Political Matters</strong></p>
<p>Women’s ascension to power in culture- and policy-making professions has been followed by extensive cultural and political changes. Why? Because women, on average, think differently than men do about cultural and political issues. This should not be surprising: The bodies and minds of women and men were shaped long ago by biological and cultural evolution for their distinct traditional roles in life. Women’s distinct roles obviously have required certain psychological traits or tendencies that are different from male traits. I think most of us would agree that these innately feminine traits include:</p>
<ol>
<li style="list-style-type: none;">
<ul>
<li>A greater emotional sensitivity and capacity for empathy/compassion/nurturing.</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ol>
<ul>
<li style="list-style-type: none;">
<ul>
<li>A greater fearfulness and aversion to risks (concerning dangers to themselves and others), including an extra sensitivity to the risks of toxic and other environmental threats (reflected in hormone-driven pregnancy behaviors such as food/odor aversions and compulsive “nesting”).</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<ul>
<li style="list-style-type: none;">
<ul>
<li>A greater affinity for people and relationships, and lesser affinity for constructed, systemized, and abstract things.</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<ul>
<li style="list-style-type: none;">
<ul>
<li>A greater tendency to align emotionally when in a group, especially a group of other women—a tendency that implies a superior ability (individually and collectively) to transmit emotions and other social contagions.</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<ul>
<li style="list-style-type: none;">
<ul>
<li>A reduced affinity for competition and capacity for resistance to aggressors.</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<ul>
<li style="list-style-type: none;">
<ul>
<li>Greater affinity for themes of suffering and victimhood, with correspondingly less interest in triumphant “male” themes of exploration and conquest.</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<p>Probably most of these traits are interrelated. In any case, when one considers these broad aspects of “innate femininity,” it isn’t hard to see that the very sudden extension of their dominance—from women’s traditional domestic domain to all areas of public life—would help account for the dramatic social changes of the past half-century or so.</p>
<p>It also isn’t hard to see that women tend to support these social changes more than men do—although it&#8217;s important to understand that by altering the culture, women have influenced not only their own but also <em>men’s</em> thinking and behavior.</p>
<p><strong>Social changes likely to have been driven by the ascendancy of female traits</strong></p>
<ul>
<li style="list-style-type: none;">
<ul>
<li>Much more generous welfare programs.</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<ul>
<li style="list-style-type: none;">
<ul>
<li>Extensions of the concept of welfare to include more types of intervention (e.g., affirmative action) and more groups needing intervention (“traditionally marginalized groups”).</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<ul>
<li style="list-style-type: none;">
<ul>
<li>Excessively honoring (e.g., with pronoun declaration rituals) anyone with a claim to victimhood or some other “special identity” status.</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<ul>
<li style="list-style-type: none;">
<ul>
<li>Very strong social reactions to media portrayals of racial injustice/inequity, e.g., the near-hysterias following the police killings of Michael Brown in Ferguson, MO and George Floyd in Minneapolis, MN.</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<p><img decoding="async" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-225" src="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2021/06/bethesdaawokening-1.jpg" alt="" width="800" height="450" srcset="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2021/06/bethesdaawokening-1.jpg 800w, https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2021/06/bethesdaawokening-1-300x169.jpg 300w, https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2021/06/bethesdaawokening-1-768x432.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 709px) 85vw, (max-width: 909px) 67vw, (max-width: 984px) 61vw, (max-width: 1362px) 45vw, 600px" /></p>
<ul>
<li style="list-style-type: none;">
<ul>
<li>Inflations of the traditional definitions of “harm,” “offense,” “trauma,” “violence,” “aggression,” etc., as reflected in new terms such as “microaggressions” and “triggers.”</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<ul>
<li style="list-style-type: none;">
<ul>
<li>An astounding belief (from men’s perspective) in slight or even imaginary emotional upsets as sources of real harm in the world. This belief is reflected in everyday female-produced media content but also in the new hyper-focus on psychological trauma in law and medicine, and of course in the vast inflation of trauma-related syndromes such as PTSD (and the recovered-trauma-memory syndromes of the 1980s/90s, before they were discredited).</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<ul>
<li style="list-style-type: none;">
<ul>
<li>A shift away from the traditional deterrence of criminal behavior with punishment and stigmatization, in preference for compassion-based, non-stigmatizing solutions (e.g., non-prosecute policies for most crimes, free needles for addicts).</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<ul>
<li style="list-style-type: none;">
<ul>
<li>Reduced tolerance of deaths in war, despite (ironically) a greater inclination to enter foreign conflicts in response to emotion-evoking atrocities portrayed on television.</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<p><img decoding="async" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-644" src="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/boy1.jpg" alt="" width="194" height="259" /></p>
<ul>
<li style="list-style-type: none;">
<ul>
<li>Less tolerance for capital punishment and other harsh sentences, especially where the “traditionally disadvantaged” are concerned.</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<ul>
<li style="list-style-type: none;">
<ul>
<li>Less restrictive immigration policy, again driven by stories and imagery (pitiable refugee children, huddled masses, etc.) that evoke maternal protective/nurturing instincts.</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<p><img decoding="async" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-646" src="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/refugee.jpg" alt="" width="800" height="524" srcset="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/refugee.jpg 800w, https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/refugee-300x197.jpg 300w, https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/refugee-768x503.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 709px) 85vw, (max-width: 909px) 67vw, (max-width: 984px) 61vw, (max-width: 1362px) 45vw, 600px" /></p>
<ul>
<li style="list-style-type: none;">
<ul>
<li>In general, much more emphasis in media and policy contexts on compassion-evoking stories of individuals, with correspondingly less emphasis on (even condemnation of!) coldly logical risk/benefit analyses focused on the long term.</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<ul>
<li style="list-style-type: none;">
<ul>
<li>Suppression of potentially upsetting ideas or expressions (“hate speech,” “mansplaining”), words, facts (e.g., on racial differences in criminality), free debate and free speech, due process of law (especially when women are plaintiffs), and even some fields of scientific inquiry.</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<ul>
<li style="list-style-type: none;">
<ul>
<li>Helicopter parenting.</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<ul>
<li style="list-style-type: none;">
<ul>
<li>Obsession with safety, e.g., as seen in new terms such as “safe space.”</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<ul>
<li style="list-style-type: none;">
<ul>
<li>Rise of “green” movement and related cultural themes involving opposition to nuclear power, GMO, “toxins,” “chemicals,” even vaccines (a movement that was increasing in popularity, with female leadership, pre-COVID-19). Related shift towards “natural” foods and medicines, including those produced by the relatively unregulated supplements industry. Rise of hysteria variants involving claims of chemical hypersensitivity, toxic metals, etc.</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<ul>
<li style="list-style-type: none;">
<ul>
<li>Decline in interest in engineering, as shown by greater reliance on foreign-born students at e-schools, loss of Western pre-eminence (to China) in advanced engineering projects.</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<ul>
<li style="list-style-type: none;">
<ul>
<li>Predominance of “social media” in Western life.</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<ul>
<li style="list-style-type: none;">
<ul>
<li>Shift away from technical themes and toward social (woke) themes in female-dominated STEM media and professions, e.g., “math is white supremacist.”</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<ul>
<li style="list-style-type: none;">
<ul>
<li>Shift away from traditional, hierarchical, rule-based religions toward more loosely structured and therapeutic forms of worship and spirituality.</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<ul>
<li style="list-style-type: none;">
<ul>
<li>Frequent and rapid social contagions of new cultural themes (e.g., wokeness and its various associated behaviors and terminology, from BLM worship to the trans mania), affecting virtually all organizations and institutions&#8212;because women, the chief transmitters of these contagions, are highly influential in organizations and institutions.</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<ul>
<li style="list-style-type: none;">
<ul>
<li>Increase in the frequency and prevalence of overtly pathological social contagions (hysterias) such as Tik-Tok-induced Tourette’s-like behavior.</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<ul>
<li style="list-style-type: none;">
<ul>
<li>Tendency of professions and institutions to become female-dominated by systematically excluding (especially white) males—who are “problematic” for grouped women, simply because of their innate male resistance to institutional feminization.</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<ul>
<li style="list-style-type: none;">
<ul>
<li>General increase in intolerant, “hive-mind” behavior in institutions and professions as a consequence of increasing female dominance.</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<ul>
<li style="list-style-type: none;">
<ul>
<li>Marked preference for inclusivity and equity over traditional meritocratic discrimination, everywhere from schools to companies to political appointees and candidates. “Participation trophies.”</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<ul>
<li style="list-style-type: none;">
<ul>
<li>Virtually uniform emphasis on victimhood themes in Western literary fiction, coincident with female takeover of publishing industry.</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<ul>
<li style="list-style-type: none;">
<ul>
<li>Reduced public interest in adventurous endeavors such as manned space exploration (“we should fix poverty and inequality here on Earth first”).</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<ul>
<li style="list-style-type: none;">
<ul>
<li>Demotion of traditional heroes such as Christopher Columbus and Thomas Jefferson and promotion of their alleged victims, e.g., Native Americans, Sally Hemings.</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<p>Obviously, not every woman out there likes or is driving these changes. The differences between men’s and women’s mindsets are differences <em>on average</em>.</p>
<p><img decoding="async" class="aligncenter wp-image-12" src="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2020/07/coulter-twitr.jpg" alt="" width="472" height="134" srcset="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2020/07/coulter-twitr.jpg 578w, https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2020/07/coulter-twitr-300x85.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 472px) 85vw, 472px" /></p>
<p>Moreover, the mindset underlying these shifts—a mindset that, in some of these cases, seems sensitive to the point of neuroticism—might not even be that of the <em>average</em> woman. I suspect it more closely represents the attitudes of the single, childless activists who have been most energetic in pushing these social changes. For them, perhaps, society and its “disadvantaged,” from African-Americans to Rio Grande-crossing illegal immigrants, are substitutes for the children they don’t have.</p>
<p><strong>Cultural Feminization is Problematic</strong></p>
<p>One sufficient and conservative reason for doubting that cultural feminization is a good thing is simply that it entails the abrupt replacement of a large set of civilizational traits that were embedded in Western people, culturally and probably biologically, over thousands of years. Not every Western trait is essential to the West’s survival or is even still adaptive in the modern world. But discarding these traits at the whim of female activists seems a bit like deleting genes willy-nilly from the human genome. Could you do that without bad consequences? Yes, conceivably&#8212;but it&#8217;s far more likely to end in disaster.</p>
<p>Another good reason to oppose or limit cultural feminization is that, while men traditionally led societies and thus would have been expected to evolve attitudes and behaviors appropriate for that role, women traditionally were confined to other, more private roles, centering on maternity. In other words, why should we suppose that being a mother, or being shaped by evolution for motherhood, is a better preparation for public life than . . . serving in public life, as men have done for ages?</p>
<p>There are further reasons that have to do with specific effects of feminization. For example, feminization appears to have brought a new cultural and political emphasis on short-term, feelgood consequences, with less emphasis on—I would say a blindness to—long-term consequences. It should be obvious that this is unsustainable and must end badly.</p>
<p>Moreover, females&#8217; lesser affinity, even hostility, for due process of law, free debate, unfettered scientific inquiry, and related aspects of Western, small-l liberalism, seems likely to render the West relatively static, sclerotic, and poor if allowed to run to its logical conclusion.</p>
<p>Then, of course, there is the apparent female (relative to male) embrace of mass immigration to the West from the Third World, which I think has the potential to dissolve Western societies faster than any other factor.</p>
<p><img decoding="async" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-165" src="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2021/03/merkel-1.jpg" alt="" width="600" height="422" srcset="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2021/03/merkel-1.jpg 600w, https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2021/03/merkel-1-300x211.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 709px) 85vw, (max-width: 909px) 67vw, (max-width: 984px) 61vw, (max-width: 1362px) 45vw, 600px" /></p>
<p>I think it’s worth mentioning too, though it&#8217;s more speculative, that the apparent decades-long slide in testosterone levels in men might be an effect of cultural feminization. Testosterone levels in men (and women) are known to be regulated by social cues, such as winning or losing competitions, and so <a href="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/testosterone-civilization-and-social-cues/">it would make sense</a> that cultural messaging condemning and suppressing traditional masculinity would have a T-lowering effect. Lower T means lower fertility, which below a certain threshold—one that Legacy Americans sank beneath long ago—leads ultimately to the extinction of the population.</p>
<p>Lastly, there is the sense of <em>taboo</em> that enshrouds the idea of cultural feminization, in general but especially when it is framed negatively. The high-profile MSM types (<a href="https://www.bloomberg.com/opinion/articles/2021-09-19/woke-movement-is-global-and-america-should-be-mostly-proud">Cowen</a>, <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2022/01/12/opinion/gender-gap-politics.html">Edsall</a>) who have touched the subject (only in the last year or so, as far as I know) have been approving or very mild in their concerns. Also, for more than a decade now, most of the short essays I’ve tried to get published on this subject, including in some pretty right wing publications, have been rejected. In every case, a female editor had veto power, and I think her male colleagues also feared the hostile ululations that would ensue if they published my unvarnished take. Anyhow, an old quote (often attributed to Voltaire) seems apt here: “If you want to know who rules over you, look at whom you’re not allowed to criticize.”</p>
<p><strong>Further reading</strong></p>
<p>&#8220;<a href="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/the-great-feminization/">The Great Feminization</a>&#8221; (2019)</p>
<p>&#8220;<a href="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/the-day-the-logic-died/">The Day the Logic Died</a>&#8221; (2019)</p>
<p>&#8220;<a href="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/cultural-feminization-a-bibliography/">Cultural Feminization: a Bibliography</a>&#8221; (2021)</p>
<p><a href="https://www.amazon.com/dp/B09Z7MWJ7R"><em>The Great Feminization: Women as Drivers of Modern Social Change</em></a> (2022)</p>
<p style="text-align: center;">* * *</p>
<p><em>Author’s note:</em></p>
<p><em>I’d appreciate it, reader, if you would link to my essays on cultural feminization (or otherwise cite them) wherever you see this topic being discussed. I’ve been writing about “cult-fem” for more than a decade—which, as far as I know, is much longer than anyone else. Some of my essays have <a href="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/cultural-feminization-a-bibliography/">circulated widely</a></em><em> in recent years, and I’ve even placed <a href="https://americanmind.org/salvo/pink-shift/">one</a></em><em> in a moderately well-read webzine. I like to think that my contributions have helped seed what is becoming an important public discourse. Yet those contributions of mine are almost never acknowledged by the better-known opinionators who have ventured into this realm in the last year or so. Being pseudonymous and writing principally from a personal website seem to have left me in the unhappy state of being “much read but seldom cited.” (I discuss the general problem of citation in the Internet age in my short essay “<a href="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/the-tree-of-knowledge/">The Tree of Knowledge</a></em><em>.”)</em></p>
<p><em>Also, though I don’t charge a subscription to this website, or put ads on it, or even solicit donations, you could buy a copy of my e-book (see image below, linked to its Amazon page) if you’d like to support my writing.</em></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>THE GREAT FEMINIZATION</title>
		<link>https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/the-great-feminization/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[j stone]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 06 Mar 2019 22:48:58 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[freedom of speech]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[immigration]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[women]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://box5257.temp.domains/~houghty5/?p=38</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Forget #TheFutureIsFemale—women have already remodeled the Western world &#160; Feminists these days spend a lot of time worrying about male-dominated culture—“patriarchal culture,” “sexual harassment culture,” “rape culture,” “the culture of silence,” and so on. But shouldn’t they be acknowledging the influence that women now have on culture: on workplace culture, on media culture, on campus &#8230; <a href="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/the-great-feminization/" class="more-link">Continue reading<span class="screen-reader-text"> "THE GREAT FEMINIZATION"</span></a>]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>Forget <em>#TheFutureIsFemale</em>—women have already remodeled the Western world</p>



<p><span id="more-38"></span></p>



<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>Feminists these days spend a lot of time worrying about male-dominated culture—“patriarchal culture,” “sexual harassment culture,” “rape culture,” “the culture of silence,” and so on. But shouldn’t they be acknowledging the influence that <em>women</em> now have on culture: on workplace culture, on media culture, on campus culture, on American culture, and on Western culture generally? That feminizing influence may be the greatest single driver of the rapid social changes seen in recent decades.</p>



<p>Consider the following U.S. Bureau of Labor Statistics chart of women’s civilian labor force participation rate.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><img decoding="async" class="size-large wp-image-19 aligncenter" src="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2020/07/fredgraph-women-1024x412.jpg" alt="women's labor participation rate" width="840" height="338" srcset="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2020/07/fredgraph-women-1024x412.jpg 1024w, https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2020/07/fredgraph-women-300x121.jpg 300w, https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2020/07/fredgraph-women-768x309.jpg 768w, https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2020/07/fredgraph-women.jpg 1168w" sizes="(max-width: 709px) 85vw, (max-width: 909px) 67vw, (max-width: 1362px) 62vw, 840px" /></p>



<figure class="wp-block-image"></figure>



<p>It shows that in 1950 only about 30 percent of working-age women were in the workforce, but by 2000 that figure had jumped to 60 percent and rivaled the participation rate for men, which had been in decline since the early 1950s. In other words, by 2000 the U.S. workforce had been mostly gender-integrated. On average, workplaces by then had almost as many women as men.</p>
<p><img decoding="async" class="size-large wp-image-18 aligncenter" src="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2020/07/fredgraph-men-1024x412.jpg" alt="" width="840" height="338" srcset="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2020/07/fredgraph-men-1024x412.jpg 1024w, https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2020/07/fredgraph-men-300x121.jpg 300w, https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2020/07/fredgraph-men-768x309.jpg 768w, https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2020/07/fredgraph-men.jpg 1168w" sizes="(max-width: 709px) 85vw, (max-width: 909px) 67vw, (max-width: 1362px) 62vw, 840px" /></p>



<figure class="wp-block-image"></figure>



<p>The historic significance of this migration on its own appears to have been underappreciated. Women never made such a move, to such a degree, in any large human society in the past. It significantly altered the structure of ordinary life.</p>
<p>But women in the late 20<sup>th</sup> century didn’t just move into the workforce. They moved into its upper ranks, to professions that strongly influence societal culture and policy. They became journalists, public relations specialists, lawyers, academics, novelists, publishers, filmmakers, TV producers, and politicians, all to an unprecedented extent. In some of these culture-making professions, by the 1990s and early 2000s, they had achieved parity or even <a href="https://www.usatoday.com/story/money/careers/employment-trends/2018/08/08/20-jobs-that-have-become-dominated-by-women/37330779/">dominance</a> (e.g., writers, authors, and public relations specialists) with respect to men. Even where they fell short of full parity, they appeared to acquire considerable “veto” power over content. A 2017 <a href="https://www.womensmediacenter.com/reports/the-status-of-women-in-u.s.-media-2017">report</a> by the Women’s Media Center noted evidence that at the vast majority of media companies, at least one woman is among the top three editors.</p>
<p>Why is the greater presence of women in culture-making professions important? Because women, on average, think differently than men on a wide range of subjects. That psychological differentness is well <a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/articles/201711/the-truth-about-sex-differences">established</a> from experiments, and is reflected in the well-known “<a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/the-2018-gender-gap-was-huge/">gender gap</a>” in voting and policy choices—a gap that is even larger when considering women who are maritally independent of men, i.e., <a href="https://prospect.org/article/untapped-voting-power-single-women">single women</a>, one of the fastest-growing demographics in the country.</p>
<p><img decoding="async" class="size-medium wp-image-12 aligncenter" src="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2020/07/coulter-twitr-300x85.jpg" alt="" width="300" height="85" srcset="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2020/07/coulter-twitr-300x85.jpg 300w, https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2020/07/coulter-twitr.jpg 578w" sizes="(max-width: 300px) 85vw, 300px" /></p>
<p>If one accepts that culture is a strong determinant of behavior, which it is really by definition, it follows that putting a high proportion of women into senior roles in culture-making professions, basically for the first time ever, will have changed the culture and therefore changed how people on average tend to think and act. It won’t have changed everyone absolutely; we are not blank slates. But it will have moved the collective needle—shifted the so-called Overton Window of publicly acceptable opinion, and shifted average behavior as well, even average male behavior. That is, in fact, the underlying logic of organizations like the Women’s Media Center, which have explicitly sought to alter, to <em>feminize</em>, the content of mass media and the resulting attitudes of the public by putting more women into newsrooms.</p>
<p>How would culture and policy have changed as a result of women’s new influence? Presumably in ways that reflect feminine psychological traits.</p>
<p>For example, women appear on average to be more <a href="https://www.sciencedaily.com/releases/2018/11/181112191650.htm">empathetic </a>and compassionate, more <a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/sexual-personalities/201504/are-women-more-emotional-men">emotionally sensitive</a><strong>.</strong> Some of the most striking social changes of the last few decades appear to have been driven by a cultural shift in that direction:</p>
<ul>
<li>More generous welfare programs</li>
<li>Expansion of the concept of welfare to include more types of intervention (affirmative action, etc.) and more groups needing intervention</li>
<li>Expansion of the definitions of “harm,” “offense,” and “trauma” (“microaggressions,” “triggers”)</li>
<li>Increased attention to psychological trauma in law and medicine, leading to a greater acceptance, and thus a higher prevalence, of trauma-related syndromes such as PTSD (and the recovered-trauma-memory syndromes of the 1990s)</li>
<li>Less tolerance of deaths in war; but, ironically, a greater inclination to enter foreign conflicts in response to emotion-evoking atrocities portrayed on television</li>
</ul>



<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="aligncenter"><img decoding="async" class="size-full wp-image-11 aligncenter" src="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2020/07/boy1.jpg" alt="" width="194" height="259" /></figure>
</div>



<ul>
<li>Less tolerance for <a href="https://www.aclu.org/blog/capital-punishment/innocence-and-death-penalty/death-penalty-2018-punishment-decline">capital punishment</a></li>
<li>Less restrictive <a href="https://qz.com/900416/most-immigration-lawyers-are-women-and-they-are-helping-stranded-immigrants-and-refugees-at-us-airports/">immigration policy</a></li>
<li>More emphasis in media and policy contexts on emotion-evoking stories of individuals (e.g., pitiable <a href="https://www.independent.co.uk/news/world/americas/us-politics/aoc-crying-ice-akelin-caal-maquin-alexandria-ocasio-cortez-protest-tears-washington-dc-a8768831.html">refugee children</a>) rather than dry analyses of long-term outcomes</li>
</ul>



<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="aligncenter"><img decoding="async" class="size-full wp-image-17 aligncenter" src="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2020/07/family1.jpg" alt="" width="300" height="169" /><br />
<ul>
<li>Suppression of any kind of emotionally disturbing speech (“hate speech,” “mansplaining,” etc.) and even <a href="https://www.journals.uchicago.edu/doi/abs/10.1086/687863">fields of scientific inquiry</a> that are likely to evoke negative emotions;</li>
<li>Less affinity for traditional, constitutionally protected forms of confrontation in the legal and political spheres, i.e., <a href="https://longreads.com/2018/09/18/no-i-will-not-debate-you/">less support for open debate</a>, <a href="https://www.nas.org/articles/from_suffrage_to_suppressing_speech_the_increasing_hostility_of_women_towar">free-speech rights</a>, and “<a href="https://www.theatlantic.com/ideas/archive/2018/10/sexual-assault-has-become-partisan-issue/572893/">due process of law</a>.”</li>
<li>Suppression/replacement of <em>words</em> that evoke emotional discomfort (e.g., “abortion clinic” becomes “women’s health center”)</li>
</ul>
<p>That’s just from one set of closely related traits. Certainly there are others. For example, women for obvious evolutionary reasons appear to have an instinctive fear of dietary and environmental toxins, which can become pronounced during pregnancy (“morning sickness,” nesting reflex, food aversions). Is it just coincidence that women’s cultural ascendancy in Western countries corresponds to a huge rise in diet-, drug-, and environment-related concerns encompassing the Green movement, anti-GMO attitudes, “detox” fads, the “herbal medicine” racket, “organic foods” preferences, and even the <a href="https://www.fatherly.com/health-science/jenny-mccarthy-masked-singer-measles-outbreak-anti-vaxxer/">anti-vaccine</a> movement?</p>
<p>Then there is the issue of systematizing. Experiments by psychologists and everyday observations by parents, etc. suggest that whereas the average “male” brain is <a href="https://www.theguardian.com/education/2003/apr/17/research.highereducation">adapted for understanding and building systems</a>, the average “female” brain is . . . not so much adapted for that. A cultural shift away from traditional “male,” systematizing thinking across society could again explain many specific social changes. One is the great, still-ongoing migration from traditional religions with their managerial hierarchies and highly systematized theologies to new, more loosely structured and personalized spiritual groups, such as Evangelical Christian groups, New Age movements, and neo-pagan groups (e.g., Wicca) which give prominent roles to women. Another plausible reflection of this de-systematizing tendency is the long-term <a href="https://www.worldexpertise.com/Declining_Interest_in_Engineering_Studies_at_a_Time_of_Increased_Business_Needs.htm">decline</a> of interest in engineering among U.S.-born students, who are now <a href="https://www.insidehighered.com/quicktakes/2017/10/11/foreign-students-and-graduate-stem-enrollment">outnumbered</a> by foreign students at U.S. engineering grad schools.</p>
<p>One of the most obvious sex-related differences in human behavior concerns aggression and violence. Women on average are far less violent than men, and consequently make up only about <a href="https://www.bop.gov/about/statistics/statistics_inmate_gender.jsp">7 percent</a> of the U.S. prison population. If women have had an unprecedented feminizing effect on the “public mind” in recent decades, in principle that would have reduced the propensity for aggression and violence even among men. Indeed there has been a <a href="http://www.pewresearch.org/fact-tank/2019/01/03/5-facts-about-crime-in-the-u-s/">striking downward trend in violent crime rates</a> in the U.S. in recent decades—a trend that would be even stronger if all the violent crimes committed by people born and raised in traditional, patriarchal societies, e.g., Mexico, were excluded.</p>
<p>How could men have been feminized to this extent? By having less <a href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/3575604/">testosterone</a>, for example. The ways in which sex hormones rise and fall in response to <a href="https://www.google.com/url?sa=t&amp;rct=j&amp;q=&amp;esrc=s&amp;source=web&amp;cd=4&amp;cad=rja&amp;uact=8&amp;ved=2ahUKEwiR7sXh1IrhAhXIsFQKHemIAM8QFjADegQIBxAB&amp;url=https%3A%2F%2Fonlinelibrary.wiley.com%2Fdoi%2Fpdf%2F10.1002%2Ftre.372&amp;usg=AOvVaw1zWHTeHK_iPcC4nNAIvBCJ">social cues</a> is an <a href="https://www.cell.com/trends/cognitive-sciences/fulltext/S1364-6613(11)00078-7">under-studied area</a>, but two trends stand out alarmingly: Age-adjusted testosterone levels in men <a href="http://thechart.blogs.cnn.com/2011/08/18/modern-life-rough-on-men/">have been falling</a> in Western countries in recent decades, and—as one would expect from that—<a href="https://www.vox.com/science-and-health/2018/9/17/17841518/low-sperm-count-semen-male-fertility">sperm counts have been falling too</a>. Interestingly, those sperm-count studies suggest that whatever is causing the trend in Western societies has been having less effect, or no effect at all, in traditional, i.e., patriarchal societies.</p>
<p>Why is it “alarming” that male testosterone levels and sperm counts have been dropping in Western countries, if one result is less violent crime? Because that’s not the only result. Declining testosterone also means declining fertility and probably also a declining motivation to marry and raise a family. Here again the statistics are consistent with the idea of a Great Feminization. The U.S. in recent decades has seen not only a <a href="http://www.pewresearch.org/fact-tank/2017/09/14/as-u-s-marriage-rate-hovers-at-50-education-gap-in-marital-status-widens/">decline in the marriage rate</a>, but also a <a href="https://www.npr.org/sections/thetwo-way/2018/05/17/611898421/u-s-births-falls-to-30-year-low-sending-fertility-rate-to-a-record-low">collapse of the birth rate</a> for U.S.-born women, to levels below what demographers consider necessary to maintain the population. The &#8220;U.S. population&#8221; now grows chiefly because of open-door immigration and births to immigrant mothers.</p>
<p>Am I crazy to link female emancipation and near-equality in the workforce to all these bad results, including population collapse? Well, no—I’m only putting forward a hypothesis, and one that seems well grounded in the data. Obviously many factors contributed to the social changes that have swept across the West in the past half century or so. But that women were one of those factors seems undeniable. And the possibility that they were, and continue to be, the <em>dominant</em> factor seems worth discussing, not least because of the potential implications for the future. Yet . . . there has been no discussion. I’ve been circulating this idea for years now, in one forum and another, and it gets no traction at all. It isn’t shot down by some fact or logical disproof; it’s just ignored or dismissed without reason. No “respectable” publication will touch it. I can’t help wondering if that response is yet another reflection of women’s new cultural power.</p>
<p><span style="color: #ff0000;">published <em>6 Mar 2019</em></span></p>
</figure>
<p style="text-align: center;">**</p>
<figure class="aligncenter">
<p><em>Postscript (3/25/19): Apparently a similar theory, blaming the West&#8217;s fertility decline on feminism, has been <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2019/03/18/technology/replacement-theory.html">kicking around in &#8220;far-right&#8221; circles</a>. That probably helps explain why doors have tended to shut in my face whenever I&#8217;ve tried (over the past 7+ years) to get a version of this essay published&#8211;and I&#8217;ve been reduced to publishing pseudonymously in <a href="https://www.returnofkings.com/42976/thanks-to-progressivism-america-is-no-country-for-men">fringe publications</a> or on <a href="https://james-the-obscure.github.io/the-demise-of-guythink/">d-i-y websites</a>. In case it&#8217;s not already clear, my &#8220;great feminization&#8221; idea is mainly about cultural feminization, doesn&#8217;t have anything directly to do with the formal &#8220;feminist&#8221; movement, and doesn&#8217;t require any dire prediction about population decline/replacement. Also, though it should be <a href="https://rationalwiki.org/wiki/Genetic_fallacy">irrelevant</a>, I&#8217;m not some woman-hating incel; I&#8217;m happily married, etc. My interest in the topic of sex differences in culture and policy attitudes developed from the fact that I, a male, work in a profession that is increasingly female-dominated.<br /></em></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><em>Author’s note (Oct 2022):</em></p>
<p><em>I’d appreciate it, reader, if you would link to my essays on cultural feminization (or otherwise cite them) wherever you see this topic being discussed. I’ve been writing about “cult-fem” for more than a decade—which, as far as I know, is much longer than anyone else. Some of my essays have <a href="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/cultural-feminization-a-bibliography/">circulated widely</a></em><em> in recent years, and I’ve even placed <a href="https://americanmind.org/salvo/pink-shift/">one</a></em><em> in a moderately well-read webzine. I like to think that my contributions have helped seed what is becoming an important public discourse. Yet those contributions of mine are almost never acknowledged by the better-known opinionators who have ventured into this realm in the last year or so. Being pseudonymous and writing principally from a personal website seem to have left me in the unhappy state of being “much read but seldom cited.” (I discuss the general problem of citation in the Internet age in my short essay “<a href="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/the-tree-of-knowledge/">The Tree of Knowledge</a></em><em>.”)</em></p>
<p><em>Also, though I don’t charge a subscription to this website, or put ads on it, or even solicit donations, you could buy a copy of my e-book (see image below, linked to its Amazon page) if you’d like to support my writing.</em></p>
</figure>
</div>














]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
