<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>time travel &#8211; Thoughts of Stone</title>
	<atom:link href="/category/time-travel/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>/</link>
	<description>short essays, usually about humans</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Fri, 09 Jun 2023 23:11:48 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=6.2.2</generator>

<image>
	<url>/wp-content/uploads/2020/07/cropped-icon-32x32.jpg</url>
	<title>time travel &#8211; Thoughts of Stone</title>
	<link>/</link>
	<width>32</width>
	<height>32</height>
</image> 
	<item>
		<title>TOURISTS FROM THE FUTURE</title>
		<link>/tourists-from-the-future/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[j stone]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 09 Jun 2023 23:07:03 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[cosmology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[ideas]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[psychology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[science]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[time travel]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[UFOs]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[USA]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=805</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[An “extratemporal terrestrial” theory for (some) UFOs ____________________________ &#8220;If time travel is possible, where are the tourists from the future?&#8221; &#8212; Stephen Hawking &#160; In 1959, at an Anglican mission in the village of Boianai, in the mountainous southeastern prong of New Guinea, there occurred one of the best-known examples of what the UFO researcher &#8230; <a href="/tourists-from-the-future/" class="more-link">Continue reading<span class="screen-reader-text"> "TOURISTS FROM THE FUTURE"</span></a>]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><em>An “extratemporal terrestrial” theory for (some) UFOs</em></p>
<p><span id="more-805"></span></p>
<p style="text-align: left;">____________________________</p>
<p><em>&#8220;If time travel is possible, where are the tourists from the future?&#8221; &#8212; Stephen Hawking</em></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>In 1959, at an Anglican mission in the village of Boianai, in the mountainous southeastern prong of New Guinea, there occurred one of the best-known examples of what the UFO researcher J. Allen Hynek would later call a “Close Encounter of the Third Kind.”</p>
<p>The case involved a series of UFO sightings—by mission staff and other locals—of odd lights in the sky and a saucer-shaped craft, over a period of several weeks, culminating in a close encounter in late June. The mission head, William Gill, a 31-year-old Australian named William Gill, had more or less dismissed these sightings in a <a href="http://rowancallick.com/article-for-png-post-courier/">letter</a> written June 26 to a senior colleague based elsewhere in PNG:</p>
<p style="padding-left: 40px;">I am inclined to believe that probably many UFOs are more likely some form of electric phenomena—or perhaps something brought about by the atom bomb explosions etc.</p>
<p>Having signed himself “Doubting William,” Gill on the very next day became a UFO believer, writing to the same colleague:</p>
<p style="padding-left: 40px;">Life is strange, isn’t it? Yesterday I wrote you a letter, expressing opinions re the UFOs. Now, less than 24 hours later I have changed my views somewhat.</p>
<p style="padding-left: 40px;">Last night we at Boianai experienced about 4 hours of UFO activity, and there is no doubt whatsoever that they are handled by beings of some kind. At times it was absolutely breathtaking.</p>
<p>What Gill and his staff and parishioners saw (and more than three dozen later signed a statement affirming the truth of Gill’s account) was a disc-shaped craft that approached the village closely, and came as low as 100 meters from the ground. It had a deck on top, from which four different beings, human in appearance, observed the people on the ground.</p>
<p style="padding-left: 40px;">One figure seemed to be standing looking down at us (a group of about a dozen). I stretched my arm above my head and waved. To our surprise the figure did the same. Ananias waved both arms over his head then the two outside figures did the same.</p>
<p style="padding-left: 40px;">Ananias and myself began waving our arms and all four now seemed to wave back. There seemed to be no doubt that our movements were answered. All mission boys made audible gasps (of either joy or surprise, perhaps both).</p>
<p style="padding-left: 40px;">As dark was beginning to close in, I sent Eric Kodawara for a torch and directed a series of long dashes towards the UFO. After a minute or two of this, the UFO apparently acknowledged by making several wavering motions back and forth.</p>
<p style="padding-left: 40px;">Waving by us was repeated and this followed by more flashes of torch, then the UFO began slowly to become bigger, apparently coming in our direction. It ceased after perhaps half a minute and came no further.</p>
<p style="padding-left: 40px;">After a further two or three minutes the figures apparently lost interest in us for they disappeared ‘below deck.’ At 6.25 pm two figures re-appeared to carry on with whatever they were doing [seemingly setting up equipment on the deck] before the interruption. The blue spotlight [emitted upward at a 45-degree angle from the top of the craft] came on for a few seconds twice in succession.</p>
<p>The craft, accompanied by others in the sky nearby, came and went over several days, and eventually the sightings petered out, more or less coincident with a series of mysterious, loud explosions in the sky.</p>
<p>Gill later commented that the saucer-like object he had seen at close range “looked a perfectly normal sort of object, an earth-made object. I realised, of course, that some people might think of this as a flying saucer, but I took it to be some kind of hovercraft the Americans or even the Australians had built. The figures inside looked <em>perfectly human</em>.” [italics mine]</p>
<p><iframe title="“They waved back!” Father William B. Gill on witnessing a UFO with beings in Papua New Guinea, 1959" width="840" height="630" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/4I75neaOIGE?feature=oembed" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" allowfullscreen></iframe></p>
<p style="text-align: center;">*</p>
<p>The Boianai encounter has long been a “classic case” that UFO enthusiasts pull out to quiet the naysayers. How could one convincingly dismiss such a close and well witnessed encounter involving a university-educated priest who was on record as being skeptical about UFOs?</p>
<p>To me, though, the Boianai case serves mainly to <em>weaken</em> the idea that true UFOs (the otherwise inexplicable ones) are extraterrestrial craft. It suggests instead the moderately less woo possibility that UFOs (maybe some, maybe all) are <em>visitors from the human future</em>—the ones from the near future being more like us and having less advanced tech, the ones from the far future being relatively “alien.”</p>
<p>But let me back up. I have never been a UFO researcher or “enthusiast.” I was once a journalist, and as such, in bygone days, I did spend a small slice of my life thinking and researching and writing about UFOs. I met, among others, senior current/former government types who told me they thought it was all real—UFOs, crash retrievals, the whole nine yards—though they couldn’t get access to verify anything. One or two of them wanted <em>me</em> to dig into it.</p>
<p>I did that eventually, in a small way, with the backing of a prominent media organization (as in “yes, feel free to tell them you’re working on a story for us—and let us know if you find anything interesting.”) I spoke to former government officials and contractors (e.g., metals experts) who should have known something, if there was something to know. Whether I approached them directly or obliquely, they all gave genial and disarmingly good impressions of ignorance about anything resembling a UFO exploitation program. Eventually I ran out of leads to pursue, and went back to writing about more ordinary stuff. I felt some relief at that&#8212;the idea of a supersecret government UFO exploitation program was unsettling, and I also felt to some extent that if it existed, there were probably good reasons for its secrecy.</p>
<p>I still found the UFO literature compelling, not in its entirety of course but in key cases involving multiple independent witnesses, radar backup, etc. I retained what could be (or anyway should be) called a <em>common-sense</em> view of UFOs, namely that we’re in a big universe, we’re unlikely to be alone, and probably some UFOs are extraterrestrial in origin.</p>
<p>I also came to the conclusion, eventually, that our ability to learn about visitors from advanced ET civilizations is probably very, very limited, so that “ufology” in the long run is likely a mug’s game, whether conducted privately or with government institutions. Had I not drifted away like that, I might even have ended up being the journalist the insiders used to break that big <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2017/12/16/us/politics/pentagon-program-ufo-harry-reid.html">story</a> in the <em>New York Times</em> in 2017.</p>
<p>In any case, thanks to those insiders, and to <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2017/12/16/us/politics/pentagon-program-ufo-harry-reid.html">Kean and Blumenthal</a>—above all to the late Senator <a href="/the-incomprehensible-alien/">Harry Reid</a>—UFOs became a mainstream thing again. New government programs were created, and the panels for these included government-employed individuals who were very enthusiastic about the subject.</p>
<p>Maybe in some cases they were too enthusiastic. UFOs have always had an ability to sow weirdness and madness, and to attract the excitable and unstable. Anyway, it appears that <a href="https://thedebrief.org/intelligence-officials-say-u-s-has-retrieved-non-human-craft/">one or two UFO-panel individuals</a> heard the same story I did, about a crash/material recovery/analysis program, and in recent months have been trying to use their positions on these panels to act as “whistleblowers” and rip the lid off the whole thing.</p>
<p>Just as a parenthetical remark, I still think it would be a shame if the government had such a program, and yet couldn’t keep it a secret due to the opportunism encouraged by whistleblower laws. Good reasons to keep it a secret include:</p>
<ul>
<li style="list-style-type: none;">
<ul>
<li>It is likely to be seriously <a href="/the-incomprehensible-alien/">demoralizing</a> to people (at least slowly, at a subconscious level), ultimately with major societal effects, when they are forced to confront the inferiority of contemporary humans.</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<ul>
<li style="list-style-type: none;">
<ul>
<li>If any of the material can be exploited technologically, then it is better for the US to do that, and to keep it secret, than to “share it with the world,” including the world’s bad actors such as China and Russia.</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<ul>
<li style="list-style-type: none;">
<ul>
<li>The knowledge that the US has such material, and the possibility that the US can exploit it, might be enough to dissuade some of those bad actors from doing seriously bad things, such as using nuclear weapons. (More than two decades ago, I started but never finished writing a novel, loosely based on my journalistic experiences, in which the whole “UFO crash retrieval” story turned out to be a psy-op against the Chinese in the run-up to their planned Taiwan invasion.)</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<p>Obviously, I don’t have any respect for the claims by the “whistleblowers” (who stand to make small fortunes from book deals etc.) that they are doing humanity a favor. If their claims are revealed to be true, then I think the demoralization effect alone will become very pronounced and consequential over the years—though as for so many other <a href="/its-not-wokeness-its-women/">adverse social trends</a>, it may be hard to get people to acknowledge the cause.</p>
<p>To return to my main point: If these claims of crashed vehicles or fragments are true (and to be clear, there are <a href="https://www.theblackvault.com/casefiles/the-ufo-files-of-mussolini-fascist-ufo-files-by-roberto-pinotti/">quite</a> a <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kecksburg_UFO_incident">few</a> <a href="https://www.publishersweekly.com/9781557784490">cases</a> in the literature that include such claims), then they suggest, once again, that “alien” visitations involve a surprisingly low and error-prone level of tech. Why would advanced, star-faring ET civs, millions or billions of years ahead of us in development, send such failure-prone craft into our skies—and with fragile, flesh-and-blood pilots?! It just doesn’t make sense. Nor does it make sense that the technology left behind by these super-advanced visitors would invite the prospect of <em>reverse engineering</em> by ourselves. (Picture a family of <em>Australopithecus afarensis</em> trying to “reverse-engineer” a crashed F-35.)</p>
<p>These crash/recovery stories, along with many other cases in the lore, would make much more sense if the visitors in question were not <em>extraterrestrial</em> at all, but instead merely <em>extratemporal*</em>—from the future.</p>
<p style="text-align: center;">*</p>
<p>How would that work? According to classical physics, or even early (“Copenhagen Interpretation”) quantum physics, it couldn’t. If you were to depart in your time machine, in Hollywood time-travel fashion, and land in your own backyard the day before, greeting yourself and your wide-eyed wife and children, then you would be changing your own past, which is generally considered impossible.</p>
<p>The now-dominant Relative State Formulation (a.k.a. the Many Worlds Interpretation) of quantum theory is, in principle, more accommodating. It implies—to simplify—that reality comprises an infinitude of ever-branching universes or timelines. In other words, apart from other physical considerations, you <em>could</em> travel “backwards in time,” though the timeline on which you alighted would be distinct (possibly differentiating at precisely that moment) from your timeline of origin. This means that if you traveled a day backwards in time, the people you met in that “destination timeline,” including your “self,” would be merely different versions of those populating your departure timeline. You’d be in a “parallel universe” version of the universe you’d left, and nothing you did there would alter your original timeline—your personal “past.”</p>
<p>How you’d jump between timelines—or fly back along your own and alight somewhere, forcing the branching of a new timeline—is, of course, the hard problem here. Possibly there would be a conservation-of-energy issue, so that major amounts of energy would have to be released or subtracted with each jump. The “earsplitting explosion” reported at Boianai, and similar explosions and flashes reported in the literature, call that issue to mind. And though most reported UFOs depart by moving rapidly upward into the sky, it is conceivable—this is all extremely speculative anyway—that any necessary energy exchange takes place high in the atmosphere where it will be less noticeable, and might even be taken for bolides when they involve energy release.</p>
<p>Why would time travelers use flying machines, rather than just materialize on the ground, as in time-travel movies? Again, this is all almost absurdly speculative, but if time travel is physically possible, then it is plausible that “arriving” at coordinates corresponding to solid matter, a mountain for example, would spell instant death for the time travelers—and thus a high-atmosphere entry, in suitably equipped flying craft, would be the standard strategy.</p>
<p>The idea that at least some UFOs are not from other star systems is not itself novel. I recall a suggestion by Jacques Vallee in one of his books that some UFO occupants are, in effect, non-human visitors from another dimension. That may be true too. This is all speculation. One thing we can be sure of now, though, is that, to paraphrase Shakespeare’s Hamlet, there are more things in Heaven and Earth than are dreamt of in our science.</p>
<p style="text-align: center;">***</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>*The term <em>extratemporal</em> already has an anatomical/neurological meaning, but perhaps it will soon acquire an additional meaning: <em>from outside of our time frame</em>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
