<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>fall of the West &#8211; Thoughts of Stone</title>
	<atom:link href="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/category/fall-of-the-west/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/</link>
	<description>short essays, usually about humans</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Mon, 22 Nov 2021 00:17:01 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=5.7.4</generator>

<image>
	<url>https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2020/07/cropped-icon-32x32.jpg</url>
	<title>fall of the West &#8211; Thoughts of Stone</title>
	<link>https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/</link>
	<width>32</width>
	<height>32</height>
</image> 
	<item>
		<title>WHAT TO DO ABOUT WOKEISM</title>
		<link>https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/what-to-do-about-wokeism/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[j stone]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sat, 20 Nov 2021 23:44:06 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[fall of the West]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[USA]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[wokeism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[women]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/?p=253</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[If you must do something, do this one thing &#160; Wokeism with its inversions and distortions of normal humane thinking, and its ability to spread rapidly among susceptible minds, is a mental and cultural plague, pandemically infectious and harmful. What can we do about it? One option, of course, is to hunker down and do &#8230; <a href="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/what-to-do-about-wokeism/" class="more-link">Continue reading<span class="screen-reader-text"> "WHAT TO DO ABOUT WOKEISM"</span></a>]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><em>If you must do something, do this one thing</em></p>
<p><span id="more-253"></span></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>Wokeism with its inversions and distortions of normal humane thinking, and its ability to spread rapidly among susceptible minds, is a mental and cultural plague, pandemically infectious and harmful. What can we do about it?</p>
<p>One option, of course, is to hunker down and do nothing, in the hope that wokeism resolves on its own, as a plague usually does—becoming less extreme as it adapts better to its hosts, or staying extreme until everyone who hasn’t been driven nuts by it has developed strong defenses against it.</p>
<p>Doing nothing probably seems a plausible option to many. In the United States, the Democratic Party’s recent wholehearted embrace of wokeism seems to have made it markedly less popular among voters than it would have been otherwise. Conceivably, the party is now so dominated by this ideology in its leadership, its elite donors, its media enablers, and its city-burning activists, that it can’t change direction, and in future elections will run full-speed off an electoral cliff.</p>
<p>I’m skeptical, though, about the wisdom of doing nothing. When a new and dangerous disease arises, the proper response is to look for its cause and then find ways to block or otherwise neutralize that cause. Wokeism also strikes me as being too robust and malignant to leave alone.</p>
<p>Wokeism is robust because, for all its absurdity as an ideology (at least, to some of us who oppose it), it offers material benefits to many people, especially those who are not what we might call Legacy Americans. These people, these non-Legacy-Americans, occupy, for obvious reasons, an increasing share of the American electorate. Even when wokeism offends them, for example by imposing “critical race theory” (CRT) or wokeist sexual degeneracy on their children in school, they recognize this mindset as a force that promotes their advancement over Legacy Americans—and probably for many of them that “pro” is more important than the “cons.” Did you think the recent GOP victory in the Virginia governor’s race spelled the end of wokeism? It didn’t—the margin of victory was very thin. The wokeists may need only to dial down the ferocity of their attack on Legacy America to start winning again.</p>
<p>There is also the problem of <a href="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/the-critical-mass-problem/">women’s susceptibility to wokeism</a>—especially those women who help run major US industries and institutions, including media, government, science, medicine, law, and education, and thus have an outsized impact on the culture. This inter-institutional gynocracy is arguably the true “Deep State”—maybe we should call it the Deep Pink State—and isn’t going away any time soon, given that the current US political and legal system offers no formal or informal mechanism for getting rid of it. Conservative white males <em>can</em> be gotten rid of by the informal Inquisitional network known as Cancel Culture; but white females are still mostly untouchable, especially if they are woke—they are the Cancellers, not the cancelled.</p>
<p>Even if its membership cannot be uprooted, can the Deep Pink State be somehow controlled? For example, at present, the legislatures of various conservative-leaning states are passing laws banning CRT, 1619 Project nonsense, or other specific elements of wokeism from classrooms or state and local government offices. Can this work?</p>
<p>Well, think about it. In places where the education system, the administrative structures of government, corporate HR departments, etc.  are substantially infiltrated by the women—especially single women—that make up wokeism’s religious hard core, isn’t it likely that any legislated “ban” of wokeism is going to be effectively nullified by these institutionally embedded believers? It’s pretty easy to imagine them continuing to teach, preach, propagandize, evangelize, and catechize, using the same wokeist gospels but now with different labels—or with those labels but with more stealth and indirection. It’s also easy to imagine these wokeistas banding together with even more solidarity, seeing themselves, of course, as history’s heroines, freedom fighters, eager martyrs for the glorious cause. There will be no end to the drama.</p>
<p>So, if “banning CRT” or other elements of wokeism is unlikely to work as intended, and if the average soft-hearted American recoils in horror from the idea of more direct and definitive measures, e.g., banning wokeists from culturally influential professions, or even exiling them to hopelessly wokeified countries such as Canada, what is there to be done?</p>
<p><strong>Try Just This One Thing</strong></p>
<p>I’ve proposed in a long series of essays (e.g., <a href="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/the-great-feminization/">here</a> and <a href="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/the-day-the-logic-died/">here</a>) that the spread of wokeism and many other striking cultural shifts of recent decades is due largely to the new and unprecedented cultural and political power of women. Put simply, this putative “pink shift” in Western societies has resulted from the essentially maternal mindset of women being brought out of its traditional domain of the home into the wider world of public affairs, a realm for which it was not adapted by biological/cultural evolution.</p>
<p>In other words, women’s maternal instincts—and I would guess that the instincts of single and/or empty-nest women are especially ungrounded or unhinged in this sense—are now at work in cultural and policy realms and bias women towards what are often faulty solutions. These include the sentimental encouragement of mass-immigration, overgenerous welfare, and discrimination in favor of the “traditionally disadvantaged,” as well as aversions to freedom of speech, free scientific inquiry, and due process of law. While such policies and attitudes wouldn’t necessarily be problematic in a home setting, I think are bound to be ruinous at the level of public policy.</p>
<p>As I’ve also written, one of the most striking things about this “great feminization” is the effective suppression of mentions of it in the mainstream media. I suspect that this is part of the whole feminization process. In other words, the female editors who now gatekeep mainstream cultural information from Hollywood to Madison Ave. and toe the women-are-oppressed feminist line, aren’t about to allow the portrayal of themselves as having real political and cultural power&#8212;let alone as having used that power to wreck the civilization that empowered them.</p>
<p>For their part, male writers and editors, having seen too many of their brethren thrown on the breadlines already, generally don’t want to cross their female colleagues by writing or publishing something that could draw the label “misogynist screed” and get them sent to the stake. Remember NYT science writer <a href="https://www.thewrap.com/ny-times-newsroom-in-chaos-over-departures-fears-of-cancel-culture/">Donald McNeil Jr.</a>? How about NYT editor <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2020/06/07/business/media/james-bennet-resigns-nytimes-op-ed.html">James Bennett</a>? Every man in Western MSM journalism knows that he could be next, and for the airiest of reasons.</p>
<p>I should add that, having tried and failed to get even very softened versions of my hypothesis published in many conservative venues, I have glimpsed a similar dynamic—I think partly rooted in worries over losing female subscribers and contributors—that serves to suppress this idea even on the right.</p>
<p>On the other hand, we still have an Internet, on which ideas still circulate relatively widely and freely, including ideas rejected by the MSM—and things that get big on the Internet usually make their way into the MSM eventually. The “great feminization” idea hasn’t quite made it to the big time yet, but thanks to some popular <a href="https://marginalrevolution.com/marginalrevolution/2021/10/wednesday-assorted-links-316.html">linkers</a>, <a href="https://americanmind.org/salvo/pink-shift/"><em>The American Mind</em></a>, and some behind-the-scenes assistance from other (female as well as male) writers, it has been getting many tens of thousands of views, including by some potentially very influential people.</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" class="size-full wp-image-266 aligncenter" src="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2021/11/senate-1.jpg" alt="" width="491" height="94" srcset="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2021/11/senate-1.jpg 491w, https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2021/11/senate-1-300x57.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 491px) 85vw, 491px" /></p>
<p>Anyhow, what I suggest is that people can combat wokeism simply by encouraging the circulation and discussion, on the Internet or wherever else they can, of this hypothesis that wokeism and related cultural shifts are only the downstream effects of cultural/elite feminization&#8212;i.e., of a maternal mindset that is dangerously out of its depth. If, having that hypothesis to guide them, people start to see supporting examples every day and become convinced of the peril to their civilization—then wokeism will be undermined, and I think that at least in its most excessive forms it ultimately must collapse.</p>
<p><em>Collapse</em> is one metaphor, although <em>melt</em>—from the dissolving effects of better knowledge—may be more apt.</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" class="size-full wp-image-256 aligncenter" src="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2021/11/melting.jpg" alt="" width="631" height="486" srcset="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2021/11/melting.jpg 631w, https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2021/11/melting-300x231.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 709px) 85vw, (max-width: 909px) 67vw, (max-width: 984px) 61vw, (max-width: 1362px) 45vw, 600px" /></p>
<p><em>To what end?</em> the wokeists cry! Do we want to silence women? Do we want to declare them unfit for public life, turning the clock back 200 years and confining them to the home?</p>
<p>Well, no—anyway <em>I</em> don’t want that. I think there is room for some rollback of women’s employment in very important professions, such as the military and police, in which men have certain innate advantages and women are apt to cause unhelpful distraction by their presence. But on the whole I think the solution to the “pink shift” problem is to limit the damage that <em>any</em> demographic group can do when it is captured by some infectious ideology to which it is especially susceptible.</p>
<p>In other words, I think the solution is broadly to limit the power of government, corporations, media, etc. to suppress or to alter the essentials of a sustainable and relatively liberal Western civilization, including the traditional virtues, structures and drives relating to family formation, free-ish markets, due process of law, and free scientific inquiry. No one has benefited more from this liberal civilization than women! And perhaps as women look around at all the burning, looting, anarchy and madness that wokeism promotes, they may start to agree&#8212;like the many female refugees from the similar excesses of the 1960s&#8212;that in a tough world where women are still the weaker sex, wokeism ultimately isn&#8217;t going to be good for them.</p>
<p style="text-align: center;">***</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>WHY YOU CAN’T HAVE NICE THINGS</title>
		<link>https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/why-you-cant-have-nice-things/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[j stone]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 01 Sep 2021 23:48:19 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[ethnicity]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[fall of the West]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[immigration]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[revolution]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[USA]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/?p=240</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[You don’t want them badly enough &#160; You want your own decent-sized, reasonably priced house, with a yard big enough for the kids to play, and a bit of space at the back for a garden, or maybe even a pool. You want a neighborhood where the houses are built in a pretty vernacular style, &#8230; <a href="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/why-you-cant-have-nice-things/" class="more-link">Continue reading<span class="screen-reader-text"> "WHY YOU CAN’T HAVE NICE THINGS"</span></a>]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><em>You don’t want them badly enough</em></p>
<p><span id="more-240"></span></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>You want your own decent-sized, reasonably priced house, with a yard big enough for the kids to play, and a bit of space at the back for a garden, or maybe even a pool. You want a neighborhood where the houses are built in a pretty vernacular style, not too close together, and there are sidewalks and lots of trees, and good schools and shops and offices and parks are just a short distance, perhaps even biking or walking distance, away.</p>
<p>You want your neighborhood to be inherently safe—the kind of place where people leave their doors unlocked at night and nothing bad happens. That means you want to be able to trust your neighbors. More than that, you want to have a sense of community and shared identity and culture with them. That in turn means you want them, the vast majority of them anyway, to share at least broadly your own deep roots in the USA and deeper roots in the Old World. You want that sense of shared roots, shared upbringing, shared values and goals, as a reminder and an encouragement, if only a subconscious one, of your collective enterprise as resident citizens, stewards of your children’s future—your nation’s future.</p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><img loading="lazy" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-243" src="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2021/09/6a0d41ae7097f0ae8339073063c4ae87cf6f33e2.jpg" alt="" width="475" height="600" srcset="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2021/09/6a0d41ae7097f0ae8339073063c4ae87cf6f33e2.jpg 475w, https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2021/09/6a0d41ae7097f0ae8339073063c4ae87cf6f33e2-238x300.jpg 238w" sizes="(max-width: 475px) 85vw, 475px" /></p>
<p>You want smaller, less burdensome government at all levels, and having shared roots and a shared culture would mean that you and your neighbors, and the wider community, could safely have a smaller government—could safely dispense with the Leviathan state that is required to keep a semblance of order in diversity-dogma countries.</p>
<p>Your policing needs, for example, might be very modest, on the order of what small American towns used to have in the 1950s. For welfare, you in your tightly knit communities would be able to find most solutions from families, churches, and philanthropists, rather than government bureaucracies. You would not encourage, or even tolerate, chronic welfare dependency among those capable of earning for themselves. Smaller government would in turn mean lower and perhaps greatly simplified taxation, reducing the cost of living and of running businesses, and in general removing considerable stress and uncertainty from economic life.</p>
<p>You want executive branches of government that are not only smaller in general but also more tightly focused on important things that cannot be done effectively through private means. Similarly, you want legislative systems at all levels, federal on down, that are much more limited in the changes they can make to the laws and social structures—systems that can therefore easily withstand the harmful <a href="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/the-critical-mass-problem/">thought-contagions</a> that now and then sweep the populace, and can protect important traditions that are necessary for the health of society. You might well favor, for example, a federal congress or parliament that meets for only a few months every year, as the first USA Congress did in 1789.</p>
<p>In keeping with the same goal, you want a more limited and more inherently conservative electorate: citizens of relatively mature age with deep roots in the country, perhaps also with property and children enough to qualify them as having “skin in the game.”</p>
<p>You want neither rightist-socialism (fascism) nor leftist-socialism (communism). You want a traditional, pro-family, moderately pro-business culture that builds up and celebrates Western civilization instead of constantly and acidly trying to dissolve it. In other words, while you want the ordinary, traditional Western freedom to “pursue happiness” in your own way by building a business or professional career, creating wealth for your descendants, etc. you also recognize the need to develop communal spirit, including that high-level communal spirit we call nationalism, through pursuits that are not rooted in mere self-interest. So you would favor, among other measures, some form of national service for young men and women—perhaps two years of military training and service for the former, and two years in non-military service (e.g., charity hospitals, elder care, national parks) for the latter.</p>
<p>On the whole you want bold and imaginative policies and initiatives that retain or reinstate the best of your civilization’s traditions, while also realizing the best possibilities thrown up by rapid technological advances. Should you be building more highways—to take but one example—when flying cars are already flitting about on the horizon? Should you be importing cheap foreign labor when you could automate instead? Should you be investing billions in vast solar- and wind-power farms if fusion-power is just around the corner?</p>
<p>I could go on and on with my own idiosyncratic desiderata: I want medieval-style walled towns in a re-wilded continent where the buffalo, and maybe their indigenous hunters, can once again roam, even as Jetson-style flying cars pepper the airspace. I want education achievement and assessment to be centered on objective standardized tests, not on subjective grades at subjectively ranked and usually overpriced schools. I want insurance mostly banned in the healthcare industry, to <a href="https://www.theatlantic.com/magazine/archive/2009/09/how-american-health-care-killed-my-father/307617/">let the free market do its thing</a> in this very important, yet very broken, realm of American life. I want the decadent, stupid, dangerous American elites—the political class, their media camp-followers, and Big Business execs, who are effectively one of the greatest gangs of villains in human history considering the civilizational damage they’ve done—to be cast down and punished in the most exemplary ways.</p>
<p>My main point here, though, is just the simple one that Americans, while they have lots of nice things and a wide range of choices when it comes to goods, services, careers, and even the sexual/mating marketplace, cannot have nice things—and are in fact afflicted with a growing helplessness and a sense of creeping dystopia—when it comes to their politics, government, and culture. Their politico-cultural system feels hopelessly broken, much in the way that a family you can’t choose can feel broken. It isn’t always much better in other countries, but the contrast in the USA between its potential and its outlook, between the traditional virtues that built it and the perverse, corrosive mindset of its current managerial class, is starker than in any other country with which I’m familiar.</p>
<p><strong>Elites, Population Expansion, and Diversity</strong></p>
<p>This American managerial or “elite” class, now heavily feminized and febrile with wokeism, acts with delusional, totalist conviction in some areas, and with cynicism in others—but the net impact is almost always to benefit itself, in terms of money and power, while making things worse for everyone else.</p>
<p>Safe neighborhoods, good schools, and social harmony? Can’t have those—not if the elites are to succeed in their grand project of assembling a perma-rule electoral coalition from white-loathing nonwhites and self-loathing whites.</p>
<p>Nicely designed, nicely integrated residential and commercial areas in our towns? Oh no! That would disrupt the standard business models of developers and other Big Business types, on whose donations the ruling elites depend.</p>
<p>Sensible healthcare system? Certainly not! For that would benefit mainstream Legacy Americans, who tend to vote for the Deplorable Party, while Elite Party voters would lose their free healthcare and the elites would have to scramble to find another way to own their votes. Plus of course, Big Pharma and Big Healthcare, those esteemed members of the elite (and key donors to the Elite Party), have a very good thing going under the current system—they can charge ludicrously high prices for most of their goods and services without fear of competition.</p>
<p>Just in general, of course—ignoring the distorting role of elites—the chances that you as a citizen will get the policies you want in a democracy have much to do with the size and diversity of the electorate. The greater that size and diversity, the greater the range of things that electorate will want—and thus the chance the resulting USA corresponds to <em>your</em> vision, rather than, say, some African-American’s or Indian-American’s or Chinese-American’s, gets ever smaller. The reader may have noticed the resemblance of the USA I described at the top of this essay, a USA with affordable houses, safer neighborhoods and better schools, to the far smaller and far less diverse USA of the 1960s and 70s. In any case, deliberately enlarging and diversifying your electorate through the mass importation of ethnically and culturally distant peoples seems bound to cause broader “why can’t I have what I want” dissatisfaction with the democratic system, and presumably past a certain point will trigger a shift to authoritarianism and/or ethnic cleansing—the only uncertainty being: who ends up on top?</p>
<p>Maybe (as an expatriate) I don’t have enough contact with other Americans who reside in the US. But even in the news and on Twitter I seldom see my countrymen discussing seriously how their system could be reworked so that they can avoid this bad fate, and can recover the possibility of having good choices in politics, or at any rate can have some of the nice things that better government would bring.</p>
<p>That reticence may be due in part to the difficulty many Americans have in letting go of their Greatest Country of All Time mythology, and all the flag-waving and Constitution-worshipping that goes with it. The USA must have contained very basic, very deep flaws if, after a run of only about 70 years as a true Superpower—combining wealth, reach, and might as no other country ever has—it is already falling apart. It might at first have seemed well designed by its vaunted Founders, but clearly its current crop of elites has learned to game its systems for their own selfish, nation-destroying ends. From such obvious conclusions, though, conservative Americans tend to look away. They seem to prefer distracting themselves with florid <a href="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/the-american-way-of-submission/">conspiracy theories</a>, often while retaining a delusional faith in the fundamentals of the existing USA—a distinctly American faith that says, like the narrator at the end of <em>Gatsby</em>, “no matter—tomorrow we will run faster, stretch out our arms farther. . .”</p>
<p>Among the Americans who are, like me, less optimistic about the country’s fate, there also seems to be a pervasive fear of talking openly about the measures that would be necessary to fix the situation—measures that could include the reversal of much of the past half-century’s immigration flow, the creation of a mostly <a href="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/the-other-n-word/">autonomous homeland</a> for African Americans, the dramatic narrowing of the voting franchise, extensive government regulation of media/cultural content, and a likely interval of authoritarian government during the transition from old USA to new. Even Americans whose vast wealth could never be removed by social cancellation shy from such notions—such realism, I would call it—and talk instead about making grand new worlds somewhere else, e.g., Thiel’s sea-steading and Musk’s Mars-colonization.</p>
<p>There has been some talk, mostly still on the cultural margins and well outside the Overton Window, of splitting the existing USA into two new countries, red and blue—similar to what might have happened peacefully in 1861. To me, that would fix things a little but not nearly enough. I would imagine the resulting red-USA (led by someone like Ron DeSantis or Tucker Carlson) to have only more muted versions of the same set of problems, the same dystopian trends, stemming from the same false premises that have been drummed into Americans for generations.</p>
<p>In principle, if the aim is to give Americans a wide range of choices so that more of them can live in a political culture that suits them, it would be better to split old-USA into dozens of sovereign micro-states (not necessarily corresponding to existing states), each set up to provide a relatively static demographic mix, governmental and political structure, and culture. Another great advantage of this approach is that it would amount to a vast ongoing experiment, continually teaching Americans and the wider world about the comparative desirability and sustainability of different arrangements. It would also, so to speak, up the ante for those who claim that modern Western countries should be a marketplace of contractual nations (not ethno-nations) for the peoples of the world—it would say: yes, let’s make it a real marketplace with real choices, including conservative, pro-family homelands for legacy Americans.</p>
<p>The big disadvantage of the micro-state idea, of course, is that such states are inherently weak and probably could not survive for long in a world where Great Power hegemons like China and Russia are constantly seeking to conquer and expand. Even wokeism and its variants—like so many American faiths before them—are hegemonic creeds, jealous gods bent on conquest.</p>
<p>More generally, Americans today seem disinclined and ill-equipped to think and act to the depth necessary to bring about such rational solutions. Perhaps there aren’t enough recent examples with which Americans can identify—in contrast to 1861 when proponents of secession readily cited the logic of the original American Revolution in justifying their cause. There also seems to be a certain intellectual inertia left over from the Union’s victory in the Civil War. Even the late Antonin Scalia <a href="https://www.politico.com/blogs/ben-smith/2010/02/scalia-no-to-secession-025119">wrote</a>: “If there was any constitutional issue resolved by the Civil War, it is that there is no right to secede.” But of course the right of self-government should be considered an innate and “inalienable” right, not established in or modifiable by any formal agreement—just as the inalienable right of personal liberty should prevent one from contracting legally to be a slave.</p>
<p>In any case, my overall impression (and I think <a href="https://dailyvoice.com/new-york/whiteplains/politics/new-poll-reveals-percentages-of-americans-who-want-to-secede-by-region/812724/">polls</a> generally back this) is that most Americans now would reject the idea even of a simple red/blue split—I guess mostly because of that mental inertia and the thought of the inconvenience. In other words, Americans for now, though they might want a nicer country, just haven’t reached the point where they collectively want it badly enough to make it happen.</p>
<p style="text-align: center;">***</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>THE &#8216;CRITICAL MASS&#8217; PROBLEM</title>
		<link>https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/the-critical-mass-problem/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[j stone]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 03 Jun 2021 02:19:28 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[fall of the West]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[women]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/?p=222</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[What if Western societies are now inherently unstable? &#160; There have been slow social changes over the past century, but there have been fast ones too. A recent one, the year-old outbreak of extreme wokeness called the Great Awokening, has spread with wildfire velocity through US and even foreign institutions, raising the basic question: why &#8230; <a href="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/the-critical-mass-problem/" class="more-link">Continue reading<span class="screen-reader-text"> "THE &#8216;CRITICAL MASS&#8217; PROBLEM"</span></a>]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><em>What if Western societies are now inherently unstable?</em></p>
<p><span id="more-222"></span></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>There have been slow social changes over the past century, but there have been fast ones too. A recent one, the year-old outbreak of extreme wokeness called the Great Awokening, has spread with wildfire velocity through US and even foreign institutions, raising the basic question: why did this happen?</p>
<p>Part of the answer is in the term itself. The Great Awakenings were several distinct episodes of intense religious fervor, chiefly in North America, in the 1700s and 1800s, and arguably in the 1960s-80s. They were social contagions, and spread, like viruses, within populations that had for various social and economic reasons been made peculiarly vulnerable to them. They included mass gatherings to hear highly charismatic—one might say hypnotic—preachers, and mass conversions, amid fainting and weeping, to less hierarchical, more personal and emotional forms of Christianity. Contagions of guilt over sinfulness were followed by outbreaks of ecstasy over salvation. But while the Awakenings were, most vividly, mass psychosocial disturbances, they also led to durable changes, in affected Christian churches, in theology and ordinary practice.</p>
<p>The Great Awokening has shown at least a superficial resemblance to its Christian forbears, in its weepy mass gatherings, its heavy inculcations of guilt, its pressure to embrace radically new ways of thinking—whiteness as a sin—and in its swift march through the media and other important institutions. Above all it looks like a social contagion.</p>
<p>Some factors that made America susceptible to this contagion are plain enough. At the time the Great Awokening started there was a deadly pandemic of a real virus, and, for many, an associated, highly stressful interruption of normal life. There were also unnerving riots, lootings, and other social disturbances in US cities, due to some unhappy police/perp encounters that were amplified by activists and politicians in the run-up to a fateful presidential election. As for the themes of the Great Awokening, they were not really new—most had been around since the 1960s, usually on the radical fringes. In general, white American guilt and perplexity over the chronic low status of the average black American has been an unassuageable stressor on the country from the time of slavery.</p>
<p>But I think there is another big piece in this puzzle of why the wokeist gospel, with its hatred of white American heroes and hagiologies of black ne&#8217;er-do-wells, ripped so easily and swiftly through the country and its key institutions, including corporations, and even now mostly retains all these conquests.</p>
<p>As readers of previous essays of mine (especially <a href="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/the-great-feminization/">this</a>, <a href="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/the-day-the-logic-died/">this</a>, <a href="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/girl-power/">this</a>, and <a href="https://americanmind.org/salvo/pink-shift/">this</a>) may have guessed already, this missing piece is the involvement of women—women as ordinary citizens, and as members of affected institutions. And although I’ve touched on this theme in these previous essays, I’m coming at it here from a slightly different, cultural dynamics angle.</p>
<p><strong>A Feminine Susceptibility</strong></p>
<p>If history has taught us anything about social contagions, it is that women, on average, are more susceptible to them than men. Women have been the key instigators and transmitters of all the most famous mass-hysterias, including the many medieval and early modern convent hysterias and witch-hunts, but also all the modern, medicalized mass-hysterias&#8211;among them Charcot’s neuroses (which kicked off modern psychiatry), multiple personality disorder and other “recovered memory” syndromes, the ongoing child gender dysphoria hysteria, and ordinary schoolyard hysterias of the “children overcome by mysterious gas leak” type. This relative susceptibility to emotional contagion is one of those feminine traits that is sort of obvious anecdotally, and occasionally is given weight by an experimental psychology study, though the idea of it runs against the prevailing pro-feminine orthodoxy in media and academia, so it isn’t mentioned much.</p>
<p>Why are women this way? To me the likeliest, if necessarily tentative, explanation is that the two sexes, with their distinct traditional roles, have evolved distinct sets of psychological leanings and behaviors, and the typical feminine set of behaviors includes a superior emotional sensitivity and sociability as a broad adaptation that facilitates, e.g., child-rearing. The fact that this “enhanced connectedness” makes women more susceptible to harmful social contagions may have been an acceptable side-effect in times when women were mostly restricted to home and hearth. Women’s <a href="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/girl-power/">greater ability to align among themselves</a> may even have ended up as part of an adaptive female defense mechanism against the physically stronger sex.</p>
<p>If we consider just this trait, or trait-set, and ask what its social impact should have been as women entered public life <em>en masse</em> over the past half-century or so, I think we end up making sense of a lot of otherwise puzzling social phenomena. In regard to the Great Awokening, we can hypothesize at least that this has been primarily a contagion among women, especially young women with high feminine energies that are not absorbed by husbands and children and need some outlet.</p>
<p>I would suggest too that the Great Awokening’s transformation of big institutions reflects not only the general fear of personal cancellation within these institutions but also the “critical mass” of susceptible women who work in them. In other words, for example, a male executive at a big corporation might only pay lip service to wokeism to preserve his status, while a female executive would be more likely to enforce it from conviction.</p>
<p>As Orwell once said through his <em>1984</em> character Winston Smith:</p>
<p style="padding-left: 40px;">It was always the women, and above all the young ones, who were the most bigoted adherents of the Party, the swallowers of slogans, the amateur spies and nosers-out of unorthodoxy.</p>
<p>I don&#8217;t think that women are equally susceptible to any orthodoxy&#8212;I don&#8217;t expect them to spawn variants of Nazism, or, say, jihadist Islamic ideology. But I think there is a broad range of stuff they go for that comports with the feminine, weaker-sex, caregiving mindset and includes themes of trauma, the loss of agency, the need for inclusivity, and protection from environmental threats. Wokeism ticks most of those boxes, but may also be appealing to women, at least subconsciously, because it is very much an anti-male ideology&#8211;so that women have inherently less to fear from it, and may even find it a useful tool for dislodging men, especially white men, who somehow stand in their way.</p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><img loading="lazy" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-224" src="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2021/06/ursula-1.jpg" alt="" width="700" height="612" srcset="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2021/06/ursula-1.jpg 700w, https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2021/06/ursula-1-300x262.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 709px) 85vw, (max-width: 909px) 67vw, (max-width: 984px) 61vw, (max-width: 1362px) 45vw, 600px" /></p>
<p><strong>Silent but Deadly</strong></p>
<p>Like all the other aspects of women’s cultural ascendancy in the West, this one seems to lie there in plain sight while remaining officially unmentionable. How often do we hear of petitions against insufficiently woke persons, usually white males, by students at a university, or reporters at a newspaper, or employees at some publishing house, in which the feminine sentiment of the complaint (“we feel unsafe”) is unmistakable, and yet no one—in a media increasingly controlled by women—mentions the striking preponderance of females among the petitioners? How often do we see images in the media of Great Awokening mass gatherings whose participants are mostly female though there is nothing in the caption or the story text to explain or even acknowledge that interesting fact? It would seem that a big part of female power, even of the modern, feminist, you-go-girl variety, still comes from feigning powerlessness.</p>
<p>In any case, if the entry of women into public life over the past few decades has now reached a “critical mass” that makes Western institutions and culture highly susceptible to runaway ideological fevers and contagions, then the West obviously has a much bigger problem than wokeness itself.</p>
<p>As noted, I’m assuming that these contagions will be broadly limited to those whose themes are consonant with female sensibilities. But, as the experience so far with wokeism suggests—and the quote from Orwell suggests too—female sensibilities may be no less likely than male sensibilities to support the establishment of totalitarian or otherwise inhumane regimes.</p>
<p>Arguably an even worse outcome is to have no regime at all—to have the chaos of anarchy. Is it far-fetched to suggest that anarchy is where the ascendancy of women is taking the West? The feminized elites of Western, especially Anglosphere, countries now promote influxes of ethnically distant foreigners, and official favoritism towards these newcomers, while preaching hatred and suppression of white legacy populations. Propaganda along these lines has become deafening over the past two decades, and it&#8217;s now hard to imagine that it could ever be reversed fully. But the long-term outcome of demeaning and replacing a dominant legacy population with a mix of very different, often half-civilized foreigners is almost by definition going to be a civilizational collapse. Another, perhaps mostly Asian-flavored civilization may arise from those ruins, but there is no guarantee that it will be better&#8212;in any sense&#8212;than the Western civilization that is now swiftly fading.</p>
<p>I want to emphasize that I don’t wish to demean women in putting forward this set of suggestions. Many women are more resistant to the wokeism nonsense than the average male—and, as females, have better insight into the quirks of the female mindset.</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-12" src="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2020/07/coulter-twitr.jpg" alt="" width="578" height="164" srcset="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2020/07/coulter-twitr.jpg 578w, https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2020/07/coulter-twitr-300x85.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 578px) 85vw, 578px" /></p>
<p>But the key idea here is that there is a difference between the <em>average</em> female and <em>average</em> male. In other words, for traits relating to social contagion susceptibility, men and women can be scored along two bell curves which mostly overlap, though they have different means. That difference in the means makes a big difference on its own. In addition, those women out on the more “extreme feminine” tail of the female curve—who I expect are mostly young, single, fertile, with passion and compassion to burn—may have an outsized impact through their particularly strong ability to align emotionally and transmit contagions.</p>
<p>I think this sex difference is also a good example of a relatively subtle average difference measured at the individual level adding up to a striking difference in collective behavior and culture.</p>
<p>All that said, I am not dogmatic about any of this. I’m broadly aware that we as modern humans, with our fixation on the individual, know too little about how our individual traits relate to the shapes and dynamics of our societies. Essentially, we don’t know the recipe for making civilizations that are good but also <em>sustainable</em>. Again and again, across history, we are born to civilizational riches and then ignorantly squander them.</p>
<p style="text-align: center;">***</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>THE OTHER N-WORD</title>
		<link>https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/the-other-n-word/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[j stone]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 14 May 2021 02:23:55 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[blacks]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[ethnicity]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[fall of the West]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[human ecology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[USA]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/?p=212</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Who&#8217;s afraid of black nationalism? &#160; America’s leftist elites regard white American nationalism as their principal ideological adversary. But they have another adversary that is often overlooked: black American nationalism. Black American nationalism is very easy to overlook, here in the third decade of the new millennium. Although it has had its day in the &#8230; <a href="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/the-other-n-word/" class="more-link">Continue reading<span class="screen-reader-text"> "THE OTHER N-WORD"</span></a>]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><em>Who&#8217;s afraid of black nationalism?</em></p>
<p><span id="more-212"></span></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>America’s leftist elites regard white American nationalism as their principal ideological adversary. But they have another adversary that is often overlooked: <em>black</em> American nationalism.</p>
<p>Black American nationalism is very easy to overlook, here in the third decade of the new millennium. Although it has had its day in the sun—even Lincoln was in favor of it, once upon a time—its best-known proponent since the Civil Rights Era, Malcolm X, died 56 years ago, at the hands of rival black nationalists, and the movement seems to have gone only downhill since. Already by the mid 1970s Richard Pryor was mocking the “Back to Africa Movement” in his stand-up routines. Black American nationalism also has been tainted (or so one is supposed to think) by the moral support it has occasionally received from overtly white supremacist organizations. In any case, although there must still be millions of black Americans of the nationalist persuasion out there, their movement has by now been relegated to the fringes—the black nationalists who make the news these days seem mostly <a href="https://www.nbcdfw.com/news/local/dallas-shooting-suspect-was-leader-in-black-nationalist-group/19317/">violent, deranged</a> and disorganized.</p>
<p>By contrast, black American activism that is <em>not</em> nationalist seems to have been doing pretty well lately, judging by the recent wildfire contagions of enthusiasm for BLM, the 1619 Project, the George Floyd hagiology, and Critical Race Theory. Last year, leading Democrats actually donned kente cloth stoles and bent a knee on the US Capitol’s marble floor during the announcement of police reform legislation, as if genuflecting to a Justifiably Angry Black God.</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" class="size-full wp-image-214 aligncenter" src="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2021/05/kente.jpg" alt="" width="700" height="467" srcset="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2021/05/kente.jpg 700w, https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2021/05/kente-300x200.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 709px) 85vw, (max-width: 909px) 67vw, (max-width: 984px) 61vw, (max-width: 1362px) 45vw, 600px" /></p>
<p>Non-nationalist black activists also seem to have been doing pretty well for themselves personally. Consider <a href="https://www.the-sun.com/news/2675013/na-patrisse-khan-cullors-houses/">Patrisse Khan-Cullors</a>, a co-founder of BLM, whose income as an activist has enabled her recently to purchase several homes collectively worth several millions of dollars. Or Nikole Hannah-Jones, of the 1619 Project, with her consulting, if that’s what one should call it, for <a href="https://www.theamericanconservative.com/dreher/the-woke-capitalism-grift-shell-oil-nikole-hannah-jones-live-not-by-lies/">Shell</a> and other large corporations, and her remarkable habit of <a href="https://spectator.us/life/1619-project-nikole-hannah-jones-products/">promoting products</a> in interviews and speeches. Or the so-called family of George Floyd, with their $27 million <a href="https://www.npr.org/2021/03/13/976785212/minneapolis-agrees-to-pay-27-million-to-family-of-george-floyd">payout</a> from the city of Minneapolis. Or Stacey Abrams with <a href="https://www.hollywoodreporter.com/tv/tv-news/nbc-stacey-abrams-while-justice-sleeps-1234951195/">her novel and its lucrative adaptation for TV</a>. Or Ta-Nehisi Coates with his <a href="https://ta-nehisicoates.com/graphic-novels/">comic books</a> and <a href="https://www.latimes.com/entertainment-arts/story/2021-02-26/ta-nehisi-coates-writing-the-script-for-next-superman-movie">film scripts</a>. Or reparations-demander Ibram X. Kendi with the <a href="https://reason.com/2020/08/20/jack-dorsey-ibram-x-kendi-twitter-ceo-racism-center/">miraculous largesse</a> he attracts from wealthy whites.</p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><img loading="lazy" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-69" src="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2020/10/huckster.png" alt="" width="385" height="376" srcset="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2020/10/huckster.png 385w, https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2020/10/huckster-300x293.png 300w" sizes="(max-width: 385px) 85vw, 385px" /></p>
<p>Now, granted, some of this flow of wealth to activists could be framed as prudent purchases of insurance by white-run organizations—inoculations against the cooties of “racism” and “white supremacy” that can afflict, and cancel, <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2020/06/09/books/poetry-foundation-black-lives-matter.html">any</a> <a href="https://www.usatoday.com/story/entertainment/tv/2021/05/10/golden-globes-2022-ceremony-dropped-nbc-after-hfpa-scandal/5026394001/">prominent organization</a> if it’s not careful.</p>
<p>But even moreso I think this wealth transfer reflects elites’ desire to <em>reward and incentivize those who tamely do their bidding</em>.</p>
<p>Malcolm X viewed elite-approved “black leaders” in his day with similar skepticism. He famously called Martin Luther King Jr. a chump and a stooge of white liberals for promoting the idea of peaceful integration within white America—an idea that to him was an empty promise, aimed as always at perpetuating white control of blacks.</p>
<p>I think he was basically right about that. And if contemporary America’s leftist elites have banished black nationalists to the fringes, and have instead anointed a bunch of racial-equity grifters as the approved “leaders” of black America, then surely black nationalism is something that Legacy Americans should support as energetically as they can.</p>
<p>I’m not just being enemy-of-my-enemy tribalistic here. I’m trying to be coldly logical. The leftist elites of the US, which is to say the leaders of the Democratic Party and their allies and henchwomen in academia, media, entertainment, big business, etc., <em>need</em> to keep American blacks in the country and on their side for the most basic electoral reasons. They cannot abide a black separatism that would lead to a new, black nationalist political party or—the elites’ ultimate nightmare—a substantial black exodus from the US to a new homeland, even an internal one. Obviously, such an exodus would, among its many consequences, fatally weaken those leftist elites, in part by removing most of the radioactive core that powers their racial-factionalist ideology.</p>
<p>There is also a strong moral argument here. African-Americans of today are descendants of West Africans who were brought to the New World against their will. Theirs is a population that was literally enslaved for a long time, and then was oppressed for a long time after that. Even as their oppression has eased it has become clear that they are, for the most part, trapped in a world not of their making. In other words, for all this time they have been denied the basic rights of ethnic nationhood and self-determination that most peoples around the world have traditionally enjoyed. The fact that European-derived whites, with their hyperverbal brains and their sentimental, empire-adapted ideology, have overwritten ancient wisdom about the primacy of ethnic nationhood and self-determination, and no longer consider it important, is—American blacks might say, with some heat—not their problem.</p>
<p>It <em>shouldn’t</em> be their problem, anyway. And yet it is. And it’s not just their problem, is it? This idea that nations should be substantially multi-racial/ethnic (“multicultural”), bound merely by civic nationalism, economic opportunism, and kumbayah songs, is really the ur-problem, the most deeply planted seed of destruction, in the United States and most other Western countries. This idea seems essentially Christian in origin, but was also elaborated in response to the circumstances of the modern West, including colonialism and the globalization of trade and labor. In the US, it was shaped <em>inter alia</em> by the issues surrounding the Civil War, and was used, e.g., to justify turning African slaves into Union soldiers and then Republican voters in the Reconstruction South.</p>
<p>Despite multiculturalism&#8217;s clash with traditional ways of organizing societies, and its century and a half of failure in the US, it persists—persists even as racial/ethnic factionalism ravages the country, burns its cities, corrupts its democracy, and ruins its quality of life.</p>
<p>Even worse, multiculturalism’s elite proponents have become ever more suppressive of traditional ethnonationalism—declaring it “white supremacy” if favored by whites—even as they openly stoke nonwhites’ racial/ethnic grievances to build their political factions.</p>
<p>So black American nationalism is really only one of a thousand notions rendered unacceptable by America’s multiculturalist cult—whose mindset has managed to colonize both of the major political factions, and has successfully compensated for its evidentiary shortcomings with an hysterical, Inquisitionist crushing of dissent.</p>
<p>Nevertheless, black American nationalism does have advantages that make it a more practical aim amid this woke, antinationalist Inquisition. For one thing, it’s about what American blacks want, and if they declare they want to live apart and self-governing, the elites have no good alternative to the granting of that wish. Again and again those elites have declared American blacks holy and inviolable. Even if the elites’ motive in saying so has been only political and expedient, many blacks, and liberal whites, have taken the assertion at face value.</p>
<p>Another practical advantage that should make black nationalism more viable as a white cause is that American whites, I guess for reasons relating to their Christian backgrounds, prefer to think of themselves as helping others, not as acting selfishly for their own benefit. What could be more unselfish than to carve out thousands of square miles from their fair land, and donate it to their black brothers and sisters, to give them a new and truer freedom?</p>
<p>Would the blacks who lived in such a country experience a decline in living standards? I expect that they would, at least initially and in material terms. But as naïve as it may seem for me to say so, the issue here really goes deeper than material considerations: It’s about self-determination and human dignity. There are about fifty million black descendants of slaves living in the United States, enough to form one of the world’s most populous countries, and in many ways they have made clear that they are a distinctive people who prefer their own kind to others. The claim that they must nevertheless be the permanent captives and pawns of one political faction or another, in a society of European origin that is majority nonblack—a society that also jails them at sky-high rates—is actually ludicrous. It is one of the many toxic lies Americans foolishly think they can continue to live with.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p style="text-align: center;">***</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>SOME REALITIES OF &#8220;PEOPLE POWER&#8221;</title>
		<link>https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/some-realities-of-people-power/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[j stone]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 13 Nov 2020 22:15:05 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[fall of the West]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[revolution]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[USA]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/?p=98</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Stray thoughts on a Red State rebellion. &#160; Almost exactly twenty years ago, on the other side of the world from the USA, the elites and middle classes of the Philippines, with low-key but ample international support, overthrew their country’s elected president, Joseph Estrada, in what was later called a “constitutional coup.” Estrada was in &#8230; <a href="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/some-realities-of-people-power/" class="more-link">Continue reading<span class="screen-reader-text"> "SOME REALITIES OF &#8220;PEOPLE POWER&#8221;"</span></a>]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><em>Stray thoughts on a Red State rebellion.</em></p>
<p><span id="more-98"></span></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>Almost exactly twenty years ago, on the other side of the world from the USA, the elites and middle classes of the Philippines, with low-key but ample international support, overthrew their country’s elected president, Joseph Estrada, in what was later called a “constitutional coup.”</p>
<p>Estrada was in many ways like Donald Trump. He was an older guy with a womanizing past and rough-edged, frat-boy attitude who was widely known through past media exposure (he’d been an action star in Filipino movies, back in the day), and had plenty of mass appeal, but was somewhat repulsive to the more educated classes.</p>
<p>A big difference was that Estrada had been credibly accused of corruption. When, in January 2001, his Senate supporters effectively suppressed key evidence in his impeachment trial, the prosecutors walked out, liberals in the Philippines threw up a hue and cry, foreign diplomats and creditors became nervous, and the idea of simply ousting Estrada spread quickly.</p>
<p>Just a decade and a half before, in 1986, a mass movement that had come to be known as the EDSA Revolution (after an avenue in Manila where the main gathering took place) had resulted in the overthrow of the dictator Ferdinand Marcos. The anti-Estrada opposition followed this obvious model, and when the impeachment trial collapsed, EDSA II took place immediately. The media were for it, the US, a key ally, gave the nod (G.W. Bush, fresh from his own Bush v. Gore court victory, was about to take office), important Philippine cabinet officials including the heads of the police and military abandoned Estrada, and even the Philippine Supreme Court blessed the coup with the airy declaration that “the welfare of the people is the supreme law” (i.e., <em>salus populi suprema lex</em>). Estrada saw that he had lost virtually all support, and resigned, allowing his successor, vice president Gloria Arroyo, to take office.</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-104" src="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2020/11/edsa-revolution-dos.jpg" alt="EDSA II" width="600" height="381" srcset="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2020/11/edsa-revolution-dos.jpg 600w, https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2020/11/edsa-revolution-dos-300x191.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 709px) 85vw, (max-width: 909px) 67vw, (max-width: 984px) 61vw, (max-width: 1362px) 45vw, 600px" /></p>
<p>(Arroyo, who later pardoned Estrada after his corruption trial and conviction, eventually faced corruption allegations herself, concerning a bribe allegedly demanded by her government from a Chinese government-linked telecom company that wanted a contract to install a “national broadband network” linking Philippine government offices. But she was viewed much more favorably by the elites than Estrada had been, and ended up serving out her terms of office.)</p>
<p>Why is any of this of interest now? Well, for one thing, it’s a reminder that presidential transitions in “democracies” are not necessarily constitutional or legal just because the media proclaim them to be. EDSA II also illustrates how Trump’s presidency, if it were restored by court action, could come to an untimely end.</p>
<p>Perhaps more importantly, this two-decade-old “people power” story highlights some of the things that Trump and his supporters, or a post-Trump Red State America, would <em>not</em> have if they were ever to try to achieve political power through a revolt or rebellion:</p>
<ul>
<li>They would not have significant foreign support.</li>
<li>They would not have the support of their country’s elites.</li>
<li>They probably would not have the support of any major media organization, domestic or foreign.</li>
<li>They almost certainly would lack support from the USA’s top military brass.</li>
</ul>
<p>Could they still prevail? Sure. But they would have to overcome all these disadvantages. And since they would not have MSM support they could not simply gather dramatically in one place and hope for a media-induced buildup of pressure on the federal government.</p>
<p><strong>Red States Army</strong></p>
<p>Essentially, Red State America would need to form an army, à la 1776. Although the needed size and firepower of that army would depend on the movement’s ultimate goals, I think that force would have to be at least several hundred thousand strong to contend with Blue States National Guard units and possibly regular army and USAF units. Much of the “Red States Army” total could come from Red State National Guard units, defecting regular military troops, and retired/reserve veterans, though it would probably be able to pad out that core with a larger group of hunters and others who own and know how to use guns.</p>
<p>This rebel movement, to the extent it could control its own territory, would have a grip on most of the former-USA’s food production, so food shouldn’t be a problem. But the movement would need to set up its own banking system, central bank, and currency, much as the Confederate States did in Civil War I. It would need to establish control over the parts of the internet and telecom networks, rail and road networks, and other infrastructure elements within its domain. It would need its own social security system. And so on, and so on.</p>
<p>Moreover, prior to rebellion at state level, this movement would need a network of benefactors who would fund the cause covertly, for example by adding soldiers and support workers to existing businesses’ payrolls, or simply in a low-visibility, cash-based system outside the federally regulated banking system. As many on the right have learned already, US banks ultimately will not (knowingly) do business with those whom the left elites designate as “enemies of the people.”</p>
<p>The goals of a Red State confederacy could be, for example simply to break away and form a sovereign country, taking existing Red States along with any adjacent Blue State rural counties whose inhabitants vote to join. At county level the USA is mostly Republican, so in principle such a Red America would include most of the land area of the lower-48 states and of course all of Alaska. This would leave Blue America with most of the GDP-producing industry of the former USA, but also with most of the long-term social and demographic problems—“vibrancy” I think they call it.</p>
<p>All that vibrancy would be reflected in whatever army the Blue States could muster following the tens or hundreds of thousands of defections by Red State-loyal troops and officers, plus the loss of the many military bases within Red States. And if the Red States’ goal were purely defensive, the Blue States would have the added burden of having to subdue Red State cities, presumably through high-cost urban warfare.</p>
<p>What of the Antifa and BLM brigades we saw in action last summer? Well, their antics don’t strike me as particularly relevant to actual combat—although I can imagine many of them being unwilling to learn that lesson except in the hardest possible way.</p>
<p>In short, when it comes to actual fighting, a Red State army could have substantial advantages. (I&#8217;m assuming that neither side would go nuclear in this conflict.)</p>
<p>My guess is that the hardest task for an independence-seeking Red America would be the political task of convincing Red State governors and legislators to secede in the first place, so that the rebellion could begin to organize at scale. They don’t make US politicians like they used to—certainly not like they did in 1861.</p>
<p>In fact, neither Trump nor any prominent Red State politician, as far as I know, has had the mental clarity and courage even to <em>raise the issue</em> of resolving the USA’s current schism through political separation. That’s despite the Woke Left’s increasingly obvious willingness to tyrannize its domestic enemies, i.e., half of the country, by demonizing, canceling, and disemploying them, silencing their political speech, and, if necessary, imprisoning them in re-education camps.</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" class="size-full wp-image-105 aligncenter" src="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2020/11/reich.jpg" alt="Turd Reich" width="300" height="370" srcset="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2020/11/reich.jpg 300w, https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2020/11/reich-243x300.jpg 243w" sizes="(max-width: 300px) 85vw, 300px" /></p>
<p><img loading="lazy" class="size-full wp-image-106 aligncenter" src="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2020/11/schmidt.jpg" alt="About Schmidt" width="300" height="398" srcset="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2020/11/schmidt.jpg 300w, https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2020/11/schmidt-226x300.jpg 226w" sizes="(max-width: 300px) 85vw, 300px" /></p>
<p>The USA was founded on the principle of self-determination as the ultimate escape from tyranny, and the tyranny of the contemporary, woke Left already threatens to be worse in some ways than what Colonial Americans faced in the run-up to their declaration of independence. So it does seem appropriate at least to start thinking about how contemporary Americans might successfully act on that hallowed principle.</p>
<p style="text-align: center;">**</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>WOKEISM IS AN INTERIM ANTICULTURE</title>
		<link>https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wokeism-is-an-interim-anticulture/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[j stone]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 19 Oct 2020 09:52:05 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[ethnicity]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[fall of the West]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[immigration]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[women]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/?p=64</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[The Great Awokening may be catastrophic for the USA but as a cultural phenomenon it is inherently transitory &#160; Is the United States in the process of remaking itself with a new ideology called Wokeism? A lot of people seem to think so, but I don&#8217;t. The idea I sketch out briefly here is that &#8230; <a href="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wokeism-is-an-interim-anticulture/" class="more-link">Continue reading<span class="screen-reader-text"> "WOKEISM IS AN INTERIM ANTICULTURE"</span></a>]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><em>The Great Awokening may be catastrophic for the USA but as a cultural phenomenon it is inherently transitory</em></p>
<p><span id="more-64"></span></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>Is the United States in the process of remaking itself with a new ideology called Wokeism?</p>
<p>A lot of people seem to think so, but I don&#8217;t. The idea I sketch out briefly here is that the recent pandemic spread of Wokeism, a.k.a. The Great Awokening, is really only a transitory cultural phenomenon, more than a mass hysteria but less than the development of a full-fledged successor culture. Wokeism does draw upon trends in Western culture that have been underway for decades. However, as an ideology or culture it is basically incoherent and destructive, and does not offer a viable guide to a sustainable new way of life. Wokeism is chiefly marking a period of cultural upheaval&#8212;and is telling us nothing of how that period of upheaval will end.</p>
<p><strong>The mess of Wokeism</strong></p>
<p>Wokeism lacks a coherent list of do’s and don’ts, of the kind that normally make up a working culture. It shows no sign of having been thought through.</p>
<p>To give one example, the people who run BLM recently published a “manifesto” on their website which included a vaguely Maoist insistence on collective parenting:</p>
<p style="padding-left: 40px;">We disrupt the Western-prescribed nuclear family structure requirement by supporting each other as extended families and ‘villages’ that collectively care for one another, especially our children, to the degree that mothers, parents, and children are comfortable.</p>
<p>Apparently this was embarrassing enough, even for the dedicated banner-carriers and fellow-travelers of BLM, that this provision along with the rest of the manifesto was removed from the website soon after it was posted. When I went to the site address (<a href="https://blacklivesmatter.com/what-we-believe/">https://blacklivesmatter.com/what-we-believe/</a>) as I was composing this essay, I got a simple 404 error—suggesting that BLM lacks not only sense but also basic IT skills.</p>
<p>Other features of Wokeism include demands for radical police reforms—radically weakening police powers—or even the defunding/abolition of police departments. Some municipal governments in the United States have been so well captured by leftists that they really seem willing to adopt such measures. But—to state the obvious—these measures, and the criminality and anarchy they are bound to unleash, are things that a developed society with a large, wealthy, and center-right business-owning class will not tolerate for long.</p>
<p>Further down the Wokeists’ unrealizable/unsustainable wishlist we find radical reforms to education, which have the ultimate goal of bringing about equality of outcomes for different racial and ethnic groups, especially in public schools where the Wokeists’ policy grip is strongest. Standardized tests will be de-emphasized, admissions exclusivity weakened, and discipline more or less abandoned, in order to accommodate more disadvantaged groups. Recitations of <a href="https://www.city-journal.org/rise-of-woke-schools">Woke ideology</a> presumably will start to crowd out traditional subjects such as math and English. To again state the obvious: this cuckoo radicalism will mean only that any family having the means to do so will take their children out of public schools, leaving the unfortunate kids whose parents can’t place them elsewhere to suffer a long nightmare of Woke education.</p>
<p>Then there is the absurd idea of reparations, to be paid somehow to American blacks who, after 155 years of post-slavery systemic racism, have managed to become the world’s richest black population by far. I wonder how serious the Wokeists are about reparations anyway, since actual payment might be construed as an end to the matter, obliging both blacks and Wokeists to move on from all their racial grievance-mongering. (We all know the grievance-mongering will never be put to rest, as it serves an essential partisan-political function.) Actual payment might also do embarrassingly little to alter the essential situation of American blacks, who in many cases would end up worse following their rapid spending of their windfalls.</p>
<p>Open-door immigration appears to be a core policy of Wokeism, though it shouldn’t be, as it obviously harms the interests of American blacks. Even among immigrant groups, the open-door policy is apt to become unpopular to the extent that these groups see further newcomers as a source of unwanted competition for jobs. Of course liberal immigration policies have prevailed anyway in the US over the past few decades, and thus they are sustainable in that retrospective sense. But open-door immigration isn’t a culture or a pillar of a culture—it is effectively an anti-cultural policy, which almost by definition will destroy the host country’s traditional way of life and create a situation in which newcomer cultures will have to duke it out for eventual supremacy. Who seriously thinks that if Chinese-Americans or Indian-Americans take over large parts of the USA, they will continue to permit mass immigration from Africa or Latin America?</p>
<p>Similarly, if the wokeists succeed in making whites second-class citizens in their own country by mandating POC-preferences in jobs and university admissions—which they clearly hope to do—the end-result is unlikely to be a harmonious multiracial/multiethnic USA living under Wokeism. Much more likely will be the outcome seen in multi-ethnic situations elsewhere in the world, namely inter-ethnic strife, followed by the triumph of one or more, presumably nonwhite ethnicities—who may just divide the old USA among themselves and, in their new American country or countries, adopt nationalistic policies favoring their own. To them, the romantic multiracialism of early 21<sup>st</sup> century whites may end up being seen as a tragically maladaptive cultural trait—vaguely reminiscent of the predilection for firewater that helped doom 19<sup>th</sup> century Native Americans.</p>
<p><strong>Wokeists embody the chaos of wokeism</strong></p>
<p>Apart from Wokeism’s specific policy notions, look at the Wokeists themselves—especially the ones at the business end of Wokeism, where ideas are turned into action. Are these activists bustling Bolsheviks, busily setting up farmers’ or manufacturers’ or soldiers’ collectives? Not exactly. They seem like supremely messed-up people, a very high proportion of whom have histories of mental illness and/or severe sexual identity issues. They seem not only fundamentally unhappy but fundamentally set against the world as it is. That is why they burn and break and topple indiscriminately, destroying even statues of <em>Lincoln</em>. They seem to want the outside world to bear a closer resemblance to the disorder they have within. In other words, they don’t seem to be <em>for</em> anything meaningful. Does an Antifa Autonomous Zone look constructive? Is it something Western people could build upon? How about a burning, rubble-strewn downtown Minneapolis?</p>
<p>OK, but what about rich Woke-capitalist billionaires like Zuckerberg and Bezos? Aren’t they formidable enough to sustain Wokeism as a new culture?</p>
<p>Well, certainly, the Zuckerbergs and the Bezoses and their ilk are powerful. But I think they have zero intention of sustaining Wokeism in a form that could be called a new culture. They are primarily businessmen who have got to where they are by adapting rapidly in a dynamic business (and political) environment. They are now adapting to Wokeism, because it is a clear and present danger to anyone with commercial interests. Their adaptation is to feign support—they fear Wokeism and don’t want to be harmed by it, and think they can escape the firebombs and boycotts if they get out in front of the whole thing with various empty gestures.</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" class="size-full wp-image-68 aligncenter" src="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2020/10/mcdonalds.jpg" alt="woke capital" width="420" height="615" srcset="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2020/10/mcdonalds.jpg 420w, https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2020/10/mcdonalds-205x300.jpg 205w" sizes="(max-width: 420px) 85vw, 420px" /></p>
<p>Needless to add, corporations are not about to start hiring obese black trans performers, let alone 75-IQ kids from the &#8216;hood, to do anything substantive. Woke capitalists’ actions will mainly be limited to the patronage of a few, influential, black “public intellectuals,” who are essentially running legal protection rackets.</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" class="size-full wp-image-69 aligncenter" src="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2020/10/huckster.png" alt="" width="385" height="376" srcset="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2020/10/huckster.png 385w, https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2020/10/huckster-300x293.png 300w" sizes="(max-width: 385px) 85vw, 385px" /></p>
<p>Woke capitalism may also encompass a more urgent hiring preference for well educated Asians and Latinos over whites—anyone but whites! But for the most part the corporate version of Wokeism will be symbolic. After all, competitive organizations need competent people, and Wokeism—because of its insistence on equality of outcomes—does almost everything possible to discourage the development of practical competence.</p>
<p>In short, Wokeism on its own can never be a constructive, society-driving ideology or culture. It may seriously damage or even topple the old culture of legacy Americans, and that process may take years and result in terrible destruction, perhaps on the scale of the French Revolution or even the Fall of Rome. But Wokeism is not itself a successor culture that will be around a couple of generations from now.</p>
<p><strong>The importance of demographics and technology</strong></p>
<p>I don’t claim to fully understand wokeism or its origins, but I don’t think <em>anyone</em> can understand it without first understanding how the cultural ground, so to speak, was prepared for it.</p>
<p>To switch to a viral analogy, wokeism was a pathogen that was always around. There is nothing really new about it. It is a mix, a pastiche, of a lot of old, discredited ideas most of which were first put forward by 1960s radicals. Why did it suddenly break out into a pandemic spread? I think the answer is that the big changes that made the outbreak possible were in the susceptibilities of host populations.</p>
<p>One big change was the cultural feminization that followed the mass entry of women into culturally influential professions such as journalism, publishing, law, politics, and science over the past half-century. I’ve written about this in <a href="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/the-great-feminization/">earlier</a> <a href="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/the-day-the-logic-died/">essays.</a> Among other things, this feminization process appears to have made the culture profoundly more vulnerable to empathy-inducing themes of oppressed minorities, downtrodden refugees, and buzz-phrases like “systemic racism.”</p>
<p>American women have not been doing particularly well under their emancipation—their estimated lifetime prevalence of major depression is now more than 20 percent, to note one adverse mental health trend among many. Marriage and birth rates are falling. More and more women, having followed the dictates of feminism and sexual liberation, are living alone and childless. Amid the anxiety and bleak isolation of the COVID-19 crisis, many of them seem to have embraced Wokeness as a belief system that is almost spiritually sublime in its ambitions, and at the same time satisfyingly engages their maternal instincts to protect the weak. Other basic instincts may be involved as well. In any case it can’t be denied that women, particularly white women, have been enormously overrepresented at woke and BLM marches and protests.</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-70" src="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2020/10/bethesdawomen.jpg" alt="" width="600" height="338" srcset="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2020/10/bethesdawomen.jpg 600w, https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2020/10/bethesdawomen-300x169.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 709px) 85vw, (max-width: 909px) 67vw, (max-width: 984px) 61vw, (max-width: 1362px) 45vw, 600px" /></p>
<p>Women’s cultural influence in America isn’t going away any time soon. Any new culture that takes hold, or any form of cultural reversion, presumably will have to suit them. But a glance around the world tells us that women on the whole are very flexible when it comes to culture, provided that certain basic needs are met—needs that center largely around motherhood. I can&#8217;t believe that Wokeism, in the long run, meets enough of those needs. It seems more like a yearning, a dance, a pose, a fling, than real life.</p>
<p>Apart from cultural feminization and the COVID-19 crisis, two other big factors have obviously been relevant. One is the Internet, and social media in particular, which has boosted in an unprecedented way the potential speed and scale of social contagions. (I think it’s also generally accepted, if not as well studied as it should be, that women tend to transmit social contagions among themselves much more efficiently than men do.)</p>
<p>The other factor is the 2020 presidential election, which has spurred various get-out-the-vote operations and generally has encouraged partisan activists to whip up emotions to energize potential voters. I think various left-wing/Democrat activists did just that in the wake of George Floyd’s death, and that was the spark on dry tinder that flamed into the Great Awokening.</p>
<p>That flame has dimmed considerably in the months since June. It may flare up again if the Democrats sweep on election day. But I think it won’t burn for 70-odd years as Marxism-Leninism did. It doesn’t have the coherence or the minimal connection to human nature that it would need to have. What stable ideology will form on the other side of Wokeism is unclear. But given the ongoing cultural decay of whites and the relative robustness of nationalism among nonwhites, it seems likely that Wokeness will only mark the transition to a new, probably nonwhite-centered culture&#8212;or cultures. Those cultures could, ironically, end up being much more conservative and traditional than the decadent mishmash from which Wokeness emerged.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>SEED OF DESTRUCTION</title>
		<link>https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/seed-of-destruction/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[j stone]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 15 Jun 2020 22:37:05 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[ethnicity]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[fall of the West]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[immigration]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/?p=55</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[An expatriate’s perspective on pan-ethnic mass immigration Western societies almost without exception in recent decades have been transformed by the large-scale additions of essentially all foreign ethnicities to their legacy European-stock populations. How this came about is less important than the fact that it happened and now festers as the central problem of Western civilization. &#8230; <a href="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/seed-of-destruction/" class="more-link">Continue reading<span class="screen-reader-text"> "SEED OF DESTRUCTION"</span></a>]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><em>An expatriate’s perspective on pan-ethnic mass immigration</em></p>
<p><span id="more-55"></span></p>
<p>Western societies almost without exception in recent decades have been transformed by the large-scale additions of essentially all foreign ethnicities to their legacy European-stock populations.</p>
<p>How this came about is less important than the fact that it happened and now festers as the central problem of Western civilization. But I think it’s fair to say that this transformation began, several decades ago, principally because Western elites wanted it, at least partly for reasons they could not openly defend. A simplified and somewhat cynical version is that Left-leaning politicians in the US, emboldened by their success in capturing “the black vote,” calculated that they could import other ethnic minorities from abroad <em>en masse</em> and ultimately assemble a permanent electoral majority that way. Businessmen and the rich, seeking a wider range of cheap-labor options, were eager to go along. This basic idea then spread to the elites of other Western countries.</p>
<p>The pan-ethnic flow has continued for those mostly-unacknowledged reasons, and also because recently arrived foreigners and their offspring have by now acquired substantial political power of their own. But the reasons that have been used to publicly justify this change, at least in recent decades, are different. The elites, who now include the mouthpieces of these new ethnic voting blocs, have been assuring the increasingly feminized, compassion-oriented legacy populations of the West that this historic transformation has been necessary as an act of compassion, and a recognition of universal civil rights—huddled masses and all that. For the special case of the USA, they have argued or implied that the country has always been a construct of immigrants, a &#8220;civic&#8221; rather than an ethnic nation, a “promised land” in the words of RFK.</p>
<p>This has always been more than a dry, reasoned argument. The elites have applied to the legacy lower orders a strong emotional and moral pressure to accept that multi-ethnicity, “diversity,” is good, that it sits on the correct side of history, that opposing it is bad and racist. Some European governments have been so successful in their browbeating that they now enforce this new moral code in actual law. But even Western elites that haven’t achieved that level of thought-control have been pretty effective in enforcing diversity dogma through threats of disemployment and social ostracism for dissidents—<em>cancellation</em>.</p>
<p>Diversity dogma as we know it today would not have had as receptive an audience in the 1960s. The cultural ground had not yet been prepared. The average Democrat then would be considered “far right” today. So when the floodgates to pan-ethnic immigration began to be opened around the middle of that decade, people were simply misled. The elites, instead of presenting the coming demographic transformation as a good thing, assured ordinary citizens that it wouldn’t happen. The influx of foreigners would constitute a social ripple rather than a sea change—nothing to worry about! “This bill we sign today”—<a href="https://cis.org/Report/Legacy-1965-Immigration-Act">claimed</a> Lyndon Johnson of the 1965 Hart-Celler Immigration Bill—“is not a revolutionary bill. It does not affect the lives of millions. It will not restructure the shape of our daily lives.”</p>
<p>It did, though. And in the context of those original false assurances, the mass migration of ethnically and culturally distant peoples to the West has been an ongoing fraud, perpetrated by Western elites against their own legacy populations. By the same token, the compassion-based, right-side-of-history argument used to justify mass immigration is mainly window dressing. Still, it has been remarkably effective, and it deserves an effective response. As I organize my own thoughts about this, I don’t suppose that I have anything truly novel to say, but still I think my presentation is a better one than mass immigration opponents in the popular media usually provide.</p>
<p><strong>It’s not about “hate”</strong></p>
<p>I have never been comfortable with arguments against mass immigration that rest heavily on the idea of immigrants as lawless primitives.</p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><img loading="lazy" class="size-full wp-image-26 aligncenter" src="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2020/07/notsendingbest.jpg" alt="" width="592" height="471" srcset="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2020/07/notsendingbest.jpg 592w, https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2020/07/notsendingbest-300x239.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 592px) 85vw, 592px" /></p>
<p>That’s not to say that immigrants never <em>are</em> lawless primitives. It’s probably always been the case that a significant proportion of them belong in that category. But an argument that focuses just on the lowlifes implies that all the lawful, hard-working immigrants are totally OK. And they’re not totally OK, any more than lawful, hard-working white Americans would be, in the eyes of their hosts, if they tried to form a huge expatriate colony within some ethnically and culturally distant society.</p>
<p>I know this because I’ve spent most of my adult life as an expatriate in ethnically and culturally distant societies, and despite being lawful and hard-working I’ve run again and again into the limits of host country tolerance for foreigners. Those limits have been manifest in laws, such as laws limiting the kinds of jobs resident foreigners can do, and the property rights they can enjoy. Those limits have also been apparent in attitudes, such as the presumption that a foreigner opposing a native in court should normally lose, and the widespread belief that foreigners should pay more for things than natives do, or the simple, murmured resentment among locals to the effect that “there are too many foreigners here.”</p>
<p>Locals’ limited tolerance for foreigners like myself has sometimes struck me as too limited, but the fact that it <em>is</em> limited has never seemed fundamentally wrong. Placing bounds on foreign influx and influence in a society has always seemed like obvious common sense—a common sense forged by biological and cultural evolution as a basic human instinct.</p>
<p>Calling this innate in-group preference “hate” is one of the contemporary Left’s most specious and dishonest ploys. <em>Don’t be a hater</em>! My own experience is that countries placing heavy restrictions on foreigners’ residency and influence typically have citizens that are very warmly disposed towards visitors from abroad—probably in part because those restricting laws give locals a measure of security, from which they feel more free to be hospitable.</p>
<p>Nor is my opposition to mass immigration in my own country rooted in hatred of foreigners: I have spent most of my adult life living in far-flung places among ethnically and culturally dissimilar folk, and even married one of them, so that my children are now ethnically and culturally half-American and half-foreign. In other words, it has long been the case that the people dearest to me are foreigners in whole or in part.</p>
<p>From what do the limits of our tolerance spring, if not from hate?</p>
<p>Well, from something more fundamental than a human emotion. An organism is not an organism if it does not have boundaries that separate it from its environment and from other organisms. If it is too permeable, it will not survive. Human societies are not as well defined in this sense, compared to flora and fauna, but clearly they have been shaped by a similar evolutionary logic.</p>
<p>If one needs to invoke an emotion as the force underlying the universally limited human tolerance of foreigners, why not invoke love? As in, love for one’s kin and country—love for one’s national and cultural identity. One can’t have those good things, those fulfilments of basic human needs, <em>and</em> open one’s borders to all the peoples of the world. It would be like opening the doors of one’s house to random strangers. Speaking of which: remember that scene in the film <em>Doctor Zhivago</em> when the doctor returns from the war to find his comfortable Moscow residence filled with several other families—his own wife and children now confined to a single room? It was a wrenchingly effective depiction of the Bolshevik disregard for basic human nature. And for the viewer, as for Zhivago, the proper objects of hatred were not the new tenants but the Bolshevik overlords that had sent them.</p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><img loading="lazy" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-35" src="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2020/07/zhivago-house-divided.jpg" alt="" width="700" height="326" srcset="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2020/07/zhivago-house-divided.jpg 700w, https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2020/07/zhivago-house-divided-300x140.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 709px) 85vw, (max-width: 909px) 67vw, (max-width: 984px) 61vw, (max-width: 1362px) 45vw, 600px" /></p>
<p>Naturally, when a flood of immigrants makes a citizen feel that he has been displaced, his country effectively overrun, a certain amount of hatred toward the foreign displacer is an understandable reaction, and historically has been pretty effective at motivating a reversal of the flood. But hatred in that context is merely a means, and a temporary one, not the end in itself.</p>
<p>Globally, and ideally, the end is a good and positive end: a system of distinct nations—homelands populated by what are, more or less, extended families, each with a dominant ethnicity and culture—in which good fences, fair trade, and moderate amounts of tourism, intermarriage, and urban cosmopolitanism make good neighbors. In principle, at least, a sane and farsighted world can realize that humane goal calmly through policy, rather than through conflict.</p>
<p><strong>Diversity destroys democracy</strong></p>
<p>There are other reasons to oppose the flood of multi-ethnic immigration that has hit the West in recent decades. One set of reasons, largely amounting to a negative version of the argument above, invokes the weakening of social bonds, the dilution of the usual sense of shared culture, neighborliness and trust in an ethnically bound society, the erosion of the usual feeling of belonging (&#8220;this no longer feels like my country&#8221;), with an attendant demoralization that has already been blamed, e.g., for the downturn in white life expectancy in the US.</p>
<p>Another set of reasons involves the economic distortions caused by mass immigration, which include downward pressure on wages, disemployment of the legacy population, and—no less important—a draining away of skilled labor from the countries supplying the immigrants.</p>
<p>Then there is the higher-crime/lower-quality-of-life angle, which is especially relevant when the majority of immigrants come from less wealthy and orderly places.</p>
<p>Lastly, there is an argument that has long seemed to me especially important and yet mostly neglected. This is the argument that heavy multi-ethnicity in a society is incompatible in the long run with democracy—at least, traditional, stable, Western-style democracy—and must in the end produce political dissolution and anarchy or anyway some other-than-democratic outcome.</p>
<p>In part, this is an argument from simple observation: Multi-ethnic states almost never form naturally, and when they have been set up artificially—e.g., by Western colonial powers over the past few centuries—the result usually has been fragmentation or the emergence of a strongman (e.g., Saddam Hussein) with a police state.</p>
<p>This is also an argument from simple logic: Shared ethnicity is a very strong social and political binder, perhaps stronger than any other, particularly when the ethnic group is a political minority and feels, or is told that they should feel, a sense of adversity and oppression. In principle, as left-leaning parties in the USA and elsewhere have recognized, a sizeable political coalition can be built from such aggrieved, bloc-voting minority groups, <em>provided that the faction-building party can manage to keep the flames of grievance alive in them</em>. I think it’s fair to say, and it is maybe self-evident from events ongoing as I write, that those flames must ultimately burn away the mutual respect and trust that a society needs to sustain a democratic style of government. Many of the founders of the U.S. Republic knew that factionalism, in general, would be a constant temptation and a major threat to its survival. Race-based factionalism, which the founders largely failed to anticipate, is arguably on historical grounds—not to mention, evolutionary-biological grounds—the most toxic.</p>
<p>In the US the Democratic Party, previously the party of southern whites, has been shifting towards this mode of racial-minority factionalism (which also encompasses non-ethnically defined marginalized groups such as women and LGBTs) at least since the civil rights era of the 1950s and 60s. Over the decades, powered especially by immigration, this strategy has strengthened the party electorally, and on a superficial analysis would seem to have positioned it now for long-term electoral dominance. But really this strategy has been self-defeating, in the sense that it effectively has destroyed the social fabric of the USA, making democracy itself now untenable as a means of stable governance.</p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><img loading="lazy" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-33" src="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2020/07/whriot.jpg" alt="" width="700" height="459" srcset="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2020/07/whriot.jpg 700w, https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2020/07/whriot-300x197.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 709px) 85vw, (max-width: 909px) 67vw, (max-width: 984px) 61vw, (max-width: 1362px) 45vw, 600px" /></p>
<p>If I’m right that my country—presaging developments elsewhere in the West—is about to see the full collapse of its political system, then the Left’s current pandering claim that slavery was America’s “original sin” may have a grain of truth to it. I would call it not only America’s original sin but also the original seed of America’s destruction: Through slavery, Americans brought a large, racially and developmentally distant minority into the country. That ultimately prompted a massive conflagration before the Republic was even 90 years old. But what came afterwards was arguably worse. The decision <em>not</em> to give ex-slaves their own separate homeland (as Lincoln among others had wanted) but to keep them in the US as citizens led ultimately, perhaps inevitably, to the emergence of civil rights ideology, diversity dogma, pan-ethnic immigration, and the current caustic factionalism that I expect will prove terminal.</p>
<p>The same fatal seed may deserve blame for the fall of the West more generally, since American-style civil rights ideology long ago infected the elites of other Western democracies and at least partly accounts for their post-colonial embraces of pan-ethnic immigration.</p>
<p>Am I too pessimistic? We’ll soon see. In the meantime, I’ll be busy preparing myself and my family for life and work outside the countries of the self-immolating West.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
